<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Family-Integrated Church 13: Why the family-integrated view dies the death of a 1000 (or at least a few) qualifications!	</title>
	<atom:link href="/family-integrated-church-13/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/family-integrated-church-13/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2011 14:48:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Jack Brooks		</title>
		<link>/family-integrated-church-13/#comment-288</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jack Brooks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2011 14:48:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=951#comment-288</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My primary concern is that it is a sin to call something sinful if the Word of God does not. The Word of God does not teach that age-based educational organization is sinful. Therefore, the FIC Movement is sinning by calling that a sin.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My primary concern is that it is a sin to call something sinful if the Word of God does not. The Word of God does not teach that age-based educational organization is sinful. Therefore, the FIC Movement is sinning by calling that a sin.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joe Johnson		</title>
		<link>/family-integrated-church-13/#comment-287</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joe Johnson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2011 22:03:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=951#comment-287</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As always, Dr. Waldron, you prove yourself to be a gentleman. Thank you for your gracious manner in handling what can be a very touchy issue for many.
Perhaps I can offer more thought to the &quot;systematic&quot; idea. What seems to be the issue here is a separate church within the church. A &quot;pastor&quot; is placed over a group within the church (saved?), in many ways treating it as a separate church. The implications of this have been dealt with already in your writing.
Having special &quot;youth&quot; meetings or gatherings is different. It&#039;s an &quot;event&quot; rather than a divided aspect of the local ministry. It also offers the parents to be involved with their children rather than being excluded.
Perhaps a good question to ask is whether or not it&#039;s biblical to divide the church along demographic lines. I wouldn&#039;t isolate youth any more than I would singles, the elderly, widows or any other group. We all benefit from the experiences, knowledge and accumulated wisdom of one another. Does not such segregation rob us of this blessing?

Blessings
Joe]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As always, Dr. Waldron, you prove yourself to be a gentleman. Thank you for your gracious manner in handling what can be a very touchy issue for many.<br />
Perhaps I can offer more thought to the &#8220;systematic&#8221; idea. What seems to be the issue here is a separate church within the church. A &#8220;pastor&#8221; is placed over a group within the church (saved?), in many ways treating it as a separate church. The implications of this have been dealt with already in your writing.<br />
Having special &#8220;youth&#8221; meetings or gatherings is different. It&#8217;s an &#8220;event&#8221; rather than a divided aspect of the local ministry. It also offers the parents to be involved with their children rather than being excluded.<br />
Perhaps a good question to ask is whether or not it&#8217;s biblical to divide the church along demographic lines. I wouldn&#8217;t isolate youth any more than I would singles, the elderly, widows or any other group. We all benefit from the experiences, knowledge and accumulated wisdom of one another. Does not such segregation rob us of this blessing?</p>
<p>Blessings<br />
Joe</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Sam Waldron		</title>
		<link>/family-integrated-church-13/#comment-286</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2011 01:49:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=951#comment-286</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Jason, thank you for your kind words and for the clarification with regard to Scott&#039;s perspective.  I accept your explanation.  It does seem to make sense of what he says.  What Scott is against is &quot;systematic age-segregation.&quot;  I have several responses.

First, I also could say that I am against systematic age-segregation because I do not believe that the corporate worship of the church should be age-segregated.  I also believe that the integrity of the family should be guarded and honored by the local church.  I also believe in parental involvement in youth activities.

Second, I should like, then, a little more definition for what constitutes &quot;systematic&quot; age-segregation.  This is apparently a very important word in the debate.  I think it is insufficient merely to say that there are exceptions to every rule.  I am certain that neither Jason or Scott would want to say that there are exceptions to God&#039;s ten main rules given us in the Ten Commandments.  What important rules are there for the church that have such exceptions?  A few examples might be instructive.

Third, Jason&#039;s response once again illustrates the importance of keeping our differences in perspective on the subject of age-segregation in the church.  The adjective, systematic, is an admission that we are dealing with issues where good men may differ.  They are, in other words, matters of judgment and not matters of principle.  I wish everyone involved in frictions over these issues might keep this in mind and not react into extreme and indefensible &quot;thou shalts&quot; and &quot;thou shalt nots.&quot; I wish that those called to be sheep might allow those called to be shepherds the rights they possess to make the judgment calls that need to be made on such issues.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jason, thank you for your kind words and for the clarification with regard to Scott&#8217;s perspective.  I accept your explanation.  It does seem to make sense of what he says.  What Scott is against is &#8220;systematic age-segregation.&#8221;  I have several responses.</p>
<p>First, I also could say that I am against systematic age-segregation because I do not believe that the corporate worship of the church should be age-segregated.  I also believe that the integrity of the family should be guarded and honored by the local church.  I also believe in parental involvement in youth activities.</p>
<p>Second, I should like, then, a little more definition for what constitutes &#8220;systematic&#8221; age-segregation.  This is apparently a very important word in the debate.  I think it is insufficient merely to say that there are exceptions to every rule.  I am certain that neither Jason or Scott would want to say that there are exceptions to God&#8217;s ten main rules given us in the Ten Commandments.  What important rules are there for the church that have such exceptions?  A few examples might be instructive.</p>
<p>Third, Jason&#8217;s response once again illustrates the importance of keeping our differences in perspective on the subject of age-segregation in the church.  The adjective, systematic, is an admission that we are dealing with issues where good men may differ.  They are, in other words, matters of judgment and not matters of principle.  I wish everyone involved in frictions over these issues might keep this in mind and not react into extreme and indefensible &#8220;thou shalts&#8221; and &#8220;thou shalt nots.&#8221; I wish that those called to be sheep might allow those called to be shepherds the rights they possess to make the judgment calls that need to be made on such issues.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jason Dohm		</title>
		<link>/family-integrated-church-13/#comment-285</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Dohm]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2011 12:29:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=951#comment-285</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Greetings Dr. Waldron.

I am a co-elder with Scott Brown.  We very much appreciate the work you have done to promote the 1689 confession.  Thank you for those contributions.  We have benefited from them.  I do want to offer a perspective on what you have written here.  It actually isn&#039;t a thousand qualifications, or even a few.  You are really analyzing only one, and I think you would agree that important principles requiring no qualification are hard to find.  And the qualification that Scott offers is a simple one.  His argument is against systematic age-segregation, which is why he is advocating the elimination of Sunday school and youth group.  The qualification does not contradict his thesis at all - his thesis is about systematic age-segregation.  That elders may see a compelling reason to make an exception does not invalidate the rule.  The exception doesn&#039;t invalidate the rule, it proves the rule.


Jason Dohm]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Greetings Dr. Waldron.</p>
<p>I am a co-elder with Scott Brown.  We very much appreciate the work you have done to promote the 1689 confession.  Thank you for those contributions.  We have benefited from them.  I do want to offer a perspective on what you have written here.  It actually isn&#8217;t a thousand qualifications, or even a few.  You are really analyzing only one, and I think you would agree that important principles requiring no qualification are hard to find.  And the qualification that Scott offers is a simple one.  His argument is against systematic age-segregation, which is why he is advocating the elimination of Sunday school and youth group.  The qualification does not contradict his thesis at all &#8211; his thesis is about systematic age-segregation.  That elders may see a compelling reason to make an exception does not invalidate the rule.  The exception doesn&#8217;t invalidate the rule, it proves the rule.</p>
<p>Jason Dohm</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
