<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Practical Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/practical-theology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 16:14:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Practical Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Social Media Controversies &#038; Moral Proximity &#124; Tom Hicks</title>
		<link>/social-media-controversies-moral-proximity/</link>
					<comments>/social-media-controversies-moral-proximity/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tom Hicks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Media]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15649</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Are you responsible for social media controversies? We live in an unprecedented time, where all the problems of the world demand our constant attention and immediate judgment on social media. Through technology, we&#8217;re connected to events all over the nation and the world. Very quickly, people are polarized into those who are “for” and those [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/social-media-controversies-moral-proximity/">Social Media Controversies &#038; Moral Proximity | Tom Hicks</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[Are you responsible for social media controversies?

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

We live in an unprecedented time, where all the problems of the world demand our constant attention and immediate judgment on social media. Through technology, we&#8217;re connected to events all over the nation and the world. Very quickly, people are polarized into those who are “for” and those who are “against” whatever controversy happens to be raging this week. We are expected to make a quick decision based on limited evidence and with limited impact upon our life or upon the lives of people near us. Some people seem to get a thrill out of the controversy and “taking a stand,” and making their voice heard, while others are exhausted by it all.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

This raises an important question. Are we responsible for every controversy? And if we&#8217;re not responsible for it, should we even be weighing into it? What things are our responsibility and what aren&#8217;t?

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2><strong>1. Moral proximity</strong></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

This biblical principle teaches that you are responsible for problems that are closest to you, beginning in your family, then in your church, then in your local community, but the further out you get in terms of relationship, distance, and time, the less personally responsible you are. This moral principle is partly based on a clear understanding of human nature. Human beings are limited creatures with limited powers. We are simply not capable of exercising responsibility over all the problems of the world. And to the degree that we try to do so, we do it very badly, and often make matters worse than had we not interfered at all. Therefore, the Bible teaches that we live within spheres of responsibility which correspond to our powers within those spheres.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

Consider a few passages of Scripture that teach this principle.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

1 Timothy 4:8 says, “But if anyone does not provide for his relatives, and especially for the members of his own household, he has denied the faith and is worse than an unbeliever.” In other words, we are responsible first for our own family unit, and only after that, to our relatives in extended family.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

Galatians 6:10 says,  “So then, as we have opportunity, let us do good to everyone, and especially to those who are of the household of faith.” Notice that we are to do good to everyone, if we have the opportunity to do so. But this is not commanding us to do good to people if we don&#8217;t have the opportunity. While we are to do good to all, the Bible says that we are especially to do good to other Christians. So, if we must choose between doing good to a non-Christian and a Christian, we must choose the Christian. This principle is further narrowed to one&#8217;s own local church, as illustrated by the “one another” passages which are directed to particular local churches.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

Christ&#8217;s parable of the Good Samaritan in Luke 10:35-37 illustrates the doctrine of moral proximity well. When the Samaritan walked into physical proximity of the man beaten by robbers, he became responsible to do what he could to save his life. He had the power to do something; so, he did. Before the Samaritan was in moral proximity, he had no responsibility to do anything about the man beaten by robbers.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

Jeremiah 29:7 says, “Seek the welfare of the city where I have sent you into exile and pray to the Lord on its behalf, for in its welfare, you will find your welfare.” After our families and churches, we are responsible within our local municipalities to do good, and to look after the welfare of our neighbors.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

The Westminster Larger Catechism, Q99, A5 says, “What God forbids is at no time to be done; what he commands, is always our duty, and yet every particular duty is not to be done at all times (Matt 12:7).” This implies that while we are to serve the poor, feed the hungry, and work for justice, we aren&#8217;t to do this all the time, but only according to our moral proximity and our station and calling in life.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2><strong>2. Problems with ignoring moral proximity on social media</strong></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

There are a number of problems that arise when people don&#8217;t observe this biblical teaching about moral proximity. The Bible warns, “Whoever meddles in a quarrel not his own is like one who takes a passing dog by the ears” (Prov 26:17). That is, bad things tend to happen if we fail to observe moral proximity.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2><em>Negative repercussions</em></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

People who weigh in on every social media debate sometimes have a false sense of accomplishment. They think because they give their opinion on an issue, they are dealing a blow for justice. But in fact, they have done very little. Worse, they sometimes feel like they&#8217;ve done the right thing, and even honored the Lord, when in fact, they have not.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

On the flip side, some hear about injustices on social media and they feel tremendous guilt that they can&#8217;t do more. They have a feeling that they should do something, but they don&#8217;t know what to do. Even after “speaking out,” they still feel anger and guilt because speaking out didn&#8217;t actually accomplish anything.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

People who forget the doctrine of moral proximity have the weight of the whole world resting upon their shoulders, when they have no real power to be able to do anything about it. They also often invest a tremendous amount of time and energy into problems they have no power to resolve. If they invested the same amount of time and effort into matters morally proximate to them, they could actually do much more good because they would have much more influence.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2><em>Gossip and slander</em></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

One of the problems with trying to “do justice” on social media is that good information is nearly always lacking. By its very nature, social media is reductionistic. It lacks context. It has become easier and more common for people to fabricate injustices, just to create outrage. Misrepresentation abounds, not only from internet trolls, but from news agencies and official sources.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

Well-meaning people see allegations of injustice on social media, and they feel outrage. They feel compelled to speak out publicly, and they might even condemn the accused in the name of justice. But the Scriptures give warning about hasty conclusions in controversies. The Bible frequently speaks of the need for two or three witnesses (Deut 19:15; Matt 18:16; 2 Cor 13:1), or two or three independent lines of evidence to establish a matter.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

Scripture gives a strong warning against gossip and mob justice in Exodus 23:1-3, saying,

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">“You shall not spread a false report. You shall not join hands with a wicked man to be a malicious witness. You shall not fall in with the many to do evil, nor shall you bear witness in a lawsuit, siding with the many so as to pervert justice, nor shall you be partial to a poor man in his lawsuit.”</blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

It&#8217;s far better to remain silent than to become a gossip or a slanderer. The word “Satan” means accuser. The word “Devil” means slanderer. Christians must never repeat a matter unless they have followed the biblical procedure for verification.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2><strong>3. Faithfully discharging moral proximity</strong></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

How then should we exercise our moral responsibility? We should invest most of our personal energy into our homes, our churches, our workplaces, and our local communities. Yes, we should be educated on national issues and try to vote wisely, but comparatively, our influence on national issues will ordinarily be quite small compared to our ability to influence things more locally.

<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/tom-hicks/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2018/03/02211852/TomHicks.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/tom-hicks/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Tom Hicks</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><div class="header">
<div class="description">Tom serves as the Senior Pastor of First Baptist Church of Clinton, LA. He&#8217;s married to Joy, and they have four children: Sophie, Karlie, Rebekah, and David. He received his MDiv and PhD degrees from The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary with a major in Church History, emphasis on Baptists, and with a minor in Systematic Theology. Tom is the author of The Doctrine of Justification in the Theologies of Richard Baxter and Benjamin Keach (PhD diss, SBTS). He serves on the board of directors for Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary and is an adjunct professor of historical theology for the Institute of Reformed Baptist Studies.</div>
</div>
<div id="featured">
<div class="hero"></div>
</div>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/social-media-controversies-moral-proximity/">Social Media Controversies &#038; Moral Proximity | Tom Hicks</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/social-media-controversies-moral-proximity/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 7 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</title>
		<link>/9-john-mark/</link>
					<comments>/9-john-mark/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 21:32:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15515</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is the 9th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here:&#160;1,&#160;2,&#160;3,&#160;4,&#160;5,&#160;6,&#160;7, 8. Chapter 7 of John Mark&#8217;s Remarkable Career&#8212;His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark The unanimous testimony of the early church is that the Gospel of Mark was written by John Mark. The earliest [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/9-john-mark/">Chapter 7 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is the 9th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here:&nbsp;<a href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">1</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">2</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/mark-career-3/">3</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/chapter-3-mark/">4</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/john-mark-5/">5</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/6-john-mark/">6</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/7-john-mark/">7</a>, <a href="/8-john-mark/">8</a>.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2><strong>Chapter 7 of John Mark&#8217;s Remarkable Career&#8212;His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</strong></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The unanimous testimony of the early church is that the Gospel of Mark was written by John Mark. The earliest testimony to this comes from two well-known Christians of the second century.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The first is a man named Papias. His testimony likely comes from around the years 110-120. He said:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><em>Mark, the interpreter of Peter, wrote down carefully what he remembered, both the sayings and the deeds of the Christ, but not in chronological order, for he did not hear the Lord nor did he accompany him. At a later time, however, he did accompany Peter, who adapted his instructions to the needs, but not with the object of making a connected series of discourses of our Lord. So, Mark made no mistake in writing the individual discourses in the order in which he recalled them. His one concern was not to omit a single thing he had heard or to leave any untruth in this account.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The second significant testimony comes from the early church father, Irenaeus. Writing around 180, he said:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><em>Matthew also issued a written Gospel among the Hebrews in their own dialect, while Peter and Paul were preaching at Rome, and laying the foundations of the Church. After their departure, Mark, the disciple and interpreter of Peter, did also hand down to us in writing what had been preached by Peter. Luke also, the companion of Paul, recorded in a book the Gospel preached by him. Afterwards, John, the disciple of the Lord, who also had leaned upon His breast, did himself publish a Gospel during his residence at Ephesus in Asia.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The best and the necessary conclusion with regard to the authorship of the Gospel of Mark is summarized in the words of another scholar:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Though the author does not directly identify himself, there is still strong evidence to attribute the Gospel to John Mark. In addition to Markan composition, church fathers also state that Mark was the interpreter of Peter, which would give reason to believe that he wrote his Gospel under the guidance or assistance of the apostle &#8230; the title &#8220;According to Mark&#8221; (KATA MARKON) is found in the earliest manuscripts. &nbsp;[https://www.blueletterbible.org/study/intros/mark.cfm]</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>John Mark&#8212;that John Mark who abandoned Christ and deserted Barnabas and Saul and was the source of the scandal of the disagreement between Paul and Barnabas&#8212;that John Mark was so restored in Christ&#8217;s church that by the grace of Christ he rose to be one of the four evangelists who penned inspired chronicles of the life of Christ!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong><em>We learn that because of Christ people of smaller talents and lesser grace can still hold useful places of service in the kingdom of God!&nbsp; </em></strong>John Mark was surrounded throughout his life by giants. Barnabas, Paul, and Peter&#8212;such giant Christians no doubt constantly reminded him of how meager and small his own talent was.&nbsp; He no doubt would have called himself a one-talent man as he compared himself to such greats! But he did not make this a reason to bury his talent. He kept on. He kept plodding. He kept serving God. And one day he became the penman of one of the four gospels! What hope and consolation and encouragement this should give to the rest of us. We also see ourselves as people of small gift, but God may also make us eminently useful like John Mark if we will be faithful to use the gift we have been given.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong><em>We learn that because of Christ you can still be greatly useful in spite of your messing up in the past!&nbsp; </em></strong>Not only did John Mark see himself as possessing very meager gifts, he surely also saw himself as having royally messed up in his past.&nbsp; And it was true.&nbsp; There was no denying it.&nbsp; Yet, despite this, Mark became greatly useful! You must not allow your view of yourself be ruled by your past messes, but by Christ&#8217;s present graces!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/9-john-mark/">Chapter 7 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/9-john-mark/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</title>
		<link>/8-john-mark/</link>
					<comments>/8-john-mark/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 20:18:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15505</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is the 8th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter 1 Peter 5:13 reads: “She who is in Babylon, chosen together with you, sends you greetings, and so does my son, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/8-john-mark/">Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>This is the 8th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here: <a href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">1</a>, <a href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">2</a>, <a href="/mark-career-3/">3</a>, <a href="/chapter-3-mark/">4</a>, <a href="/john-mark-5/">5</a>, <a href="/6-john-mark/">6</a>, <a href="/7-john-mark/">7</a>.</em></p>



<h2><strong>Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</strong></h2>



<p>1 Peter 5:13 reads: “She who is in Babylon, chosen together with you, sends you greetings, and so does my son, Mark.” No serious doubt may be entertained that Peter here refers to the John Mark we have been studying.&nbsp; And he refers to him in the most affectionate terms. He calls him “his son.” Most conservative scholars date 1 Peter around AD 64-65. Thus, this remark of the Apostle Peter may have taken place a year or two before that of Paul’s remark in AD 67, but at about the same time.</p>



<p>We learn, then, that John Mark’s reputation had been rehabilitated not only with Paul and the wing of the church that he led.&nbsp; It had also been restored in the part of the church led by Peter. What a clear testimony to the renewed usefulness and respected status of John Mark in the early church!</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn that by the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ you can receive deliverance from past sins and not be doomed by your past mistakes!&nbsp; </em></strong>The example of John Mark ought to encourage those who live with a sneaking suspicion that they have forfeited God’s best for their lives. It should give hope to those who think that their past mistakes have condemned them to a useless life and sad existence. If deliverance could come through Christ to John Mark, it can come to you.</p>



<p>But this statement is not the greatest testimony to God’s restoring grace in John Mark’s remarkable career. That is rather his authoring of the Gospel of Mark. We will consider that in the next blog.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/8-john-mark/">Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/8-john-mark/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 4 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Pivotal and Tragic Place in the Disagreement between Barnabas and Saul</title>
		<link>/6-john-mark/</link>
					<comments>/6-john-mark/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 21:55:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15496</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chapter 4 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Pivotal and Tragic Place in the Disagreement between Barnabas and Saul This is the 6th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 5 parts here: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. It is the account of the disagreement between Barnabas and Saul in Acts 15:37-39 [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/6-john-mark/">Chapter 4 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Pivotal and Tragic Place in the Disagreement between Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3><strong>Chapter 4 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Pivotal and Tragic Place in the Disagreement between Barnabas and Saul</strong></h3>



<p><em>This is the 6th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 5 parts here: <a href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">1</a>, <a href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">2</a>, <a href="/mark-career-3/">3</a>, <a href="/chapter-3-mark/">4</a>, <a href="/john-mark-5/">5</a>.</em></p>



<p>It is the account of the disagreement between Barnabas and Saul in Acts 15:37-39 which we are now considering. It is not my purpose to analyze that disagreement in detail. We do need to look at it with regard to our present purpose of understanding the life of John Mark.</p>



<p><em>Acts 15:37 Barnabas wanted to take John, called Mark, along with them also. 38 But Paul kept insisting that they should not take him along who had deserted them in Pamphylia and had not gone with them to the work. 39 And there occurred such a sharp disagreement that they separated from one another, and Barnabas took Mark with him and sailed away to Cyprus.</em></p>



<p>Have you ever thought about this situation from the viewpoint of John Mark? I had not until I was thinking about it recently. Ask yourself, What would it have been like for John Mark in this situation? He was rejected by the Apostle Paul; the cause of sharp disagreement between Paul and Barnabas; the subject of prolonged discussion between Paul and Barnabas; and—no doubt—the focus of public conversation in the Christian community at Jerusalem. You can imagine how difficult the situation became for John Mark!&nbsp; Whatever we think of Barnabas leaving as he did, leaving was almost a necessity for John Mark.&nbsp; How could he stay in Jerusalem?&nbsp; He would be the occasion of disagreement, discussion, suspicion, and endless questions.&nbsp; This would not be good for him or for the church. Barnabas’s decision to take John Mark with him to Cyprus and get him out of this emotional pressure-cooker—whatever else it was—was a deliverance for John Mark. It removed him from a very difficult, perhaps unbearable, and certainly embarrassing situation.&nbsp; Far away in Cyprus where this difficulty was not well-known, John Mark might have time to pray, reflect, and, if necessary, to repent.</p>



<p>At this point in our account of the life of John Mark one could not be blamed for thinking that any usefulness for John Mark was finished.&nbsp; The days of effective labor for the kingdom would never return for John Mark—that is what we must, it would seem, necessarily conclude. Nevertheless, praise God, the career of John Mark turned out much differently than we might have expected or feared.</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn how easy it is to be stained with a bad reputation and the difficulties it may create for you!&nbsp; </em></strong>Can you imagine people shaking their heads at the mention of John Mark? Abandoning the Lord, deserting the missionaries, he was thought to be unstable as water. And then the terrible disagreement it provoked between Paul and Barnabas! What a scandal and he was in the middle of it! Little and surely not sufficiently had John Mark the difficulties that would result from his unstable desire to run home to Momma in Jerusalem. And perhaps the most spiritually deadly aspect of it all was that John Mark deeply struggled with believing this assessment and agreeing with the worst opinion of himself.</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn how badly we need sympathetic Christian brothers to help us see our sins and repent and find restoration through Christ! </em></strong>I cannot resist the notion that Barnabas, the son of encouragement, was the means in no small measure of John Mark’s recovery. He took John Mark to a place where he could recover.&nbsp; He gave him the sympathetic ear which enabled him not to be crushed into despair by his sins. I am sure he was faithful to guide him to the place of repentance, faith, and forgiveness in Christ.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/6-john-mark/">Chapter 4 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Pivotal and Tragic Place in the Disagreement between Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/6-john-mark/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career Continued—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</title>
		<link>/john-mark-5/</link>
					<comments>/john-mark-5/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 19:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15322</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career Continued—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul In the last blog we looked at how John Mark began his travels with Barnabas and Paul.&#160; In this blog we considered the text which speaks of the sad conclusion of those travels. Acts 13:13 Now Paul and his [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-mark-5/">Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career Continued—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career Continued—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</h2>



<p>In the last blog we looked at how John Mark began his travels with Barnabas and Paul.&nbsp; In this blog we considered the text which speaks of the sad conclusion of those travels.</p>



<p><em>Acts 13:13 Now Paul and his companions put out to sea from Paphos and came to Perga in Pamphylia; but John left them and returned to Jerusalem.</em></p>



<p>Now, by itself, you might not put a negative construction on John’s departure from Barnabas and Saul recorded here.&nbsp; The text merely says that John departed.&nbsp; There is no necessary negative connotation to place upon this word.&nbsp; One might, in fact, imagine good reasons for him to return to Jerusalem. There is, however, good reason to think that this decision on John’s part was not one to be admired.&nbsp; Why must we say this? There are several reasons.</p>



<ul><li>First and notoriously, the Apostle Paul saw it in a very negative light. Famously, he resisted the idea of taking John Mark along on the proposed second missionary journey.&nbsp; In Acts 15:38 he describes John Mark’s departure in Acts 13:13 as “desertion.” Paul uses a word that can even in some cases mean to apostatize. Paul surely would not have reacted so firmly to a departure that was justifiable.</li><li>Second, the decision of John Mark to leave for Jerusalem seems double-minded.&nbsp; He had agreed to accompany and help the missionaries.&nbsp; We may assume that this help was felt necessary for them and this experience was deemed important to his development.&nbsp; Yet, before the missionary journey was hardly begun, John heads for home. It seemed like desertion to Paul and probably to everybody else.&nbsp; He judged it to reveal instability in John’s character. Yes, Barnabas was willing to forgive and forget. That was his big-hearted generosity as the son of encouragement (Acts 4:36). Paul could not regard such “flakiness” so lightly.</li><li>Third, while I do not believe that we should judge Barnabas too harshly, the fact is that there seems to be a precipitous or rushed feeling about Barnabas taking John Mark and leaving for Cyprus in Acts 15.&nbsp; On the other hand, Luke takes the time to tell us that Paul and Silas were committed by the brethren to the grace of Lord.&nbsp; There is no such notation with regard to Barnabas and John when they left for Cyprus.&nbsp; Once more, this seems to say that the generality of the church in Jerusalem agreed with Paul’s reservations about John Mark.&nbsp; This means that they also felt that there was a kind of “desertion” in John’s departure from the missionaries.</li></ul>



<p>There is, then, another red flag raised about John Mark in our passage.&nbsp; Not only had he deserted the Lord in the Garden, he had deserted the missionaries in Cyprus. Of such repeated events reputations are made.&nbsp; This reputation was not a good one.</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn the dreadful consequences of abandoning your solemn responsibilities and how shameful it is to do so!&nbsp; </em></strong>Do you think that Mark ever thought he would bring on himself the kind of shame that he did by deserting the missionaries?&nbsp; Who knows what easy rationalizations he had for doing so? But the shame that he brought upon himself surely was a constant reminder of his unfaithfulness.</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn also that anyone—no matter their religious pedigree or background may fall into unfaithfulness!</em></strong>&nbsp; John Mark was at the center of the Christian movement.&nbsp; He had physically seen the Lord.&nbsp; He had been in the house when the Last Supper was celebrated.&nbsp; He was the close relative of prominent Christians.&nbsp; Yet he forsook his post and proved unfaithful.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-mark-5/">Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career Continued—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/john-mark-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</title>
		<link>/chapter-3-mark/</link>
					<comments>/chapter-3-mark/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 15:04:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15296</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul When I speak of Mark’s “interesting” and “abortive” travels with Barnabas and Saul, I have three texts in mind.&#160; In this blog I want to look at them in order of their occurrence in the Book of Acts. The first [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/chapter-3-mark/">Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</strong></p>



<p>When I speak of Mark’s “interesting” and “abortive” travels with Barnabas and Saul, I have three texts in mind.&nbsp; In this blog I want to look at them in order of their occurrence in the Book of Acts. The first is …</p>



<p><em>Acts 12:25 And Barnabas and Saul returned from Jerusalem when they had fulfilled their mission, taking along with them John, who was also called Mark.</em></p>



<p>Remember that Barnabas and Saul had been in Jerusalem on a relief mission from Antioch because of the famine in Jerusalem. While Barnabas had renewed his acquaintance with Mark, his cousin. Perhaps the emissaries from Antioch had even stayed at the home of Mary, the aunt of Barnabas.&nbsp; It would at least have been natural for them to do so. Somehow during their stay in Jerusalem, the idea had been birthed that it would be good for John Mark to accompany Barnabas and Saul back to Antioch.&nbsp; If we are right about the young man in Mark’s gospel being John Mark himself, then a dozen years later Mark had to be in his mid-20’s at least.</p>



<p><em>Acts 13:5 When they reached Salamis, they began to proclaim the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews; and they also had John as their helper.</em></p>



<p>We are informed in this text that John accompanied Barnabas and Saul on the first missionary journey.&nbsp; Nothing is said of this in the account in verses 1-3. In verse 4 it is Barnabas and Saul who are sent out by the Holy Spirit. They were the missionaries—not John Mark.</p>



<p>But, we are told, they had John as their “helper.” A great deal of discussion has taken place with regard to the exact role John occupied in the missionary band and what it meant for him to be their “helper.”&nbsp; Let me say a number of things about this that may help to clear up this question.</p>



<ul><li>First, let me tell you about the word, helper. Its literal meaning originally was <em>under-rower</em>. It referred to a very subordinate seaman—a rower of the lowest rank. But this meaning had probably receded into the background by Luke’s day.&nbsp; By then it simply emphasized that someone was an underling or subordinate.&nbsp; John is thus identified somewhat emphatically as the subordinate of Barnabas and Saul—one who supported them in their role as missionaries.</li><li>Second, consider what his subordinate-servant-helper role might have involved more specifically. <em>Well, actually I think it is wrong to be very specific.&nbsp; It involved many things and might have developed in important respects.</em> It certainly involved taking care of all the menial and mundane tasks that would have distracted Barnabas and Saul from their main ministerial and missionary responsibilities. What such tasks might have involved in that day and age I do not know exactly. But without telephones and laptops and internet there were no doubt many errands to be run, many messages to be carried, and many things to be purchased in the local marketplace.&nbsp;</li></ul>



<p>But did John Mark assist in more spiritual and ministerial ways?&nbsp; I think it is possible that he did.&nbsp; Certainly, if someone began to ask questions about the gospel, John Mark was, on the basis of his personal experience, in a position to answer many such questions.&nbsp; Though it is clear that he would not have been one of the main speakers and preachers, he likely would have occasionally assisted in such roles as well.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Furthermore, I think it is likely that in connection with such occasional, spiritual assistance that Barnabas and Saul intended John Mark’s traveling with them to be a maturing experience. They probably hoped that he would develop as a Christian minister and missionary.&nbsp; We do not need to assume that John Mark’s role was static.&nbsp; The goal might have been for him to assist at first mainly with the menial and mundane tasks of life that would distract Barnabas and Saul, but also under their mentoring gradually to develop as a minister of the gospel.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Now there is a word for this that we use in the church today.&nbsp; We call a person who fulfills a similar role an intern.&nbsp; We have a pastoral intern at GRBC. What does he do? The old joke is <em>Anything your pastors do not want to do</em>! More accurately I should say, anything that your pastors do not have time to do without distraction. He puts together the notes for the semi-annual meeting. He runs errands for us that we do not have time to take care of. He assists with and upgrades the website—a task that none of us can get to.&nbsp; He is a kind of diaconal assistant.&nbsp; But we also hope to see him develop as a minister of the gospel.&nbsp; Thus, he speaks at the nursing home for us.&nbsp; Thus also, he may teach an adult SS class or two for us in the near future.&nbsp; This is what our intern does.&nbsp; He is our own John Mark.&nbsp; Of course, we hope that he turns out better in his role than John Mark did in his. But that thought brings us to the third and last text of this third chapter of John Mark’s life.&nbsp; We will consider that text and the conclusion of this chapter of John Mark’s life in our next blog.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/chapter-3-mark/">Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/chapter-3-mark/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 2 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—Relation and Position in the Church at Jerusalem (Acts 12:12)</title>
		<link>/mark-career-3/</link>
					<comments>/mark-career-3/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 16:20:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15287</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chapter 2 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—Relation and Position in the Church at Jerusalem (Acts 12:12) We left John Mark huddled in his home in Jerusalem. We discover him again in the same exact location about twelve years later.&#160; Not only is the place the same, the occasion is similar.&#160; It is another occasion of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mark-career-3/">Chapter 2 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—Relation and Position in the Church at Jerusalem (Acts 12:12)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>Chapter 2 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—Relation and Position in the Church at Jerusalem (Acts 12:12)</h2>



<p>We left John Mark huddled in his home in Jerusalem. We discover him again in the same exact location about twelve years later.&nbsp; Not only is the place the same, the occasion is similar.&nbsp; It is another occasion of threatening persecution.&nbsp; Acts 12:12 reads: “And when he realized this, he went to the house of Mary, the mother of John who was also called Mark, where many were gathered together and were praying.”</p>



<p>Remember that James, the brother of John and one of the Sons of Thunder, had just before this prayer meeting been put to death by Herod.&nbsp; Peter himself had then been arrested and imprisoned just before Passover. This was the very same time of year that Jesus had been arrested.&nbsp; It was probably about twelve years later.&nbsp; Herod was probably waiting till after Passover to bring him to trial and then execution. Many Christians were gathered at the house of Mary the mother of John Mark to pray.&nbsp; This Mary must have been the aunt of Barnabas if John Mark was Barnabas’s cousin. I am persuaded that this was very likely the very house in the upper room of which the Last Supper had been held.&nbsp; Luke makes a point of introducing John Mark in his account of the early church on this occasion.&nbsp;</p>



<p>You see how deeply John Mark was associated with the church in Jerusalem.&nbsp; He occupied a deep relationship to and central place in the original church at Jerusalem and among the original disciples of Christ.&nbsp; If we understand that, then what happens next will not surprise us!</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mark-career-3/">Chapter 2 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—Relation and Position in the Church at Jerusalem (Acts 12:12)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mark-career-3/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Remarkable Career of John Mark and What It Says Especially To Pastors and Pastoral Students: Pt. 2 &#8211; His Probable and Improbable Escapade as a Young Man (Mark 14:51-52)</title>
		<link>/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/</link>
					<comments>/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 15:09:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15247</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>His Probable and Improbable Escapade as a Young Man (Mark 14:51-52) Look first at Mark 14:51-52: “A young man was following Him, wearing nothing but a linen sheet over his naked body; and they seized him. But he pulled free of the linen sheet and escaped naked.” The Mark referenced in the title of this [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">The Remarkable Career of John Mark and What It Says Especially To Pastors and Pastoral Students: Pt. 2 &#8211; His Probable and Improbable Escapade as a Young Man (Mark 14:51-52)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>His Probable and Improbable Escapade as a Young Man (Mark 14:51-52)</h2>



<p>Look first at Mark 14:51-52: “A young man was following Him, wearing nothing but a linen sheet over his naked body; and they seized him. But he pulled free of the linen sheet and escaped naked.” The Mark referenced in the title of this gospel is, of course, John Mark.&nbsp; We will look later at the reasons why we say this and the significance of this, but right now it is important because it impacts the interpretation of these somewhat obscure verses.</p>



<p>I have called this escapade or peculiar incident <strong><em>both probable and improbable</em></strong>.&nbsp; Let me explain why.</p>



<p><strong><em>It is probable in the sense that this is probably Mark’s own cryptic reference to himself in his gospel. </em></strong>Why do I say this?&nbsp; Why do I believe that this a reference to John Mark himself? My foundation for believing this is that this story is found in the Gospel of Mark himself.</p>



<ul><li>There are similar cryptic references in the Gospel of John to John the author of that gospel.&nbsp; Cf. John 19:26-27. Just as John did not name himself in his gospel, so also modesty forbid Mark to say with reference to the young man in this story, “This young man was I.”</li><li>This account of the young man fleeing naked from the Garden of Gethsemane is only given in Mark.&nbsp; The implication is that this incident had some particular importance for Mark. That particular importance is easily explained if the young man was Mark himself.&nbsp; Hendriksen says: “Neither Matthew nor Luke has retained this item. It does not appear to have been of special interest to them. But to Mark, to him alone, it was of sufficient importance to be included in the Gospel. This is understandable if he himself was that young man.”</li><li>The story told here of the young man really does seem a somewhat strange thing to include in the gospel story. What might be important about this crazy and madcap story of a young man streaking naked late at night through the streets of Jerusalem? This strangeness disappears, however, if the young man was Mark himself.&nbsp; Once more Hendriksen remarks: “By itself the item is rather insignificant, except if it refers to what the author, Mark, himself experienced that solemn night.”</li></ul>



<p>Bottom-line?&nbsp; This young man was probably John Mark himself. That is the most <strong><em>probable</em></strong> interpretation of the passage. On the other hand …</p>



<p><strong><em>It is improbable, because this story contains details which are strange and peculiar.</em></strong>&nbsp; Let me just recount it, and you will see what I mean.&nbsp; The setting of this story in the Gospel of Mark follows the account of the Garden of Gethsemane. That ended, you remember, with the flight of the disciples after Jesus’s arrest. We are then told that another follower of Jesus was there in the Garden. He had sneaked off from his home after the Last Supper following Jesus and the eleven.&nbsp; Most likely he had been in bed asleep or trying to sleep when he heard them all leaving.&nbsp; This means that the very old tradition that the Last Supper was held in the home of Mary the mother of John Mark is probably true.&nbsp; If he had been in bed in the very house where the Last Supper was held by Jesus and his disciples, this would explain both the fact that he follows Jesus and the eleven and that he was wearing nothing but a linen.&nbsp; That is the broad meaning of the Greek word used here. This linen was either a linen bed sheet; or it could also possibly be a linen undergarment or even pajamas. Cf. the use of this word in Proverbs 31:24 (where it means garment) and Luke 23:53 (where it is used of the sheet in which Jesus body was wrapped.) This very young man followed Jesus and the eleven. He saw the arrest of Jesus and the flight of the disciples from the darkness of his hiding place.&nbsp; Then he was spotted by someone in the crowd sent to arrest Jesus.&nbsp; They actually seized him and got their hands on him.&nbsp; But slipping off his linen (whether it was a sheet, undergarment, or pajamas), he was able to escape.&nbsp; His escape was both dramatic and accomplished with not a little agility and dexterity. It was also entirely lacking in dignity. We are forced to imagine him late at night streaking stark naked through the streets of Jerusalem and finally rushing into his home and perhaps huddling and shuddering in bed from the near and close escape.&nbsp; Now certainly this is a weird, wacky, and bizarre story that makes us shake our heads and, in spite of the seriousness of the event of Jesus’ death, smile at the naked streaker as he flees from the Garden through the streets of Jerualem to his home.</p>



<p><strong>What are we supposed to make of all this practically? &nbsp;</strong>Why does Mark include this account? Of course, it had personal importance for him, but he must have felt it was significant for his readers as well. Why did he think it was important to include in his account of the gospel?</p>



<ul><li>John Mark is confessing humbly his own fear and flight. Perhaps he is deprecating himself by making a little joke at his own expense. At any rate, he is saying that like the other disciples he too had been a spiritual coward. He also had fled the scene of Jesus’s capture and abandoned the Savior.</li><li>At the same time, perhaps he felt that his escape, cowardly though it was, was also due to the providential protection of God who allowed the other disciples to escape as well. Jesus had told the crowd which had come to arrest him to let his disciples go (John 18:8). Mark no doubt saw his escape as arranged also by the providence of the Son of God. He wants to glorify God for his escape.</li><li>Another spiritual lesson of this account would surely be to underscore the majestic bravery of Jesus as compared to the fearfulness of His disciples.&nbsp; Hendriksen speaks in this connection of the “unshakable and majestic composure of Jesus.”</li><li>But more directly to our purposes, we begin to learn something about John Mark.&nbsp; He is a young disciple growing up in the very middle of the historical revelation of the gospel. He is there at the Last Supper—at least in the house.&nbsp; He is there in the Garden of Gethsemane.&nbsp; He is a witness, though not in the same sense as the apostles of Christ, of the original facts of the gospel.&nbsp; He is also revealed to be what we might call a curious coward.&nbsp; He is inquisitive and adventurous enough to follow Jesus to the Garden of Gethsemane late at night. Yet he is a fickle and fearful young man. At the cost of the loss of his dignity and self-respect, he runs away from the arrest of Jesus and abandons him.</li></ul>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">The Remarkable Career of John Mark and What It Says Especially To Pastors and Pastoral Students: Pt. 2 &#8211; His Probable and Improbable Escapade as a Young Man (Mark 14:51-52)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Remarkable Career of John Mark And What it Says Especially to Pastors &#038; Pastoral Students: Pt. 1 &#8211; The Bible Tells Stories About People</title>
		<link>/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/</link>
					<comments>/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 22:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Mark]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pastors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Students]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15185</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Bible Tells Stories About People One of the special things about the Bible is that it tells stories—stories not just about God, but about human beings. This makes it much more interesting actually than the Koran which simply provides saying after saying and is in my opinion not only terribly wrong but deadly boring.&#160; [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">The Remarkable Career of John Mark And What it Says Especially to Pastors &#038; Pastoral Students: Pt. 1 &#8211; The Bible Tells Stories About People</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>The Bible Tells Stories About People</h2>



<p>One of the special things about the Bible is that it tells stories—stories not just about God, but about human beings. This makes it much more interesting actually than the Koran which simply provides saying after saying and is in my opinion not only terribly wrong but deadly boring.&nbsp; Usually stories in the Bible about particular persons are told in one book.&nbsp; Sometimes you will get the same story in two books of the Bible.&nbsp; Occasionally, as in the supremely important story of the Christ, these stories are told in four gospels.</p>



<p>But the story of the person I want to talk about in this blog series is actually told in bits and pieces across the New Testament. It is not told in any one, continued account. These bits and pieces of the story I have in mind are told in six books of the New Testament.&nbsp; This is the unusual way in which the Holy Spirit decided to tell the story of the man called, John Mark.</p>



<p>I have been preaching on the Book of Acts on and off for a couple of years now to GRBC Owensboro.&nbsp; Recently, I took the time to enlarge on the little statement in Acts 13:5 about John Mark. It reads as follows: “When they reached Salamis, they began to proclaim the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews; and they also had John as their helper.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>As I have studied the references to this man in the New Testament, I have divided the story told of his life into seven chapters.&nbsp; I have entitled them, <em>The Remarkable Career of John Mark.</em>&nbsp; But before I come to that, there are a couple of things to be said by way of introduction:</p>



<p>The first thing is that there are actually four different Johns in the New Testament.&nbsp;</p>



<ul><li>The first and least known John is the father of Simon Peter. He is only mentioned in the Gospel of John. Cf. John 1:42; 21:15-17.</li><li>The second is well-known. It is John the Baptist, the forerunner of Jesus.&nbsp; He is the son of Zacharias and Elizabeth, the relative of Mary, the mother of Jesus.</li><li>There is John the Apostle, the brother of James.&nbsp; James and John were “the Sons of Thunder” and the sons of Zebedee.</li><li>There is also John Mark. As we will discover, he was the cousin of Barnabas.</li></ul>



<p>We will discover a great deal about John Mark from the several mentions of him in the New Testament.&nbsp; But there is something else you need to know.</p>



<p><strong><em>John Mark is not always identified in the same way.</em></strong>&nbsp; There are passages that refer to him as John Mark (Acts 12:12, 25; 15:37). There are passages that refer to him as John (Acts 13:5; 13). And there are passages that refer to him simply as Mark (Acts 15:39; Col. 4:10; Phm. 1:24; 2 Tim. 4:11; 1 Pet. 5:13). There is even a passage which I think speaks of him without giving us his name (Mark 14:51-52).</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">The Remarkable Career of John Mark And What it Says Especially to Pastors &#038; Pastoral Students: Pt. 1 &#8211; The Bible Tells Stories About People</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Private Rebuke</title>
		<link>/the-private-rebuke/</link>
					<comments>/the-private-rebuke/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 22:17:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Church Discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[church discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[practical theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13942</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In a previous post the subject of church discipline was considered and 6 introductory observations were given. In this post, step 1 of seeking forgiveness will be considered: The private individual rebuke. You can find the first post in the series here. Matthew 18:15 &#8211; &#8220;If your brother sins against you, go and tell him [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-private-rebuke/">The Private Rebuke</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>In a previous post the subject of church discipline was considered and 6 introductory observations were given. In this post, step 1 of seeking forgiveness will be considered: The private individual rebuke</em></strong><em>. </em><strong><em>You can find the first post in the series </em><a href="/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/"><em>here</em></a></strong><em>.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>Matthew 18:15 &#8211;  &#8220;If your brother sins against you, go and tell him his fault, between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained your brother.&#8221;</em></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is the first step of seeking forgiveness from a brother
or sister who has sinned against you. I want to consider this step under two
questions: first, what is to be done and second, where is it to be done?</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>1.) What is to be Done?</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The ESV reads, &#8220;if you brother sins against you, go and tell
him his fault.&#8221; I think this translation is a bit too soft. It least it can be
taken that way. The Greek actually says, &#8220;If your brother sins against you, go
rebuke or reprove him.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The word &#8220;reprove&#8221; means to expose and convict someone of
his or her sin. The Bible teaches that reproving someone is what the three
Persons of the Godhead do.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is something Christ does: </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Hebrews 12:5</strong> says, &#8220;And have you forgotten the exhortation that addresses you as sons? &#8216;My son, do not regard lightly the discipline of the Lord, nor be weary <strong>when reproved</strong> by Him.&#8217;&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>He says to the church in Laodicea in <strong>Revelation 3:19:</strong>
&#8220;Those whom I love, <strong>I reprove</strong> and discipline, so be zealous and repent.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is something that the teaching of Jesus Christ does: <strong>John
3:20:</strong> For everyone who does wicked things hates the light and does not come
to the light, lest his works should <strong>be exposed</strong>.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If you come to the light, if you allow the words of Christ
to shine upon your heart and your actions, it will all be exposed. Nothing will
remain hidden any longer.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is something the Holy Spirit does when He is sent to
the earth: <strong>John 16:8:</strong> And when He comes, He <strong>will convict</strong> the
world concerning sin and righteousness and judgment:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is something the law of God does: <strong>James 2:9:</strong> But
if you show partiality, you are committing sin and <strong>are convicted</strong> by the
law as transgressors.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>And this is something God does to the wicked: <strong>Psalm
50:21:</strong> These things you have done, and I have been silent; you thought that
I was one like yourself. But now <strong>I rebuke</strong> you and lay the charge before
you.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>God is rebuking the wicked by bringing his case against the
wicked and laying out their wicked crimes against Him.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, rebuking or reproving someone, in the context of Matthew
18, is more than just telling that person his fault. It means to formally
accuse someone of wrongdoing. You are not to take someone to court over this,
but your meeting should be court-like. It should reflect the very justice and
judgment of God.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Your judgment should align with God&#8217;s judgment. You should
have sufficient proof based on God&#8217;s law that someone has done wrong to you,
and then you should go and issue a formal complaint against that person. So,
the burden is on you to possess convincing and compelling evidence that someone
has indeed sinned against you. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>It can&#8217;t just be that I <em>think</em> you have sinned against
me, or I <em>feel</em> like you have sinned against me, or it <em>seems</em> like
you have sinned against me. No. It must be, &#8220;I have proof you have sinned
against me and here it is.&#8221; Your accusation has to hold up not just in the
court of public opinion but in the court of God&#8217;s law. If it doesn&#8217;t, your case
against the brother or sister must be thrown out.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>The Grounds for Rebuke &#8211; the Law of God</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There is a great lesson here for us. And it&#8217;s this: if you
are going to seek forgiveness with someone, make sure they have sinned against
you. Jesus says, &#8220;If your brother<strong> sins</strong> against you, go and tell him his
fault.&#8221; The key word here is &#8220;sins.&#8221; He didn&#8217;t say, &#8220;If your brother offends
you or irritates you or annoys you or makes you feel bad or crosses your
traditions and customs or goes against your counsel and advice.&#8221; Maybe it&#8217;s not
the best thing for a person to do those things, but you can only rebuke someone
and start the process of church discipline if he or she breaks the law of God
against you &#8211; if he or she violates one of the 6 commandments contained in the
second table of the law. If that person does not love you in a biblical way
according to the law of God, then you have a right to go to that person and
tell him his fault. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>We should thank and praise God for this! God has not left us
in the dark to come up with our own definition of sin. He has graciously given
us an objective, everlasting standard which is outside of us to know if someone
has sinned against us. It is written down for all of us to read and examine in
the Bible.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If this wasn&#8217;t the case, just think how dysfunctional the
church would be. If we didn&#8217;t have the written law of God to tell us what
righteousness is and what sin is, we would be accusing one another left and
right of all kinds of things that aren&#8217;t actually sinful.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There would be so much chaos in the church, especially in
today&#8217;s church where so many people simply emote. They don&#8217;t think; they don&#8217;t
consider; they don&#8217;t weigh the evidence; they don&#8217;t exercise self-control; they
simply are led by their emotions. Their feelings become their truth. And if
they feel like they have been sinned against, well, how dare we question that
they have indeed been sinned against! We are told to respect their version of
truth as truth! Well, as one country singer says, &#8220;That ain&#8217;t gonna fly,&#8221; and
that ain&#8217;t gonna fly in the church!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If your grievance with another brother or sister isn&#8217;t
according to the biblical definition of sin, Jesus&#8217; teaching here doesn&#8217;t apply
to your case. I&#8217;m sorry, it just doesn&#8217;t. You can still go talk to that person.
You can still share with that person how you feel and how you can better dwell
in peace and unity with one another, but you would be the one in sin if you
unrighteously accused someone of something that isn&#8217;t really sinful.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, we should praise God for this, and we should be very
careful about bringing a formal accusation against another brother or sister in
Christ.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>2.) Where is it to be Done?</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus teaches that this is to be a one-on-one, face-to-face
private meeting. You are to go and rebuke the person to his face. Jesus said,
&#8220;go and tell him.&#8221; He did not say, &#8220;Sit back and write a letter to him&#8221; or in
our modern times &#8220;call him or text him or Facebook-message him.&#8221; For something
as serious as this, those forms of communication are too impersonal. This needs
to be said while looking the offender in the eye.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus also did not say, &#8220;Go and appoint a representative to
bring the complaint to the person you think has sinned against you, whether it
be your pastors or a trustworthy friend.&#8221; No, He says, &#8220;You (in the singular)
go.&#8221; In other words, go by yourself. &#8220;Go&#8221; here can mean &#8220;to depart&#8221; or &#8220;to
withdraw&#8221; to a place. In other words, going means sinking out of sight and
having this conversation covered in secrecy so others won&#8217;t know the contents
of your conversation. But Jesus explicitly teaches this rebuke must be private
when He says to rebuke your brother &#8220;between you and him alone.&#8221; Since this is
a private sin, it should be a private confrontation. No one else is to be
involved at this time. You are the offended party, the sin was against you in
particular, and it is your responsibility to go confront that person privately.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus is not teaching something new here. Confronting
someone privately concerning his or her sin against you is the very essence of
love taught in the Old Testament. This is what it means to love your neighbor
as himself. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Leviticus 19:17-18 (HCSB)</strong> says, &#8220;You must not harbor hatred against your brother. Rebuke [same Greek verb is used in Matthew 18:15] your neighbor directly, and you will not incur guilt because of him. 18Do not take revenge or bear a grudge against members of your community, but love your neighbor as yourself; I am Yahweh.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Proverbs 25:8-10:</strong> &#8220;8do not hastily bring into court, for what will you do in the end, when your neighbor puts you to shame? 9Argue your case with your neighbor himself, and do not reveal another&#8217;s secret, 10lest he who hears you bring shame upon you, and your ill repute have no end.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>A great illustration of this is Joseph&#8217;s actions against
Mary, whom he was betrothed to. After she became pregnant by the powerful work
of the Holy Spirit, Joseph incorrectly thought she had committed sexual
immorality against him. But what did he do? Tell the whole world? No. He kept
the matter private. <strong>Matthew 1:19</strong> says, &#8220;And her husband Joseph, being a
just man and unwilling to put her to shame, resolved to divorce her quietly.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>We are not to blow up, not to refuse to talk to them, not to
gossip by telling everybody else about their sins, but to talk to them and seek
forgiveness and reconciliation privately.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Reconciliation Means the Sin Remains Private</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Be careful not to make public another person&#8217;s sins which
have been dealt with privately. If step 1 has born fruit and the brother or
sister has listened to you and has repented, you have won him or her back to
the truth, it all ends there. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There is not a step 2. And there is certainly not a step 3
or 4. The process is over. Reconciliation has occurred! And since the process
is over, going around and telling others about how badly that person sinned
against you is wicked, cruel, and not in line with loving your fellow
Christian. The goal of step 1 is to cover sins, not expose them for all to see.
It is to bury the hatchet, not to use the hatchet as a weapon to hack up your
reconciled brother in Christ. As <strong>Proverbs 17:9</strong> says, &#8220;Whoever covers an
offense seeks love, but he who repeats a matter separates close friends.&#8221; Or as
<strong>1 Peter 4:8</strong> says, &#8220;Love covers a multitude of sins.&#8221; If forgiveness has
been established, in a qualified sense you need to forget that it ever
happened. You need to let it die. That person&#8217;s dirty laundry has already been
washed and cleansed by the blood of Christ. The sin has been dealt with and you
have won your brother back. Hallelujah! At the very least, you need to make
sure it never becomes the topic of conversation with others.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Confront the Brother Yourself</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Make sure to confront someone privately about his or her sin
before telling others about it. When someone sins against you, what is the
first thing you do? Pray? Check your own heart to make sure you are not
overreacting or being overly emotional? Search the Scriptures? Go directly to
that person?</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Or do you tell another person about it? Do you let your
spouse know? Or your parents know? Or your closest friends know? Or do you post
it on Facebook for everyone to know? And do you do this without ever going to
that person?</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Hopefully you understand how terribly childish this sort of
approach is when you deal with someone who has wronged you. But it is so easy
to do because it&#8217;s extremely hard to confront someone. For some here, it may be
the most difficult thing you will ever have to do. None of us enjoy confronting
ourselves about our own sins, let alone confronting another person about his or
her sins.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>I will say this: if you come to one of your pastors &amp; tell them about how someone has sinned against you, you should hear this counsel from them every time: &#8220;Have you gone to that person first? Have you followed the first step of seeking forgiveness laid out for you in Matthew 18:15?&#8221; If not, we are not going to say anything else to you. If we want to be faithful to Christ&#8217;s commands, we can&#8217;t say anything else to you. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, you have to confront that person yourself. That takes
courage. That takes strength. That takes faith. Cry out to God for these
graces, and obey Christ&#8217;s commandment and go lovingly rebuke that person to his
face. It may be one of the best things you ever do!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>When You Are the Offender</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If you have sinned against another, go tell that offended
brother or sister your own fault. It&#8217;s a sad thing that discipline has to be
taken to step 2, 3, and even 4 in some cases. It should remain at step 1. In
fact, it shouldn&#8217;t even have to get to step 1. If you have sinned against
someone, you should go to that person yourself and ask for forgiveness. Why
wait for the person to come to you? Why does he have to hunt you down and
confront you about your sin against him? Go and make things right yourself!
Repent and humble yourself and seek that person&#8217;s forgiveness!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Something is not right with your heart if you can sin
against someone without your conscience cutting you down and compelling you to
go make things right. How can a believer go through life knowing that he has
deeply hurt and offended another believer without seeking his forgiveness?</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is the very teaching of Christ. In <strong>Matthew 5:23-24</strong>,
He says, &#8220;23So if you are offering your gift at the altar and there remember
that your brother has something against you, 24leave your gift there before the
altar and go. First be reconciled to your brother, and then come and offer your
gift.&#8221; God will not accept your worship until you make things right with your
offended brother. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But if you have really sinned against a person and he or she
confronts you, you should love that person.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>You shouldn&#8217;t get angry at that person. He or she had the
courage to say something to you &amp; the love to pursue you when you were
doing astray. You should praise God for that person and thank him or her for
dealing honestly * faithfully with your soul. As the Scriptures say, it is for
your benefit &amp; blessing.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Prov. 9:8-9:</strong> 8Do not reprove a scoffer, or he will hate you; reprove a wise man, &amp; he will love you. 9Give instruction to a wise man, &amp; he will be still wiser; teach a righteous man, &amp; he will increase in learning.</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Psalm 141:5:</strong> Let a righteous man strike me- it is a kindness; let him rebuke [same Greek verb used in Matthew 18:15] me- it is oil for my head; let my head not refuse it. Yet my prayer is continually against their evil deeds.</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Prov. 27:6:</strong> Faithful are the wounds of a friend; profuse are the kisses of an enemy.</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Lord-willing, in future posts we will consider steps 2-4. May God bless the preaching of His Word to the building up of His church, through Jesus Christ our Lord, to whom be honor and glory forever and ever. Amen. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-private-rebuke/">The Private Rebuke</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-private-rebuke/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
