<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Ben Carlson | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/author/ben/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 16:24:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Ben Carlson | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 2 of 2]: Analysis and Conclusion</title>
		<link>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/</link>
					<comments>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 15:51:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15601</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ben CarlsonBen has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 2 of 2]: Analysis and Conclusion</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_0 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_0">
								<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_0  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_0  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><em>This is part 2 of a 2 part series on Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology. You can read part 1 <a href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/">here</a></em>.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>II.) Analysis of Calvin’s Teaching on Natural Theology</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>1.) Calvin clearly distinguishes between natural revelation and natural theology.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

For Calvin, there is a substantial difference between the reality of the knowledge of God in the universe and the use of the knowledge of God by sinful man. The reality that God clearly and continually reveals Himself to man as Creator within him and around him is called natural or general revelation. The interpretation and use of that knowledge by men, who in this fallen world are enslaved in sin, is called natural theology. This is their creaturely attempt to interpret and understand general revelation (the knowledge of God in creation) without the help or aid of special revelation (the knowledge of God in Scripture). It is important to highlight the differences if we would correctly understand Calvin’s thought.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>2.) Calvin teaches that since natural revelation is so distorted and corrupted by fallen man, natural theology is a futile endeavor that leads one to a throng of feigned gods but never to the true God.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

God’s revelation of Himself in creation is meant to be a teacher and guide to men to point out the right way (1:5:15). Ideally, all image bearers of God would rightly respond to this knowledge. Yet Calvin is clear that because of sin, man lacks the ability to come to a knowledge of God worthy of the name. With only natural reasoning and common understanding as his guide, sinful man poisons and corrupts natural revelation to such an extent that by itself it only produces the worst possible fruits in him. According to Calvin, no matter if one is chieftain of the whole tribe of philosophers or the worst of the vulgar folk, the best that natural theology can do is lead one to the worship of an unknown god. Therefore, the true knowledge of God cannot be grasped by fallen man on the basis of natural revelation. There must be another way.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>3.) Calvin teaches that special revelation, or the Scriptures, is necessary not only to properly understand the knowledge of God in salvation but also to properly understand the knowledge of God in creation.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

The Bible not only teaches us about God the Redeemer. It also teaches us about God the Creator. In addition to the Book of Nature, the Scriptures are another and better help “which direct us aright to the very Creator of the Universe” and “clearly shows us the true God” (1:6:1). In fact, without their aid and assistance, “the human mind because of its feebleness can in no way attain to God” (1:6:4). In order to do this, we need the spectacles of special revelation (1:6:1). As Calvin says, “We must come, I say, to the Word, where God is truly and vividly described to us from his works, while these very works are appraised not by our depraved judgment but by the rule of eternal truth. If we turn aside from the Word, as I have just now said, though we may strive with strenuous haste, yet, since we have got off the track, we shall never reach the goal. For we should so reason that the splendor of the divine countenance, which even the apostle calls ‘unapproachable’ [I Tim. 6:16], is for us like an inexplicable labyrinth unless we are conducted into it by the thread of the Word; so that it is better to limp along this path than to dash with all speed outside it” (1:6:3). And, “Now, in order that true religion may shine upon us, we ought to hold that it must take its beginning from heavenly doctrine and that no one can get even the slightest taste of right and sound doctrine unless he be a pupil of Scripture” (1:6:2).

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>4.) Calvin teaches that using evidences apart from Scripture as proofs for God’s existence is unnecessary.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

Since men do not need to be taught about God in the classroom but are masters of divinity from their mothers’ wombs (1:3:3), and since men suppress any knowledge of God they do possess by nature, the attempt to prove the existence of God from natural theology is unnecessary.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

We see that no long or toilsome proof is needed to elicit evidences that serve to illuminate and affirm the divine majesty; since from the few we have sampled at random, whithersoever you turn, it is clear that they are so very manifest and obvious that they can easily be observed with the eyes and pointed out with the finger. (1:5:9)

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

What is necessary, however, is faith.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

It is therefore in vain that so many burning lamps shine for us in the workmanship of the universe to show forth the glory of its Author. Although they bathe us wholly in their radiance, yet they can of themselves in no way lead us into the right path. Surely they strike some sparks, but before their fuller light shines forth these are smothered. For this reason, the apostle, in that very passage where he calls the worlds the images of things invisible, adds that through faith we understand that they have been fashioned by God’s word [Heb. 11:3]. He means by this that the invisible divinity is made manifest in such spectacles, but that we have not the eyes to see this unless they be illumined by the inner revelation of God through faith. (1:5:14)

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>III.) Conclusion from Calvin’s Teaching on Natural Theology</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

After surveying the evidence, Calvin is highly critical of any teaching that ascribes to sinful man sound reasoning concerning the knowledge of God. He cannot be any plainer in his assessment: “Human reason, therefore, neither approaches, nor strives toward, nor even takes a straight aim at, this truth: to understand who the true God is or what sort of God he wishes to be toward us” (2:2:18). Yet the natural theology propounded by the medieval scholastics teaches that human reason can do just that. How biblical this teaching is should be addressed exegetically from the relevant passages of Scripture. But from a historical standpoint, it seems clear from Calvin’s own critique of natural theology that it was not consistent with the views of Reformed theology, especially with the teaching on man’s fallen and depraved state.

<!-- /wp:paragraph --></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->			
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->		
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 2 of 2]: Analysis and Conclusion</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 1 of 2]: Summary</title>
		<link>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/</link>
					<comments>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 20:11:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15583</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ben Carlson Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 1 of 2]: Summary</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_1 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_1">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_1  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_1  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p><em>This is part 1 of a 2 part series on Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology. You can read part 2 <a href="http://calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/">here</a></em>.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>What was Calvin’s view of natural theology? That is an important question to ask today, especially in light of the discussions and debates taking place concerning the legitimacy of natural theology within Reformed epistemology and apologetics.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>One of the clearest places in the <em>Institutes</em> where Calvin’s evaluation of natural theology can be found is in Book 1, Chapter 5, Section 12. There he states, “Yet hence it appears that if men were taught only by nature, they would hold to nothing certain or solid or clear-cut, but would be so tied to confused principles as to worship an unknown god [cf. Acts 17:23].”</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>John T. McNeill, the editor of Ford Lewis Battles’ translation of the <em>Institutes</em>, makes this noteworthy remark in a footnote after Calvin’s words: “Natural theology (human reasoning about God, under the conditions of sin, unaided by special revelation) has been the subject of this chapter through section 12. All scholars agree that the above words present Calvin’s verdict upon it, held consistently in all his writings.”</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>In this brief essay, I will attempt to lay out Calvin’ critique of natural theology by first summarizing his teaching on the subject from the first six chapters of Book 1, second by analyzing his teaching, and third by offering a concluding thought. As “the theologian” of the Reformation, Calvin gives us a pivotal perspective concerning natural theology that aligns with his teachings on the doctrines of God, man, sin, Scripture, and grace. Therefore, his evaluation needs to be carefully read and understood.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>I.) Summary of Calvin’s Teaching on Natural Theology</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>1.) Calvin states that natural revelation is unmistakably and unfailingly clear to man.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Calvin argues that natural revelation, or the knowledge of God as Creator, Governor, and Judge of the world, is both inscribed on man’s heart and proclaimed throughout the universe.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>First, Calvin says that all men have an awareness of divinity, seed of religion, sense of deity, sort of divinity, and signs of immorality implanted and inscribed by God in their souls. This is the innate, inward, undeniable, and indelible knowledge of God as Creator. All men undoubtedly know Him as such and have no excuse to claim ignorance.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>There is within the human mind, and indeed by natural instinct, an awareness of divinity. This we take to be beyond controversy. To prevent anyone from taking refuge in the pretense of ignorance, God himself has implanted in all men a certain understanding of his divine majesty. (1:3:1)</p>
<p>And they who in other aspects of life seem least to differ from brutes still continue to retain some seed of religion. (1:3:1)</p>
<p>Therefore, since from the beginning of the world there has been no region, no city, in short, no household that could do without religion, there lies in this a tacit confession of a sense of deity inscribed in the hearts of all. (1:3:1)</p>
<p>Men of sound judgment will always be sure that a sense of divinity which can never be effaced is engraved upon men’s minds. (1:3:2)</p>
<p>.  . . that there is some God, is naturally inborn in all, and is fixed deep within, as it were in the very marrow. (1:3:3)</p>
<p>From this we conclude that it is not a doctrine that must first be learned in school, but one which each of us is master from his mother’s womb and which nature itself permits no one to forget, although many strive with every nerve to this end. (1:3:3)</p>
<p>As experience shows, God has sown a seed of religion in all men. (1:4:1)</p>
<p>Yet that seed remains which can in no wise be uprooted: that there is some sort of divinity. (1:4:4)</p>
<p>From this, my present contention is brought out with greater certainty, that a sense of divinity is by nature engraven on human hearts. (1:4:4)</p>
<p>These are unfailing signs of divinity in man. (1:5:5)</p>
<p>What ought we to say here except that the signs of immortality which have been implanted in man cannot be effaced? (1:5:5)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Second, Calvin states that all men are constantly confronted with the knowledge of God as Creator from the dazzling theater of His glory (1:5:8) that He has placed them in as spectators (1:6:2).</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>The final goal of the blessed life, moreover, rests in the knowledge of God [cf. John 17:3]. Lest anyone, then, be excluded from access to happiness, he not only sowed in men’s minds that seed of religion of which we have spoken but revealed himself and daily discloses himself in the whole workmanship of the universe. As a consequence, men cannot open their eyes without being compelled to see him. . . . But upon his individual works he has engraved unmistakable marks of his glory, so clear and so prominent that even unlettered and stupid folk cannot plead the excuse of ignorance. (1:5:1)</p>
<p>Yet, in the first place, wherever you cast your eyes, there is no spot in the universe wherein you cannot discern at least some sparks of his glory. (1:5:1)</p>
<p>There are innumerable evidences both in heaven and on earth that declare his wonderful wisdom; . . . Even the common folk and the most untutored, who have been taught only by the aid of the eyes, cannot be unaware of the excellence of divine art, for it reveals itself in this innumerable and yet distinct and well-ordered variety of the heavenly host. It is, accordingly, clear that there is no one to whom the Lord does not abundantly show his wisdom. (1:5:2)</p>
<p>Therefore, however fitting it may be for man seriously to turn his eyes to contemplate God’s works, since he has been placed in this most glorious theater to be a spectator of them, . . . (1:6:2)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>2.) Calvin states that natural revelation should teach man to fear, love, trust, and hope in God.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Calvin is clear that the knowledge of God in creation has a purpose, and that purpose is to greatly benefit man.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>For this sense of the powers of God is for us a fit teacher of piety, from which religion is born. I call “piety” that reverence joined with love of God which the knowledge of his benefits induces. (1:2:1)</p>
<p>Rather, our knowledge should serve first to teach us fear and reverence; secondly, with it as our guide and teacher, we should learn to seek every good from him, and, having received it, to credit it to his account. . . . Again, you cannot behold him clearly unless you acknowledge him to be the fountainhead and source of every good. From this too would arise the desire to cleave to him and trust in him . . . (1:2:2)</p>
<p>Knowledge of this sort, then, ought not only to arouse us to the worship of God but also to awaken and encourage us to the hope of the future life. (1:5:10)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>3.) Calvin states that natural revelation is unprofitable for sinful man.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Although the knowledge of God as Creator in creation should greatly benefit man, Calvin states that in a fallen world it does no such thing because of man’s sinfulness and blindness to the truth. Instead, with it man falls into superstitions, deserts God, or lives hypocritically. No matter the person, fallen man’s interpretation and response to natural revelation “corrupt by vanity the pure truth of God” (1:5:11) and “seduce[] his mind from rightly seeking him” (1:2:2).</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>But although the Lord represents both himself and his everlasting Kingdom in the mirror of his works with very great clarity, such is our stupidity that we grow increasingly dull toward so manifest testimonies, and they flow away without profiting us. (1:5:11)</p>
<p>Besides while some may evaporate in their own superstitions and others deliberately and wickedly desert God, yet all degenerate from the true knowledge of him. And so it happens that no real piety remains in the world. (1:4:1)</p>
<p>They see such exquisite workmanship in their individual members, from mouth and eyes even to their very toenails. Here also they substitute nature for God. (1:5:4)</p>
<p>Finally, they entangle themselves in such a huge mass of errors that blind wickedness stifles and finally extinguishes those sparks which once flashed forth to show them God’s glory. Yet that seed remains which can in no wise be uprooted: that there is some sort of divinity; but this seed is so corrupted that by itself it produces only the worst fruits. (1:5:4)</p>
<p>Sometimes we are driven by leading and direction of these things to contemplate God; this of necessity happens to all men. Yet after we rashly grasp a conception of some sort of divinity, straightway we fall back into the ravings or evil imaginings of our flesh, and corrupt by our vanity the pure truth of God. In one respect we are indeed unalike, because each one of us privately forges his own particular error; yet we are very much alike in that, one and all, we forsake the one true God for prodigious trifles. Not only the common folk and dull-witted men, but also the most excellent and those otherwise endowed with keen discernment, are infected with this disease. In this regard how volubly has the whole tribe of philosophers shown their stupidity and silliness! (1:5:11)</p>
<p>It is therefore in vain that so many burning lamps shine for us in the workmanship of the universe to show forth the glory of its Author. Although they bathe us wholly in their radiance, yet they can of themselves in no way lead us into the right path. Surely they strike some speaks, but before their fuller light shines forth these are smothered. (1:5:14)</p>
<p>Therefore, although the Lord does not want for testimony while he sweetly attracts men to the knowledge of himself with many and varied kindnesses, they do not cease on this account to follow their own ways, that is, their fatal errors. (1:5:14)</p>
<p>But, however that may be, yet the fact that men soon corrupt the seed of the knowledge of God, sown in their minds out of the wonderful workmanship of nature (thus preventing it from coming to a good and perfect fruit), must be imputed to their own failing; (1:5:15)</p>
<p>For at the same time as we have enjoyed a slight taste of the divine from contemplation of the universe, having neglected the true God, we raise up in his stead dreams and specters of our own brains, and attribute to anything else than the true source the praise of righteousness, wisdom, goodness, and power. Moreover, we so obscure or overturn his daily acts by wickedly judging them that we snatch away from them their glory and from their Author his due praise. (1:5:15)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>4.) Calvin states that natural theology is useless for sinful man.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Calvin argues that sinful man can never attain the true and pure knowledge of God with his depraved understanding. In other words, natural theology, or the ability of man to truly know and positively respond to God’s natural revelation, in a fallen world leads only to confused principles and a diversity of opinions about God, none of which are correct.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>But among the philosophers who have tried with reason and learning to penetrate into heaven, how shameful is the diversity! (1:5:12)</p>
<p>. . . but no mortal ever contrived anything that did not basely corrupt religion. (1:5:12)</p>
<p>But since all confess that there is nothing concerning which the learned and the unlearned at the same time disagree so much, hence one may conclude that the minds of men which thus wander in their search after God are more than stupid and blind in the heavenly mysteries. (1:5:12)</p>
<p>Yet hence it appears that if men were taught only by nature, they would hold to nothing certain or solid or clear-cut, but would be so tied to confused principles as to worship an unknown god [cf. Acts 17:23]. (1:5:12)</p>
<p>In short, even if not all suffered under crass vice, or fell into open idolatries, yet there was no pure and approved religion, found upon common understanding alone. For even though few persons did not share in the madness of the common herd, there remains the firm teaching of Paul that the wisdom of God is not understood by the princes of this world [I Cor. 2:8]. But if even the most illustrious wander in darkness, what can we say of the dregs? (1:5:13)</p>
<p>But although we lack the natural ability to mount up unto the pure and clear knowledge of God, all excuse is cut off because the fault of dullness is within us. (1:5:15)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>In the next post, I will present some analysis of Calvin&#8217;s teaching on Natural Theology.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 1 of 2]: Summary</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Private Rebuke</title>
		<link>/the-private-rebuke/</link>
					<comments>/the-private-rebuke/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 22:17:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Church Discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[church discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[practical theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13942</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In a previous post the subject of church discipline was considered and 6 introductory observations were given. In this post, step 1 of seeking forgiveness will be considered: The private individual rebuke. You can find the first post in the series here. Matthew 18:15 &#8211; &#8220;If your brother sins against you, go and tell him [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-private-rebuke/">The Private Rebuke</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>In a previous post the subject of church discipline was considered and 6 introductory observations were given. In this post, step 1 of seeking forgiveness will be considered: The private individual rebuke</em></strong><em>. </em><strong><em>You can find the first post in the series </em><a href="/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/"><em>here</em></a></strong><em>.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>Matthew 18:15 &#8211;  &#8220;If your brother sins against you, go and tell him his fault, between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained your brother.&#8221;</em></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is the first step of seeking forgiveness from a brother
or sister who has sinned against you. I want to consider this step under two
questions: first, what is to be done and second, where is it to be done?</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>1.) What is to be Done?</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The ESV reads, &#8220;if you brother sins against you, go and tell
him his fault.&#8221; I think this translation is a bit too soft. It least it can be
taken that way. The Greek actually says, &#8220;If your brother sins against you, go
rebuke or reprove him.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The word &#8220;reprove&#8221; means to expose and convict someone of
his or her sin. The Bible teaches that reproving someone is what the three
Persons of the Godhead do.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is something Christ does: </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Hebrews 12:5</strong> says, &#8220;And have you forgotten the exhortation that addresses you as sons? &#8216;My son, do not regard lightly the discipline of the Lord, nor be weary <strong>when reproved</strong> by Him.&#8217;&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>He says to the church in Laodicea in <strong>Revelation 3:19:</strong>
&#8220;Those whom I love, <strong>I reprove</strong> and discipline, so be zealous and repent.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is something that the teaching of Jesus Christ does: <strong>John
3:20:</strong> For everyone who does wicked things hates the light and does not come
to the light, lest his works should <strong>be exposed</strong>.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If you come to the light, if you allow the words of Christ
to shine upon your heart and your actions, it will all be exposed. Nothing will
remain hidden any longer.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is something the Holy Spirit does when He is sent to
the earth: <strong>John 16:8:</strong> And when He comes, He <strong>will convict</strong> the
world concerning sin and righteousness and judgment:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is something the law of God does: <strong>James 2:9:</strong> But
if you show partiality, you are committing sin and <strong>are convicted</strong> by the
law as transgressors.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>And this is something God does to the wicked: <strong>Psalm
50:21:</strong> These things you have done, and I have been silent; you thought that
I was one like yourself. But now <strong>I rebuke</strong> you and lay the charge before
you.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>God is rebuking the wicked by bringing his case against the
wicked and laying out their wicked crimes against Him.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, rebuking or reproving someone, in the context of Matthew
18, is more than just telling that person his fault. It means to formally
accuse someone of wrongdoing. You are not to take someone to court over this,
but your meeting should be court-like. It should reflect the very justice and
judgment of God.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Your judgment should align with God&#8217;s judgment. You should
have sufficient proof based on God&#8217;s law that someone has done wrong to you,
and then you should go and issue a formal complaint against that person. So,
the burden is on you to possess convincing and compelling evidence that someone
has indeed sinned against you. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>It can&#8217;t just be that I <em>think</em> you have sinned against
me, or I <em>feel</em> like you have sinned against me, or it <em>seems</em> like
you have sinned against me. No. It must be, &#8220;I have proof you have sinned
against me and here it is.&#8221; Your accusation has to hold up not just in the
court of public opinion but in the court of God&#8217;s law. If it doesn&#8217;t, your case
against the brother or sister must be thrown out.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>The Grounds for Rebuke &#8211; the Law of God</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There is a great lesson here for us. And it&#8217;s this: if you
are going to seek forgiveness with someone, make sure they have sinned against
you. Jesus says, &#8220;If your brother<strong> sins</strong> against you, go and tell him his
fault.&#8221; The key word here is &#8220;sins.&#8221; He didn&#8217;t say, &#8220;If your brother offends
you or irritates you or annoys you or makes you feel bad or crosses your
traditions and customs or goes against your counsel and advice.&#8221; Maybe it&#8217;s not
the best thing for a person to do those things, but you can only rebuke someone
and start the process of church discipline if he or she breaks the law of God
against you &#8211; if he or she violates one of the 6 commandments contained in the
second table of the law. If that person does not love you in a biblical way
according to the law of God, then you have a right to go to that person and
tell him his fault. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>We should thank and praise God for this! God has not left us
in the dark to come up with our own definition of sin. He has graciously given
us an objective, everlasting standard which is outside of us to know if someone
has sinned against us. It is written down for all of us to read and examine in
the Bible.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If this wasn&#8217;t the case, just think how dysfunctional the
church would be. If we didn&#8217;t have the written law of God to tell us what
righteousness is and what sin is, we would be accusing one another left and
right of all kinds of things that aren&#8217;t actually sinful.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There would be so much chaos in the church, especially in
today&#8217;s church where so many people simply emote. They don&#8217;t think; they don&#8217;t
consider; they don&#8217;t weigh the evidence; they don&#8217;t exercise self-control; they
simply are led by their emotions. Their feelings become their truth. And if
they feel like they have been sinned against, well, how dare we question that
they have indeed been sinned against! We are told to respect their version of
truth as truth! Well, as one country singer says, &#8220;That ain&#8217;t gonna fly,&#8221; and
that ain&#8217;t gonna fly in the church!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If your grievance with another brother or sister isn&#8217;t
according to the biblical definition of sin, Jesus&#8217; teaching here doesn&#8217;t apply
to your case. I&#8217;m sorry, it just doesn&#8217;t. You can still go talk to that person.
You can still share with that person how you feel and how you can better dwell
in peace and unity with one another, but you would be the one in sin if you
unrighteously accused someone of something that isn&#8217;t really sinful.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, we should praise God for this, and we should be very
careful about bringing a formal accusation against another brother or sister in
Christ.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>2.) Where is it to be Done?</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus teaches that this is to be a one-on-one, face-to-face
private meeting. You are to go and rebuke the person to his face. Jesus said,
&#8220;go and tell him.&#8221; He did not say, &#8220;Sit back and write a letter to him&#8221; or in
our modern times &#8220;call him or text him or Facebook-message him.&#8221; For something
as serious as this, those forms of communication are too impersonal. This needs
to be said while looking the offender in the eye.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus also did not say, &#8220;Go and appoint a representative to
bring the complaint to the person you think has sinned against you, whether it
be your pastors or a trustworthy friend.&#8221; No, He says, &#8220;You (in the singular)
go.&#8221; In other words, go by yourself. &#8220;Go&#8221; here can mean &#8220;to depart&#8221; or &#8220;to
withdraw&#8221; to a place. In other words, going means sinking out of sight and
having this conversation covered in secrecy so others won&#8217;t know the contents
of your conversation. But Jesus explicitly teaches this rebuke must be private
when He says to rebuke your brother &#8220;between you and him alone.&#8221; Since this is
a private sin, it should be a private confrontation. No one else is to be
involved at this time. You are the offended party, the sin was against you in
particular, and it is your responsibility to go confront that person privately.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus is not teaching something new here. Confronting
someone privately concerning his or her sin against you is the very essence of
love taught in the Old Testament. This is what it means to love your neighbor
as himself. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Leviticus 19:17-18 (HCSB)</strong> says, &#8220;You must not harbor hatred against your brother. Rebuke [same Greek verb is used in Matthew 18:15] your neighbor directly, and you will not incur guilt because of him. 18Do not take revenge or bear a grudge against members of your community, but love your neighbor as yourself; I am Yahweh.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Proverbs 25:8-10:</strong> &#8220;8do not hastily bring into court, for what will you do in the end, when your neighbor puts you to shame? 9Argue your case with your neighbor himself, and do not reveal another&#8217;s secret, 10lest he who hears you bring shame upon you, and your ill repute have no end.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>A great illustration of this is Joseph&#8217;s actions against
Mary, whom he was betrothed to. After she became pregnant by the powerful work
of the Holy Spirit, Joseph incorrectly thought she had committed sexual
immorality against him. But what did he do? Tell the whole world? No. He kept
the matter private. <strong>Matthew 1:19</strong> says, &#8220;And her husband Joseph, being a
just man and unwilling to put her to shame, resolved to divorce her quietly.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>We are not to blow up, not to refuse to talk to them, not to
gossip by telling everybody else about their sins, but to talk to them and seek
forgiveness and reconciliation privately.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Reconciliation Means the Sin Remains Private</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Be careful not to make public another person&#8217;s sins which
have been dealt with privately. If step 1 has born fruit and the brother or
sister has listened to you and has repented, you have won him or her back to
the truth, it all ends there. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There is not a step 2. And there is certainly not a step 3
or 4. The process is over. Reconciliation has occurred! And since the process
is over, going around and telling others about how badly that person sinned
against you is wicked, cruel, and not in line with loving your fellow
Christian. The goal of step 1 is to cover sins, not expose them for all to see.
It is to bury the hatchet, not to use the hatchet as a weapon to hack up your
reconciled brother in Christ. As <strong>Proverbs 17:9</strong> says, &#8220;Whoever covers an
offense seeks love, but he who repeats a matter separates close friends.&#8221; Or as
<strong>1 Peter 4:8</strong> says, &#8220;Love covers a multitude of sins.&#8221; If forgiveness has
been established, in a qualified sense you need to forget that it ever
happened. You need to let it die. That person&#8217;s dirty laundry has already been
washed and cleansed by the blood of Christ. The sin has been dealt with and you
have won your brother back. Hallelujah! At the very least, you need to make
sure it never becomes the topic of conversation with others.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Confront the Brother Yourself</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Make sure to confront someone privately about his or her sin
before telling others about it. When someone sins against you, what is the
first thing you do? Pray? Check your own heart to make sure you are not
overreacting or being overly emotional? Search the Scriptures? Go directly to
that person?</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Or do you tell another person about it? Do you let your
spouse know? Or your parents know? Or your closest friends know? Or do you post
it on Facebook for everyone to know? And do you do this without ever going to
that person?</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Hopefully you understand how terribly childish this sort of
approach is when you deal with someone who has wronged you. But it is so easy
to do because it&#8217;s extremely hard to confront someone. For some here, it may be
the most difficult thing you will ever have to do. None of us enjoy confronting
ourselves about our own sins, let alone confronting another person about his or
her sins.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>I will say this: if you come to one of your pastors &amp; tell them about how someone has sinned against you, you should hear this counsel from them every time: &#8220;Have you gone to that person first? Have you followed the first step of seeking forgiveness laid out for you in Matthew 18:15?&#8221; If not, we are not going to say anything else to you. If we want to be faithful to Christ&#8217;s commands, we can&#8217;t say anything else to you. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, you have to confront that person yourself. That takes
courage. That takes strength. That takes faith. Cry out to God for these
graces, and obey Christ&#8217;s commandment and go lovingly rebuke that person to his
face. It may be one of the best things you ever do!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>When You Are the Offender</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If you have sinned against another, go tell that offended
brother or sister your own fault. It&#8217;s a sad thing that discipline has to be
taken to step 2, 3, and even 4 in some cases. It should remain at step 1. In
fact, it shouldn&#8217;t even have to get to step 1. If you have sinned against
someone, you should go to that person yourself and ask for forgiveness. Why
wait for the person to come to you? Why does he have to hunt you down and
confront you about your sin against him? Go and make things right yourself!
Repent and humble yourself and seek that person&#8217;s forgiveness!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Something is not right with your heart if you can sin
against someone without your conscience cutting you down and compelling you to
go make things right. How can a believer go through life knowing that he has
deeply hurt and offended another believer without seeking his forgiveness?</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is the very teaching of Christ. In <strong>Matthew 5:23-24</strong>,
He says, &#8220;23So if you are offering your gift at the altar and there remember
that your brother has something against you, 24leave your gift there before the
altar and go. First be reconciled to your brother, and then come and offer your
gift.&#8221; God will not accept your worship until you make things right with your
offended brother. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But if you have really sinned against a person and he or she
confronts you, you should love that person.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>You shouldn&#8217;t get angry at that person. He or she had the
courage to say something to you &amp; the love to pursue you when you were
doing astray. You should praise God for that person and thank him or her for
dealing honestly * faithfully with your soul. As the Scriptures say, it is for
your benefit &amp; blessing.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Prov. 9:8-9:</strong> 8Do not reprove a scoffer, or he will hate you; reprove a wise man, &amp; he will love you. 9Give instruction to a wise man, &amp; he will be still wiser; teach a righteous man, &amp; he will increase in learning.</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Psalm 141:5:</strong> Let a righteous man strike me- it is a kindness; let him rebuke [same Greek verb used in Matthew 18:15] me- it is oil for my head; let my head not refuse it. Yet my prayer is continually against their evil deeds.</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong>Prov. 27:6:</strong> Faithful are the wounds of a friend; profuse are the kisses of an enemy.</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Lord-willing, in future posts we will consider steps 2-4. May God bless the preaching of His Word to the building up of His church, through Jesus Christ our Lord, to whom be honor and glory forever and ever. Amen. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-private-rebuke/">The Private Rebuke</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-private-rebuke/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</title>
		<link>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/</link>
					<comments>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 20:10:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Church Discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[church discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[practical theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13854</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Bible teaches us that holiness is one of the major marks of a true church. The church&#8217;s holiness is based off the great command found in Leviticus 19:2, &#8220;You shall be holy, for I the LORD your God am holy.&#8221; And the church&#8217;s holiness is the result of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Jesus [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/">Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-drop-cap">The Bible teaches us that holiness is one of the major marks
of a true church. The church&#8217;s holiness is based off the great command found in
Leviticus 19:2, &#8220;You shall be holy, for I the LORD your God am holy.&#8221; And the
church&#8217;s holiness is the result of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Jesus has saved
the church by giving Himself up for her. He saved her by spilling His own
precious blood on the cross. And as a result, the church has become the body
and bride of Jesus Christ. It belongs to Him. He is her Head and her Husband.
And Jesus didn&#8217;t die to purchase a sick body and an ugly bride. He died for the
church to be holy and without blemish. He died so she would reflect His holy
character. He died so that she would be holy as He is holy! Holy in her
profession of the truth and holy in her practice of living out the truth. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But in saying this, a problem should arise in our minds. A
big problem. And it&#8217;s this: the church is not perfect. At least not yet. If you
have but a faint understanding of your own heart, hopefully that&#8217;s not a
surprise. The church is full of saints but saints who are still sinners. Sadly,
saints who still break God&#8217;s commandments. And saints who still hurt one
another with their words and their actions.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Therefore, it must be the priority of every true church to
carry out what is called church discipline. This simply means the church must
have in place a way of dealing with and correcting sin when it rears its ugly
head. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If we are thinking of the church as the body of Christ,
church discipline is like undergoing surgery in order to cut out cancerous
tumors from the body so that the body would be healthy again. Or if we are
thinking of the church as the bride of Christ, church discipline is like
getting a top-of-the-line spa treatment in order for the dirt and filth and
warts and lumps to all be removed so that the bride would be beautiful again.&nbsp;&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Church discipline may not feel good, but it is absolutely
necessary. Church discipline must be enforced if any church wants to remain
pure, and holy, and undefiled before her Lord. If we let the tumors grow and do
nothing about them, the body will eventually die. And if we let the filth build
up without ever cleaning ourselves, the husband may become so disgusted with
his bride that he eventually leaves her! </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The classic passage on church discipline is found in Matthew
18:15-20. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>[15] &#8220;If your brother sins against you, go and tell him his fault, between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained your brother. [16] But if he does not listen, take one or two others along with you, that every charge may be established by the evidence of two or three witnesses. [17] If he refuses to listen to them, tell it to the church. And if he refuses to listen even to the church, let him be to you as a Gentile and a tax collector. [18] Truly, I say to you, whatever you bind on earth shall be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven. [19] Again I say to you, if two of you agree on earth about anything they ask, it will be done for them by my Father in heaven. [20] For where two or three are gathered in my name, there am I among them.&#8221; (ESV)</em></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In future posts, we will consider these verses in greater
detail. But for the present, consider six introductory remarks concerning
Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"large"} -->
<p class="has-large-font-size"><strong>Introductory Remarks</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>1.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline in Matthew 18:15-20 must never be severed from its context. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The context of this passage is very important. Sometimes
Jesus&#8217; overall teaching in this section is not emphasized enough when we think
about and talk about church discipline. This teaching on church discipline
comes in the midst of Jesus&#8217; teaching on how His disciples should love each
other, especially how they should love the least of His disciples. Remember, in
Matthew 18, Jesus teaches His disciples what it means to live as a citizen in
His kingdom. More than that, He teaches them what it means to be great in His
kingdom &#8211; and it has nothing to do with how the world defines greatness.
Greatness for Christ is not about popularity or power or riches or fame or
attractiveness or anything else the world is impressed with. Instead, greatness
in Christ&#8217;s kingdom is shown through humble service &amp; brotherly love. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus teaches this in Matthew 18 in four different ways: First,
His disciples are to show humility to one another (vv. 1-4). Second, His
disciples are to protect each other specifically from sin (vv. 5-9). Third, His
disciples are to highly esteem each other (vv. 10-14). And finally, His
disciples are to continually forgive each other (vv. 15-35). This teaching on
church discipline, then, makes up the first part in the fourth and final
section in this chapter, which deals with forgiveness.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>What does this mean then? It means that church discipline
and forgiveness and true Christian love are all vitally connected. We may be
tempted to think that church discipline and forgiveness have little or nothing
to do with each other. We may be tempted to think that church discipline is all
law while forgiveness is all grace, that church discipline is enslaving while
forgiveness is freeing, that church discipline makes me feel bad while
forgiveness makes me feel good!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Well, this dichotomy, this separation of church discipline
and forgiveness, is nowhere in Jesus&#8217; teaching. In fact, the exact opposite
occurs. Jesus&#8217; teaching on love and forgiveness includes church discipline!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus teaches us here that church discipline is the means of
forgiveness. It is the way of bringing about forgiveness and reconciliation and
restoration! And the goal of church discipline is forgiveness. Why are members
disciplined? So that forgiveness would occur. When forgiveness is not reached
between two people, discipline must be administered so that forgiveness might
become a reality!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Hopefully you see that church discipline and forgiveness
should not be pitted against each other but should work hand-in-hand to glorify
God, to keep the church pure and holy, and to bring about much peace and
happiness in the lives of God&#8217;s people. When we think about church discipline, we
should think about seeking forgiveness. The first is the means of obtaining the
second.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>2.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline concerns professing Christians. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>What Jesus says here concerns those who are brothers and
sisters in Christ. They are those who have made credible professions of faith,
have been baptized, and are members of a local church of Jesus Christ. In other
words, this teaching is for church members, for those who have been publicly
recognized as brothers and sisters in Christ. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>It is not, however, for unbelievers. How would it make any
sense to take your grievances to the church if the person who has sinned
against you is not even in the church to begin with? What can the church do
about it? If your unbelieving coworker sins against you, the only things we can
do is preach the gospel to him and pray for his salvation, but we can&#8217;t
discipline him. He has never been a part of this holy society we call the
church. He is an unbeliever outside of the kingdom of God. So we can&#8217;t put him
out of an organization he has never joined in the first place!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This doesn&#8217;t mean you shouldn&#8217;t seek forgiveness with people
in other areas of life; it simply means this step-by-step process that Jesus
teaches us is given specifically to the church and for the church to use with
its own members. It was not given to families or to schools or to society as a
whole.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are good principles there for anyone to follow, but it
is given specifically for the body and bride of Christ.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>3.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline deals with private sins committed against another brother or sister in Christ.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is important to note. The character of the kind of sin
Jesus is describing is private, not public. And it is against an individual,
not a group. Since it is private, certain measures are put in place by our Lord
to try to keep things as private as possible.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>John Calvin spends much time distinguishing between private
sins and public sins in his section on church discipline in the <em>Institutes</em>.
For sins that have been committed more openly, sins that affect more than just
one or two people but sins done in public where everyone knows about them and
where the whole church is immediately scandalized by them, Calvin argues that
these types of sin don&#8217;t fall within the instructions of Christ here in Matthew
18. People who sin in a public, grievous way are to be swiftly, solemnly, and
immediately rebuked in public, meaning something needs to be said to the church
when they gather together to worship God. We have examples of this happening in
the New Testament. Just think about Peter&#8217;s scandalous sin of distorting the
gospel of grace when he refused to eat with Gentile believers and how Paul
openly rebuked him to his face before the believers in Antioch (Galatians
2:11-14). This was no private meeting between the two apostles. The sin was so
grievous and so public that Paul was forced to rebuke Peter before the church.
And then he writes about it for all to read!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But for sins that have been committed more privately where
very few people know about it and very few people have been offended by it, the
steps laid down by Christ here in Matthew 18 must be followed. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are always exceptions to the rule. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are certain private sins that are so grievous that
immediate public church discipline must be enforced. Some of these sins might
include things that would put a person behind bars for a long time. Even if the
crime was committed in private, sometimes it must be exposed by the light for
all to see and abhor, including the civil authorities. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are also certain people who commit private sins that
must be made public. Here I am thinking about church officers. If a church
officer commits a particular sin that disqualifies him from the office of
either elder or deacon, something needs to be said to the church to give them
the reason why he has stepped down.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But the private sins I am talking about might include the
following: theft of some small amount, deliberately lying to another brother&#8217;s
face for your own personal advantage, unrighteous anger directed at another
believer, a complete lack of respect and honor for an older member of the
church, gossiping and slandering the good name of a Christian, a divisive
spirit that tries to stir up trouble in the church, and being a stumbling block
to one of Christ&#8217;s little ones. These may be small offenses in the eyes of our
society but let me tell you this: they are grave offenses in the sight of our
holy God who commands us to love one another as Christ loves us.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, all public sin should at all times be publicly rebuked;
some private sins should also at all times be publicly rebuked; but most
private sins should at first be privately rebuked. (but of course, it should
lead to a public rebuke in the presence of all if the person persists in sin).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>4.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline gives us a methodical, step-by-step process to deal with unrepentant sin. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Seeking forgiveness and reconciliation may be a process. I
wish it wasn&#8217;t the case. I wish that when someone sinned against another he or
she would immediately seek forgiveness. But sadly, while we live in this fallen
world, that is not always the case. And if forgiveness does not immediately
occur, there are distinct steps that must be taken in order to secure it. In
fact, there are four steps listed here in Matthew 18 that must be taken in
order to bring about forgiveness from an unrepentant Christian.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, we should not be trigger happy to discipline, and even
more than that, to excommunicate unrepentant members who have sinned in a
private way. As William Hendriksen says, &#8220;Church discipline, when viewed
negatively, is a matter of last resort&#8221; (699, Gospel of Matthew). None of this
should be rushed. Each step takes time to complete. Careful attention must be
taken and certain measures must be exhausted before moving on to the next step.
</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Maybe an illustration might be helpful. Instead of thinking
of these steps as little stair steps like the ones before me which only take a
second to climb (and easy to skip if you have some jumping abilities), think of
these steps to secure forgiveness like riding escalators from floor to floor at
the Mall of America. The Mall of America has four floors. And it has escalators
that will take you up to each floor. But it takes some time to go from one
floor to the next. And it takes a lot of time to go from the bottom floor to
the very top. You have to slowly but surely move from one to the next. Well, in
a similar way, each escalator of church discipline must be ascended before one
moves on to the next. Getting from step one to step four should not be
instantaneous.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>5.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline has, as its goal, the gaining or winning back of a professing Christian who has gone astray.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This step-by-step process of church discipline is
redemptive. The unrepentant professing Christian is like a sheep that has gone
astray. He or she has left the fold of Christ. He or she has sinned and turned
from the Highway of Holiness. And if that person keeps living in unrepentant
sin, if that person keeps walking down crooked, dark paths, he or she will not
reach the Celestial City. He or she will be attacked by deadly predators and will
be completely destroyed.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So seeking forgiveness in the way prescribed by Christ gets them back on the right track. It brings them back to the fold of God. It displays the very heart of Jesus Christ, the Good Shepherd, who leaves the 99 sheep on the mountains in order to search and find the one that went astray. As James says in James 5:19-20:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>&#8220;[19] My brothers, if anyone among you wanders from the truth and someone brings him back, [20] let him know that whoever brings back a sinner from his wandering will save his soul from death and will cover a multitude of sins.&#8221; (ESV)</em></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, in this area of church discipline, we need to check our
hearts. We need to make sure that if we want to walk up these steps, we are
doing so for the glory of God and for the ultimate good of the straying
Christian. It must not be our desire to seek vengeance or to get even with
someone who has wronged us. We also must not revel in another person&#8217;s
downfall. Instead, we must show brotherly love and tender affection to those
who have wronged us. We must remember how wicked our own hearts are, how much
we daily offend our Lord, and how much He has mercy on us. We have to keep ever
before us the goal of church discipline, which is repentance and forgiveness
and restoration, not condemnation and damnation. We want to win our brother and
sister back; not destroy them.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>6.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline is steeped in OT laws and principles.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus was not one who wanted to unhitch the Old Testament
from the New Testament. There have been teachers throughout church history who
have taught that New Testament believers should move on from the Old Testament
and leave that baggage behind as they follow Christ.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Well, certainly there are some things in the Old Testament
that shouldn&#8217;t be practiced any more in light of the coming of Christ, animal
sacrifices being one of them, but we should never dishonor or take lightly the
teaching of the Old Testament. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Why? Because Jesus didn&#8217;t. Jesus had a high view of the
Scriptures. And He saw a lot of use for the Old Testament in the New Testament
church. In fact, His step-by-step procedure for dealing with sin is based on
teaching from the Mosaic law! Yes, parts of the OT law were to inform and
structure the way the church of Jesus Christ governs itself and functions in
this world. Every step finds its roots in laws given to the nation of Israel.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This makes us think that Jesus may have considered the
church as the New Israel. And it also makes us think that there were more than
just temporary, ceremonial laws in the OT. Some of the laws in the Old
Testament transcend OT Israel and have direct application to the church of
Jesus Christ today. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, the Old Testament wasn&#8217;t to be thrown out or seen as
irrelevant for Christians. Instead, it was to be studied and examined and
applied to various situations which crop up in the church today. We will see
this as we go through the steps of church discipline.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is how I believe we should look at these steps: Two of them occur privately, and two of them occur publicly, in that order. So in future posts, we will look at the two private steps of seeking forgiveness, and then we will look at the two public steps of seeking forgiveness. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/">Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does the Bible Teach Common Grace?</title>
		<link>/does-the-bible-teach-common-grace/</link>
					<comments>/does-the-bible-teach-common-grace/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2017 17:40:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9143</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Reformed Contentions It is a popular assertion of those who oppose the doctrine of common grace to claim that in the Bible, the word grace only refers to God&#8217;s saving grace given to the elect and never to God&#8217;s common grace displayed to the reprobate. This is in fact what Ron Hanko, son of Herman [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/does-the-bible-teach-common-grace/">Does the Bible Teach Common Grace?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Reformed Contentions</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">It is a popular assertion of those who oppose the doctrine of common grace to claim that in the Bible, the word <em>grace</em> only refers to God&#8217;s saving grace given to the elect and never to God&#8217;s common grace displayed to the reprobate. This is in fact what Ron Hanko, son of Herman Hanko and a minister in the Protestant Reformed Church, asserts. He says, &#8220;The word <em>grace</em> is used over 300 times in the Bible. . . . Never once in the Bible is it used in reference to the reprobate wicked. Never once. Go home and check it.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> If this wasn&#8217;t clear enough, he later emphatically declares that the term <em>grace</em> (as well as <em>love</em>) is &#8220;never, never used in reference to the reprobate wicked. Never.&#8221; Instead, Hanko unashamedly proclaims that &#8220;in all of His common providence [God&#8217;s] disposition toward them is unremitting and unchangeable hatred.&#8221; He likens the providential operations of God to the care of a meat farmer for his livestock: the farmer does not attend to the needs of his animals because he loves them but only because he is raising them for the slaughter. But the doctrine of common grace includes more terms than simply <em>grace</em>. Hanko admits that many more words are included under the general umbrella of grace when he says, &#8220;When we are speaking about common grace we are also speaking of common love, common mercy, common goodness, common longsuffering. They all go together. They can&#8217;t be separated. . . . They all stand or fall together.&#8221; If this is so, showing from the Bible that God displays any of these affections towards the non-elect will substantiate the doctrine of common grace. Unfortunately, the scope of this paper is limited to only the term <em>grace</em>. The question I set out to answer is simply this: &#8220;Does the Bible ever say that God shows grace to the reprobate?&#8221; If it does, common grace is a biblical doctrine, and its avowed enemies who condemn it should rightly be silenced.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a> If, however, the Bible does not use the term <em>grace</em> in this way, common grace can still be substantiated in other ways,<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a> but its advocates should be willing to reassess their assertions in light of the biblical evidence. In what follows, I will endeavor to examine the word <em>grace</em> in both its Old and New Testament contexts in order to answer this question. I will only list and comment upon the verses that are relevant to this issue, i.e. God showing grace to those who will never be saved.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Precise Classification</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Before we begin, the question must be asked, &#8220;What does common grace mean?&#8221; Richard Muller, in his <em>Dictionary of Latin and Greek Theological Terms</em>, gives this historic, Reformed definition:</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">i.e., a nonsaving, universal grace according to which God in his goodness bestows his favor upon all creation in the general blessings of physical sustenance and moral influence for the good. &nbsp;Thus, rain falls on the just and the unjust, and all men have the law engraved on their hearts. &nbsp;<em>Gratia communis</em> is therefore contrasted by the Reformed with particular or special grace (<em>gratia particularis sive specialis</em>, q.v.).<a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Though this explanation is adequate, I also believe that the doctrine of common grace includes what Muller calls <em>gratia universalis</em>,<a href="#_ftn5" name="_ftnref5">[5]</a> or what Abraham Kuyper calls general grace,<a href="#_ftn6" name="_ftnref6">[6]</a> i.e. God&#8217;s universal desire for all men to be saved. Nevertheless, the issue is whether or not God has a favorable disposition (or as Muller puts it, &#8220;God in his goodness bestows his favor&#8221;) to the wicked in this present life. Whether that disposition includes a desire to bless the reprobate with physical and/or spiritual good is an altogether different matter and should only be discussed by those who affirm the doctrine of common grace, since those who reject it deny that God desires to bestow any kind of favor on the reprobate.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">I must also assert that the doctrine of common grace relates directly to God&#8217;s preceptive will and not to His decretive will. This dimension of God&#8217;s will truly tells us something about God&#8217;s heart towards His creation, although mystery abounds in attempting to harmonize His universal beneficence with His decree of predestination, election, and reprobation in eternity passed.<a href="#_ftn7" name="_ftnref7">[7]</a> The fact is, if the Bible says that God pours out grace upon those that will never be saved, He is not pretending to do so; He really has a gracious disposition towards all who are created in His own image, sinner and saint alike. In giving providential gifts to the ungodly, God is not just displaying His &#8220;divine power&#8221; but in &#8220;back of the bestowal there is an attitude on the part of God, called love, which constrains him to bestow these tokens of his lovingkindness.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn8" name="_ftnref8">[8]</a> Let us now examine the Scriptures to see if these things are so.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Biblical Concentration</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Does the Bible ever use the term <em>grace</em> in a common or universal way? Even among those who affirm the doctrine of common grace, there is disagreement. For instance, the great Dutch theologian, Herman Bavinck, does not think so. He says, &#8220;Used with reference to God, however, its object is never creatures in general, nor the Gentiles, but only his people.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn9" name="_ftnref9">[9]</a> Is he correct?</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Old Testament Usage of Grace (???/ ?????)</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The noun ??? is used 69 times in the Old Testament, and its verbal form ????? is used 78 times. It is the most common word for grace, favor, acceptance, and good-will. Virtually every example of God showing grace to people in the OT has to do with the elect.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">God bestows grace on Noah (Gen. 6:8), Jacob (Gen. 33:5,11), Benjamin (Gen. 43:29), those whom God decides to be gracious to (Exod. 33:11), Moses (Exod. 33:12,17), the people of Israel (Num. 6:25; Ps. 67:1; 2 Kings 13:23), Gideon (Judges 6:17-18), David (2 Sam. 15:25; Ps. 4:1; 6:2; 9:13; 25:16; 26:11; 27:7; 30:10; 31:9; 41:4,10; 51:1, 56:1, 57:1, 86:3,16; 119:29,58,132), those who walk uprightly (Ps. 84:11), Zion (Ps. 102:13,14), God&#8217;s servants (Ps. 123:2-3), those who never let steadfast love and faithfulness leave them (Prov. 3:4), the humble (Prov. 3:34), a people who shall dwell in Zion (Is. 30:18-19), Isaiah and those who wait for the LORD (Is. 33:2), those who survived the sword (Jer. 31:2), the remnant of Joseph (Amos 5:15), the finished temple/Christ (Zech. 4:7), and the house of David and the inhabitants of Jerusalem (Zech. 12:10).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">God&#8217;s grace is so bound up in His relationship with His people that in two places, David explicitly prays that the Lord would not be gracious to his wicked enemies. He says, &#8220;You, O LORD God of hosts, the God of Israel, Awake to punish all the nations; Do not be gracious to any who are treacherous in iniquity&#8221; (Ps. 59:5). Again, he says, &#8220;Let there be none to extend lovingkindness to him, Nor any to be gracious to his fatherless children&#8221; (Ps. 109:12). More than this, God actually commands the Israelites to show no grace to &#8220;the Hittites, the Girgashites, the Amorites, the Canaanites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites, seven nations more numerous and mightier than you&#8221; (Deut. 7:1-2). Instead, these nations were to be devoted to complete destruction. Additionally, Isaiah prophesies that God will not be gracious to Babylon when He destroys her in the eschaton. He proclaims, &#8220;When its limbs are dry, they are broken off; Women come and make a fire with them, For they are not a people of discernment, Therefore their Maker will not have compassion on them. And their Creator will not be gracious to them&#8221; (Is. 27:11). Even though God is their Maker and Creator, He is under no obligation to show grace to rebellious sinners. It is all freely given to those whom He desires to be gracious to.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">However, there is one place in the OT where God is said to show grace to the wicked. Isaiah 26:10 reads, &#8220;Though the wicked is shown favor, He does not learn righteousness; He deals unjustly in the land of uprightness, And does not perceive the majesty of the LORD.&#8221; The ESV, HCSB, ISV, and the NET Bible all use the word if: &#8220;If favor is shown to the wicked . . .&#8221; This would seem to imply that Isaiah is giving a hypothetical scenario whereby grace is really not shown to the wicked.<a href="#_ftn10" name="_ftnref10">[10]</a> The meaning would be, &#8220;If grace were somehow shown to the wicked, they would still not learn righteousness.&#8221; But I do not believe this verse should be understood as a hypothetical scenario divorced from reality. What Isaiah is saying is a statement of fact: God shows grace to the wicked, though it does not make them any better off. Why do I think this? First, the word <em>if</em> is not found in the original Hebrew. The text literally reads, &#8220;Show favor to the wicked.&#8221; <em>If</em> is supplied by these versions primarily as a matter of interpretation, not translation. Other versions such as the NIV, NASB, and KJV omit this word. Secondly, the context suggests the reality of God being gracious to the wicked. In this passage, Isaiah is stressing the importance of God sending His judgments on the earth. &#8220;All the inhabitants of the earth&#8221; learn righteousness when God&#8217;s judgments are displayed (v. 9). Isaiah says this as a matter of fact. God&#8217;s uplifted hand against sin causes both the righteous and the wicked to fear Him and turn away from evil, even if for the wicked it is only an outward reformation of their lives. Matthew Henry comments,</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">It is God&#8217;s gracious design, in sending abroad his judgments, thereby to bring men to seek him and serve him: When thy judgments are upon the earth, laying all waste, then we have reason to expect that not only God&#8217;s professing people, but even the inhabitants of the world, will learn righteousness, will have their mistakes rectified and their lives reformed, will be brought to acknowledge God&#8217;s righteousness in punishing them, will repent of their own unrighteousness in offending God, and so be brought to walk in right paths.<a href="#_ftn11" name="_ftnref11">[11]</a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">But Isaiah correctly observes in verse 10 that when only grace is shown to the wicked, they will not learn righteousness but go on in their evil and corrupt ways. As Calvin points out, &#8220;. . . the wicked cannot be brought in any way to love God, though he endeavor, by every sort of kindness, to draw and gain them over . . . whatever may be the acts of kindness by which God draws the wicked, they will never learn to act uprightly.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn12" name="_ftnref12">[12]</a> Although God&#8217;s grace is meant to lead them to repentance, they abuse it and distort it by going on in their sin. Therefore, they store up for themselves justly-deserved wrath (Rom. 2:4-5). And that fiery wrath will fall upon their own heads if they continue on in their rebellion (v. 11). Verses 9 and 10 then demonstrate realities which produce separate and polarizing results for the enemies of God. Though God shows grace to the wicked, the wicked show disrespect to God, and their hearts are given fully to do evil (Ecc. 8:11). Therefore, as God pours out grace upon evildoers, God must also unsheathe His iron rod of judgment in order to restrain their sins and teach them righteousness.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">New Testament Usage of Grace (?????/?????????)</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The noun ????? is used 157 times in the New Testament, and its verbal form ????????? is used 23 times. HELPS Word-studies says that grace is &#8220;preeminently used of the Lord&#8217;s <em>favor</em>, freely <em>extended to give Himself</em> away to people (because He &#8216;ever leans toward them&#8217;).&#8221;<a href="#_ftn13" name="_ftnref13">[13]</a> Bavinck adds, &#8220;. . . subjectively, it means favor, a positive disposition on the part of the giver, and gratitude and devotion on the part of the recipient. Ascribed to God, grace is the voluntary, unrestrained, and unmerited favor that he shows to sinners and that, instead of the verdict of death, brings them righteousness and life.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn14" name="_ftnref14">[14]</a> By his definition, Bavinck seems to assert that all grace in the New Testament is <em>saving</em> grace. Is he correct? Here are my findings:</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">God bestows grace on Mary (Lk. 1:30), the young Jesus (Lk. 2:40,52), the children of God (Jn. 1:16), the apostles and the whole church (Acts 4:33), Stephen (Acts 6:8), Joseph (Acts 7:10), David (Acts 7:46), the new converts in the church at Antioch (Acts 11:23), newly converted Jews and God-fearing proselytes (Acts 13:43), Paul and Barnabus (Acts 14:26), Silas (Acts 15:40), believers in Achaia (Acts 18:27), the Ephesian elders (Acts 20:32), Paul (Acts 27:24, Rom. 1:5; 12:3; 15:15; 1 Cor. 3:10; 15:10; 2 Cor. 12:9; Eph. 3:2,7,8; 1 Tim. 1:14), saints in Rome (Rom. 1:7; 16:20), all believers (Rom. 3:24, 5:2; 5:15,17; 6:14; 8:32; 12:6; 1 Cor. 2:12; 2 Cor. 8:9; Eph. 1:6,7; 2:5,7,8; 4:7,32; Col. 2:13; 3:13), 2 Thess. 1:12; 2:16; 3:18; 2 Tm. 1:9; Tit. 2:11; 3:7; Heb. 2:9; 1 Pet. 1:10,13; 1 Pet. 4:10; 1 Pet. 5:12; 2 Pet. 3:18; Rev. 22:21), a believing remnant of Jews (Rom. 11:5), saints in Corinth (1 Cor. 1:3,4; 16:23; 2 Cor. 1:2; 2 Cor. 9:8,14; 13:14; Gal. 1:15; 2:9), Paul and Timothy (2 Cor. 1:12), new converts (2 Cor. 4:15), the churches of Macedonia (2 Cor. 8:1), the churches of Galatia (Gal. 1:3,6; 6:18), Abraham (Gal. 3:18), the saints in Ephesus (Eph. 1:2; 6:4), the saints at Philippi (Phil. 1:2,29; 4:23), Paul and the Philippian church (Phil. 1:7), the exalted Jesus (Phil. 2:9), the saints at Colossae (Col. 1:2,6; 4:18), the church of the Thessalonians (1 Thess. 1:1; 5:28; 2 Thess. 1:2), Timothy (1 Tm. 1:2; 6:21, 2 Tm. 1:2; 2:1; 4:22), Titus (Tit. 1:4), Titus and the Cretan believers (Tit. 3:15), Philemon (Phlm. 1:3,25), the Hebrew churches (Heb. 13:25), the humble (Jam. 4:6), the elect exiles of the Dispersion (1 Pet. 1:2; 2 Pet. 1:2, those who suffer for righteousness&#8217; sake (1 Pet. 2:20). Christian husbands and wives (1 Pet. 3:7), the elect lady and her children (2 Jn. 1:3), and the seven church in Asia (Rev. 1:4).<a href="#_ftn15" name="_ftnref15">[15]</a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">As it was in the OT, so it is in the New: virtually all NT references to God&#8217;s grace concern God&#8217;s favor towards His people. But there are a few places that seem to say otherwise.</span></p>
<p><strong> <span style="font-size: x-large;">1.) The Blind</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Luke 7:21 reads, &#8220;In that hour He healed many people of diseases and plagues and evil spirits, and on many who were blind He bestowed sight.&#8221; Jesus did this to demonstrate to John the Baptist and his disciples that He was the promised Messiah who would bring about cosmic restoration to a world shattered by sin (vv. 22-23). In verse 21, the verb &#8220;bestowed&#8221; is the Greek verb &#8220;to show grace.&#8221; It was Jesus who &#8220;graced&#8221; sight on many of the blind. His gracious disposition toward them moved Him to heal them of their physical infirmities. Now I think most would agree that during His earthly ministry, Jesus performed physical miracles upon some who never experienced the spiritual miracle of regeneration.<a href="#_ftn16" name="_ftnref16">[16]</a> If this was the case, we have good reason to believe that from this passage Jesus showed grace to some who were never saved. Unless one will argue that all those who received their sight were the elect, here is an instance where the God-man gave gracious blessings to some who would never have the eyes of their hearts opened to behold His glory.</span></p>
<p><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">2.) Unloving Debtors</span></strong><a href="#_ftn17" name="_ftnref17"><strong>[17]</strong></a></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">In Luke 7:41-42, Jesus tells this parable: &#8220;A moneylender had two debtors: one owed five hundred denarii, and the other fifty. When they were unable to repay, he graciously forgave them both. So which of them will love him more?&#8221; The phrase &#8220;graciously forgave&#8221; is the Greek verb &#8220;to be gracious.&#8221; Both of these debtors were &#8220;graced&#8221; of their debts by the moneylender. The one who had a lesser debt was Simon the Pharisee, and the one who had the greater debt was the woman crying at Jesus&#8217; feet. Jesus refers to Himself as the moneylender. Both Simon and the woman had their sins &#8220;graced&#8221; by Jesus, yet only the woman went home that day forgiven and justified.<a href="#_ftn18" name="_ftnref18">[18]</a> Granting that we must be careful in our interpretation of parables, this parable still teaches us something about the disposition of Christ to sinners. We learn that Jesus can be gracious and merciful to some who are never truly forgiven. He can show grace to Pharisees, although not all Pharisees thank and love Him for it.</span></p>
<p><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">3.) All Professing Believers</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">There are several interesting passages that speak about God&#8217;s grace to those who are in danger of falling away or who have already apostatized. They are 2 Corinthians 6:1, Galatians 5:4, Hebrews 10:29, and Hebrews 12:15. In 2 Corinthians 6:1, Paul says, &#8220;Working together with Him, then, we appeal to you not to receive the grace of God in vain.&#8221; Similarly, Paul says in Galatians 5:4, &#8220;You are severed from Christ, you who would be justified by the law; you have fallen away from grace.&#8221; In Hebrews 10:29 he says, &#8220;How much worse punishment, do you think, will be deserved by the one who has trampled underfoot the Son of God, and has profaned the blood of the covenant by which he was sanctified, and has outraged the Spirit of grace?&#8221; And again, in Hebrews 12:15 he says, &#8220;See to it that no one fails to obtain the grace of God; that no &#8216;root of bitterness&#8217; springs up and causes trouble, and by it many become defiled.&#8221; How do we understand these passages? Does God give His grace (and even the Spirit of grace) to those who eventually fail to obtain salvation? Is Paul saying that someone can receive the grace of God in vain and so be eternally lost? Paul seems to think that this was a real possibility! Calvin did too. He said that sinners could &#8220;willfully render useless [God&#8217;s] grace, by which they had been favored.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn19" name="_ftnref19">[19]</a> Of course, I am not referring to the efficacious grace of God. If a professing believer would perish in his sin, it would only prove that these passages were talking about the offer of grace or the common gracious operations of the Holy Spirit upon the reprobate, i.e. resistible grace, not effectual saving grace to the elect. But the fact remains, Paul taught that there is some sort of grace in the outward call of the gospel that professing believers could receive in vain, profane, fall away from, or fail to obtain through their own slothfulness and hardheartedness. He can only give these exhortations because God is really offering and holding out grace to everyone who hears the gospel. But, as John Gill points out, even this &#8220;declaration of the love and grace of God to sinners&#8221; can be resisted and received in vain &#8220;when it is but notionally received, or received in word only: when it is abused and perverted to vile purposes, and when men drop, deny it, and fall off from it.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn20" name="_ftnref20">[20]</a> God, then, shows grace to those who finally prove themselves to be goats amidst the sheepfold.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Concluding Comments</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Are the PRC and other Hyper-Calvinists correct in saying that the term <em>grace</em> is only reserved for the elect and their salvation? Not entirely. Hanko&#8217;s assertion that in the Bible the word <em>grace</em> is never used in reference to the reprobate wicked is not biblical. There may be only one reference to God showing grace to the non-elect in the Old Testament (Is. 26:10), but it is an important one. In the New Testament, however, there may be several places where God shows grace to those who finally perish in their sins. I admit that if this word study teaches us anything, it is this: God has a special, saving grace reserved only for His people. Nearly every reference to the term <em>grace</em> refers to God&#8217;s special favor and love for the elect. Both Old and New Testaments seem adamant about jealously reserving the grace of God for the people of God and no others. But there are exceptions to the rule. Isaiah 26:10 affirms that God shows grace to the wicked, Luke 7:21 and Luke 7:41-42 imply that Jesus showed grace to some who were never saved, and passages such as 1 Corinthians 6:1 and Hebrews 10:29 teach us that God offers grace through the gospel to all professing believers, even those who eventually fall away. These usages are by far rare, but from examining how the Bible uses this word, we stand on sure and steady ground to declare that common grace is a biblical doctrine. The Bible proves God shows grace to the wicked. And if space were permitted, the same could be said for God&#8217;s common love,<a href="#_ftn21" name="_ftnref21">[21]</a> steadfast love,<a href="#_ftn22" name="_ftnref22">[22]</a> mercy,<a href="#_ftn23" name="_ftnref23">[23]</a> goodness,<a href="#_ftn24" name="_ftnref24">[24]</a> compassion,<a href="#_ftn25" name="_ftnref25">[25]</a> longsuffering,<a href="#_ftn26" name="_ftnref26">[26]</a> and blessing.<a href="#_ftn27" name="_ftnref27">[27]</a></span></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Ron Hanko, &#8220;Common Grace: Is it Biblical?&#8221; (audio of sermon, Loughbrickland, Northern Ireland, February 3, 1995), tinysa.com/sermon/22706142927.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> For instance, David Engelsma, in his book <em>Christianizing the World</em>, says, &#8220;The theory of common grace is not only condemned by scripture, but also is refuted by history and experience.&#8221; See David J. Engelsma, <em>Christianizing the World</em> (Jenison, MI: Reformed Free Publishing Association, 2016), 133.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Even if the Bible never used the precise terminology of common or universal grace, the concept could still be encoded in the pages of Scripture. We must not commit the word/concept fallacy. We recognize that the words Trinity, the hypostatic union, the Covenant of Works, the Covenant of Grace, and amillenialism are not found in the Bible, but the concepts are present. Matthew 5:43-48 and Luke 6:27-36 do not explicitly say that God is loving and merciful to the reprobate, but sound exegesis of these texts proves that these concepts are certainly implied.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> Richard Muller, <em>Dictionary of Latin and Greek Theological Terms</em> (Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Academic, 1995), 130.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref5" name="_ftn5">[5]</a> Ibid, 133. Muller defines universal grace as &#8220;that grace of God in the universal call of the gospel according to which salvation is offered to all.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref6" name="_ftn6">[6]</a> Discussed by Engelsma in <em>Christianizing the World</em>, 164.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref7" name="_ftn7">[7]</a> One way of reconciling this blessed paradox while upholding God&#8217;s simplicity and impassibility is differentiating between God&#8217;s will of propension and God&#8217;s will of volition/purpose. R.L. Dabney states, &#8220;. . . God does have compassion for the reprobate, but not express volition to save them, because his infinite wisdom regulates his whole will and guides and harmonizes (not suppresses) all its active principles.&#8221; In other words, God can possess &#8220;natural propensions of pity towards persons whom his wisdom restrains him from ever purposing to save.&#8221; See R.L. Dabney, &#8220;God&#8217;s Indiscriminate Proposals of Mercy, As Related to His Power, Wisdom, and Sincerity,&#8221; <em>The Princeton Review</em> (1878), accessed September 21, 2017, <a href="http://www.romans45.org/dabney/mercy.htm">http://www.romans45.org/dabney/mercy.htm</a>.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref8" name="_ftn8">[8]</a> John Murray, &#8220;The Free Offer of the Gospel&#8221; (report presented to the Fifteenth (1948) General Assembly of the Orthodox Presbyterian Church, Wildwood, NJ, May 1948), accessed September 13, 2017, <a href="http://opc.org/GA/free_offer.html">http://opc.org/GA/free_offer.html</a>. Engelsma argues in <em>Christianizing the World </em>that providence is not grace but divine power. He goes on to say that &#8220;God&#8217;s providence is his power upholding and governing the creation he made in the beginning. In his providence, God maintains even the ungodly in their humanity, so that they can develop the creation, uncovering and using its bounties; order their society, especially by government; and in general direct their life together in such a way as to benefit themselves and avoid many evils. But providence is not inherently grace and blessing, not even in the instances in which providence provides the ungodly with many good gifts, for example order in society, or health, or nourishing food. The things themselves are good, but if God gives them to a man or woman in his wrath and if the man or woman uses and enjoys them without acknowledgement of God the giver, without gratitude to God, and without a use of them that serves God, the things are a curse to the one who so misuses them. . . . To the reprobate unbeliever, all the good things of providence are a curse in divine wrath, exposing his inexcusable wickedness and increasing his guilt (135-6). I agree that the wicked twist and distort the good gifts of God to their own destruction. But their intentions and motives are not the issue. Our concern has to do with the disposition of God in giving these things. If the Bible specifically says that God shows grace to the wicked, His providential gifts of &#8220;health, earthly riches, a good job, and the order kept by civil government&#8221; flow not from divine power or wrath but are &#8220;inherently, necessarily, and always grace and grace&#8217;s blessings&#8221; (70). It would be a contradiction in terms if God &#8220;graced&#8221; the reprobate out of His wrath and hatred for him!</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref9" name="_ftn9">[9]</a> Herman Bavinck, <em>Reformed Dogmatics: God and Creation</em>, ed. John Bolt, trans. John Vriend (1895; repr., Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Academic, 2004), 2:214.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref10" name="_ftn10">[10]</a> This is in fact how Franz Delitzsch interprets Isaiah&#8217;s words: &#8220;???? ??? is a hypothetical clause, which is left to be indicated by the emphasis, like Nehemiah 1:8 (Ewald, 357, b): granting that favour (che?n equals &#8220;goodness,&#8221; Romans 2:4) is constantly shown to the wicked man.&#8221; See Franz Delitzsch, <em>Commentary on the Old Testament: Isaiah</em>, trans. James Martin (repr., Grand Rapids, MI: William B. Eerdmans, 1991), 7:446.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref11" name="_ftn11">[11]</a> Matthew Henry, <em>Matthew Henry&#8217;s Commentary on the Whole Bible</em>, vol. 4, <em>Isaiah to Malachi</em> (repr., Peabody, MA: Hendrickson Publishers, 2011), 109.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref12" name="_ftn12">[12]</a> John Calvin, <em>Commentary on Isaiah &#8211; Volume 2</em>, trans. William Pringle (Grand Rapids, MI: Christian Classics Ethereal Library, 2005), 178-79, accessed September 14, 2017, <a href="http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom14.pdf">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom14.pdf</a>.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref13" name="_ftn13">[13]</a> <em>HELPS Lexicon</em>, s.v. &#8220;Charis,&#8221; accessed September 14, 2017, <a href="http://thediscoverybible.com/">http://thediscoverybible.com/</a>.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref14" name="_ftn14">[14]</a> Bavinck, <em>Reformed Dogmatics, </em>2:214.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref15" name="_ftn15">[15]</a> God bestowing grace on Christians is a rather broad category. To be more specific, BDAG states, &#8220;The context will show whether the emphasis is upon the <em>possession of divine grace</em> as a source of blessings for the believer, or upon a <em>store of grace </em>that is dispensed, or a <em>state of grace </em>(i.e. standing in God&#8217;s favor) that is brought about, or a <em>deed of grace </em>wrought by God in Christ, or a <em>work of grace </em>that grows fr. more to more.&#8221; See Walter Bauer et al., <em>A Greek-English Lexicon of the New Testament and Other Early Christian Literature</em>, 2nd ed. (Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1979), 878.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref16" name="_ftn16">[16]</a> A prime example of this would be what happened to the large crowd of 5,000. Jesus had compassion on them, healed them, and fed them (Matt. 14:13-21; Jn. 6:1-15). They both witnessed and experienced physical miracles. But later on Jesus told them, &#8220;Truly, truly, I say to you, you are seeking Me, not because you saw signs, but because you ate your fill of the loaves. Do not work for the food that perishes, but for the food that endures to eternal life, which the Son of Man will give to you. For on Him God the Father has set his seal&#8221; (Jn. 6:26-27). What was the result of this conversation? &#8220;After this many of His disciples turned back and no longer walked with Him&#8221; (Jn. 6:66). &nbsp;Many of the same disciples who partook of Jesus&#8217; physical miracles (restored physical health) did not partake of Jesus&#8217; spiritual miracles (eternal life). They were blessed materially, not spiritually.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref17" name="_ftn17">[17]</a> It is interesting to note that in another parable about debtors (The Parable of the Unforgiving Debtor in Matt. 18:23-35), the king/master, who represents Jesus&#8217; heavenly Father (v. 35), shows patience (??????????) (v.26), compassion (?????????????) (v.27), and mercy (?????) (v. 33) to one who eventually ends up in jail for the rest of his life due to his unforgiving heart. This parable teaches us that God shows patience, compassion, and mercy to sinners who are eventually thrown into the dungeon of hell for all eternity.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref18" name="_ftn18">[18]</a> Calvin comments that Simon was probably not forgiven: &#8220;From the words of Christ, therefore, we are not at liberty to infer, that Simon had been a debtor to a small amount, or that he was absolved from guilt. It is more probable that, as he was a blind hypocrite, he was still plunged in the filth of his sins.&#8221; See John Calvin, <em>Commentary on a Harmony of the Evangelists, Matthew, Mark, and Luke &#8211; Volume 2</em>, ed. William Pringle (Grand Rapids, MI: Christian Classics Ethereal Library, 2005), 115, accessed September 14, 2017, http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom32.pdf.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref19" name="_ftn19">[19]</a> John Calvin, <em>Commentary on Hebrews</em>, ed. John Owen (Grand Rapids, MI: Christian Classics Ethereal Library, 2005), 218, accessed September 13, 2017, <a href="http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom44.pdf">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom44.pdf</a>. Here is the full quote: &#8220;Hence learn that all who willfully render useless his grace, by which they had been favored, act disdainfully towards the Spirit of God.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref20" name="_ftn20">[20]</a> John Gill, &#8220;The Second Epistle of Paul the Apostle to the Corinthians,&#8221; in <em>The Baptist Commentary Series Volume I: John Gill&#8217;s Exposition of the Old and New Testaments</em>, vol. 8, <em>John to Galatians</em> (1809; repr., Paris, AR: The Baptist Standard Bearer, 2006), 793-94.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref21" name="_ftn21">[21]</a> In the OT, God sets His love on Cyrus (Is. 48:14) and the idolatrous children of Israel (Hos. 3:1). In the NT, Jesus as the God-man loves sinners and tax collectors (Matt. 11:19; Lk. 7:34) and the unconverted rich young man (Mk. 10:21), and God the Father loves sinful mankind in general (Jn. 3:16; Tit. 3:4).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref22" name="_ftn22">[22]</a> In the OT, God&#8217;s steadfast love fills the earth (Ps. 33:5; 119:64). If steadfast love only refers to God&#8217;s covenant love, how can God show <em>hesed</em> to sinners and saints alike? It may be that this love is displayed in the general blessings that come to the whole world due to the Noahic Covenant (Gen. 9:8-17). If this is the case, even the chief of wicked reprobates is a recipient of God&#8217;s <em>hesed</em>.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref23" name="_ftn23">[23]</a> In the OT, God shows mercy to the stiff-necked and hard-hearted people of Judah (2 Chron. 36:15-17). In the NT, God in Jesus shows mercy to a demon possessed boy (Matt. 17:14-18), the unforgiving servant (Matt. 18:33), and the ten lepers (Mk. 10:11-19).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref24" name="_ftn24">[24]</a> In a partial study of the OT, God&#8217;s goodness extends to Jacob&#8217;s family and the surrounding nations (Gen. 50:20), the nation of Israel in general (Exod. 3:8/Deut. 1:25; Exod. 18:9; Num. 10:29,32; Deut. 6:24/10:13; 8:10; 26:11; Josh. 21:45; 1 Kings 8:56; Neh. 9:20), and wicked men (Job 22:18). In the NT, God is good to those who labor and are heavy laden (Matt. 11:28-30), the hungry (Lk. 1:53), the ungrateful and the evil (Lk. 6:35), the rich man in hell (Lk. 16:25), those at the wedding feast in Cana (Jn. 2:1-11), pagans at Lystra (Acts 14:17), hypocrites (Rom. 2:4), those who do good and submit to civil authorities (Rom. 13:4), those who committed the unpardonable sin (Heb. 6:4-6), and everyone who receives something good from the hands of God (Jam. 1:17).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref25" name="_ftn25">[25]</a> In the OT, God shows compassion on the idolatrous and blasphemous Israelites (Neh. 9:19) and on all that He has made (Ps. 145:9). In the NT, God through Christ feels compassion on the crowds (Matt. 9:36; 14:14; 15:32; Mk. 6:34; 8:2), the unforgiving debtor (Matt. 18:27), and the prodigal son (Lk. 15:20).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref26" name="_ftn26">[26]</a> In the OT, God exercises longsuffering toward the rebellious and stiff-necked Israelites (Neh. 9:17). In the NT, God is patient with a faithless and twisted generation (Matt. 17:17; Mk. 9:19; Lk. 9:41), the unforgiving debtor (Matt. 18:26), hypocrites (Rom. 2:4), vessels of wrath prepared for destruction (Rom. 9:22), and the wicked who were destroyed by the Flood (1 Pt. 3:20).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref27" name="_ftn27">[27]</a> In the OT, God blesses Noah and his sons (Gen. 9:1), Ishmael (Gen. 17:20), and Laban (Gen. 30:27,30). In the NT, God in Christ blesses children (Mk. 10:16) and the Old Covenant Jews (Acts 3:26).</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/does-the-bible-teach-common-grace/">Does the Bible Teach Common Grace?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/does-the-bible-teach-common-grace/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Critical Review of Donald Macleod&#8217;s &#8220;The Person of Christ&#8221;</title>
		<link>/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/</link>
					<comments>/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 13:48:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donald Macleod]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Person of Christ]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7656</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Introduction Do the ancient creeds of Nicea and Chalcedon accurately describe the person of Christ? Is He truly, very God and very man as these documents teach? Donald Macleod, principal and professor of systematic theology at the Free Church of Scotland College in Edinburgh, Scotland, defends the reliability of these creeds against the onslaught of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/">A Critical Review of Donald Macleod&#8217;s &#8220;The Person of Christ&#8221;</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Introduction</span></strong></p>
<p>Do the ancient creeds of Nicea and Chalcedon accurately describe the person of Christ? Is He truly, very God and very man as these documents teach? Donald Macleod, principal and professor of systematic theology at the Free Church of Scotland College in Edinburgh, Scotland, defends the reliability of these creeds against the onslaught of higher criticism in his book <em>The Person of Christ</em>. Macleod states, “This book…reflects my belief that the great creeds, far from betraying the gospels, faithfully encapsulate their central concern to portray Jesus as the incarnate Son of God” (15). Concerning his approach, Macleod begins his treatment of Christology with one that is &#8220;from above&#8221; and not &#8220;from below.&#8221; As he states himself, &#8220;The New Testament, almost unanimously, presents us with a Christology from above. It starts from the side of his deity, not from that of his humanity&#8221; (22). Part one, then, covers the deity of Christ while part two covers His humanity.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Summary</span></strong></p>
<p>Chapter one deals with the meaning and defense of the virgin birth. Macleod shows how the virgin birth is a miraculous sign that points to the supernatural nature of Christ and the gospel message, the judgment on sinful man, and a new humanity. It also serves to teach us about the divine sonship of Christ, His sinlessness, and the positive roles of the Holy Spirit and Mary. In chapter two, Macleod moves backward one logical step from the virgin birth to the pre-existence of Christ. The Gospel of John, the Epistle to the Hebrews, the Pauline corpus of writings, and parts of the synoptic Gospels provide enough evidence for even the skeptic to conclude that Jesus possessed a self-consciousness prior to His being sent into the world by the Father. But can Christ’s pre-existence be affirmed apart from His deity? Macleod says no: “no formal distinction can be drawn between deity and pre-existence” (57)…A person who was divine could not but be pre-existent. His godhead proved that he could not have come into being in 4 BC” (70). Chapter three presents the reader with a necessary implication of Christ’s pre-existence: His divine sonship. Macleod begins by explaining the term <em>monogenes hyios </em>as it relates to Christ: it refers to the uniqueness, and not the begottenness, of Jesus. He then goes on to deny any ontological subordinationism in the Son and affirms the co-equalness of the Son with the Father. He does, however, affirm economical subordination as it came to be in the covenant of redemption. Chapter four deals with the reliability of the church&#8217;s witness to the deity of Christ. Macleod argues that the Jesus of history is the Christ of faith. The written testimonies of the early church concerning Jesus are both genuine and reliable, but only the testimony of the Holy Spirit will persuade men of their divine authenticity. Macleod comments, &#8220;Scholarship can give a substantial vindication of the facts, but it cannot enable us to see compelling beauty in the face of Jesus. That is possible only when God the Father, through the Holy Spirit, shares with us his own view of his Son&#8221; (118). Chapter five is concerned with explaining the theology of and circumstances surrounding the Nicean Creed&#8217;s famous declaration that &#8220;Christ, as the Son of God, was <em>homoousios</em> (consubstantial) with the Father&#8221; (121). The Arian heresy, which denied Jesus&#8217; self-existence, eternity, and co-equality with God the Father, was the reason for such a statement to be drawn at the Council of Nicea in 325 AD. If Christ was not God, Christianity was a failed and doomed religion. Macleod then goes on to define the contours of the Son&#8217;s consubstantiality with the Father: He is a distinct person, He was eternally begotten of the very essence of the Father (what he terms &#8216;eternal sonship&#8217;), and He was eternally generated, not originated or made. Macleod next explains that <em>homoousios</em> means that the Father and Son are &#8220;one being and one God&#8221; or &#8220;identically one and the same substance&#8221; (139), defines <em>perichoresis</em> in this manner: &#8220;within the one godhead the three persons co-inhere in each other and interpenetrate each other&#8221; (140), argues that <em>filioque</em> should be understood as the procession of the Spirit from the Father and Son relationally, not causally, and affirms that the essence of the Son and the Spirit is <em>autotheos</em> and not subordinate to the Father&#8217;s in any way.</p>
<p>Chapter six begins part two of the book, which is entitled “Very God, Very Man”—Chalcedon &amp; Beyond. In this chapter he covers the incarnation. The heresies of Docetism and Apollinarianism drove the early church to formulate its doctrine of the incarnation around two premises: “Christ took a true human body and he took a reasonable human soul” (161). In other words, Christ partook of all human attributes, including ignorance and emotions, save sin alone in order to save us “from alongside us” (180). Chapter seven addresses the relationship of Christ’s two natures in the Council of Chalcedon. The heresies of Nestorianism and Eutychianism were combatted with the formulation of the hypostatic union of Christ’s two natures. This formula encapsulates three truths: “that Christ is one person; that the union between his two natures arises from the fact that they both belong to one and the same person; and that this one person, the Son of God, is the Agent behind all of the Lord’s actions, the Speaker of all his utterances and the Subject of all his experiences” (189). Macleod ends with an extended discussion of the <em>communication idiomatum </em>in the person of Christ and the <em>enhypostasia </em>of His human nature. Chapter eight deals with the concept of <em>kenosis</em>. In this act of making Himself nothing, Christ did not abandon, retract, or transpose certain attributes of His deity to assume humanity but instead the pre-incarnate Christ, who “occupied a position of the highest imaginable eminence” (212), did not insist on His rights to be served, worshipped, and glorified but voluntarily veiled His glory and made Himself nothing (or vanity) by taking upon Himself a human nature and dying under the curse and wrath of God. Chapter nine touches on the inherent and actual sinlessness of Christ. It is to be remembered that He assumed a perfect human nature, not a fallen one, when He entered into a state of humiliation. Finally, chapter ten presents several modern approaches to the doctrine of Christ divorced from the Chalcedonian Creed. Denials of the incarnation, resurrection, and uniqueness of Christ from different nineteenth and twentieth-century theologians are discussed and dismantled by Macleod.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Critique</span></strong></p>
<p>            Macleod certainly interacts with the entire spectrum of Christological issues and their differing viewpoints in this book. The sheer breadth of the theologians he quotes from and is conversant with is quite impressive. In other words, Macleod has done his homework! But if his goal was to uphold the creeds of the past, I think he was close but missed the bullseye of his target. As stated in the introduction of this paper, Macleod declares his belief that the Nicaean and Chalcedonian creeds “faithfully encapsulate [the gospels’] central concern to portray Jesus as the incarnate Son of God” (15). It is true that throughout this book Macleod constantly battles against those who reject these ancient confessions of faith in order to vindicate them as true summaries of what the Bible teaches concerning the person of Christ. I heartily commend him for entering into the arena of higher criticism and coming out the victor. But in the process, he does seem to modify or even reinterpret certain concepts and terms in these creeds to fit his own theological system. Nowhere is this illustrated more clearly than with Macleod&#8217;s understanding of the Son&#8217;s begottenness.</p>
<p>Macleod is quite clear about rejecting the historical and traditional meaning of the begottenness of Christ. Though he affirms His eternal sonship and begottenness, Macleod takes a modern approach to understanding the term <em>monogenes</em>. He states, “But what is that concept? There is little doubt that <em>monogenes</em> expresses the uniqueness of Jesus. He is the only one of his kind” (72). He goes on to ask,</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">But is there a uniqueness more fundamental than that the Son is uniquely loved? Is he uniquely loved because there is something either in the origin of his existence or in the mode of his existence that is unique? It is extremely doubtful where <em>monogenes</em> by itself refers to uniqueness of origin (73).</span></p></blockquote>
<p>He also states that <em>monogenes </em>carries with it little conceptual content: “It is doubtful that <em>begotten</em> adds anything to <em>Son</em>, apart from laying down that he is Son in a unique way” (73). In another place he states,</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The problem, as we have seen, is that although we know that the Son is distinguished by the fact that he is begotten, we know little or nothing of what divine begottenness is. It carries us little beyond, &#8216;Is the Son of&#8217;&#8230;The truth is, we are lost. We know that the Son is distinguished by the fact that he is begotten, but we do not know what <em>begotten</em> is&#8221; (137).</span></p></blockquote>
<p>He then concludes,</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The following conclusions, then, seem safe. First, <em>monogenes</em> says nothing about origins because the Son is unoriginated. Secondly, it emphasizes the uniqueness of Jesus’ sonship. Thirdly, this uniqueness consists in four things: he is an object of special love, he is the Father’s equal, he is the Father’s likeness and he is an eternal, not an adopted, Son (74).</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Here are my issues with such an approach:</p>
<p>(1) This sort of agnosticism to the term <em>mongenes </em>is absolutely unnecessary. Certainly, if begotten only means “unique” I can understand the mountainous problems Macleod faces. All one would know is that the Son is unique from the Father, but the content of that uniqueness remains shrouded in mystery and only slightly revealed in God&#8217;s plan of redemption. If begottenness is stripped of derivation, causation, or origination, this term really has no meaning at all! In fact, &#8220;Son&#8221; loses all its practical meaning as well! We do, however, know what this term means if we don&#8217;t limit its definition to merely &#8220;unique&#8221; but include the necessary ideas of generation and subordination. Etymologically, there is a good case to be made that <em>monogenes </em>is related to <em>gennao </em>and not <em>ginomai</em>. Although he asserts the opposite, he is mistaken. The King James Version does not “probably rest on a misapprehension” (73) but on the correct interpretation of the word. Sadly, he even goes so far as to quote Raymond Brown, avowed critic of the orthodox faith, to back up his claim! If Macleod would simply allow begottenness to retain its etymological and historical meaning, the derivation and subordination of the Son to the Father would serve as a key distinction between the two divine persons. Begottenness then would supply us with rich content that helps explain the personal distinctions inherent in the immanent Trinity.</p>
<p>(2) Macleod seems to think that the Patristic Fathers believed in an ontological subordination of the Son to the Father which tainted not only their writings but also their creeds. He says that “Christian orthodoxy has been only too willing to allow a subordinationist strain to remain in its own confession, just beside the insistence on Jesus’ deity” (76). He quotes Chrysostom as saying, “If anyone say that the Father is greater, inasmuch as he is the cause of the Son, we will not contradict this.” But Chrysostom was not saying this about the Son’s essence but His person! There is a whole world of difference between saying that the Father is greater than the Son according to His subsistence rather than according to His being!</p>
<p>(3) Though Macleod believes the Greek fathers were wrong to translate <em>monogenes </em>as “only-begotten,” he later criticizes the modern-day theologian Hugh Montefiore for not opting to translate <em>apaugasma </em>as “effulgence” like the Greek fathers did by stating, “The Greek fathers (who, after all, spoke the language) were surely in a better position to evaluate such grammatical niceties” (79). But didn’t virtually all the Greek fathers translate <em>monogenes </em>as only-begotten? If so, Macleod may benefit from a taste of his own medicine!</p>
<p>(4) At times Macleod seems to oppose the very thesis he sets out to defend. His stance is this: “If the Son and the Spirit are God then they are unoriginate (<em>agenetos</em>), that neither generation nor procession can mean origination and hence that all talk of derivation and causation are inappropriate (145).” But he admits that the general position of Patristic theology (and by implication the express teaching of the ancient creeds of Nicaea and Chalcedon) was that the eternal generation of the Son implied derivation, and therefore some sort of subordination (76). Isn’t Macleod contradicting and even arguing against his own claim that these documents “faithfully encapsulate [the gospels’] central concern to portray Jesus as the incarnate Son of God” (15) when he unwittingly charges them with incorrect views on the Son’s generation? The fact is, talk of derivation and causation are in these creeds, and if Macleod is consistent, he would have to call them (or at least parts of them) “inappropriate” instead of “faithful” to the teaching of the New Testament, thereby undermining his entire thesis and siding with the Enlightenment instead of the early church.</p>
<p>(5) It seems to me that Macleod functions as if the categories of subordination are only economical and ontological. It appears that he entirely bypasses the category of subordination of hypostases/modes of subsistences. This is seen when he fails to distinguish between the persons of the Trinity and the being of the Trinity as he denies generation and subordinationism. He claims that since Christ is the eternal Son He has no origin. That of course is true concerning the Son of God’s essence. He is <em>homousias </em>with the Father and <em>autotheos</em>. But what about the Son’s <em>hypostasis</em>? Is his personal subsistence without origin as well? Macleod says nothing. He has no issue with affirming an economical subordination of the Son to the Father brought about in the <em>pactum salutis </em>but goes no further than that. He explicitly states this when he says, “New Testament subordinationism is federal, not ontological” (78). But what about hypostatical? Again, this category seems to be missing from Macleod’s understanding.</p>
<p>(6) Macleod believes the language of derivation and origination &#8220;is fatal to the co-equal deity of the Son&#8221; (144). He thinks it creates &#8220;a totally asymmetrical Trinity in which the Father held the essence underived, while the Son and Spirit held it as derived from him&#8221; (144). He accuses John of Damascus and Augustine of enmeshing themselves &#8220;hopelessly in the language of causality&#8221; (144). For him, this language was influenced more by &#8220;Origen&#8217;s subordinationism&#8221; (145) than by biblical exegesis. Any hint of causality within the godhead reeks of &#8220;tritheism&#8221; (144). Since generation and procession have nothing to do with causality, Macleod believes &#8220;there is nothing inherently shocking about&#8221; speaking of the Son proceeding from the Father and Spirit (147). In fact, the Father Himself &#8220;owes it to the Son and Spirit that he is what he is (Father) as much as they owe to him and to each other that they are what they are (respectively Spirit and Son)&#8221; (149). Although Macleod attempts to avoid the pitfall of essential subordinationism, he falls into another by erasing any distinctions within the Godhead. If causality implies tritheism, Macleod’s view implies modalism!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Conclusion</span></strong></p>
<p>            In conclusion, Macleod’s treatment of the person of Christ is generally balanced and in line with the creedal statements of Nicea and Chalcedon. Though I disagree with him on his view of the Son’s begottenness and believe he strays from the ancient creeds at this point, his overall defense of historic Christian beliefs against the theologians of the Enlightenment assists the modern-day church in its proclamation that God descended from heaven and assumed flesh “<em>for us men and for our salvation</em>” (250).</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/">A Critical Review of Donald Macleod&#8217;s &#8220;The Person of Christ&#8221;</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
