<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Covenant Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/covenant-theology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 17:08:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Covenant Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Why is Theonomy Unbiblical?</title>
		<link>/why-is-theonomy-unbiblical/</link>
					<comments>/why-is-theonomy-unbiblical/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tom Hicks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 17:08:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Civil Government]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Covenant Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=18787</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Before critiquing theonomy, we need a good definition. Some people today who use the word “theonomy” don’t mean anything more than “God’s law” because the etimology of the word theonomy is “theos” which means God, and “nomos” which means law. They only want to affirm that God’s law is supreme over man’s law. And they’re right about that. God’s transcendent moral law is the norm that norms all norms. Governmental laws should always be consistent with God’s law and human law must never violate God’s law.</p>
<p>But in this post, I’ll be using the word “theonomy” in a more technical sense, which is rooted in the historic usage of the term.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-is-theonomy-unbiblical/">Why is Theonomy Unbiblical?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_0 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_0">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_0  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_0  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p>Before critiquing theonomy, we need a good definition. Some people today who use the word “theonomy” don’t mean anything more than “God’s law” because the etimology of the word theonomy is “theos” which means God, and “nomos” which means law. They only want to affirm that God’s law is supreme over man’s law. And they’re right about that. God’s transcendent moral law is the norm that norms all norms. Governmental laws should always be consistent with God’s law and human law must never violate God’s law.</p>
<p>But in this post, I’ll be using the word “theonomy” in a more technical sense, which is rooted in the historic usage of the term. Theonomy, in the technical sense, teaches that Old Covenant judicial laws are the universal moral standard of civil law for all Gentile nations. The basic presupposition of theonomy is that God gave the judicial law to the nation of Israel as a universal law of perfect justice for all nations because it is a perfect reflection of God’s own moral character. Some of the most prominent early proponents of this kind of theonomy include Greg Bahnsen, Rousas Rushdoony and Gary North. For a discussion of “general equity theonomy,”<span> </span><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://pastortomhicks.com/2021/03/16/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/" target="_blank">see here</a>.</p>
<p>I’m convinced that theonomy is unbiblical for a number of reasons.</p>
<h3><em><strong>1. Theonomy has a flawed hermeutic of Old Testament priority.</strong></em></h3>
<p>Theonomy arrives at its conclusions by insisting that particular Old Testament laws persist, unless they are specifically abrogated by the New Testament. But this reads the Bible improperly. Theonomy’s hermeneutic is consistent with paedobaptism, which says that since the New Testament does not abrogate the Old Testament inclusion of infants, then infants must be given the sign of baptism. Theonomy is also consistent with the Old Testament priority<span> </span><a href="https://www.the-highway.com/theonomy-hermeneutic_Irons.html">hermeneutic of dispensationalism</a>, which teaches that the promises God made for Israel cannot be typologically fulfilled in Christ and the church, but must be literally fulfilled in national Israel. But theonomy’s hermeneutic isn’t consistent with<span> </span><a href="https://founders.org/2016/05/26/hermeneutics-new-testament-priority/">the hermeneutic of New Testament priority</a>.</p>
<p>It is true that earlier revelation is vital for understanding the context of later revelation. In that sense, earlier revelation is logically prior to later revelation. But sound hermeneutical principles recognize that later revelation has interpretive priority over earlier revelation. Therefore, when later Old Testament texts explain earlier parts of the Old Testament, we should pay close attention to what the later texts say and allow them to explain and draw out implications of earlier Old Testament texts, making explicit what was only previously implicit. Similarly, when the New Testament explains Old Testament passages of Scripture, the New Testament has priority of interpretation over the Old Testament.</p>
<p>If the New Testament says an Old Testament passage has a particular meaning, we should assign that meaning to the Old Testament passage. The same is true of New Testament letters, which explain the earlier life and work of Jesus Christ in the Gospels.</p>
<p>This is nothing other than what Augustine taught when he said, “The New is in the Old concealed; the Old is in the New revealed.” The light of revelation is brighter as we move toward the end of the Bible (Louis Berkhof,<span> </span><em>Principles of Interpretation</em>, pp. 54, 133, 135, 137). Berkhof says, “The New Testament is implicit in the Old, so the Old is explicit in the new” (135). And “The more perfect revelation of the New Testament illumines the pages of the Old” (137-138).</p>
<p>This isn’t really any different from the way we read any book by a single author. We allow the later parts of a book to interpret the earlier parts of the book. Orthodox theology is rooted in the idea that the one true God authored the whole of the Scriptures. Thus, we should pay close attention to His intended meaning in light of His explanation of His own Word.</p>
<h3><em><strong>2. Theonomy does not account for the fact that Gentile nations are not and never were under the Old Covenant.</strong></em></h3>
<p>The laws peculiar to the Old Covenant do not bind Gentile nations. Gentile nations are under natural law, which is the work of the moral law written on the hearts of all human beings. Romans 2:14 says, “For when the Gentiles, who do not have the law, by nature, do what the law requires, they are a law to themselves, even though they do not have the law. They show that the work of the law is written on their hearts.”</p>
<p>When God judged the Gentile nations in the Old Testament, He never judged them for violating Old Covenant judicial law. Rather, He judged them for violating His moral law, as summarized in the Ten Commandments (Jerermiah 46-51; Ezekiel 25-32; Amos 1-2; Obadiah; Jonah; Nahum; Habakkuk 2 – a taunt song against the Babylonians for violating God’s moral law; Zephaniah 2).</p>
<h3><em><strong>3. Theonomy doesn’t properly account for the fact that the Old Covenant as a whole, together with all of its laws, has been abolished.</strong></em></h3>
<p>Numerous passages of Scripture teach that the Old Covenant has been fulfilled and abolished with the coming of Christ and the establishment of the New Covenant.</p>
<ul>
<li>Hebrews 7:12 says, “For when there is a change in the priesthood, there is necessarily a change in the law as well.”</li>
<li>Hebrews 7:18 says, “A former commandment is set aside because of its weakness and uselessness.”</li>
<li>Hebrews 8:13 says, “In speaking of a new covenant, he makes the first one obsolete.”</li>
<li>Hebrews 10:9 says, “He abolishes the first in order to establish the second.”</li>
<li>Ephesians 2:14-15 says that Christ “has broken down in his flesh the dividing wall of hostility, by abolishing the law of commandments and ordinances.”</li>
</ul>
<p>To be clear, the moral law, which is summarized in the Ten Commandments,<span> </span><a href="https://pastortomhicks.com/2020/01/22/are-the-ten-commandments-distinct-from-other-old-testament-law/">has not been abolished</a>. The moral law is rooted in God’s own eternal moral character and is part of the image of God in human beings. Moral aspects of Old Covenant law can never be abolished because they are rooted in nature, not merely in a covenant. But the positive laws of the Old Covenant have been abolished. Theonomy does not properly account for this fact.</p>
<p>Rich Barcellos correctly notes, “The New Testament clearly abrogates the whole Old Covenant, including the Decalogue, as it functioned within the Old Covenant, and yet borrows from its documents as the basis for New Covenant ethics (see for instance 1 Cor. 9:9-10; 14:34; 2 Cor 13:1; Eph 6:2-3, and many other texts)” (<em>In Defense of the Decalogue</em>, p. 68).</p>
<h3><em><strong>4. Theonomy doesn’t acknowledge the existence of positive law in contrast to moral or natural law.</strong></em></h3>
<p>This is related to numbers 2 and 3 above. Natural law is law that people know innately. Romans 2:14-15 is clear that God writes the work of His natural law on the hearts of all men, and Romans 2:21-24 shows that natural law is summarized in the Ten Commandments. Natural law is nothing other than the reflection of God’s moral character in human beings who are made in His image.</p>
<p>Positive law, on the other hand, is law that God posited by way of special revelation in a particular covenant. No one would have known that they ought to obey positive law, unless it had been revealed to them in a biblical covenant.</p>
<p>To give you an example of the distinction between natural/moral and positive law, consider Adam in the Garden of Eden. Adam knew by nature not to worship false gods, not to steal, not to murder, etc. He knew these laws because he was made in the image of God. But Adam would never have known not to eat of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, if God had not revealed and commanded that positive law to him in the covenant of works.</p>
<p>To give you another example, Abraham knew by nature that it was wrong to lie to Pharoah about Sarah being his wife. God never had to tell Abraham that lying was wrong because all images of God know it’s wrong to lie, even if they suppress that truth in unrighteousness. But Abraham would never have known that he had to be circumcised except for the fact that God revealed that law to him and commanded him to be circumcised in the covenant of circumcision. Natural law is known innately, but positive law would never be known apart from covenantal revelation.</p>
<p>Natural or moral law transcends all covenants. It’s immutably rooted in the nature and character of God and also in human nature. Fallen human beings suppress their knowledge of natural law, which is why we need Scripture to reassert and clarify it. But even fallen human beings are not completely ignorant of natural law. Positive law, on the other hand, is covenantal, must be specially revealed to be known, and serves a particular purpose within the covenant in which it is given. When covenants change, positive laws change, but moral or natural law does not.</p>
<p>Theonomy does not grasp this crucial distinction. The judicial laws of the Old Covenant are not transcendent moral or natural law, but positive laws, which God commanded in the Old Covenant for a particular reason.</p>
<h3><em><strong>5. Theonomy does not account for the fact that the judicial laws of Israel were only to be practiced in the land of Canaan.</strong></em></h3>
<p>It’s impossible to separate Israel’s judicial law from the land of Canaan. The Old Covenant law was given to the Old Covenant people, who were to keep the law in the Old Covenant land. Deuteronomy 4:14 says, “And the LORD commanded me at that time to teach you statues and rules that you might do them<span> </span><em>in the land</em><span> </span>that you are going over to possess.”</p>
<p>To give one example, consider the law of the parapet. Deuteronomy 22:8 says, “When you build a new house, you shall make a parapet for your roof, that you may not bring the guilt of blood upon your house, if anyone should fall from it.” This judicial law, which is based on blood-guilt, only makes sense because the land of Israel is holy. According to the Old Covenant, blood-guilt defiles the land and results in the expulsion of the people. Deuteronomy 19:10 warns that if blood guilt comes upon the land, the guilt of blood shall be shed upon the people.</p>
<p>While there is certainly an element of perpetual moral law (general equity, “do not murder”) in the law of the parapet, the law itself could only be practiced in the land of Canaan, which is the case for all Old Covenant judicial law.</p>
<h3><em><strong>6. Theonomy misunderstands the reason for the death penalties in Old Covenant judicial law.</strong></em></h3>
<p>Before discussing the death penalty in Old Covenant judicial law, it’s important to understand that the covenant of common grace establishes the death penalty for murder. The death penalty for murder is part of universal moral law. In Genesis 9:6, the Noahic covenant of common grace says, “Whoever sheds the blood of man, by man shall his blood be shed, for God made man in his own image.” That is a transcendent moral principle: the punishment must fit the crime. It is<span> </span><em>lex talionis</em>, which is the “law of the same,” often expressed as “an eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth.” It refers to equal weights and measures in justice. So, the death penalty for murder is moral law.</p>
<p>But other Old Testament death penalties are tied to Old Covenant worship. The term “devoted to destruction” or “devoted to the ban” (Hebrew:<span> </span><em>cherem</em>) involves the death penalty, and it is connected to the purity of the land, holy war, and Old Covenant worship.</p>
<p>Deuteronomy 13:12-16 says:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>“If you hear in one of your cities, which the Lord your God is giving you to dwell there, that certain worthless fellows have gone out among you and have drawn away the inhabitants of their city, saying, ‘Let us go and serve other gods,’ which you have not known, then you shall inquire and make search and ask diligently. And behold, if it be true and certain that such an abomination has been done among you, you shall surely put the inhabitants of that city to the sword, devoting it to destruction, all who are in it and its cattle, with the edge of the sword. You shall gather all its spoil into the midst of its open square and burn the city and all its spoil with fire, as a whole burnt offering to the Lord your God. It shall be a heap forever. It shall not be built again.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is saying that if a city comes under the influence of idolaters, there is to be a careful inquiry, and if it’s found to be true that the city is under the influence of idolaters, then the whole city is to be put to death, together with the cattle.</p>
<p>This law is not simply a matter of moral justice. Verse 16 says that the city becomes a “whole burnt offering to the Lord your God.” It’s an offering to God. This is a law about holy war and Israel’s possession of the holy land. It’s a kind of ceremonial purification.</p>
<p>It also anticipates Judgment Day. The New Testament seems to teach that the death penalties of the Old Covenant are types of eternal condemnation.</p>
<p>Hebrews 10:28 says:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>“Anyone who has set aside the law of Moses dies without mercy on the evidence of two or three witnesses. How much<span> </span><em>worse</em><span> </span>punishment, do you think, will be deserved by the one who has trampled underfoot the Son of God, and has profaned the blood of the covenant by which he was sanctified, and has outraged the Spirit of grace? For we know him who said, “Vengeance is mine; I will repay.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In other words, under the Old Covenant, the penalty for breaking the law was physical death. But the corresponding doctrine of the New Testament is eternal condemnation for those without Christ.</p>
<p>So, the death penalties of the Old Testament are associated with Israel’s unique place in redemptive history. I’m convinced that scholars have shown that all of the death penalties of the Old Covenant are based on the distinctive purposes of the Old Covenant. I recommend Vern Poythress’s book,<span> </span><em>The Shadow of Christ in the Law of Moses</em>, which illustrates this very well. I don’t agree with everything in that book, but it is a good resource to have.</p>
<p>Due to their special character, therefore, it would be unjust to apply Old Covenant death penalties in a Gentile nation. It was perfectly just for Israel to put people to death for all sorts of reasons because God has the right to command the death of any sinner, and He commanded the death of many sinners via the Old Covenant for reasons that were unique to that covenant. But we have no right to implement such penalties in Gentile nations.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the death penalties of the Old Covenant are reflective of the fact that it is a “work for the right to inheritance” covenant. Leviticus 18:5 says, “You shall therefore keep my statutes and my rules; if a person does them, he shall live by them: I am the LORD.” But the new covenant gives the inheritance by grace, not by works. Galatians 3:12-13 denies this works principle under the gospel, “But the law is not of faith, rather, ‘the one who does them shall live by them.’ Christ redeemed us from the curse of the law by becoming a curse for us — for it is written, ‘Cursed is everyone who is hanged on a tree.&#8217;”</p>
<h3><em><strong>7. Theonomy does not account for the fact that the Old Covenant law was intentionally severe to preserve the line of promise.</strong></em></h3>
<p>The nation of Israel was largely an unbelieving nation. The people needed a severe legal system to chasten them and to preserve them as a nation until Christ would come from them. The severity of Old Covenant judicial law is especially evident in the liberal use of the death penalty. The death penalty was prescribed for false-worship and apostasy (Deut 13:6-11; 17:5), blasphemy (Lev 24:10-16, 23), sabbath-breaking (Num 15:31-36), rebellious sons (Deut 21:18-21), fornication (Deut 22:20-23), adultery (Lev 20:10-11), homosexuality (Lev 20:13) and many other sins. These are very heavy penalties.</p>
<p>Galatians 3:19 explains one of the reasons for such laws: “Why then the law? It was added because of transgressions,<span> </span><em>until</em><span> </span>the offspring should come to whom the promise had been made.” Similarly, Galatians 3:24-25 says, “So, then the law was our guardian<span> </span><em>until</em><span> </span>Christ came, in order that we might be justified by faith. But<span> </span><em>now</em><span> </span>that faith has come, we are no longer under a guardian.”</p>
<p>Scripture is saying that the severe Old Covenant law was given because of the sins of the people of Israel. It was given to them as a nation, to chasten them, and to act as a deterrent for outward sin, and to keep them from destroying themselves,<span> </span><em>until</em><span> </span>Christ came from them.</p>
<p>The Jerusalem council discussed the fact that some wanted the church to practice circumcision. Acts 15:10 says, “Now, therefore, why are you putting God to the test by placing a yoke on the neck of the disciples that neither our fathers nor we have been able to bear?” The covenant of circumcision, and the Old Covenant as a whole, was a heavy legal yoke. Those who try to impose it upon Christians or Gentile nations are heaping a heavy burden upon them. Now that Christ has come, there is no reason for it. The yoke of the Old Covenant has been fulfilled and abolished with the coming of Christ.</p>
<h3><em><strong>8. In each case, when the New Testament applies one of the judicial laws of the Old Covenant, it applies the law’s general equity to the church, and never to the government of a Gentile nation.</strong></em></h3>
<p>This is important because of the hermeneutical principle of New Testament priority. The New Testament teaches us how to interpret and use the Old Testament, which means we need to pay attention to how the New Testament applies Old Covenant judicial laws. You will never find a single New Testament example of an Old Covenant judicial law being applied to a Gentile government.</p>
<p>For example, 1 Timothy 5:17-18 says, “Let the elders who rule well be considered worthy of double honor, especially those who labor in preaching and teaching. For the Scripture says, ‘You shall not muzzle an ox when it treads out the grain,’ and ‘the laborer deserves his wages.” “Do not muzzle the ox while it treads out the grain” is a judicial law that comes from Deuteronomy 25:4. But here, Paul applies the law’s general equity (do not steal) to paying pastors properly in the church. He does not apply it to a Gentile government.</p>
<p>Another example comes from 1 Corinthians 5:13, where Paul is discussing church discipline, and he says, “Purge the evil person from among you.” That’s a judicial law from Deuteronomy 13:5, 17:7, 12, and many other places. In the Old Covenant, “purging the evil person from among you” referred to the death penalty. But in the New Covenant, that judicial law is applied to church discipline, not to the civil death penalty.</p>
<p>So, if we allow the New Testament to teach us how to interpret Old Covenant judicial laws, then we will think of their general equity first as applying to the church, not primarily to Gentile civil governments.</p>
<h3><em><strong>9. To sum up, theonomy’s central mistake is believing that God gave the judicial law of Israel as a universal norm of societal justice for all nations.</strong></em></h3>
<p>Certainly, the moral law of the Old Covenant is a universal norm for all nations. And we ought to use the Old Testament to help us understand God’s moral law. But the positive laws of the Old Covenant had many different functions according to Scripture, and all of them were bound to the unique objectives of the Old Covenant.</p>
<p>As we have seen, the judicial law was tied to the land, to ceremonial worship, and to the preservation of Christ’s line of promise. Some of the judicial laws were simply designed to create a distinct culture for Israel that separated them from the nations. Others were about preserving family lines for the sake of property and inheritance. But all of the positive laws of the Old Covenant were related to the typological character of the Old Covenant and/or to its unique cultural situation and place in redemptive history.</p>
<p>In conclusion, theonomy, in the technical sense of the term is not a biblical idea. Scripture itself refutes the theonomic position, such that in fact, theonomy is not in favor of God’s law at all, but adds to the good law of God positive covenantal precepts that were designed to expire with the coming of the Lord Jesus.</p>
<p>While this article has been a critique of Theonomy, and I have not outlined a positive biblical theology of civil government, the<span> </span><em>Second London Baptist Confession of Faith</em>, chapter 24, provides a wonderful framework for civil government. I wrote an exposition of that chapter here:<span> </span><a href="https://pastortomhicks.com/2020/04/02/what-is-the-role-of-civil-government/">What is the role of civil government?</a></p>
<p>For another good resource on Theonomy<span> </span><a href="https://contrast2.wordpress.com/2020/09/18/theonomy/">see this article by Brandon Adams</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section -->
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/tom-hicks/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2018/03/02211852/TomHicks.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/tom-hicks/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Tom Hicks</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><div class="header">
<div class="description">Tom serves as the Senior Pastor of First Baptist Church of Clinton, LA. He&#8217;s married to Joy, and they have four children: Sophie, Karlie, Rebekah, and David. He received his MDiv and PhD degrees from The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary with a major in Church History, emphasis on Baptists, and with a minor in Systematic Theology. Tom is the author of The Doctrine of Justification in the Theologies of Richard Baxter and Benjamin Keach (PhD diss, SBTS). He serves on the board of directors for Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary and is an adjunct professor of historical theology for the Institute of Reformed Baptist Studies.</div>
</div>
<div id="featured">
<div class="hero"></div>
</div>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-is-theonomy-unbiblical/">Why is Theonomy Unbiblical?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/why-is-theonomy-unbiblical/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is &#8220;General Equity Theonomy&#8221; a Confessional and Biblical Doctrine?</title>
		<link>/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/</link>
					<comments>/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tom Hicks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 21:28:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Civil Government]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Covenant Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=18755</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Some of those who identify as theonomists today refer to themselves as “general equity theonomists,” believing that this identification lands them within the boundaries of Reformed confessional orthodoxy. But if it does, then the term “general equity” needs to be defined the same way the tradition defined it. The technical term “general equity” is used in both the Westminster Confession and the Second London Baptist Confession.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/">Is &#8220;General Equity Theonomy&#8221; a Confessional and Biblical Doctrine?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_1 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_1">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_1  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_1  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><h2><em><strong>Is “General Equity Theonomy” a Confessional and Biblical Doctrine?</strong></em></h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Some of those who identify as theonomists today refer to themselves as “general equity theonomists,” believing that this identification lands them within the boundaries of Reformed confessional orthodoxy. But if it does, then the term “general equity” needs to be defined the same way the tradition defined it. The technical term “general equity” is used in both the <em>Westminster Confession</em> and the <em>Second London Baptist Confession</em>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em>The Westminster Confession of Faith</em> 19.4 says, “To them also, as a body politic, He gave sundry judicial laws, which expired together with the State of that people; not obliging any other now, further than the <em>general equity</em> thereof may require.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Following the <em>Savoy Declaration</em>, the <em>Second London Baptist Confession of Faith</em> 19.4 says, “To them also he gave sundry judicial laws, which expired together with the state of that people, not obliging any now by virtue of that institution; their <em>general equity</em> only being of moral use.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>So, while the confessions teach that the “general equity” of the judicial law obliges us, the question remains as to whether “general equity theonomists” mean the same thing by general equity that the confessions mean.  I have found it hard to nail down a single clear definition of “general equity theonomy” that universally describes those who say they hold to it. The term seems to be defined variously and even in contradictory ways. So, rather than focus on the personalities involved in this debate, or cite definitions from a number of different adherents, I want to address what some appear to mean by “general equity theonomy,” which is that the essential or core principles of Old Testament judicial laws have binding authority today. That is, many say that the Old Testament judicial laws have been abrogated, but the essential principles of the judicial laws continue to bind all people today. </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><em> 1. <strong style="font-size: 22px;">The Historic Meaning of the Term “General Equity”</strong></em></h3>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The question as to the meaning of the term “general equity” is a matter of historical research. I am indebted to Brandon Adams for several of the quotations found in this section.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>John Calvin identifies the term “equity” with moral law. “It is a fact that the law of God which we call the <em>moral law</em> is nothing else than a testimony of <em>natural law</em> and of that conscience which God has engraved upon the minds of men. Consequently, the entire scheme of this <em>equity</em> of which we are now speaking has been prescribed in it. Hence, <em>this equity alone must be the goal and rule and limit of all laws</em>” (<em>Institutes</em> 4.20.15-16, italics in the text are mine).</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Calvin’s successor in Geneva, Theodore Beza, wrote, “Although we do not hold to the forms of the Mosaic polity, yet when such <em>judicial laws</em> prescribe <em>equity</em> in judgments, <em>which is part of the decalogue</em>, we, not being under obligation to them insofar as they were prescribed by Moses to only one people, are nevertheless bound to observe them to the extent that they embrace that <em>general equity</em> which should everywhere be in force . . . . Because it follows <em>natural equity</em>, and expounds that <em>perpetual precept of the decalogue</em>, Thou shalt not steal, to this extent all are bound to fulfill them both” (<em>De Haereticis a civili Magistratu puniendis Libellus, </em>Geneva: Robert Stephanus, 1554, pp. 222-23, italics in the text are mine). Beza clearly linked general equity to the decalogue and natural law.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>William Perkins wrote, “Judicial laws so far as they have in them the <em>general or common equity</em> of the <em>law of nature</em> <em>are moral</em> and therefore binding in conscience as <em>the moral law</em>” (<em>A Discourse on Cases of Conscience</em> in <em>The Whole Works, </em>London, 1631, 1.520).</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Thus, the historic meaning of the term “general equity” refers exclusively to the moral law, summarized in the Ten Commandments, which is also revealed in the law of nature. The crucial thing to understand about the general equity of the old covenant judicial law is that the judicial law’s general equity is not first to be found in the judicial laws themselves. If there is general equity in any given old covenant judicial law, it is first found in nature, in creation and conscience, and it is also summarily taught in the Ten Commandments. Therefore, we should not approach old covenant judicial laws to discover distinctive or new principles of law, which are not already revealed in creation, conscience, or the decalogue. Old covenant judicial laws do not establish timeless principles of law; rather, to the extent that there is any general equity in them, it is based on the larger trans-covenantal moral law of nature, which is found outside of those laws.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Therefore, if “general equity theonomy” means that the core principles of the judicial laws remain in force, but those principles do not necessarily entail God’s transcendent moral and natural law summarized in the Ten Commandments, then that definition of general equity is contrary to the Reformed confessional tradition. According to the confessional tradition, we must not begin with judicial law to discover principles of general equity. Rather, we must begin with the decalogue and see whether there is any moral or natural law principle in any given judicial law.</p>
<p><em style="font-size: 22px;"><strong></strong></em></p>
<p><em style="font-size: 22px;"><strong>2. The New Testament Use of Judicial Law</strong></em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>If it’s true that the essential core principles of the judicial laws remain binding for us today, then consider how we might interpret Deuteronomy 25:4, which says, “You shall not muzzle an ox when it is treading out the grain.” Without the inspired New Testament commentary on this passage, we might say that a core principle of this passage is “You should allow your animals to feed while they are working.” One way to apply this law might be to say that people should see to it that their hunting dogs always have access to a portion of the meat they kill during the hunt as a matter of biblical law. That would seem to be a reasonable application of the core principle of this judicial law, recognizing that the law itself has been abrogated, but that the essence of it is perpetually binding.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>And yet, the New Testament does not derive any such essential principle from Deuteronomy 25:4. Rather, the New Testament finds the eighth commandment embedded in Deuteronomy 25:4, which is an element of transcendent moral and natural law, “You shall not steal” (Ex 20:15). 1 Timothy 5:17-18 says, “Let the elders who rule well be considered worthy of double honor, especially those who labor in preaching and teaching. For the Scripture says, ‘You shall not muzzle an ox when it treads out the grain,’ and, ‘The laborer deserves his wages.’” The general equity of the law of the muzzled ox is that you must not steal wages from the one who works. Paul saw that the general equity of Deuteronomy 25:4 is nothing other than the eighth commandment, which means that churches should pay their pastors. The same general equity of Deuteronomy 25:4 would apply to refusing to use unjust weights and balances, to forbidding customers from stealing from merchants, merchants from stealing from customers, etc.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In conclusion, any version of “general equity theonomy,” which does not look for prior transcendent moral law within the judicial law, which is summarized in the decalogue and/or revealed in nature, uses a hermeneutic contrary to the New Testament. The issue at stake is the controls on our interpretation and application of judicial law.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em style="font-size: 22px;"><strong>3. The Way to Find and Apply General Equity of Judicial Law</strong></em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Take Deuteronomy 22:8 as an example. It says, “When you build a new house, you shall make a parapet for your roof, that you may not bring the guilt of blood upon your house, if anyone should fall from it.” Someone wrote, “We are not morally required to build a parapet around our roof line because we don’t go up there. But general equity would require a rail around your second story deck.” In this instance, the application of general equity theonomy seems to keep tightly to the essential core principles of the judicial law in question. Not a roof, but a second story deck. Not a parapet, but a railing. It’s not the particulars of the law that are binding, but the essential principles.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>But it’s crucial to understand that the general equity of the law of the parapet isn’t merely a matter of the essential principles of that particular judicial law. The general equity of the law of the parapet is nothing other than the sixth commandment, “You shall not murder” (Ex 20:13). Does the law’s general equity require a railing around a second story deck to protect the lives of people who go up there? Absolutely. But railings on second story decks are not required because of the law of the parapet itself. Rather, general equity requires a railing on a second story deck because of the transcendent moral law, summarized in the decalogue, which stands behind the law of the parapet: “You shall not murder.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Understood properly, the general equity of the law of the parapet requires us to protect other people’s lives, and not merely do what is expedient, cheaper, or more convenient for ourselves. The general equity of the law of the parapet applies in a number of circumstances. People who use guns should practice gun safety principles. If you have a deadly illness, take precautions not to spread it to others as far as it depends on you. Salt your sidewalks after an ice storm. Drive safely so as not to endanger others. Don’t leave live electrical wires exposed in your home. The sixth commandment requires that you not be concerned merely for yourself, but must always live so as to protect the lives of other people. That is the general equity of the law of the parapet, the sixth commandment, “do not murder.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2><em><strong>Conclusion</strong></em></h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In conclusion, any understanding of the term general equity, which neglects the decalogue, or natural law revealed in creation or conscience, as the essence of general equity is not accurately defining the term according to its historic and confessional sense. Any version of general equity theonomy that does not look for a moral law that transcends Old Testament judicial law but instead sees Old Testament judicial law as itself a subset of moral law that remains binding is not following the example of the New Testament.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The greatest mistake of such a hermeneutic is that it does not begin with the universal transcendent norms of natural and moral law, summarized in the Ten Commandments, seeking to find those moral principles within judicial law. Rather, it begins with the judicial laws themselves and tries to uncover the essential principles within those laws, wrongly assuming they are all moral, in order to apply them universally.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section -->
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/tom-hicks/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2018/03/02211852/TomHicks.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/tom-hicks/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Tom Hicks</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><div class="header">
<div class="description">Tom serves as the Senior Pastor of First Baptist Church of Clinton, LA. He&#8217;s married to Joy, and they have four children: Sophie, Karlie, Rebekah, and David. He received his MDiv and PhD degrees from The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary with a major in Church History, emphasis on Baptists, and with a minor in Systematic Theology. Tom is the author of The Doctrine of Justification in the Theologies of Richard Baxter and Benjamin Keach (PhD diss, SBTS). He serves on the board of directors for Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary and is an adjunct professor of historical theology for the Institute of Reformed Baptist Studies.</div>
</div>
<div id="featured">
<div class="hero"></div>
</div>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/">Is &#8220;General Equity Theonomy&#8221; a Confessional and Biblical Doctrine?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The 2LBC &#038; the Covenant of Works</title>
		<link>/the-2lbc-the-covenant-of-works/</link>
					<comments>/the-2lbc-the-covenant-of-works/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rexford Semrad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 16:04:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Covenant Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=16126</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is part 2 of a blog series by Rex Semrad on Covenant Theology. You can find part 1 here. There has been an unfortunate amount of confusion regarding the relationship between the Second London Baptist Confession of Faith (1677/1689) and the doctrine of the Covenant of Works. In one sense this is understandable for [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-2lbc-the-covenant-of-works/">The 2LBC &#038; the Covenant of Works</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>This is part 2 of a blog series by Rex Semrad on Covenant Theology. You can find part 1 <a href="/covenant-theology-the-2lbc-cbts/" data-type="URL" data-id="/covenant-theology-the-2lbc-cbts/">here</a>.</em></p>



<p>There has been an unfortunate amount of confusion regarding the relationship between the Second London Baptist Confession of Faith (1677/1689) and the doctrine of the Covenant of Works. In one sense this is understandable for the following reason.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Both the Westminster Confession of Faith and the Savoy Declaration state in chapter 7, paragraph 2: “The first covenant made with man was a covenant of works, wherein life was promised to Adam, and in him to his posterity, upon condition of perfect and personal obedience.” The 2LBC omits this paragraph completely, which has led some to the conclusion that the authors of our confession chose not to confess the Covenant of Works.</p>



<p>This conclusion, though understandable, must be rejected if the confession as a whole is rightly understood. If we closely examine the 2LBC, we will find that the omission of this paragraph was made for editorial purposes and was not intended as a rejection of the content of the paragraph.</p>



<p><strong>The Covenant of Works in 2LBC Chapter 6</strong></p>



<p>To begin with, the substance of the Covenant of Works (C o W) is added to chapter 6 of the 2LBC as can be seen in paragraphs 1 &amp; 3.&nbsp; The term C o W is not used, but the doctrine is clearly confessed.</p>



<p><strong>Chapter 6:&nbsp;Of the Fall of Man, Of Sin, And of the Punishment Thereof</strong></p>



<p>1. Although God created man upright and perfect, and <em>gave him a righteous law, which had been unto life had he kept it</em>, <em>and threatened death upon the breach thereof</em>, yet he did not long abide in this honour; Satan using the subtlety of the serpent to subdue Eve, then by her seducing Adam, who, without any compulsion, did willfully transgress the law of their creation, <em>and the command given unto them</em>, in eating the forbidden fruit, which God was pleased, according to his wise and holy counsel to permit, having purposed to order it to his own glory.&nbsp;(italics mine)</p>



<p>The most important thing to note here is that God gave Adam “a righteous law, which had been unto life had he kept it…”&nbsp; We see here that though this arrangement is not explicitly called a covenant in this paragraph, a covenant must be what is being confessed.&nbsp; The very first paragraph of the next chapter of the confession makes this abundantly clear:</p>



<p><strong>Chapter 7:&nbsp;Of God&#8217;s Covenant</strong></p>



<p>1. The distance between God and the creature is so great, that although reasonable creatures do owe obedience to him as their creator, yet <em>they could never have attained the reward of life but by some voluntary condescension on God&#8217;s part, which he hath been pleased to express by way of covenant.</em> (italics mine)</p>



<p>According to the 2LBC, the <em>only</em> way a creature can attain a “reward of life” is by a “voluntary condescension on God&#8217;s part” which is called a covenant.&nbsp; So when we confess that a righteous law would have been unto life had it been kept, we are confessing that this was a covenant.</p>



<p>Before moving on, we must take note of two other points in chapter 6.&nbsp; In paragraph 1, we see that “Adam… did willfully transgress the law of their creation, <em>and the command given unto them</em>…” The authors of the confession are making an important distinction here.&nbsp; A distinction is made between the “law of their creation” and “the command given unto them.” The command not to partake of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil was not simply a part of the law of creation, it is a positive law added to it.&nbsp; Positive laws are laws pertaining to specific covenants as opposed to natural law, which is the moral law of God which all men are subject to by creation and nature.</p>



<p>We also see federal headship clearly confessed in 2LBC 6:3 “…by God&#8217;s appointment, standing in the room and stead of all mankind, the guilt of the sin was imputed, and corrupted nature conveyed, to all their posterity descending from them by ordinary generation…”&nbsp; It is not simply by nature that Adam stood as the federal head of all mankind, but specifically by Divine appointment.</p>



<p><strong>The Covenant of Works in 2LBC Chapters 19 &amp; 20</strong></p>



<p>While it seems clear from chapter 6 alone that the 2LBC does not reject the Covenant of Works, chapters 19 &amp; 20 make this conclusion beyond any reasonable doubt. Chapter 19 begins:</p>



<p><strong>Chapter 19: Of the Law of God</strong></p>



<p>1. God gave to Adam a law of universal obedience written in his heart, and a particular precept of not eating the fruit of the tree of knowledge of good and evil; by which he bound him and all his posterity to personal, entire, exact, and perpetual obedience; promised life upon the fulfilling, and threatened death upon the breach of it, and endued him with power and ability to keep it.&nbsp;</p>



<p>We have here a most explicit statement of the C o W.&nbsp; It could practically be the answer to a catechism question, “What is the covenant of works?”&nbsp; The only thing missing is federal headship, which we saw confessed in 6:3!&nbsp; The term “covenant” is not used, but we see here again a promise of life that can only be possible by way of a covenant according to 7:1.</p>



<p>But one might object, “We still have not seen the term “Covenant of Works” used. If the authors indeed confessed it, why did they not use the term?”&nbsp; The answer is that they did use the term.</p>



<p><strong>Chapter 20:&nbsp;Of the Gospel, and of the Extent of the Grace Thereof</strong></p>



<p>1. <em>The covenant of works being broken by sin, and made unprofitable unto life</em>, God was pleased to give forth the promise of Christ, the seed of the woman, as the means of calling the elect, and begetting in them faith and repentance; in this promise the gospel, as to the substance of it, was revealed, and [is] therein effectual for the conversion and salvation of sinners. (italics mine)</p>



<p>Here we have the explicit use of the term, and the confession that the covenant of works has been broken. How could we confess that something we don’t believe existed was broken?</p>



<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>



<p>The authors of the 2LBC made the editorial decision to move the first mention of the Covenant of Works from chapter 7 to chapter 6.&nbsp; This is quite understandable.&nbsp; It makes perfect sense to begin the chapter on the fall of man with the substance of the covenant from which he fell. Why didn’t they use the term in chapter 6?&nbsp; The covenant of works was not a doctrine that was disputed among them. It was the common parlance of the day. Those reading the confession in the day in which it was written would have recognized what was being confessed.&nbsp; They simply did not feel the need to say “this is the covenant of works” every time they mentioned it.</p>



<p>Unfortunately in our day, broad evangelicalism has forgotten or rejected this important doctrine, something the authors of the 2LBC could not have foreseen. The failures of the modern church must not taint our impressions of those upon whose shoulders we stand. Let us follow in the footsteps of our Particular Baptist forefathers and heartily confess this important doctrine.</p>



<p>For further reading I highly recommend:</p>



<p>Barcellos, <em>The Covenant of Works: Its Confessional and Scriptural Basis</em></p>



<p>Barcellos, <em>Getting the Garden Right</em></p>



<p>Renihan, <em>From Shadow to Substance, The Federal Theology of the English Particular Baptists (1642-1704)</em></p>



<p>Renihan, <em>The Mystery of Christ, His Covenant &amp; His Kingdom</em></p>



<p><a href="https://www.1689federalism.com/tag/covenant-of-works/">https://www.1689federalism.com/tag/covenant-of-works/</a></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/rex/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/03/23164330/rex-semrad.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/rex/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Rexford Semrad</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Rexford Semrad has served as an administrator at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary since 2015. He is married to his wife of 32 years, Marion, and has 8 children. He is a member of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, KY where he serves as a Deacon and a Gifted Brother. Among other things, Rex particularly enjoys theology, hot sauce and Church history.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-2lbc-the-covenant-of-works/">The 2LBC &#038; the Covenant of Works</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-2lbc-the-covenant-of-works/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Covenant Theology, the 2LBC &#038; CBTS</title>
		<link>/covenant-theology-the-2lbc-cbts/</link>
					<comments>/covenant-theology-the-2lbc-cbts/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rexford Semrad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 21:57:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Covenant Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=16089</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In my years here at CBTS I’ve fielded a plethora of questions from potential students and curious inquirers.&#160; If you were to ask me what the most common topic brought up was, my answer would be instantaneous, 1689 Federalism! “What’s the relationship between CBTS and 1689 Federalism?” “Is CBTS 1689 Federalist?” “Does CBTS support 1689 [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/covenant-theology-the-2lbc-cbts/">Covenant Theology, the 2LBC &#038; CBTS</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In my years here at CBTS I’ve fielded a plethora of questions from potential students and curious inquirers.&nbsp; If you were to ask me what the most common topic brought up was, my answer would be instantaneous, 1689 Federalism! “What’s the relationship between CBTS and 1689 Federalism?” “Is CBTS 1689 Federalist?” “Does CBTS support 1689 Federalism?”&nbsp; I’ve also seen many ask in various social media contexts, “Is there a 1689 Federalist seminary?” or “What’s the best 1689 Federalist seminary?”&nbsp; I’ve had the desire to address this issue in a series of blog posts for many years now, but I’ve been unable to carve out the time.&nbsp; But now that Dr. Fred Malone is about to reteach Baptist Covenant Theology for us beginning in January, I think it’s high time to address this popular issue publicly.</p>



<p>This post will deal primarily with CBTS &amp; 1689 Federalism (1689Fed from here on out), but I plan to follow this up with some posts regarding Covenant Theology and the 1689 London Baptist Confession of Faith (2LBC from here on), what it does and does not confess regarding the subject.</p>



<p><strong>Defining Terms</strong></p>



<p>From the way many use the term 1689Fed today, it seems evident that there is a general lack of understanding of exactly what people think the term means or was meant to convey when the term was coined.&nbsp; In early 2013, Pascal Denault published his Master’s thesis under the title, <em>The Distinctiveness of Baptist Covenant Theology, A Comparison Between Seventeenth Century Particular Baptist and Paedobaptist Federalism</em>. We owe a great debt to the author for bringing to light a wealth of information about how the Particular Baptists in the era of the writing of our confession framed their covenant theology, especially in contrast to their Paedobaptist brethren. A plethora of information that had literally been lost for centuries was brought to light in a most refreshing and enlightening way.</p>



<p>I don’t remember the date, but shortly after this publication the website, 1689federalism.com was created by our brother Brandon Adams. I don’t know if Brandon expected the catchy term to gain both acceptance and notoriety as it has, but it’s become a buzzword among Calvinistic Baptists in a way I’ve never before observed.&nbsp; The site was (and still is) extremely helpful with a number of compelling videos and helpful charts laying out both the commonalities and distinctions between the Covenant Theology of the 17<sup>th</sup> Century Baptists and other systems like Paedobaptist Covenant Theology, Dispensationalism, and New Covenant Theology.</p>



<p>Though it is no longer found on the website, at one time there was also a chart comparing 1689 Federalism to 20<sup>th</sup> Century Reformed Baptists.&nbsp; I believe the terms used in this distinction were well meant, and in one sense accurate, but time has shown that they could be easily misunderstood.&nbsp; This is the sense in which they are accurate.&nbsp; What has become known as 1689Fed today is indeed an expression of the covenant theology espoused by the majority of those who originally subscribed to the 2LBC.&nbsp; What was termed 20<sup>th</sup> Century Reformed Baptists is an accurate expression of the covenant theology taught by many Reformed Baptist pastors over the last 40 years. As I noted, this terminology is no longer found on the website, but I still find people making this distinction regularly today.</p>



<p>That being said, I think the terms have been misunderstood by many to mean something I’m quite sure they were never meant to convey.&nbsp; It’s far too common now to see people use the term 1689Fed as though it means the covenant theology actually confessed in the 2LBC.&nbsp; This then leads to the false conclusion that those who might be called 20<sup>th</sup> Century RBs do not fully subscribe to the 2LBC, or at least not properly so.<a href="#_edn1">[i]</a> This has had the very discouraging result of a number of faithful, seasoned, and fully confessional Reformed Baptist men being falsely branded as less than confessional.</p>



<p>There are some facts that if understood should clear up this misapprehension.</p>



<p>1. The 2LBC does not even begin to lay out the entire system of covenant theology held by its authors and original subscribers.&nbsp; The fact is that there is nothing at all written in chapter 7, “Of God’s Covenant” that any Reformed Paedobaptist should not be willing to confess!&nbsp; The purpose of the Confession was not to lay out all the ways the Baptists differed from their paedobaptist brethren with regard to covenant theology.&nbsp; In fact, it was quite the opposite.&nbsp; The confession was published in order to demonstrate the orthodoxy of the churches who subscribed to it. So, while they did confess the ways in which they differed from their brethren in the areas of the sacraments and ecclesiology, the vast majority of the confession focuses on the doctrine commonly confessed with them.</p>



<p>2. While the covenant theology now known as 1689Fed is indeed reflective of what can be seen to be the majority view in the 17<sup>th</sup> Century among Particular Baptists, it was not universal among them.&nbsp; There were some in that day who held to something more akin to what is now ascribed to 20<sup>th</sup> century Reformed Baptists.</p>



<p>3. Even those with the majority view were not unanimous in the way they viewed particular aspects of covenant theology and the terminology they chose to use. <em>From Shadow to Substance: The Federal Theology of the English Particular Baptists (1642-1704)</em> by Dr. Sam Renihan is a must read for every Reformed Baptist.&nbsp; The author provides a goldmine of detail regarding the covenant theology of our Baptist forefathers and is particularly gifted in helping the reader understand the terminology of the day.<a href="#_edn2">[ii]</a></p>



<p>4. The men who are commonly lumped together as 20<sup>th</sup> Century Reformed Baptists differ from each other in a number of aspects of their covenant theology. In addition, the men of our day who are known as 1689 Federalists, though they are in agreement on the majority of issues, also differ on some finer points, such as the nature of the promise of life in the Mosaic Covenant.</p>



<p>5. The terms “substance and administration” with regard to the covenants has been used by some baptists both in the 17<sup>th</sup> and 20<sup>th</sup> century.&nbsp; Since this is the terminology used by many paedobaptists to identify the OT covenants with the covenant of grace, many have assumed that the baptists who retained that terminology were using it in the same way.&nbsp; That is not always the case.<a href="#_edn3">[iii]</a> (I’ll need to flesh this out a bit more in a later post.)</p>



<p>6. The manner in which the 17<sup>th</sup> century Particular Baptists differentiated between <em>a</em> covenant of works and <em>a</em> covenant of grace has been a matter of great confusion.&nbsp; Modern 1689 Federalists have adopted it, but it sounds very strange to the ears of many who have only ever used the terminology covenant of works for <em>THE</em> covenant of works. (Lord willing, I’ll address this more fully in a later post as well.)</p>



<p><strong>CBTS &amp; 1689 Federalism</strong></p>



<p>With this necessary foundation laid, I want to say a little about the relationship of CBTS to 1689 Fed. I think many people get confused, because we have two visiting professors who are commonly associated with 1689Fed (Dr. Sam Renihan &amp; Dr. Richard Barcellos), while our two most primary professors (Dr. Sam Waldron &amp; Dr. Fred Malone) are commonly lumped in with 20<sup>th</sup> Century Reformed Baptists. I will do my best to clear this up.</p>



<p>Dr. Waldron is first and foremost a systematician. Systematic Theology is his forte, and he has written very little with regard to covenant theology. While it is true that he has not embraced 1689Fed, I would say that he has much in common with the system.&nbsp;He has always held the substance of the Covenant of Works, now embraces the terminology, and believes this doctrine to be a foundational support to a right understanding of the doctrine of justification.He has never held to the idea that the OT covenants were simply administrations of the covenant of grace.&nbsp; He recently embraced the teaching that the New Covenant is the covenant of grace.&nbsp; He is the President of CBTS and was in hearty agreement with inviting Dr. Sam Renihan to teach the Origins of Baptist Covenant Theology for us. And on a personal note, though he knows well that I embrace 1689Fed, he asked me to teach on chapter 7 of our confession for the adult SS class here at GRBC. Finally, after reading&nbsp;<em>The Mystery of Christ, His Covenant, and His Kingdom</em>, he told me that he was greatly benefitted by it.</p>



<p>Dr. Fred Malone teaches our Reformed Baptist Covenant Theology class, as I mentioned above.&nbsp; Last time he taught the class live was in January of 2015.&nbsp; I was a student at that module and I asked him what his opinion of 1689Fed was. His answer was simply that he was aware of the website but had not taken the time to examine it. That being said, though he does not use all the same terminology as 1689Fed in the same way they do, having taken his class I can say that I don’t see anything he teaches as incompatible with it.&nbsp; Both Pascal Denault’s book and the Coxe/Owen volume were assigned reading for the class, and he said nothing in the class as corrections or exceptions to their content. Here is the list of assigned and recommended texts for his class next semester:</p>



<ul><li>Samuel E. Waldron. <em>A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith </em>Chapter 7 “On the Covenants”</li><li>Nehemiah Coxe. <em>Covenant Theology from Adam to Christ</em>.</li><li>Samuel Bolton. <em>True Bounds of Christian Freedom</em></li><li>Samuel D. Renihan. <em>The Mystery of Christ, His Covenant &amp; His Kingdom</em></li><li>Richard C. Barcellos. <em>Getting the Garden Right</em></li><li>Samuel D. Renihan. <em>From Shadow to Substance: The Federal Theology of the English Particular Baptists (1642-1704)</em></li><li>Fred A. Malone. <em>The Baptism of Disciples Alone: Revised and Expanded</em></li><li>Pascal Denault. <em>The Distinctiveness of Baptist Covenant Theology</em></li></ul>



<p>As you can see from the above list, Dr. Malone isn’t against what is now known as 1689Fed.&nbsp; This really shouldn’t be surprising to anyone since he wrote a recommendation for Denault’s book, as did Dr. Tom Nettles who also teaches for us.</p>



<p>To sum things up, CBTS is a confessional seminary holding to the 1689 London Baptist Confession of Faith.&nbsp; While this does not infer that 1689 Federalism is the official covenantal position of the seminary, you would be hard pressed to find things taught here that are not compatible with the system.&nbsp; On the other hand, we stand firmly against the idea that one must adopt 1689Fed in order to be fully confessional.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Forgive me if this seems out of place, but I can’t help myself. I simply cannot say anything about covenant theology without recommending Sam Renihan’s book, <em>The Mystery of Christ</em>. Sam is an extremely humble young man, so he probably cringes when he hears me say this, but I am convinced that <em>The Mystery of Christ</em> is the best book on covenant theology ever written. I would have given my left arm to have such a work twenty-some years ago when I was trying to make heads or tails of covenant theology and was limited almost exclusively to paedobaptist works.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><a href="#_ednref1">[i]</a> &nbsp;This idea is actually directly contradicted in the FAQ section of the 1689Fed website: <a href="http://www.1689federalism.com/faq/does-the-2nd-london-baptist-confession-only-permit-1689-federalism/">http://www.1689federalism.com/faq/does-the-2nd-london-baptist-confession-only-permit-1689-federalism/</a></p>



<p><a href="#_ednref2">[ii]</a> Assuming the reader has already read the Coxe/Owen volume, <em>Covenant Theology from Adam to Christ</em>, I highly recommend rereading it after reading <em>From Shadow to Substance</em>.&nbsp; Much of Coxe was mysterious to me upon first reading, but after reading Renihan, I went back to Coxe with a great deal of profit.&nbsp; These interactive outlines are also helpful: <a href="http://www.1689federalism.com/interactive-outline-of-coxe-on-the-covenants/">http://www.1689federalism.com/interactive-outline-of-coxe-on-the-covenants/</a> &nbsp;<a href="http://www.1689federalism.com/interactive-outline-of-john-owens-exposition-of-hebrews-86-13/">http://www.1689federalism.com/interactive-outline-of-john-owens-exposition-of-hebrews-86-13/</a></p>



<p><a href="#_ednref3">[iii]</a> John Gill for example <a href="https://contrast2.wordpress.com/2017/04/14/some-comments-on-john-gills-covenant-theology/">https://contrast2.wordpress.com/2017/04/14/some-comments-on-john-gills-covenant-theology/</a></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/rex/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/03/23164330/rex-semrad.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/rex/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Rexford Semrad</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Rexford Semrad has served as an administrator at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary since 2015. He is married to his wife of 32 years, Marion, and has 8 children. He is a member of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, KY where he serves as a Deacon and a Gifted Brother. Among other things, Rex particularly enjoys theology, hot sauce and Church history.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/covenant-theology-the-2lbc-cbts/">Covenant Theology, the 2LBC &#038; CBTS</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/covenant-theology-the-2lbc-cbts/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
