<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Family-Integrated Church 10: Is the Old Testament Adequate to Provide the Church’s Philosophy of Ministry? (Part 2)	</title>
	<atom:link href="/family-integrated-church-10/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/family-integrated-church-10/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 01:32:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Aashik		</title>
		<link>/family-integrated-church-10/#comment-220</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Aashik]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 01:32:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=796#comment-220</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thank you for your gracious and charitable discussion of the FIC movement in your posts, Dr. Waldron.

With regards to this post, I think that the point that the folks at NCFIC are trying to make, is not that we should conform every detail of our church life to national Israel. Rather, it is the fact that the duty of discipleship, teaching, and evangelism of children is always seen, in both OT and NT as the duty of the parents (especially the father).

Consequently, seeing this as an eternal principle of God&#039;s moral law, the church does not have the right to usurp that authority from parents, and establish itself as the discipler of children (even temporarily on Sunday mornings). Rather, it&#039;s ministry to children should be through the proper means, namely the equipping fathers to raise their children in the Lord. As such, the focus of church ministries is not on meeting the particular needs of children, as much as the ministering to the family to do the duty that God has specifically called them to.

I think a big part of this discussion is that of sphere sovereignty. The church&#039;s duty of teaching children is a general evangelistic duty, not a specific one. Just as most churches would not establish special groups to reach out to alcoholics, catholics, or any other &#039;lost&#039; group, it shouldn&#039;t establish special groups to reach the &#039;lost&#039; group, of children. Rather, the church is to &#039;teach them to obey all that I have commanded you&#039;, which means to call catholics, atheists, and children to repentance - and to call heads of households to do their duty of raising their children.

Just some thoughts; I do appreciate the time you are taking in discussing these important issues.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thank you for your gracious and charitable discussion of the FIC movement in your posts, Dr. Waldron.</p>
<p>With regards to this post, I think that the point that the folks at NCFIC are trying to make, is not that we should conform every detail of our church life to national Israel. Rather, it is the fact that the duty of discipleship, teaching, and evangelism of children is always seen, in both OT and NT as the duty of the parents (especially the father).</p>
<p>Consequently, seeing this as an eternal principle of God&#8217;s moral law, the church does not have the right to usurp that authority from parents, and establish itself as the discipler of children (even temporarily on Sunday mornings). Rather, it&#8217;s ministry to children should be through the proper means, namely the equipping fathers to raise their children in the Lord. As such, the focus of church ministries is not on meeting the particular needs of children, as much as the ministering to the family to do the duty that God has specifically called them to.</p>
<p>I think a big part of this discussion is that of sphere sovereignty. The church&#8217;s duty of teaching children is a general evangelistic duty, not a specific one. Just as most churches would not establish special groups to reach out to alcoholics, catholics, or any other &#8216;lost&#8217; group, it shouldn&#8217;t establish special groups to reach the &#8216;lost&#8217; group, of children. Rather, the church is to &#8216;teach them to obey all that I have commanded you&#8217;, which means to call catholics, atheists, and children to repentance &#8211; and to call heads of households to do their duty of raising their children.</p>
<p>Just some thoughts; I do appreciate the time you are taking in discussing these important issues.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Mike Waters		</title>
		<link>/family-integrated-church-10/#comment-219</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Waters]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 12:51:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=796#comment-219</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[P Sam.

Thanks for your clarification. I fully agree. Having re-read your opening statement helped:

&quot;I am affirming that texts on the family and especially texts on the family from the Old Testament cannot provide us with an adequate philosophy of ministry for the New Testament church.&quot;

I think we would agree that Deut 6 does form &quot;an adequate philosophy of ministry&quot; for the family today. 

Yet, I think my question is this. Do not men such as Scott Brown also affirm that new birth brings you into the family of God, and that elders are given to teach that single and diverse family (texts such as Deut 6 and Eph 6)?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>P Sam.</p>
<p>Thanks for your clarification. I fully agree. Having re-read your opening statement helped:</p>
<p>&#8220;I am affirming that texts on the family and especially texts on the family from the Old Testament cannot provide us with an adequate philosophy of ministry for the New Testament church.&#8221;</p>
<p>I think we would agree that Deut 6 does form &#8220;an adequate philosophy of ministry&#8221; for the family today. </p>
<p>Yet, I think my question is this. Do not men such as Scott Brown also affirm that new birth brings you into the family of God, and that elders are given to teach that single and diverse family (texts such as Deut 6 and Eph 6)?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Sam Waldron		</title>
		<link>/family-integrated-church-10/#comment-218</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 00:20:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=796#comment-218</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Mike,

Thanks for your comment.  I do think you slightly misunderstand my point.  I completely agree that Deuteronomy 6 should be preached to NC families.  My point is that it is not an adequate philosophy of ministry for the NC church because the church is not a family of families--as Israel was!

John 1:11-13 state a NC reality and emphasize the distinctiveness of the NC.  The point is that in the OC people did become sons and daughters of God without birth from God and on the basis bloodlines and circumcision.  In that sense John 1:13 does not describe OC sonship or covenantal sonship in the the Old Covenant.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mike,</p>
<p>Thanks for your comment.  I do think you slightly misunderstand my point.  I completely agree that Deuteronomy 6 should be preached to NC families.  My point is that it is not an adequate philosophy of ministry for the NC church because the church is not a family of families&#8211;as Israel was!</p>
<p>John 1:11-13 state a NC reality and emphasize the distinctiveness of the NC.  The point is that in the OC people did become sons and daughters of God without birth from God and on the basis bloodlines and circumcision.  In that sense John 1:13 does not describe OC sonship or covenantal sonship in the the Old Covenant.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Mike Waters		</title>
		<link>/family-integrated-church-10/#comment-217</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Waters]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2011 20:09:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=796#comment-217</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thanks pastor Sam.

I agree. Old covenant Israel was typical of new covenant Israel. Birth brought you into both. Physical birth in the former and spiritual in the latter. Thus I understand your caution in using texts like Deut.6:6-7. 

Yet, Deut.6:6 underscores the need to have the word in our heart. To believe it. To then teach it to our children. How does this not apply?

Fundamentally families have not changed from old to new testament religion. While I understand physical birth and circumcision brought you into the old covenant, wasn&#039;t John 1:13 true in the OT as well. Spiritual birth (or circumcision) was just as necessary.

I too am uncomfortable with the concept of the church as a family of families. But personally, I feel much more liberty in preaching Deut.6 to NC families.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks pastor Sam.</p>
<p>I agree. Old covenant Israel was typical of new covenant Israel. Birth brought you into both. Physical birth in the former and spiritual in the latter. Thus I understand your caution in using texts like Deut.6:6-7. </p>
<p>Yet, Deut.6:6 underscores the need to have the word in our heart. To believe it. To then teach it to our children. How does this not apply?</p>
<p>Fundamentally families have not changed from old to new testament religion. While I understand physical birth and circumcision brought you into the old covenant, wasn&#8217;t John 1:13 true in the OT as well. Spiritual birth (or circumcision) was just as necessary.</p>
<p>I too am uncomfortable with the concept of the church as a family of families. But personally, I feel much more liberty in preaching Deut.6 to NC families.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
