<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Worship | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/worship/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 20:10:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Worship | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</title>
		<link>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/</link>
					<comments>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 20:10:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Church Discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[church discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[practical theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13854</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Bible teaches us that holiness is one of the major marks of a true church. The church&#8217;s holiness is based off the great command found in Leviticus 19:2, &#8220;You shall be holy, for I the LORD your God am holy.&#8221; And the church&#8217;s holiness is the result of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Jesus [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/">Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-drop-cap">The Bible teaches us that holiness is one of the major marks
of a true church. The church&#8217;s holiness is based off the great command found in
Leviticus 19:2, &#8220;You shall be holy, for I the LORD your God am holy.&#8221; And the
church&#8217;s holiness is the result of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Jesus has saved
the church by giving Himself up for her. He saved her by spilling His own
precious blood on the cross. And as a result, the church has become the body
and bride of Jesus Christ. It belongs to Him. He is her Head and her Husband.
And Jesus didn&#8217;t die to purchase a sick body and an ugly bride. He died for the
church to be holy and without blemish. He died so she would reflect His holy
character. He died so that she would be holy as He is holy! Holy in her
profession of the truth and holy in her practice of living out the truth. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But in saying this, a problem should arise in our minds. A
big problem. And it&#8217;s this: the church is not perfect. At least not yet. If you
have but a faint understanding of your own heart, hopefully that&#8217;s not a
surprise. The church is full of saints but saints who are still sinners. Sadly,
saints who still break God&#8217;s commandments. And saints who still hurt one
another with their words and their actions.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Therefore, it must be the priority of every true church to
carry out what is called church discipline. This simply means the church must
have in place a way of dealing with and correcting sin when it rears its ugly
head. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If we are thinking of the church as the body of Christ,
church discipline is like undergoing surgery in order to cut out cancerous
tumors from the body so that the body would be healthy again. Or if we are
thinking of the church as the bride of Christ, church discipline is like
getting a top-of-the-line spa treatment in order for the dirt and filth and
warts and lumps to all be removed so that the bride would be beautiful again.&nbsp;&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Church discipline may not feel good, but it is absolutely
necessary. Church discipline must be enforced if any church wants to remain
pure, and holy, and undefiled before her Lord. If we let the tumors grow and do
nothing about them, the body will eventually die. And if we let the filth build
up without ever cleaning ourselves, the husband may become so disgusted with
his bride that he eventually leaves her! </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The classic passage on church discipline is found in Matthew
18:15-20. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>[15] &#8220;If your brother sins against you, go and tell him his fault, between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained your brother. [16] But if he does not listen, take one or two others along with you, that every charge may be established by the evidence of two or three witnesses. [17] If he refuses to listen to them, tell it to the church. And if he refuses to listen even to the church, let him be to you as a Gentile and a tax collector. [18] Truly, I say to you, whatever you bind on earth shall be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven. [19] Again I say to you, if two of you agree on earth about anything they ask, it will be done for them by my Father in heaven. [20] For where two or three are gathered in my name, there am I among them.&#8221; (ESV)</em></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In future posts, we will consider these verses in greater
detail. But for the present, consider six introductory remarks concerning
Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"large"} -->
<p class="has-large-font-size"><strong>Introductory Remarks</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>1.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline in Matthew 18:15-20 must never be severed from its context. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The context of this passage is very important. Sometimes
Jesus&#8217; overall teaching in this section is not emphasized enough when we think
about and talk about church discipline. This teaching on church discipline
comes in the midst of Jesus&#8217; teaching on how His disciples should love each
other, especially how they should love the least of His disciples. Remember, in
Matthew 18, Jesus teaches His disciples what it means to live as a citizen in
His kingdom. More than that, He teaches them what it means to be great in His
kingdom &#8211; and it has nothing to do with how the world defines greatness.
Greatness for Christ is not about popularity or power or riches or fame or
attractiveness or anything else the world is impressed with. Instead, greatness
in Christ&#8217;s kingdom is shown through humble service &amp; brotherly love. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus teaches this in Matthew 18 in four different ways: First,
His disciples are to show humility to one another (vv. 1-4). Second, His
disciples are to protect each other specifically from sin (vv. 5-9). Third, His
disciples are to highly esteem each other (vv. 10-14). And finally, His
disciples are to continually forgive each other (vv. 15-35). This teaching on
church discipline, then, makes up the first part in the fourth and final
section in this chapter, which deals with forgiveness.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>What does this mean then? It means that church discipline
and forgiveness and true Christian love are all vitally connected. We may be
tempted to think that church discipline and forgiveness have little or nothing
to do with each other. We may be tempted to think that church discipline is all
law while forgiveness is all grace, that church discipline is enslaving while
forgiveness is freeing, that church discipline makes me feel bad while
forgiveness makes me feel good!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Well, this dichotomy, this separation of church discipline
and forgiveness, is nowhere in Jesus&#8217; teaching. In fact, the exact opposite
occurs. Jesus&#8217; teaching on love and forgiveness includes church discipline!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus teaches us here that church discipline is the means of
forgiveness. It is the way of bringing about forgiveness and reconciliation and
restoration! And the goal of church discipline is forgiveness. Why are members
disciplined? So that forgiveness would occur. When forgiveness is not reached
between two people, discipline must be administered so that forgiveness might
become a reality!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Hopefully you see that church discipline and forgiveness
should not be pitted against each other but should work hand-in-hand to glorify
God, to keep the church pure and holy, and to bring about much peace and
happiness in the lives of God&#8217;s people. When we think about church discipline, we
should think about seeking forgiveness. The first is the means of obtaining the
second.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>2.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline concerns professing Christians. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>What Jesus says here concerns those who are brothers and
sisters in Christ. They are those who have made credible professions of faith,
have been baptized, and are members of a local church of Jesus Christ. In other
words, this teaching is for church members, for those who have been publicly
recognized as brothers and sisters in Christ. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>It is not, however, for unbelievers. How would it make any
sense to take your grievances to the church if the person who has sinned
against you is not even in the church to begin with? What can the church do
about it? If your unbelieving coworker sins against you, the only things we can
do is preach the gospel to him and pray for his salvation, but we can&#8217;t
discipline him. He has never been a part of this holy society we call the
church. He is an unbeliever outside of the kingdom of God. So we can&#8217;t put him
out of an organization he has never joined in the first place!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This doesn&#8217;t mean you shouldn&#8217;t seek forgiveness with people
in other areas of life; it simply means this step-by-step process that Jesus
teaches us is given specifically to the church and for the church to use with
its own members. It was not given to families or to schools or to society as a
whole.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are good principles there for anyone to follow, but it
is given specifically for the body and bride of Christ.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>3.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline deals with private sins committed against another brother or sister in Christ.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is important to note. The character of the kind of sin
Jesus is describing is private, not public. And it is against an individual,
not a group. Since it is private, certain measures are put in place by our Lord
to try to keep things as private as possible.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>John Calvin spends much time distinguishing between private
sins and public sins in his section on church discipline in the <em>Institutes</em>.
For sins that have been committed more openly, sins that affect more than just
one or two people but sins done in public where everyone knows about them and
where the whole church is immediately scandalized by them, Calvin argues that
these types of sin don&#8217;t fall within the instructions of Christ here in Matthew
18. People who sin in a public, grievous way are to be swiftly, solemnly, and
immediately rebuked in public, meaning something needs to be said to the church
when they gather together to worship God. We have examples of this happening in
the New Testament. Just think about Peter&#8217;s scandalous sin of distorting the
gospel of grace when he refused to eat with Gentile believers and how Paul
openly rebuked him to his face before the believers in Antioch (Galatians
2:11-14). This was no private meeting between the two apostles. The sin was so
grievous and so public that Paul was forced to rebuke Peter before the church.
And then he writes about it for all to read!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But for sins that have been committed more privately where
very few people know about it and very few people have been offended by it, the
steps laid down by Christ here in Matthew 18 must be followed. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are always exceptions to the rule. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are certain private sins that are so grievous that
immediate public church discipline must be enforced. Some of these sins might
include things that would put a person behind bars for a long time. Even if the
crime was committed in private, sometimes it must be exposed by the light for
all to see and abhor, including the civil authorities. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are also certain people who commit private sins that
must be made public. Here I am thinking about church officers. If a church
officer commits a particular sin that disqualifies him from the office of
either elder or deacon, something needs to be said to the church to give them
the reason why he has stepped down.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But the private sins I am talking about might include the
following: theft of some small amount, deliberately lying to another brother&#8217;s
face for your own personal advantage, unrighteous anger directed at another
believer, a complete lack of respect and honor for an older member of the
church, gossiping and slandering the good name of a Christian, a divisive
spirit that tries to stir up trouble in the church, and being a stumbling block
to one of Christ&#8217;s little ones. These may be small offenses in the eyes of our
society but let me tell you this: they are grave offenses in the sight of our
holy God who commands us to love one another as Christ loves us.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, all public sin should at all times be publicly rebuked;
some private sins should also at all times be publicly rebuked; but most
private sins should at first be privately rebuked. (but of course, it should
lead to a public rebuke in the presence of all if the person persists in sin).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>4.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline gives us a methodical, step-by-step process to deal with unrepentant sin. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Seeking forgiveness and reconciliation may be a process. I
wish it wasn&#8217;t the case. I wish that when someone sinned against another he or
she would immediately seek forgiveness. But sadly, while we live in this fallen
world, that is not always the case. And if forgiveness does not immediately
occur, there are distinct steps that must be taken in order to secure it. In
fact, there are four steps listed here in Matthew 18 that must be taken in
order to bring about forgiveness from an unrepentant Christian.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, we should not be trigger happy to discipline, and even
more than that, to excommunicate unrepentant members who have sinned in a
private way. As William Hendriksen says, &#8220;Church discipline, when viewed
negatively, is a matter of last resort&#8221; (699, Gospel of Matthew). None of this
should be rushed. Each step takes time to complete. Careful attention must be
taken and certain measures must be exhausted before moving on to the next step.
</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Maybe an illustration might be helpful. Instead of thinking
of these steps as little stair steps like the ones before me which only take a
second to climb (and easy to skip if you have some jumping abilities), think of
these steps to secure forgiveness like riding escalators from floor to floor at
the Mall of America. The Mall of America has four floors. And it has escalators
that will take you up to each floor. But it takes some time to go from one
floor to the next. And it takes a lot of time to go from the bottom floor to
the very top. You have to slowly but surely move from one to the next. Well, in
a similar way, each escalator of church discipline must be ascended before one
moves on to the next. Getting from step one to step four should not be
instantaneous.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>5.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline has, as its goal, the gaining or winning back of a professing Christian who has gone astray.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This step-by-step process of church discipline is
redemptive. The unrepentant professing Christian is like a sheep that has gone
astray. He or she has left the fold of Christ. He or she has sinned and turned
from the Highway of Holiness. And if that person keeps living in unrepentant
sin, if that person keeps walking down crooked, dark paths, he or she will not
reach the Celestial City. He or she will be attacked by deadly predators and will
be completely destroyed.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So seeking forgiveness in the way prescribed by Christ gets them back on the right track. It brings them back to the fold of God. It displays the very heart of Jesus Christ, the Good Shepherd, who leaves the 99 sheep on the mountains in order to search and find the one that went astray. As James says in James 5:19-20:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>&#8220;[19] My brothers, if anyone among you wanders from the truth and someone brings him back, [20] let him know that whoever brings back a sinner from his wandering will save his soul from death and will cover a multitude of sins.&#8221; (ESV)</em></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, in this area of church discipline, we need to check our
hearts. We need to make sure that if we want to walk up these steps, we are
doing so for the glory of God and for the ultimate good of the straying
Christian. It must not be our desire to seek vengeance or to get even with
someone who has wronged us. We also must not revel in another person&#8217;s
downfall. Instead, we must show brotherly love and tender affection to those
who have wronged us. We must remember how wicked our own hearts are, how much
we daily offend our Lord, and how much He has mercy on us. We have to keep ever
before us the goal of church discipline, which is repentance and forgiveness
and restoration, not condemnation and damnation. We want to win our brother and
sister back; not destroy them.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>6.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline is steeped in OT laws and principles.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus was not one who wanted to unhitch the Old Testament
from the New Testament. There have been teachers throughout church history who
have taught that New Testament believers should move on from the Old Testament
and leave that baggage behind as they follow Christ.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Well, certainly there are some things in the Old Testament
that shouldn&#8217;t be practiced any more in light of the coming of Christ, animal
sacrifices being one of them, but we should never dishonor or take lightly the
teaching of the Old Testament. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Why? Because Jesus didn&#8217;t. Jesus had a high view of the
Scriptures. And He saw a lot of use for the Old Testament in the New Testament
church. In fact, His step-by-step procedure for dealing with sin is based on
teaching from the Mosaic law! Yes, parts of the OT law were to inform and
structure the way the church of Jesus Christ governs itself and functions in
this world. Every step finds its roots in laws given to the nation of Israel.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This makes us think that Jesus may have considered the
church as the New Israel. And it also makes us think that there were more than
just temporary, ceremonial laws in the OT. Some of the laws in the Old
Testament transcend OT Israel and have direct application to the church of
Jesus Christ today. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, the Old Testament wasn&#8217;t to be thrown out or seen as
irrelevant for Christians. Instead, it was to be studied and examined and
applied to various situations which crop up in the church today. We will see
this as we go through the steps of church discipline.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is how I believe we should look at these steps: Two of them occur privately, and two of them occur publicly, in that order. So in future posts, we will look at the two private steps of seeking forgiveness, and then we will look at the two public steps of seeking forgiveness. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/">Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 8 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-8-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-8-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 18:49:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1st day of the week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7475</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 6 of 8, click here for part 1, part 2, part 3, part 4, part 5, part 6 &#38; part 7)  The Reason for First-Day Meetings in the New Testament (continued) [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-8-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 8 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: medium;">This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</span></strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 6 of 8, click here for <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">part 1</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">part 2</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">part 3</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/">part 4</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/">part 5</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/">part 6</a> &amp; <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-7-of-8/">part 7</a>)</p>
<p><strong><em> </em></strong><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">The Reason for First-Day Meetings in the New Testament (continued)</span></em></strong></p>
<p>It is important to recognize that the resurrection is an epoch-changing event. The resurrection is seen as the beginning of the new creation. Believers are united to Christ in his death, burial, and resurrection through faith.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Or do you not know that all of us who have been baptized into Christ Jesus have been baptized into His death? <sup>4</sup> Therefore we have been buried with Him through baptism into death, so that as Christ was raised from the dead through the glory of the Father, so we too might walk in newness of life. <sup>5</sup> For if we have become united with <em>Him </em>in the likeness of His death, certainly we shall also be <em>in the likeness </em>of His resurrection, <sup>6</sup> knowing this, that our old self was crucified with <em>Him</em>, in order that our body of sin might be done away with, so that we would no longer be slaves to sin (Rom. 6:3-6)</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;">and in Him you were also circumcised with a circumcision made without hands, in the removal of the body of the flesh by the circumcision of Christ; <sup>12</sup> having been buried with Him in baptism, in which you were also raised up with Him through faith in the working of God, who raised Him from the dead. (Col. 2:11-12)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Union with Christ brings believers into the orbit of redemptive privilege. They may know “the power of His resurrection” (Phil. 3:10) because they are united to him through faith. God “made us alive together with Christ . . . and raised us up with Him, and seated us with Him in heavenly <em>places</em> in Christ Jesus” (Eph. 2:5-6). Being in Christ makes believers citizens of heaven (Phil. 3:20).</p>
<p>Union with Christ also involves existence in two ages at once—this age (the old creation) and the age to come (the new creation). The age to come is the age of the resurrection.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Jesus said to them, “The sons of this age marry and are given in marriage, <sup>35</sup> but those who are considered worthy to attain to that age and the resurrection from the dead, neither marry nor are given in marriage; <sup>36</sup> for they cannot even die anymore, because they are like angels, and are sons of God, being sons of the resurrection. (Luke 20:34-36)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Christ’s resurrection is the first bodily resurrection of the age to come because it was “the firstfruits” (1 Cor. 15:20).</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">But now Christ has been raised from the dead, the first fruits of those who are asleep. <sup>21</sup> For since by a man <em>came </em>death, by a man also <em>came </em>the resurrection of the dead. <sup>22</sup> For as in Adam all die, so also in Christ all will be made alive. <sup>23</sup> But each in his own order: Christ the first fruits, after that those who are Christ&#8217;s at His coming (1 Cor. 15:20-23)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Christ’s resurrection was the first of similar resurrections to come. But being “the firstfruits,” it is not totally other than that which follows. It is different in time, but it is part of the same resurrection. It is part of the same harvest, just the first of the much greater harvest to come. Gaffin, commenting on “firstfruits,” says:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The word is not simply an indication of temporal priority. Rather it brings into view Christ’s resurrection as the “firstfruits” of the resurrection-harvest, the initial portion of the whole. His resurrection is the representative beginning of the resurrection of believers. In other words, the term seems deliberately chosen to make evident the organic connection between the two resurrections. In the context, Paul’s “thesis” over against his opponents is that the resurrection of Jesus has the bodily resurrection of “those who sleep” as its necessary consequence. His resurrection is not simply a guarantee; it is a pledge in the sense that it is the actual beginning of the general event. In fact, on the basis of this verse it can be said that Paul views the two resurrections not so much as two events but as two episodes of the same event.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Christ’s resurrection is the most powerful sign of the presence of the age to come. His resurrected body took on qualities it did not possess prior to the resurrection (Rom. 1:4). It was an age-to-come body, existing in this age for a brief time on the earth and now in heaven. In Christ’s resurrection, then, we see the age to come eclipsing this age. This is why Paul says, “Therefore, if anyone <em>is </em>in Christ, <em>he is</em> a new creation; old things have passed away; behold, all things have become new” (2 Cor. 5:17, NKJV). This is not only true of personal renovation but also a state of existence in the new creation brought in by Christ. In Galatians 6:15, Paul says, “For neither is circumcision anything, nor uncircumcision, but a new creation.”</p>
<p>The age to come has eclipsed this age in the resurrection of Christ. Hebrews 6:5 says that some “have tasted the good word of God and the powers of the age to come.” Waldron says, “The great realities of the age to come have in some sense broken into and become operative in this age.”<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a> Waldron’s further comments are helpful at this point:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The New Testament teaches, therefore, that there is a new creation in Christ (Gal. 6:15; 2 Cor. 5:17; Eph. 2:10). The idea of new creation is frequently associated with Christ’s resurrection (cf. Eph. 2:10 with 2:5,7; Eph. 4:24; Col. 3:10 with Rom. 6:1-6; Col. 1:15-18). By union with Christ in His death, the old man is destroyed. By union with Christ in His resurrection, the new man is created. When He rose again He became the firstborn of God’s new creation. As He was the beginning of the old creation, so He is now the beginning of the new (Rev. 3:14). Thus, the memorial of Christ’s resurrection is of necessity a memorial of the new creation. Thus, the Lord’s Day like the Sabbath and unlike any other religious observance points to both creation and redemption.<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Christ’s resurrection is the apex of all of God’s redemptive work on the earth. It is an epoch-changing event. It ushers in the first phase of the new creation, the last Adam’s entrance into glory. In one sense, it affects everything. But how does it affect the Sabbath under the inaugurated new covenant? That it is the redemptive-historical, theological, and Christological basis for first-day church meetings seems clear. But does it mark the end of all Sabbaths for the people of God? Or does it function as the first creation did in relation to the first Sabbath? Does it function as the basis for the change of the Sabbath from the seventh to the first day because it is the day Christ ceased from his redemptive work, as God rested from his creative work? Surely, no greater, more unique event could be asked for to change the day of sacred rest for the people of God.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Richard B. Gaffin, Jr., <em>Resurrection and Redemption</em> (Phillipsburg, NJ: Presbyterian and Reformed Publishing, 1987), 34-35.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Samuel E. Waldron, <em>The End Times Made Simple</em> (Amityville, NY: Calvary Press, 2003), 49.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Waldron, <em>Lord’s Day</em>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-8-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 8 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-8-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 7 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-7-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-7-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2017 12:25:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1st day of the week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[First Day of the Week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7445</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 6 of 8, click here for part 1, part 2, part 3, part 4, part 5 &#38; part 6) The Reason for First-Day Meetings in the New Testament Finally, consider [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-7-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 7 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: medium;">This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</span></strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 6 of 8, click here for <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">part 1</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">part 2</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">part 3</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/">part 4</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/">part 5</a> &amp; <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/">part 6</a>)</p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">The Reason for First-Day Meetings in the New Testament</span></em></strong></p>
<p>Finally, consider the reason for first-day meetings in the New Testament. Though it does not state the reason in explicit terms, the New Testament does present enough evidence to provide an answer. The reason for first-day meetings can be none other than the fact and implications of Christ’s first-day resurrection. The resurrection, the pivotal, epoch-changing event in redemptive history, becomes the redemptive-historical and theological basis for first-day meetings in the New Testament. It is seen as an epoch-changing event—the beginning of the new creation. It is also seen as the day in which Christ ceased from his redemptive labors (Heb. 4:9-10).</p>
<p>Schreiner admits that the day of Christ’s resurrection is unique, saying, “Even by stating that it [i.e., the resurrection of Christ] was the first day of the week, the authors assign a special significance to that day.”<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> He then appears to acknowledge that subsequent first days of the week were viewed in a unique way. He says:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">We also see hints elsewhere in the NT that the church gathered for worship on the Lord’s Day, the first day of the week (Acts 20:7; 1 Cor 16:2; cf. Rev 1:10). Such a practice is most naturally linked to Sunday being the day on which the Lord rose from the dead, though no explicit link is made between the two.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Schreiner identifies church gatherings “for worship on the Lord’s Day, the first day of the week . . . [as] a practice . . . most naturally linked to Sunday being the day on which the Lord rose from the dead.”</p>
<p>Wells makes a similar statement, though with a degree of hesitation not evident in Schreiner:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">I have argued that the meeting day of the early church was not fixed by apostolic authority, but by convenience. Nevertheless there <em>might</em> have been a natural preference for the first day of the week. Why? Because our Lord rose from the dead on that day.<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Both Schreiner and Wells claim the connection between first-day church meetings and the resurrection of our Lord is a natural one, though Wells does so reluctantly. If one is reminded that the resurrection is a redemptive-historical act of God in Christ, a better word to use to indicate the connection is “theological” instead of “natural.” In other words, the practical implication of the resurrection of our Lord in terms of church gatherings for worship finds its basis in a redemptive-historical reality. It appears Schreiner would agree with this. I do not think Wells does, however. He claims that first-day meetings were “fixed . . . by convenience.” Earlier in his discussion of 1 Corinthians 16:1-2, he says, “If, however, we ask why Paul said, ‘On the first day of every week?’ there is a good chance that he chose that day because the Christians met on that day.”<a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a> The question we are asking and seeking to answer is <em>why</em> they met on the first day. Wells says it was out of convenience, though he does not argue his case cogently. Then he suggests, “there might have been a natural preference for the first day of the week.” If there is a redemptive-historical reason for first-day meetings, however, it is a theologically revealed basis and does not and cannot change, whether convenient for us or not. If the early Christians met on the basis of convenience, would it not have been less threatening to their well-being to meet on the last day of the week (especially Jewish believers) so as not to draw unwanted and potentially adverse attention to themselves? As will be argued below, the reason for first-day meetings of the church is not based on the mere natural connection between the resurrection of our Lord and first-day meetings. It is, in fact, very redemptive-historical, theological, and even Christological.</p>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of…ment-part-8-of-8/"><strong>Part 8</strong></a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Schreiner, “Good-bye and Hello,” 186.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Schreiner, “Good-bye and Hello,” 186-87.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Wells, <em>The Christian and the Sabbath,</em> 95; emphasis added.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> Wells, <em>The Christian and the Sabbath</em>, 95.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-7-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 7 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-7-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 6 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 15:28:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1st day of the week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7406</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 6 of 8, click here for part 1, part 2, part 3, part 4 &#38; part 5) First-Day Corporate Meetings in the New Testament (continued) It is no small [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 6 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: medium;">This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</span></strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 6 of 8, click here for <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">part 1</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">part 2</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">part 3</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/">part 4</a> &amp; <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/">part 5</a>)</p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">First-Day Corporate Meetings in the New Testament (continued)</span></em></strong></p>
<p>It is no small matter for the apostle Paul to give orders to the churches concerning first-day meetings. Apostolic authority is binding for all churches. When Paul gave orders to the churches, his orders were the orders of Christ himself. John 16:13-14 (referenced above) contain a promise from Christ of inspired truth to complete the revelation of the Father’s will. This promise refers to the apostolate. Ephesians 2:20 says that the church was “built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets.” First Corinthians 4:17 says:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">For this reason I have sent to you Timothy, who is my beloved and faithful child in the Lord, and he will remind you of my ways which are in Christ, just as I teach everywhere in every church. (1 Cor. 4:17)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>What Paul taught “everywhere in every church” was binding on the Corinthians. In 1 Corinthians 7:17, Paul says, “Only, as the Lord has assigned to each one, as God has called each, in this manner let him walk. And so I direct in all the churches.” Paul had authority to ordain the same things in all the churches. First Corinthians 11:2 says, “Now I praise you because you remember me in everything and hold firmly to the traditions, just as I delivered them to you.” Apostolic traditions were binding on the Corinthians (see 2 Thess. 2:15).</p>
<p>So for Paul to give orders to the churches means that whatever he ordered was binding on them (and subsequent churches). Apostolic authority carried with it the authority of Christ himself. The apostles were the revelatory agents through whom Christ completed the will of his Father. As the saying goes, the apostle of the man is as the man himself. First-day meetings of the church for worship, then, are the will of Christ for his churches, revealed through his apostles.</p>
<p>It is of interest to note something that goes on in the New Testament that relates to our discussion. Paul’s words in 1 Corinthians 16 imply that it is the will of our Lord that churches gather on the first day of the week. As Paul told us, what he ordered for the Corinthians he had done for the Galatian churches, which assumes they met on the first day of the week as well. According to Acts 20:7 and the other relevant factors noted above, first-day meetings for acts of public worship by the churches was the New Testament norm. It is interesting to consider the practice of first-day church worship meetings, the assumption that the basis for such is the resurrection of our Lord (to be discussed under the next heading and in chapter 14, agreed upon by most), noting the authoritative approval of the apostle Paul for such meetings, assuming this to be dominical and apostolic sanction for such, in light of the probability that 1 Corinthians was written prior to the letters to the Romans and Colossians. If one takes Romans 14:5-6, Galatians 4:9-10, and Colossians 2:16-17 as the negation of all special days pertaining to Christians and churches, this would seem to contradict the assumption of 1 Corinthians 16 and other parts of the New Testament. The words of William Ames are worth pondering at this point:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">. . . in the practice of the churches at the time of the apostles, when mention is made of the observance of the first day, Acts 20:7; 1 Cor. 16:2, it is not remembered as some recent ordinance but as something long since accepted by the disciples of Christ. . . . [I]n all things the apostles delivered to the churches what they had received from Christ, 1 Cor. 11:23. . . . [T]his institution could have been deferred not more than one week after the death of Christ if God’s own law of one sanctified day per week were to remain firm . . . The placing of the holy sabbath of the Jews on the seventh day was abrogated by the death of Christ. . . . [I]t was also most appropriate that the day of worship in the New Testament should be ordained by him who ordained the worship itself and from whom all blessing and grace is to be expected in worship.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Assuming what Ames says is the case (and I think it is), how can Romans 14, Galatians 4, and Colossians 2 refer to the Lord’s Day? Ames comments on these texts as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">First, in all these passages the observance of some day for religious use by the action of Christ is no more condemned or denied than the choice of certain meat for religious use by the action of the same Christ. But no Christian would reasonably conclude from those passages that the choice of bread and wine for religious use in the Lord’s Supper is either unlawful or not ordained by Christ. Nothing, therefore, can be drawn from these passages against the observance of the Lord’s Day on the authority of Christ. Second, the Apostle in Rom. 14 expressly speaks of the judgment about certain days which then produced offense among Christians; but the observance of the Lord’s Day which the Apostle himself teaches had already taken place in all the churches (1 Cor. 16:1, 2) and could not be the occasion of offense. Third, it is most probable that the Apostle in this passage is treating of a dispute about choosing of days to eat or to refuse certain meats, for the question is put in Rom. 14:2 about meats only and in verses 5 and 6 the related problem of duty is discussed; and in the remainder of the chapter he considers only meats, making no mention of days. Fourth, in the Galatians passage the discussion relates only to the observance of days, months, and years as an aspect of bondage to weak and beggarly elemental spirits (4:9). But it was far from the Apostle’s mind and altogether strange to the Christian faith to consider any commandment of the decalogue or any ordinance of Christ in such a vein. Fifth, in Col. 2 the sabbaths mentioned are specially and expressly described as new moons and ceremonial shadows of things to come in Christ. But the sabbath commanded in the decalogue and our Lord’s Day are of another nature entirely, as has been shown.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Whether or not readers agree with every element of Ames’ arguments is not the point. The point being made is that prior to the writing of Romans and Colossians, holy drink and food (i.e., the Lord’s Supper), and a holy day (i.e., the Lord’s Day) were already in place. Whatever particular issues each passage is addressing, they cannot teach against the bread and wine and the sanctity of the first day of the week.</p>
<p>A further dilemma for those who think Romans 14, Galatians 4, and Colossians 2 deny the sanctity of the Lord’s Day needs mention at this time. If the Lord’s Day, the first day of the week, has not been sanctioned by our Lord himself through the apostles for churches to gather for public worship, who determines when churches ought to gather for such? If one says it is up to each church, does each church then have the authority to discipline one of its own for preferring another day and rarely attending their own church’s meetings for worship? Would this not be a violation of the interpretation of Romans 14, Galatians 4, and Colossians 2 that those who advocate against the sanctity of the first day take? It seems to me it would. If the words “Each person must be fully convinced in his own mind” refer to the Lord’s Day, the first day of the week, as well as all other days, how could a church discipline any of its members for forsaking the assembly of the saints, let alone encourage them to assemble on a stated day? Romans 14 cannot be a universal law against all holy days, just as it cannot be a universal law against all holy food and drink, and neither can Galatians 4 or Colossians 2. If they were, the Lord’s Supper could just as well be observed by using tacos and beer.</p>
<p>First day of the week meetings in the New Testament were sanctioned by Christ through his apostles. These meetings for worship are not to be placed in the category of <em>adiaphora</em>, something indifferent or outside the law of Christ. This is not an issue of Christian liberty, left up to each individual soul to determine what’s best for them. It is the will of Christ revealed to us in the New Testament in various ways to be practiced by his churches until he comes again.</p>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-7-of-8/">Part 7</a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Ames, <em>The Marrow of Theology</em>, 2.15.30 (295).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Ames, <em>The Marrow of Theology</em>, 2.15.32 (297).</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 6 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 5 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 20:39:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1st day of the week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7395</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 5 of 8, click here for part 1, part 2, part 3 &#38; part 4) First-Day Corporate Meetings in the New Testament Notice the phenomenon of first-day [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 5 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 5 of 8, click here for <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">part 1</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">part 2</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">part 3</a> &amp; <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/">part 4</a>)</p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">First-Day Corporate Meetings in the New Testament</span></em></strong></p>
<p>Notice the phenomenon of first-day corporate meetings in the New Testament. Acts 2:1 indicates that the Jerusalem disciples were assembled on the day of Pentecost, the first day of the week. “When the day of Pentecost had come, they were all together in one place.”</p>
<p>Acts 20:7 says, “Now on the first day of the week, when the disciples came together to break bread, Paul, ready to depart the next day, spoke to them and continued his message until midnight.” Here Luke tells us that the disciples in Troas met “on the first day of the week” with no comment on the reason why. This is not a command to meet on the first day of the week. It does, however, appear to assume a practice already in place. As Owen says, “This [i.e., gathering on the first day] they did without any extraordinary warning or calling together . . .”<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> It is not the institution of first-day meetings; it is a record of one such. On this day, the disciples conducted activities with special religious significance. Some understand the breaking of bread as the Lord’s Supper. Paul spoke to them, surely teaching them apostolic doctrine (i.e., authoritative oral apostolic tradition). They met on the first day of the week and had fellowship around spiritual matters. This text echoes aspects of the conduct of the early church, as recorded in Acts 2:42, “And they continued steadfastly in the apostles’ doctrine and fellowship, in the breaking of bread, and in prayers.” It is also of interest to note that Paul was in a hurry to get to Jerusalem (Acts 20:16), yet he stayed seven days in Troas (Acts 20:6) and did not leave until the day after the one described in 20:7. He left on Monday. Commenting on Acts 20:7, Martin notes:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">. . . it seems that this incident occurred on the day that the churches ordinarily gathered for worship, for the way that Luke includes a reference to the church meeting “on the first day of the week,” <em>i.e.</em>, with no further explanation, indicates that this was, as Owen says, “that which was in common observance amongst all the disciples of Christ.”<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>The reference to the first day of the week in Acts 20:7 seems to be something early readers of Acts would not need explained to them. Though the basis for meeting on that day as opposed to another day is not stated, putting the various pieces of evidence provided for us in the New Testament together, it is not a leap in the dark to assume they met on that day due to the theological and practical implications for the church of our Lord’s resurrection.</p>
<p>In 1 Corinthians 16:1-2 we read:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Now concerning the collection for the saints, as I directed the churches of Galatia, so do you also. <sup>2</sup> On the first day of every week each one of you is to put aside and save, as he may prosper, so that no collections be made when I come. (1 Cor. 16:1-2)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Here the Corinthians are told to do something that Paul had ordered the churches of Galatia to do. Though the specific apostolic injunction has to do with a first-century need is agreed upon by all, Paul’s mention of “the first day of every week” is what is of interest to our discussion. Paul does not order first-day meetings in Corinth in this text; he assumes that’s when they meet, and he assumes that they meet every week. Earlier in 1 Corinthians, Paul discusses the meeting of the Corinthian church in the context of the Lord’s Supper. In 1 Corinthians 11:17-22, we read:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">But in giving this instruction, I do not praise you, because you come together not for the better but for the worse. <sup>18</sup> For, in the first place, when you come together as a church, I hear that divisions exist among you; and in part I believe it. <sup>19</sup> For there must also be factions among you, so that those who are approved may become evident among you. <sup>20</sup> Therefore when you meet together, it is not to eat the Lord’s Supper, <sup>21</sup> for in your eating each one takes his own supper first; and one is hungry and another is drunk. <sup>22</sup> What! Do you not have houses in which to eat and drink? Or do you despise the church of God and shame those who have nothing? What shall I say to you? Shall I praise you? In this I will not praise you. (1 Cor. 11:17-22)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Paul distinguishes between the gathered church, the house of God, and their own homes in verses 17 (“you [plural] come together”), 18 (“when you [plural] come together as a church”), 20 (“when you [plural] meet together”), and 22 (“Do you [plural] not have houses in which to eat and drink?”). He specifically mentions coming together for the purpose of partaking of the Lord’s Supper (v. 20), though they had so trampled upon it that their practice had ceased being what they intended it to be. Upon what day of the week did the Corinthians “come together as a church”? Though chapter 11 does not tell us, we do have 1 Corinthians 16:1-2 and other considerations from the New Testament that lead us to the conclusion that they came “together as a church” every first day of the week.</p>
<p>Some want to argue what Paul is requiring in 1 Corinthians 16 is a private putting aside and saving, but if that were his intent, they would have to take a collection when he came. This, in fact, is what he does not want.<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a> Martin’s words are to the point:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">He is not saying, as is often suggested, that each one should lay aside his contributions privately at home, for then, any day of the week would do as well as another and a final collection still would need to be made. In specifying the first day of the week, Paul makes it clear that he is speaking of an activity that will take place at the time of their public assemblies. And he assumes that this will take place on the same day as in the churches of Galatia.<a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/">Part 6</a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Owen, <em>Works</em>, 18:423.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Martin, <em>The Christian Sabbath</em>, 278. The quote from Owen is cited as “John Owen, <em>Hebrews</em>, 2:423.”</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Wells, <em>The Christian and the Sabbath</em>, 95, commenting on 1 Cor. 16:1-2, says: “Is Paul speaking of an activity that was to take place in church meetings here? Probably not.”</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> Martin, <em>The Christian Sabbath</em>, 281-82. See Owen, <em>Works</em>, 18:424.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 5 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 4 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 11:32:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1st day of the week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[First Day of the Week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7359</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 4 of 8, click here for part 1, part 2 &#38; part 3) The Prominence of the First Day Immediately Subsequent to Christ’s Resurrection Notice [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 4 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 4 of 8, click here for <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">part 1</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">part 2</a> &amp; <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">part 3)</a></p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: large;">The Prominence of the First Day Immediately Subsequent to Christ’s Resurrection</span></em></strong></p>
<p>Notice the prominence of the first day immediately subsequent to Christ’s resurrection.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Matt. 28:1</strong> Now after the Sabbath, as it began to dawn toward the first <em>day </em>of the week, Mary Magdalene and the other Mary came to look at the grave. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Matt. 28:5-6</strong> The angel said to the women, “Do not be afraid; for I know that you are looking for Jesus who has been crucified. <sup>6</sup> “He is not here, for He has risen, just as He said. Come, see the place where He was lying. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Matt. 28:9-10</strong> And behold, Jesus met them and greeted them. And they came up and took hold of His feet and worshiped Him. <sup>10</sup> Then Jesus said to them, “Do not be afraid; go and take word to My brethren to leave for Galilee, and there they will see Me.” </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Mark 16:9</strong> Now when he rose early in the first day of the week, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Mark 16:12</strong> After that, he appeared in another form to two of them as they walked and went into the country. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Mark 16:14</strong> Afterward he appeared to the eleven as they sat at the table” </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Luke 24:1-2</strong> Now on the first day of the week, very early in the morning, they, and certain other women with them, came to the tomb bringing the spices which they had prepared. But they found the stone rolled away from the tomb. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Luke 24:13-15</strong> Now behold, two of them were traveling that same day to a village called Emmaus, which was seven miles from Jerusalem. And they talked together of all these things which had happened. So it was, while they conversed and reasoned, that Jesus himself drew near and went with them. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Luke 24:36</strong> Now as they said these things, Jesus himself stood in the midst of them, and said to them, “Peace to you.” </span></p></blockquote>
<p>These post-resurrection appearances of Christ all happened on the first day of the week. How can we best account for this? Waldron comments on this phenomenon:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">(1) We note first the phrase in John 20:26, “eight days later”. Since the Jews counted inclusively, this eighth day was the first day of the week. John is careful to include these details of time because they point to his Lord’s Day theology (Rev. 1:10). In fact, four of the eight New Testament references to the first or Lord’s Day are in the Johannine literature of the New Testament (John 20:1,19,26; Rev. 1:10). John 20:26 increases strikingly in its significance when it is compared with John 21:14. There the appearance beside the Sea of Tiberias is said to be “the third time that Jesus was manifested to His disciples.” This statement is, of course, problematic and must be qualified in some fashion. Whatever its specific meaning, it clearly marks the post-resurrection appearances of Jesus of John 20:19, 20:26, and 21:1 as unique and distinct. There were no intervening appearances of like character. Probably the meaning is that Jesus between these three appearances did not appear to a large group of disciples (Apostles). This means, of course, that between the first and eighth days of John 20 there were no like appearances to the disciples. This fact must have had a psychological effect upon the gathered disciples which would have clearly marked the first day of the week as of special significance for their resurrected Lord.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;">(2) Acts 2:1f. is also significant because the day of Pentecost occurred upon the first day of the week (Lev. 23:15-21). Pentecost, it is interesting to note was a day upon which no laborious work was to be done. Thus, it was in a sense a Sabbath. At any rate, the two constitutive events of the New Covenant and New Creation (the resurrection of Christ and the Pentecostal giving of the Spirit) both occurred on the first day of the week. Surely the disciples of Christ could not have overlooked or failed to ponder these facts.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Though these observations of themselves do not prove that the first day of the week is the Christian sacred day for church worship, taken together with the many other issues we have discussed and will discuss below, they indicate that something is very unique about the first day of the week <em>even after Christ rose from the dead</em>. In other words, the New Testament notes recurring first days after the resurrection of Christ. These post-resurrection and pre-ascension appearances seem to assume something peculiar about the first day of the week. Just what that peculiarity is demands further revelation.</p>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/">Part 5</a> </p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Waldron, <em>Lord’s Day</em>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 4 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 3 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2017 11:28:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[First Day of the Week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabatarian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7340</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 3 of 8, click here for part 1 &#38; part 2) Now notice what Luke records in Acts 6:2-4: So the twelve summoned the congregation [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 3 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 3 of 8, click here for <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>part 1</strong> </a>&amp; <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>part 2</strong></a>)</p>
<p>Now notice what Luke records in <strong>Acts 6:2-4</strong>:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">So the twelve summoned the congregation of the disciples and said, “It is not desirable for us to neglect the word of God in order to serve tables. <sup>3</sup> “Therefore, brethren, select from among you seven men of good reputation, full of the Spirit and of wisdom, whom we may put in charge of this task. <sup>4</sup> “But we will devote ourselves to prayer and to the ministry of the word.” (Acts 6:2-4)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>The “ministry of the word” most likely refers to the message preached, the things proclaimed by the apostles. This is, in fact, the ministry of the word of God. This is confirmed for us in <strong>1 Thessalonians 2:13.</strong></p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">For this reason we also constantly thank God that when you received the word of God which you heard from us, you accepted <em>it </em>not <em>as </em>the word of men, but <em>for </em>what it really is, the word of God, which also performs its work in you who believe. (1 Thess. 2:13)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Kruger comments on this text as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Paul emphasizes that the apostolic message borne by the apostles was to be received as the authoritative word of God . . . Although this message was certainly passed along orally by the apostles, it is clear that Paul expected his written letters to bear the same weight as his words spoken in the Thessalonians’ presence. Second Thessalonians 2:15 says, “Stand firm and hold to the traditions that you were taught by us, <em>either by our spoken word or by our letter.”</em> It is difficult to imagine that the Thessalonians would have understood Paul’s letters in any other way than as the authoritative apostolic message that demanded their submission and obedience.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>The apostles realized their message was God’s message in light of the sufferings and glory of our Lord. It was God’s message through them, something communicated by Christ in them by virtue of the promise and ministry of the Spirit. Our Lord had prepared them to expect this.</p>
<p>The following words by the Lord to the disciples prior to his death and resurrection apply to them in a unique way as apostles.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">These things I have spoken to you while abiding with you. <sup>26</sup> “But the Helper, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in My name, He will teach you all things, and bring to your remembrance all that I said to you. (John 14:25-26)</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;">When the Helper comes, whom I will send to you from the Father, <em>that is </em>the Spirit of truth who proceeds from the Father, He will testify about Me, <sup>27</sup> and you <em>will </em>testify also, because you have been with Me from the beginning. (John 15:26-27)</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;">“But when He, the Spirit of truth, comes, He will guide you into all the truth; for He will not speak on His own initiative, but whatever He hears, He will speak; and He will disclose to you what is to come. <sup>14</sup> “He will glorify Me, for He will take of Mine and will disclose <em>it </em>to you. <sup>15</sup> “All things that the Father has are Mine; therefore I said that He takes of Mine and will disclose <em>it </em>to you. (John 16:13-15)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>These promises set the background for the apostolic ministry. The apostolic ministry includes both speaking and writing on behalf of Christ in fulfillment of these very words.</p>
<p>The apostles have left the church with what has been termed apostolic tradition. These apostolic traditions were first spoken by the apostles and then written for us in the New Testament. This means that some things done by the early churches prior to the writing of the New Testament were based on the authoritative spoken word of the apostles (e.g., the Lord’s Supper in Corinth [1 Cor. 10 and 11]; the presence and function of teachers of the word in Galatia [Gal. 6:6]; the presence and function of overseers and deacons in Philippi [Phil. 1:1]; and the presence and function of laborers who oversee and instruct in Thessalonica [1 Thess. 5:12-13]). It is important to note, as Kruger asserts, the authoritative tradition that the New Testament speaks of is not human tradition or ecclesiastical tradition, but apostolic tradition.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a> It is also important to realize that what was first spoken was subsequently written and canonized. As Kruger acknowledges:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Although this apostolic tradition was initially delivered orally as the apostles preached, taught, and visited churches (2 Thess. 2:15), it very soon began to be preserved and passed along in written form. Of course, this transition did not happen all at once—oral apostolic tradition and written apostolic tradition would have existed side by side for a period of time.<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;">In sum, the New Testament documents can be understood as the written expression of the authoritative, foundational, and eyewitness tradition delivered by the apostles of Jesus Christ.<a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Oral apostolic tradition is assumed and further explicated by written apostolic tradition.</p>
<p>What does the discussion above about apostolic tradition have to do with the fact that Christ rose from the dead on the first day of the week? The resurrection of our Lord is not left as a self-interpreting act of God. Its theological and practical implications were brought to the early church by the apostles via both oral and written apostolic tradition. Though we do not necessarily possess the oral apostolic tradition in the exact words in which it was first delivered, the written assumes the oral and builds upon it. This being the case, if the New Testament indicates that the church met on the first day for public worship (i.e., practice), that it did so due to the first-day resurrection of our Lord (i.e., redemptive-historical basis), and that this practice was approved by an apostle or apostles (i.e., authoritative approval), is it too difficult to conclude that first-day meetings of the church for worship were also ordained by Christ through the apostles (i.e., dominical and apostolic sanction)? Just as the Book of Acts and the Epistles do not command the Lord’s Supper to be instituted, neither do they command the churches to meet on the first day of the week. Just as the Lord’s Supper is assumed by the Epistles, so the Lord’s Day is assumed as well. The churches addressed in the New Testament, <em>and the things they practiced</em>, existed prior to letters being written to them. As we shall see in our discussion of 1 Corinthians 16:1-2, first-day church meetings at Corinth are assumed to be in place, just as the Lord’s Supper is assumed to be in place, and both prior to the writing of 1 Corinthians. The importance of the discussion on apostolic tradition will become more evident in the discussion which follows.</p>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/"><strong>Part 4 </strong></a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 186-87; emphasis original.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> See Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 177. As understood and explained by Kruger, apostolic tradition is categorically different from Roman Catholic tradition.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 179.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 181.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 3 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 2 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 13:35:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1st day of the week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[First Day of the Week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lord's Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7332</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright &#169; 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 2 of 8. &#160;Read part 1 here.) One interesting aspect of the book of Acts and the Epistles is there are points at which it [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 2 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright &copy; 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 2 of 8. &nbsp;Read <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">part 1</a> here.)</p>
<p>One interesting aspect of the book of Acts and the Epistles is there are points at which it may be observed that the early Christians did certain things that are assumed as already in practice prior to the written record concerning the practice. For example, in 1 Corinthians 10:21, Paul writes about &#8220;the cup of the Lord&#8221; and &#8220;the table of the Lord.&#8221; Then in 1 Corinthians 11:20 he reduces those phrases to the phrase &#8220;the Lord&#8217;s Supper.&#8221; In 1 Corinthians 11:23-25, he recounts the words of the first institution of the Supper by our Lord. It is obvious that the Corinthians did not first partake of the Lord&#8217;s Supper after Paul wrote 1 Corinthians. He wrote to them to correct their thinking and practice, not to institute something never before practiced. In other words, the Corinthians knew about the Lord&#8217;s Supper and were in fact abusing it prior to Paul writing to them about it. This indicates that the practice of the Lord&#8217;s Supper predates Paul&#8217;s corrective concerning it. In 1 Corinthians 11:23, Paul says, &#8220;For I received from the Lord that which I also delivered to you . . .&#8221; This pertains to the Lord&#8217;s Supper. Paul had already delivered to the Corinthians the words of institution and their practical significance for the Corinthian church. Interestingly, in 1 Corinthians 11:2, Paul says, &#8220;Now I praise you because you remember me in everything and hold firmly to the traditions, just as I delivered them to you.&#8221; In context, it seems inescapable that one of those apostolic traditions is the Lord&#8217;s Supper. This is an instance where what is recorded for us in the Gospels (i.e., our Lord&#8217;s words of institution) is brought by an apostle to a local church by means of theological and practical implications. But when did Paul first bring the theological and practical implications of the institution of the Supper by our Lord to the Corinthians? The answer is he did so prior to writing 1 Corinthians, and he did so in the form of authoritative apostolic tradition.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> Paul does not say, however, &#8220;By the way, I am an apostle. The traditions I delivered to you as a church are the theological and practical implications of the redemptive-historical acts of God in Christ. Just as the events recorded for us in the Pentateuch form the historical and theological basis for the rest of the Old Testament and from which the writers of the Old Testament draw out theological and practical inferences for the people of God, so it goes with the events connected to our Lord&#8217;s sufferings and glory and the church of the inaugurated new covenant.&#8221; Though he does not say this, it is the best way to account for what took place in the first century. The Lord&#8217;s Supper did not start with Paul. It was instituted by our Lord and put into practice by other apostles prior to Paul&#8217;s conversion, and even prior to the writing of any New Testament books. When was it first called &#8220;the Lord&#8217;s Supper&#8221;? Though we cannot pinpoint an exact date, we know that it at least predates the writing of 1 Corinthians. Most likely, it goes back either to our Lord himself prior to his ascension or to the apostles prior to Paul. Why do I assert this?</p>
<p>Recall that the eleven were addressed by our Lord after his resurrection. The event to which I am referring is recorded for us in Luke 24:44-49.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Now He said to them, &#8220;These are My words which I spoke to you while I was still with you, that all things which are written about Me in the Law of Moses and the Prophets and the Psalms must be fulfilled.&#8221; <sup>45</sup> Then He opened their minds to understand the Scriptures, <sup>46</sup> and He said to them, &#8220;Thus it is written, that the Christ would suffer and rise again from the dead the third day, <sup>47</sup> and that repentance for forgiveness of sins would be proclaimed in His name to all the nations, beginning from Jerusalem. <sup>48</sup> &#8220;You are witnesses of these things. <sup>49</sup> &#8220;And behold, I am sending forth the promise of My Father upon you; but you are to stay in the city until you are clothed with power from on high.&#8221; (Luke&nbsp;24:44-49)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Our Lord could have instructed them about the Lord&#8217;s Supper and called it such at this time (or before), though we cannot know for certain.</p>
<p>The Book of Acts (written by Luke) informs us of other post-resurrection appearances by our Lord to the apostles. We read in Acts 1:1-4 the following:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The first account I composed, Theophilus, about all that Jesus began to do and teach, <sup>2</sup> until the day when He was taken up <em>to heaven</em>, after He had by the Holy Spirit given orders to the apostles whom He had chosen. <sup>3</sup> To these He also presented Himself alive after His suffering, by many convincing proofs, appearing to them over <em>a period of </em>forty days and speaking of the things concerning the kingdom of God. <sup>4</sup> Gathering them together, He commanded them not to leave Jerusalem, but to wait for what the Father had promised, &#8220;Which,&#8221; <em>He said</em>, &#8220;you heard of from Me; . . .&#8221; (Acts&nbsp;1:1-4)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>The &#8220;first account&#8221; (v. 1) refers to the Gospel of Luke. The words &#8220;all that Jesus began to do and teach&#8221; imply the Book of Acts concerns what Jesus continued to do and teach after his resurrection. Alan J. Thompson says:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Luke tells Theophilus in the first verse in Acts that his first book was all about what Jesus began to do and teach. The implication of these opening words in Acts is that he is now going to write about all that Jesus <em>continues</em> to do and teach.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Thompson adds, &#8220;Acts 1:1 indicates that the book is going to be about what Jesus is continuing to do and teach; therefore, the &#8216;Acts of the Risen Lord Jesus&#8217; would be a better title.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a> Before Christ&#8217;s ascension, he &#8220;had given orders to the apostles . . .&#8221; He appeared &#8220;to them over <em>a period of </em>forty days and&#8221; spoke &#8220;of the things concerning the kingdom of God.&#8221; He also reminded them of what Luke records for us in Luke 24 (see Acts 1:4). They were to wait in Jerusalem for Pentecost, at which time they would receive a special pneumatic endowment, equipping them for apostolic ministry while Christ was in heaven.</p>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">Part 3</a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> See the compelling discussion on apostolic tradition in Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 174-94.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Alan J. Thompson, <em>The Acts of the Risen Lord Jesus: Luke&#8217;s account of God&#8217;s unfolding plan</em>, New Studies in Biblical Theology (Downers Gove, IL: InterVarsity Press, 2011), 48; emphasis original. Thompson&#8217;s book is highly recommended.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Thompson, <em>The Acts of the Risen Lord Jesus</em>, 49.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 2 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 1 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2017 11:28:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[First Day of the Week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Getting the Garden Right]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lord's Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7318</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. It will serve us well to be reminded of the uniqueness of the first day of the week in the New Testament. The concept of a unique day [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 1 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: large;">This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</span></strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">It will serve us well to be reminded of the uniqueness of the first day of the week in the New Testament. The concept of a unique day of the week is not novel to the New Testament. What is novel is the uniqueness of the first day of the week. In order to identify that the first day is unique in the New Testament, why it is so, and what implications for Christians entail in light of it, the following will be examined: 1) the fact that Christ rose from the dead on the first day; 2) the prominence of the first day immediately subsequent to our Lord’s resurrection; 3) that the New Testament Christians met on the first day; and 4) identifying the reason for such first-day meetings. This will display that the uniqueness of the first day of the week in the New Testament is rooted in the epoch-changing, redemptive-historical event of the resurrection of our Lord Jesus Christ.</span></p>
<p>Conservative biblical scholars admit the first-day resurrection of our Lord. The prominence of the first day of the week immediately after our Lord’s resurrection is an indisputable phenomenon in the New Testament, as is the fact that the early Christians met on the first day of the week. The debate comes when seeking to determine the reason for and the implications of first-day meetings of the church. If the reason is mere convenience, then there is nothing significant in the resurrection of Christ in terms of directing orthopraxy or conduct with respect to public church worship on the first day of the week. If the reason is redemptive-historical, however, there is a theological basis for first-day church meetings that transcends the first century and ought to shape our conduct. If the reason is convenience, then anyone who mandates a particular day for churches to gather and conduct public worship has violated the law of Christ. If the reason is redemptive-historical, and therefore theological, then first-day church meetings for worship are rooted in the act of Christ and we should expect the apostles and writers of the New Testament to reflect this. These are important issues which we need to think through carefully. We will come back to the issue of the basis for first-day meetings in the discussion below.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: large;"><em>Christ Rose from the Dead on the First Day of the Week</em></span></strong></p>
<p>The New Testament is clear: the Lord Christ rose from the dead on the first day of the week. The first day is the day “after the Sabbath . . . the first <em>day</em> of the week” (Matt. 28:1; see Luke 24:1; John 20:1, 19), “when the Sabbath was over” (Mark 16:1). Several passages testify of Christ’s first-day resurrection (Matt. 28:1-8; Mark 16:1-11; Luke 24:1-12; John 20:1-23). Jesus rose from the dead early on the first day of the week (Mark 16:2, 9). Five times the Gospels mention this fact (Matt. 28:1; Mark 16:1; Luke 24:1; John 20:1, 19). Sam Waldron comments on this unique phenomenon, suggesting a reason why:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Is this five-fold re-occurrence of the phrase “the first day of the week” merely an interesting detail or is it of religious significance? The singular importance of this repeated reference to the first day of the week may be seen by asking the question, How many times are days of the week mentioned by their number in the New Testament? The answer is not once. The third day after Christ’s death is mentioned. The Lord’s Day is also mentioned. The preparation day for the Sabbath is mentioned. Yet, there is no other reference to a day of the week by its number in the entire New Testament. This being the case it is difficult to think that the mention of “the first day of the week” five times by the evangelists is incidental. We are constrained to think that it has religious significance. But what is that significance? It appears to be recorded to show the origin of the church’s practice of observing the first day. There is no other natural explanation of this peculiar insistence on the “first day of the week” in the resurrection account.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Most conservative biblical scholars agree that the New Testament church met on the first day of the week because Christ rose from the dead on that day. What Waldron is asking is how should we understand the repeated phenomena of the Gospels mentioning the fact of Christ’s first-day resurrection? Is it merely historical accounting with no theological and practical entailments? Or could it be that the accounting of redemptive history in the Gospels lays a basis for theological and practical significance which awaits further revelation for its explanation? Let’s explore this a bit before continuing the discussion. It is very important to consider.</p>
<p>We have seen that historical acts of God subsequently recorded for us in narrative accounts are often the basis from which further explanation of their significance is teased out by the human agents of said subsequent written revelation. Could this be the case with Christ’s resurrection? If this is the case (and I think it is), we should not demand or even expect the Gospel accounts to draw out the theological and practical implications of the resurrection of our Lord for the church of the inaugurated new covenant. The Gospels record the redemptive-historical acts of God in the sufferings and glory of Christ. It is left up to divine revelation via divinely appointed agents to draw out the implications of these redemptive-historical acts. We have this in the apostles and the other books of the New Testament (i.e., Acts-Revelation). The theological and practical implications of Christ’s first-day resurrection are not left up to us to interpret on our own. God has acted in Christ’s sufferings and glory recorded for us in the Gospels. God also interprets those acts through his divinely ordained agents, drawing out the implications for us in the rest of the New Testament. As Michael J. Kruger says:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">God did not simply perform redemptive acts and then leave the announcement and promulgation of those redemptive acts to chance or to random movements of human history. Instead, God established the authority structure of his apostolate to be the foundation of his church for generations to come.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/"><strong>Part 2 </strong></a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Samuel E. Waldron, <em>Lectures on the Lord’s Day</em>, unpublished.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Michael J. Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited: Establishing the Origins and Authority of the New Testament Books</em> (Wheaton, IL: Crossway, 2012), 174-75.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 1 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Peter Preached at Pentecost (part 3 of 3)</title>
		<link>/peter-preached-at-pentecost-part-3-of-3/</link>
					<comments>/peter-preached-at-pentecost-part-3-of-3/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 18:46:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pentecost]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=6950</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ten Characteristics of True Preaching (6-10) Preaching Is Scriptural! It is clear from Peter&#8217;s proclamation and preaching that preaching necessarily centrally involves the exposition of Scripture.&#160; This is clear from several aspects of Peter&#8217;s sermon. It is clear from the way in which he opens his message by referring to Joel&#8217;s prophecy and expounding its [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/peter-preached-at-pentecost-part-3-of-3/">Peter Preached at Pentecost (part 3 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><span style="font-size: xx-large;">Ten Characteristics of True Preaching (6-10)</span></strong></p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">Preaching Is Scriptural!</span></em></strong></p>
<p>It is clear from Peter&#8217;s proclamation and preaching that preaching necessarily centrally involves the exposition of Scripture.&nbsp; This is clear from several aspects of Peter&#8217;s sermon.</p>
<ul>
<li>It is clear from the way in which he opens his message by referring to Joel&#8217;s prophecy and expounding its relevance to what was happening on that Pentecost. Acts 2:16-21.</li>
<li>It is clear from the way in which he comments at length on the meaning of Psalm 16 in Acts 2:25-32.</li>
<li>It is clear from the recitation of the Apostolic witness to the words and deeds of Jesus the Christ in verses 22-24 and verses 33-36. What Peter says was not yet inscripturated, but it was tantamount to Scripture and would become Scripture.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now, of course, all of this makes perfect sense&#8212;if you understand what I said in my first point.&nbsp; <strong><em><a href="/peter-preached-at-pentecost-part-2-of-3/">Preaching is royal</a>!</em></strong>&nbsp; If preaching is a herald of the Divine King communicating His royal decree to His people, then, of course, the content of that preaching must be pervasively scriptural&#8212;<strong><em>It must be the Word of that King!</em></strong></p>
<p>True preaching must be expository.&nbsp; It may be consecutive expository preaching.&nbsp; It may be topical expository preaching.&nbsp; It must, however, be the exposition of the Word of God&#8212;or it is not preaching!&nbsp; Clearly, if this is true, much of what is called preaching today, simply is not, because it is not the faithful exposition of God&#8217;s Word.</p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">Preaching Is Practical!</span></em></strong></p>
<p>What I mean is that preaching is not intended merely to inform people&#8217;s minds.&nbsp; Now it is intended to do that, of course!&nbsp; But preaching is intended by informing people&#8217;s mind to lead them to do something.&nbsp; This becomes eminently clear in Peter&#8217;s preaching.</p>
<ul>
<li>It is clear in his very practical denial of the wicked mockery of those who said the phenomena of the Pentecost were to be attributed to the drunken-ness of the Apostles. This stupid mockery stood in the way of what Peter wanted people to do as a result of his preaching and had to be refuted and put in its place.</li>
<li>It is clear from the response that Peter&#8217;s preaching actually had. The implications of Peter&#8217;s message were only too clear.&nbsp; It made many in the multitude cry out, <em>Brothers, what shall we do!</em>&nbsp; Yes, they had understood Peter&#8217;s preaching.&nbsp; It was exactly intended to make them ask this very practical question.</li>
<li>It is also clear from the way Peter&#8217;s dialogue with them after his preaching was concluded is described. Look at verse 40.&nbsp; &#8220;And with many other words he solemnly testified and kept on exhorting them, saying, &#8216;Be saved from this perverse generation!&#8217;&#8221; &nbsp;He calls on them to save themselves from their accursed generation!</li>
<li>It is finally clear from the practical response to Peter&#8217;s preaching. They repented, were baptized, joined the church, and continued with the church in its worship.&nbsp; Acts 2:41-42.&nbsp; &#8220;So then, those who had received his word were baptized; and that day there were added about three thousand souls. <sup>42</sup> They were continually devoting themselves to the apostles&#8217; teaching and to fellowship, to the breaking of bread and to prayer.&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>The question in your mind as you hear preaching should be practical.&nbsp; It is not merely, <em>What can I learn from the preaching?</em>&nbsp; It is rather, <em>What must I do because of this preaching!</em>&nbsp; But this leads directly to my next point.</p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">Preaching Is Consequential!</span></em></strong></p>
<p>What I mean to convey by saying that preaching is consequential is that preaching has to do with very serious matters.&nbsp; Also I mean that your response to preaching will have the most serious consequences!</p>
<ul>
<li>This is conveyed by Peter at the outset of his message when he lifts up his voice and when he urges his hearers to give heed to what he is saying.</li>
<li>This is also made plain when in the dialogue at the end of his preaching he says plainly to his hearers that they must save themselves from the perverse generation in which they lived.</li>
</ul>
<p>Preaching always has to do with your salvation.&nbsp; Your response to preaching will save you or it will further your damnation.&nbsp; Oh, dear friend, how do you hear preaching?&nbsp; Do you realize how serious the consequences are of your response to the preaching of the Word of God?</p>
<p>Let us determine that we will rightly hear the preaching of God&#8217;s Word!&nbsp; This means a number of very practical things.</p>
<ul>
<li>We will train our children not to be a distraction in worship. Our children need to know that there is something important going on during the preaching, and that it is more important than their selfish desires.</li>
<li>We will strive to minimize anything that may distract us. We will use the restroom before the preaching.&nbsp; We will make sure our children have all such needs attended to before the preaching of God&#8217;s Word.&nbsp; We will not needlessly walk in and out during the preaching of God&#8217;s Word.&nbsp; We will do all we can to cut down on such distractions during the preaching of God&#8217;s Word.&nbsp; We will turn off our phones unless there is some emergency to which we may need to attend.</li>
<li>If we have to leave during the worship for some emergency, we will not linger and waste time. We will do our necessary business and get back to the worship of God.</li>
<li>We will focus our hearts and minds on what God is saying to us in the preaching! We will lock in our attention on the preaching of God&#8217;s Word.</li>
<li>We will come with properly rested hearts and minds to the worship of God by getting to bed early enough on Saturday evening. The right hearing of the preaching of God&#8217;s Word begins with getting to bed at a proper time the night before.</li>
<li>We will remind ourselves and our families of what preaching really is! It is God speaking to us through His appointed messenger.&nbsp; We will set them an example of how to hear the Word of God!</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">Preaching Is Christological!</span></em></strong></p>
<p>Another attribute of the true preaching of God&#8217;s Word is that it has a specific message.&nbsp; That message is Christological.&nbsp; By that big word I simply intend to say that true preaching is Christ-centered!&nbsp; It is indisputable that Peter&#8217;s first message after the Spirit was poured out and the gospel age dawned focused on the life, words, deeds, and saving power of Jesus Christ.&nbsp; His preaching in this passage is Christ-centered.</p>
<p>Now, of course, this important fact should not be distorted or misapplied.&nbsp; It does not mean that we can never preach anything but the doctrines of grace.&nbsp; It does not mean that we can never preach anything but justification by faith alone.&nbsp; It does not mean that we can only preach the priestly work of Christ.&nbsp; Christ has three offices&#8212;not just one!&nbsp; Christ is our sanctifier as well as our justifier!&nbsp; Christ orders His church by His law and ordinances.&nbsp; There is more in the Bible than the doctrines of grace.&nbsp; We may preach, for example, messages about the primacy of Peter and the propriety of preaching.</p>
<p>But having said that, we must never forget that all the diverse, rich, multi-faceted themes of the Bible lead back to Christ.&nbsp; The primacy of Peter among the plurality of Apostles leads us back to the great singularity of Christ as the center of both the universal and local church!&nbsp; The propriety of preaching requires that we finally say that true preaching is centered and focused on Christ!</p>
<p>What a condemnation this is of Christ-less preaching!&nbsp; What a condemnation this is of preaching that goes no farther than telling you how to be healthy, wealthy, and wise by the standards of this world!&nbsp; What a condemnation this is of preaching that does nothing more than moralize on the basis of a scriptural pretext!&nbsp; Preaching must lead back to Christ.&nbsp; As all roads led to Rome in the Roman Empire, so also in true preaching all true preaching leads back finally to Christ!</p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">Preaching Is Universal!</span></em></strong></p>
<p>Let me point out another further trait of true preaching.&nbsp; It is universal.&nbsp; It is not addressed only to God&#8217;s elect.&nbsp; It is not addressed only to Christians.&nbsp; It is not addressed only to those who show signs of being converted.&nbsp; True preaching is to be addressed universally to all men.&nbsp; We saw that, when he stepped forward, Peter addressed &#8220;the men of Judea and all who dwelt in Jerusalem.&#8221;&nbsp; All were to be addressed with the message.&nbsp; All were to be sincerely, freely, and with a well-meant offer called to save themselves from that perverse generation.</p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">Preaching Is Effectual!</span></em></strong></p>
<p>We are surrounded by people who think they are experts in religion, and those people tell us that preaching doesn&#8217;t work.&nbsp; Small groups work, they think.&nbsp; Contemporary music works, they think.&nbsp; Dialogue works, they will tell you.&nbsp; But preaching?&nbsp; Standing up and simply declaring God&#8217;s Word in a long monologue to people?&nbsp; They will tell you firmly, and with great sympathy for your na&iuml;vet&eacute; and how out of touch you are, that preaching does not work!</p>
<p>But preaching did work on the Day of Pentecost!&nbsp; Of course, it was and is only a means, but it is a divinely appointed means of grace.&nbsp; And when Peter was done preaching on the Day of Pentecost, verse 41 tells us there were three thousand more Christians than there were before!&nbsp; Let us trust God&#8217;s methods and close our ears to those who say that God&#8217;s appointed means of preaching will not work!</p>
<p><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Final Thoughts:&nbsp; </span></strong>Let me leave you with just three closing thoughts:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><em>It is a glorious calling to be called to preach God&#8217;s Word.</em></strong> Do not turn a deaf ear if the Spirit is calling you to be a servant and preacher of the Word of God!&nbsp; Do not run from the sacrifice to which such a calling commits you.</li>
<li><strong><em>It is a serious calling to undertake to preach God&#8217;s Word. </em></strong>There are preparations to be made both in your life and in your mind.&nbsp; There are standards of godliness.&nbsp; There are standards of gift.&nbsp; Both are set by the Word of God!&nbsp; You must not lightly skip over those standards or those preparations in your eagerness to preach.&nbsp; Neither should the church!&nbsp; The church should exercise great care in who is allowed to preach God&#8217;s Word as the formal representatives of God and especially in the house of God itself!</li>
<li><strong><em>It is a solemn thing to refuse the preaching of God&#8217;s Word!</em></strong> We are only the heralds of that great King.&nbsp; But when men sit there unmoved and disobedient to the preaching they are not rejecting that King&#8217;s humble heralds merely!&nbsp; They are rejecting the King of Kings!</li>
</ul>
<p>Sam Waldron</p>
<p>Peter Preached at Pentecost <a href="/peter-preached-on-pentecost-part-1-of-3/">part 1</a></p>
<p>Peter Preached at Pentecost <a href="/peter-preached-at-pentecost-part-2-of-3/">part 2</a></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/peter-preached-at-pentecost-part-3-of-3/">Peter Preached at Pentecost (part 3 of 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/peter-preached-at-pentecost-part-3-of-3/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
