<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Richard Barcellos | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/author/richard-barcellos/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 21:17:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Richard Barcellos | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Did the authors of the New Testament Epistles know they were writing  Holy Scripture?</title>
		<link>/new-testament-authors/</link>
					<comments>/new-testament-authors/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 21:17:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9497</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>full sermon here Did the authors of the Epistles know they were writing Holy Scripture? To answer this question, I want to look at 2 Peter 3:15-16 and consider another text in 2 Peter 3. 2 Peter 3:15-16 and regard the patience of our Lord as salvation; just as also our beloved brother Paul, according [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/new-testament-authors/">Did the authors of the New Testament Epistles know they were writing  Holy Scripture?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.sermonaudio.com/sermoninfo.asp?SID=325182341141"><strong>full sermon here</strong></a></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Did the authors of the Epistles know they were writing Holy Scripture? To answer this question, I want to look at 2 Peter 3:15-16 and consider another text in 2 Peter 3.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>2 Peter 3:15-16</strong></span></p>
<blockquote><p><span style="font-size: large;">and regard the patience of our Lord <em>as </em>salvation; just as also our beloved brother Paul, according to the wisdom given him, wrote to you, <sup>16</sup> as also in all <em>his </em>letters, speaking in them of these things, in which are some things hard to understand, which the untaught and unstable distort, as <em>they do </em>also the rest of the Scriptures, to their own destruction. (2 Pet. 3:15-16)</span></p></blockquote>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">Note, first, that Paul wrote letter<strong>s</strong> or epistle<strong>s</strong>.</span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">Note, second, that Peter places Paul&#8217;s letters on the same level as &#8220;the rest of the Scriptures,&#8221; which refers at least to the Old Testament.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">Note, third, that Peter identifies some who are &#8220;untaught and unstable . . . [who] distort . . . the Scriptures, to their own destruction.&#8221; Now listen to Jude 17-18, &#8220;But you, beloved, ought to remember the words that were spoken beforehand by the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ, <sup>18</sup> that they were saying to you, &#8216;In the last time there will be mockers, following after their own ungodly lusts.&#8217;&#8221; These kinds of statements occur elsewhere in the New Testament. For example, here&#8217;s Paul in Acts 20:29-30, &#8220;I know that after my departure savage wolves will come in among you, not sparing the flock; and from among your own selves men will arise, speaking perverse things, to draw away the disciples after them.&#8221; Listen to Paul in 1 Timothy 4:1, &#8220;But the Spirit explicitly says that in later times some will fall away from the faith, paying attention to deceitful spirits and doctrines of demons.&#8221; Here&#8217;s Paul in 2 Timothy 3:1, &#8220;But realize this, that in the last days difficult times will come.&#8221; Here&#8217;s Paul again in 2 Timothy 4:3, &#8220;For the time will come when they will not endure sound doctrine; but <em>wanting </em>to have their ears tickled, they will accumulate for themselves teachers in accordance to their own desires.&#8221; And finally, hear the words of Peter in 2 Peter 3:3, &#8220;Know this first of all, that in the last days mockers will come with <em>their </em>mocking, following after their own lusts.&#8221; What Jude calls &#8220;the words that were spoken beforehand by the apostles of our Lord&#8221; appear to be referring to written words, authoritative words, words contained in various places of our New Testaments.</span></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>2 Peter 3:1-2</strong></span></p>
<blockquote><p><span style="font-size: large;">This is now, beloved, the second letter [Gk. &#8216;epistle&#8217;] I am writing to you in which I am stirring up your sincere mind by way of reminder, <sup>2</sup> that you should remember the words spoken beforehand by the holy prophets and the commandment of the Lord and Savior <em>spoken </em>by your apostles.&#8221; Here is the ESV, &#8220;that you should remember the predictions of the holy prophets and the commandment of the Lord and Savior through your apostles. (2 Pet. 3:1-2)</span></p></blockquote>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">&#8220;The predictions of the holy prophets&#8221; were written down. Peter recognized the authority of the ancient prophets&#8217; written documents in 1 Peter 1:10-12 and in the book of Acts when he refers to the Old Testament (Acts 2).</span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">It could be that Peter is implying that &#8220;the commandment of the Lord and Savior through the apostles&#8221; is also written. If the words of the holy prophets were written, then the commandment of our Lord through the apostles is also written. Peter places the Old Testament prophets&#8217; written documents and the New Testament&#8217;s apostolic &#8220;command of the Lord&#8221; on the same level of authority.</span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">As well, this would mean that more apostles than Paul (cf. 2 Pet. 3:16) are being referred to, since Peter says &#8220;apostle<strong>s</strong>.&#8221; In fact, Peter identifies himself as an apostle in 1 Peter 1:1 and 2 Peter 1:1. He also identifies himself as an apostolic Epistle-writer (2 Pet. 3:1).</span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">Also, words very similar to &#8220;commandment of the Lord&#8221; are used by Paul. Here is 1 Corinthians 14:37, &#8220;If anyone thinks he is a prophet or spiritual, let him recognize that the things which I write to you are the Lord&#8217;s commandment.&#8221; Written apostolic words are &#8220;the Lord&#8217;s commandment.&#8221;</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">Interestingly, in the extra-biblical document the <em>Didache</em>, we read these words: &#8220;Nor should you pray like the hypocrites, but as the<em> Lord commanded in his gospel,</em> you should pray as follows, &#8216;Our Father in heaven. . . .&#8221; Michael Kruger follows this quote up with these words: &#8220;Here we have a reference to what Jesus &#8216;commanded&#8217; and are told it is contained in a &#8216;gospel,&#8217; and then this text proceeds to cite the Lord&#8217;s Prayer in a manner very close to Matthew 6:9-13.&#8221;<a name="_ftnref1"></a>[1]</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">The <em>Didache</em> also says this: &#8220;Do not abandon the commandments of the Lord, but guard what you have received, , neither adding to them or taking away.&#8221; This is an echo of Deuteronomy 4:2. Kruger comments: &#8220;Most noteworthy, the &#8216;commandments of the Lord&#8217; in this passage of the <em>Didache</em> no longer refer to the Old Testament commandments in Deuteronomy 4:2, but now refer to the teachings of Jesus.&#8221;<a name="_ftnref2"></a>[2] And the teachings of Jesus are contained in the four Gospels.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">All of this seems to indicate a &#8220;Scripture-writing consciousness&#8221; by Peter and other apostles. And this &#8220;Scripture-writing consciousness&#8221; traces back to the words of our Lord to the apostles in John 14-16.</span></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>Concluding thoughts</strong></span></p>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">Though we do not know the point in time when the authors of the New Testament Epistles realized they were writing authoritative letters on the same level with the Old Testament, there is enough evidence in their letters to indicate that they did realize it at some point. The Epistles at various points indicate to us that what the apostles wrote and what was approved by an apostle carried with it the status of being from the Lord. Their writings are &#8220;the command of the Lord and Savior,&#8221; in the words of Peter. When apostles wrote as apostles, their words were considered as the words of our Lord. This leads me to a second and final consideration.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">The basis for the New Testament Epistles being on the same level of authority with the Old Testament Scriptures is not to be found in the apostles themselves. In other words, the apostles did not appoint themselves to this task. The apostles did not assume something of themselves that was not true of themselves. Their authority for writing Holy Scripture did not come from themselves nor did it come from the church. The church does not have authority to determine what is and what is not authoritative Holy Scripture for it. In fact, the apostles do not have authority <em>in</em> and <em>by</em> themselves to determine what&#8217;s authoritative Scripture for the church. This prerogative, this right, this power, this sovereignty is found only in our Lord, the cornerstone and builder of His church. Recall the words of our Lord to the apostles, &#8220;the Helper, the Holy Spirit . . . will teach you all things, and bring to your remembrance all that I said to you&#8221; (John 14:26), &#8220;He will testify about Me, and you will testify also, because you have been with Me from the beginning&#8221; (John 15:26-27), and &#8220;He will guide you into all the truth . . . He will disclose to you what is to come&#8221; (John 16:13). Our Lord Himself is the basis for the Epistles being added to the Old Testament Scriptures as the written Word of God. Brothers and sisters, we can have confidence that what our Lord promised to the apostles He has fulfilled in their written documents contained in our New Testaments.</span></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">Let me add some final words for unbelievers to consider. If you have followed my argument, you can see the reason why Christians believe the New Testament to be the written Word of God. In one sense, it is &#8220;the commandment of the Lord and Savior&#8221; Himself. The New Testament books are not contrary to the Old Testament books. In their unique way both testaments declare salvation by our Lord Jesus Christ. The Old Testament does this in the language of promise; the New Testament in the language of fulfillment. What God promised through the prophets He has confirmed in the written words of the apostles. &#8220;In the fullness of time [and in agreement with &#8220;the Scriptures of the prophets&#8221;], God sent forth His Son . . . so that He might redeem&#8221; or save sinners from the consequences of their sins. And, in agreement with the Old Testament promise of salvation, the New Testament calls you to believe upon Christ for the forgiveness of all your sins. Will you obey the Lord? I hope you will.</span></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>________________________________________</p>
<p><a name="_ftn1"></a>[1] Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 212.</p>
<p><a name="_ftn2"></a>[2] Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 213.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/new-testament-authors/">Did the authors of the New Testament Epistles know they were writing  Holy Scripture?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/new-testament-authors/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 8 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-8-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-8-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 18:49:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1st day of the week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7475</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 6 of 8, click here for part 1, part 2, part 3, part 4, part 5, part 6 &#38; part 7)  The Reason for First-Day Meetings in the New Testament (continued) [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-8-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 8 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: medium;">This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</span></strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 6 of 8, click here for <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">part 1</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">part 2</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">part 3</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/">part 4</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/">part 5</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/">part 6</a> &amp; <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-7-of-8/">part 7</a>)</p>
<p><strong><em> </em></strong><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">The Reason for First-Day Meetings in the New Testament (continued)</span></em></strong></p>
<p>It is important to recognize that the resurrection is an epoch-changing event. The resurrection is seen as the beginning of the new creation. Believers are united to Christ in his death, burial, and resurrection through faith.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Or do you not know that all of us who have been baptized into Christ Jesus have been baptized into His death? <sup>4</sup> Therefore we have been buried with Him through baptism into death, so that as Christ was raised from the dead through the glory of the Father, so we too might walk in newness of life. <sup>5</sup> For if we have become united with <em>Him </em>in the likeness of His death, certainly we shall also be <em>in the likeness </em>of His resurrection, <sup>6</sup> knowing this, that our old self was crucified with <em>Him</em>, in order that our body of sin might be done away with, so that we would no longer be slaves to sin (Rom. 6:3-6)</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;">and in Him you were also circumcised with a circumcision made without hands, in the removal of the body of the flesh by the circumcision of Christ; <sup>12</sup> having been buried with Him in baptism, in which you were also raised up with Him through faith in the working of God, who raised Him from the dead. (Col. 2:11-12)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Union with Christ brings believers into the orbit of redemptive privilege. They may know “the power of His resurrection” (Phil. 3:10) because they are united to him through faith. God “made us alive together with Christ . . . and raised us up with Him, and seated us with Him in heavenly <em>places</em> in Christ Jesus” (Eph. 2:5-6). Being in Christ makes believers citizens of heaven (Phil. 3:20).</p>
<p>Union with Christ also involves existence in two ages at once—this age (the old creation) and the age to come (the new creation). The age to come is the age of the resurrection.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Jesus said to them, “The sons of this age marry and are given in marriage, <sup>35</sup> but those who are considered worthy to attain to that age and the resurrection from the dead, neither marry nor are given in marriage; <sup>36</sup> for they cannot even die anymore, because they are like angels, and are sons of God, being sons of the resurrection. (Luke 20:34-36)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Christ’s resurrection is the first bodily resurrection of the age to come because it was “the firstfruits” (1 Cor. 15:20).</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">But now Christ has been raised from the dead, the first fruits of those who are asleep. <sup>21</sup> For since by a man <em>came </em>death, by a man also <em>came </em>the resurrection of the dead. <sup>22</sup> For as in Adam all die, so also in Christ all will be made alive. <sup>23</sup> But each in his own order: Christ the first fruits, after that those who are Christ&#8217;s at His coming (1 Cor. 15:20-23)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Christ’s resurrection was the first of similar resurrections to come. But being “the firstfruits,” it is not totally other than that which follows. It is different in time, but it is part of the same resurrection. It is part of the same harvest, just the first of the much greater harvest to come. Gaffin, commenting on “firstfruits,” says:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The word is not simply an indication of temporal priority. Rather it brings into view Christ’s resurrection as the “firstfruits” of the resurrection-harvest, the initial portion of the whole. His resurrection is the representative beginning of the resurrection of believers. In other words, the term seems deliberately chosen to make evident the organic connection between the two resurrections. In the context, Paul’s “thesis” over against his opponents is that the resurrection of Jesus has the bodily resurrection of “those who sleep” as its necessary consequence. His resurrection is not simply a guarantee; it is a pledge in the sense that it is the actual beginning of the general event. In fact, on the basis of this verse it can be said that Paul views the two resurrections not so much as two events but as two episodes of the same event.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Christ’s resurrection is the most powerful sign of the presence of the age to come. His resurrected body took on qualities it did not possess prior to the resurrection (Rom. 1:4). It was an age-to-come body, existing in this age for a brief time on the earth and now in heaven. In Christ’s resurrection, then, we see the age to come eclipsing this age. This is why Paul says, “Therefore, if anyone <em>is </em>in Christ, <em>he is</em> a new creation; old things have passed away; behold, all things have become new” (2 Cor. 5:17, NKJV). This is not only true of personal renovation but also a state of existence in the new creation brought in by Christ. In Galatians 6:15, Paul says, “For neither is circumcision anything, nor uncircumcision, but a new creation.”</p>
<p>The age to come has eclipsed this age in the resurrection of Christ. Hebrews 6:5 says that some “have tasted the good word of God and the powers of the age to come.” Waldron says, “The great realities of the age to come have in some sense broken into and become operative in this age.”<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a> Waldron’s further comments are helpful at this point:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The New Testament teaches, therefore, that there is a new creation in Christ (Gal. 6:15; 2 Cor. 5:17; Eph. 2:10). The idea of new creation is frequently associated with Christ’s resurrection (cf. Eph. 2:10 with 2:5,7; Eph. 4:24; Col. 3:10 with Rom. 6:1-6; Col. 1:15-18). By union with Christ in His death, the old man is destroyed. By union with Christ in His resurrection, the new man is created. When He rose again He became the firstborn of God’s new creation. As He was the beginning of the old creation, so He is now the beginning of the new (Rev. 3:14). Thus, the memorial of Christ’s resurrection is of necessity a memorial of the new creation. Thus, the Lord’s Day like the Sabbath and unlike any other religious observance points to both creation and redemption.<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Christ’s resurrection is the apex of all of God’s redemptive work on the earth. It is an epoch-changing event. It ushers in the first phase of the new creation, the last Adam’s entrance into glory. In one sense, it affects everything. But how does it affect the Sabbath under the inaugurated new covenant? That it is the redemptive-historical, theological, and Christological basis for first-day church meetings seems clear. But does it mark the end of all Sabbaths for the people of God? Or does it function as the first creation did in relation to the first Sabbath? Does it function as the basis for the change of the Sabbath from the seventh to the first day because it is the day Christ ceased from his redemptive work, as God rested from his creative work? Surely, no greater, more unique event could be asked for to change the day of sacred rest for the people of God.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Richard B. Gaffin, Jr., <em>Resurrection and Redemption</em> (Phillipsburg, NJ: Presbyterian and Reformed Publishing, 1987), 34-35.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Samuel E. Waldron, <em>The End Times Made Simple</em> (Amityville, NY: Calvary Press, 2003), 49.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Waldron, <em>Lord’s Day</em>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-8-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 8 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-8-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 6 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 15:28:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1st day of the week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7406</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 6 of 8, click here for part 1, part 2, part 3, part 4 &#38; part 5) First-Day Corporate Meetings in the New Testament (continued) It is no small [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 6 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: medium;">This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</span></strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 6 of 8, click here for <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">part 1</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">part 2</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">part 3</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/">part 4</a> &amp; <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/">part 5</a>)</p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">First-Day Corporate Meetings in the New Testament (continued)</span></em></strong></p>
<p>It is no small matter for the apostle Paul to give orders to the churches concerning first-day meetings. Apostolic authority is binding for all churches. When Paul gave orders to the churches, his orders were the orders of Christ himself. John 16:13-14 (referenced above) contain a promise from Christ of inspired truth to complete the revelation of the Father’s will. This promise refers to the apostolate. Ephesians 2:20 says that the church was “built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets.” First Corinthians 4:17 says:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">For this reason I have sent to you Timothy, who is my beloved and faithful child in the Lord, and he will remind you of my ways which are in Christ, just as I teach everywhere in every church. (1 Cor. 4:17)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>What Paul taught “everywhere in every church” was binding on the Corinthians. In 1 Corinthians 7:17, Paul says, “Only, as the Lord has assigned to each one, as God has called each, in this manner let him walk. And so I direct in all the churches.” Paul had authority to ordain the same things in all the churches. First Corinthians 11:2 says, “Now I praise you because you remember me in everything and hold firmly to the traditions, just as I delivered them to you.” Apostolic traditions were binding on the Corinthians (see 2 Thess. 2:15).</p>
<p>So for Paul to give orders to the churches means that whatever he ordered was binding on them (and subsequent churches). Apostolic authority carried with it the authority of Christ himself. The apostles were the revelatory agents through whom Christ completed the will of his Father. As the saying goes, the apostle of the man is as the man himself. First-day meetings of the church for worship, then, are the will of Christ for his churches, revealed through his apostles.</p>
<p>It is of interest to note something that goes on in the New Testament that relates to our discussion. Paul’s words in 1 Corinthians 16 imply that it is the will of our Lord that churches gather on the first day of the week. As Paul told us, what he ordered for the Corinthians he had done for the Galatian churches, which assumes they met on the first day of the week as well. According to Acts 20:7 and the other relevant factors noted above, first-day meetings for acts of public worship by the churches was the New Testament norm. It is interesting to consider the practice of first-day church worship meetings, the assumption that the basis for such is the resurrection of our Lord (to be discussed under the next heading and in chapter 14, agreed upon by most), noting the authoritative approval of the apostle Paul for such meetings, assuming this to be dominical and apostolic sanction for such, in light of the probability that 1 Corinthians was written prior to the letters to the Romans and Colossians. If one takes Romans 14:5-6, Galatians 4:9-10, and Colossians 2:16-17 as the negation of all special days pertaining to Christians and churches, this would seem to contradict the assumption of 1 Corinthians 16 and other parts of the New Testament. The words of William Ames are worth pondering at this point:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">. . . in the practice of the churches at the time of the apostles, when mention is made of the observance of the first day, Acts 20:7; 1 Cor. 16:2, it is not remembered as some recent ordinance but as something long since accepted by the disciples of Christ. . . . [I]n all things the apostles delivered to the churches what they had received from Christ, 1 Cor. 11:23. . . . [T]his institution could have been deferred not more than one week after the death of Christ if God’s own law of one sanctified day per week were to remain firm . . . The placing of the holy sabbath of the Jews on the seventh day was abrogated by the death of Christ. . . . [I]t was also most appropriate that the day of worship in the New Testament should be ordained by him who ordained the worship itself and from whom all blessing and grace is to be expected in worship.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Assuming what Ames says is the case (and I think it is), how can Romans 14, Galatians 4, and Colossians 2 refer to the Lord’s Day? Ames comments on these texts as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">First, in all these passages the observance of some day for religious use by the action of Christ is no more condemned or denied than the choice of certain meat for religious use by the action of the same Christ. But no Christian would reasonably conclude from those passages that the choice of bread and wine for religious use in the Lord’s Supper is either unlawful or not ordained by Christ. Nothing, therefore, can be drawn from these passages against the observance of the Lord’s Day on the authority of Christ. Second, the Apostle in Rom. 14 expressly speaks of the judgment about certain days which then produced offense among Christians; but the observance of the Lord’s Day which the Apostle himself teaches had already taken place in all the churches (1 Cor. 16:1, 2) and could not be the occasion of offense. Third, it is most probable that the Apostle in this passage is treating of a dispute about choosing of days to eat or to refuse certain meats, for the question is put in Rom. 14:2 about meats only and in verses 5 and 6 the related problem of duty is discussed; and in the remainder of the chapter he considers only meats, making no mention of days. Fourth, in the Galatians passage the discussion relates only to the observance of days, months, and years as an aspect of bondage to weak and beggarly elemental spirits (4:9). But it was far from the Apostle’s mind and altogether strange to the Christian faith to consider any commandment of the decalogue or any ordinance of Christ in such a vein. Fifth, in Col. 2 the sabbaths mentioned are specially and expressly described as new moons and ceremonial shadows of things to come in Christ. But the sabbath commanded in the decalogue and our Lord’s Day are of another nature entirely, as has been shown.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Whether or not readers agree with every element of Ames’ arguments is not the point. The point being made is that prior to the writing of Romans and Colossians, holy drink and food (i.e., the Lord’s Supper), and a holy day (i.e., the Lord’s Day) were already in place. Whatever particular issues each passage is addressing, they cannot teach against the bread and wine and the sanctity of the first day of the week.</p>
<p>A further dilemma for those who think Romans 14, Galatians 4, and Colossians 2 deny the sanctity of the Lord’s Day needs mention at this time. If the Lord’s Day, the first day of the week, has not been sanctioned by our Lord himself through the apostles for churches to gather for public worship, who determines when churches ought to gather for such? If one says it is up to each church, does each church then have the authority to discipline one of its own for preferring another day and rarely attending their own church’s meetings for worship? Would this not be a violation of the interpretation of Romans 14, Galatians 4, and Colossians 2 that those who advocate against the sanctity of the first day take? It seems to me it would. If the words “Each person must be fully convinced in his own mind” refer to the Lord’s Day, the first day of the week, as well as all other days, how could a church discipline any of its members for forsaking the assembly of the saints, let alone encourage them to assemble on a stated day? Romans 14 cannot be a universal law against all holy days, just as it cannot be a universal law against all holy food and drink, and neither can Galatians 4 or Colossians 2. If they were, the Lord’s Supper could just as well be observed by using tacos and beer.</p>
<p>First day of the week meetings in the New Testament were sanctioned by Christ through his apostles. These meetings for worship are not to be placed in the category of <em>adiaphora</em>, something indifferent or outside the law of Christ. This is not an issue of Christian liberty, left up to each individual soul to determine what’s best for them. It is the will of Christ revealed to us in the New Testament in various ways to be practiced by his churches until he comes again.</p>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-7-of-8/">Part 7</a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Ames, <em>The Marrow of Theology</em>, 2.15.30 (295).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Ames, <em>The Marrow of Theology</em>, 2.15.32 (297).</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 6 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-6-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 4 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 11:32:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1st day of the week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[First Day of the Week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7359</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 4 of 8, click here for part 1, part 2 &#38; part 3) The Prominence of the First Day Immediately Subsequent to Christ’s Resurrection Notice [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 4 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 4 of 8, click here for <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">part 1</a>, <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">part 2</a> &amp; <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">part 3)</a></p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: large;">The Prominence of the First Day Immediately Subsequent to Christ’s Resurrection</span></em></strong></p>
<p>Notice the prominence of the first day immediately subsequent to Christ’s resurrection.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Matt. 28:1</strong> Now after the Sabbath, as it began to dawn toward the first <em>day </em>of the week, Mary Magdalene and the other Mary came to look at the grave. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Matt. 28:5-6</strong> The angel said to the women, “Do not be afraid; for I know that you are looking for Jesus who has been crucified. <sup>6</sup> “He is not here, for He has risen, just as He said. Come, see the place where He was lying. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Matt. 28:9-10</strong> And behold, Jesus met them and greeted them. And they came up and took hold of His feet and worshiped Him. <sup>10</sup> Then Jesus said to them, “Do not be afraid; go and take word to My brethren to leave for Galilee, and there they will see Me.” </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Mark 16:9</strong> Now when he rose early in the first day of the week, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Mark 16:12</strong> After that, he appeared in another form to two of them as they walked and went into the country. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Mark 16:14</strong> Afterward he appeared to the eleven as they sat at the table” </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Luke 24:1-2</strong> Now on the first day of the week, very early in the morning, they, and certain other women with them, came to the tomb bringing the spices which they had prepared. But they found the stone rolled away from the tomb. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Luke 24:13-15</strong> Now behold, two of them were traveling that same day to a village called Emmaus, which was seven miles from Jerusalem. And they talked together of all these things which had happened. So it was, while they conversed and reasoned, that Jesus himself drew near and went with them. </span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;"><strong>Luke 24:36</strong> Now as they said these things, Jesus himself stood in the midst of them, and said to them, “Peace to you.” </span></p></blockquote>
<p>These post-resurrection appearances of Christ all happened on the first day of the week. How can we best account for this? Waldron comments on this phenomenon:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">(1) We note first the phrase in John 20:26, “eight days later”. Since the Jews counted inclusively, this eighth day was the first day of the week. John is careful to include these details of time because they point to his Lord’s Day theology (Rev. 1:10). In fact, four of the eight New Testament references to the first or Lord’s Day are in the Johannine literature of the New Testament (John 20:1,19,26; Rev. 1:10). John 20:26 increases strikingly in its significance when it is compared with John 21:14. There the appearance beside the Sea of Tiberias is said to be “the third time that Jesus was manifested to His disciples.” This statement is, of course, problematic and must be qualified in some fashion. Whatever its specific meaning, it clearly marks the post-resurrection appearances of Jesus of John 20:19, 20:26, and 21:1 as unique and distinct. There were no intervening appearances of like character. Probably the meaning is that Jesus between these three appearances did not appear to a large group of disciples (Apostles). This means, of course, that between the first and eighth days of John 20 there were no like appearances to the disciples. This fact must have had a psychological effect upon the gathered disciples which would have clearly marked the first day of the week as of special significance for their resurrected Lord.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;">(2) Acts 2:1f. is also significant because the day of Pentecost occurred upon the first day of the week (Lev. 23:15-21). Pentecost, it is interesting to note was a day upon which no laborious work was to be done. Thus, it was in a sense a Sabbath. At any rate, the two constitutive events of the New Covenant and New Creation (the resurrection of Christ and the Pentecostal giving of the Spirit) both occurred on the first day of the week. Surely the disciples of Christ could not have overlooked or failed to ponder these facts.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Though these observations of themselves do not prove that the first day of the week is the Christian sacred day for church worship, taken together with the many other issues we have discussed and will discuss below, they indicate that something is very unique about the first day of the week <em>even after Christ rose from the dead</em>. In other words, the New Testament notes recurring first days after the resurrection of Christ. These post-resurrection and pre-ascension appearances seem to assume something peculiar about the first day of the week. Just what that peculiarity is demands further revelation.</p>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-5-of-8/">Part 5</a> </p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Waldron, <em>Lord’s Day</em>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 4 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 3 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2017 11:28:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[First Day of the Week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabatarian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7340</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 3 of 8, click here for part 1 &#38; part 2) Now notice what Luke records in Acts 6:2-4: So the twelve summoned the congregation [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 3 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 3 of 8, click here for <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>part 1</strong> </a>&amp; <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>part 2</strong></a>)</p>
<p>Now notice what Luke records in <strong>Acts 6:2-4</strong>:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">So the twelve summoned the congregation of the disciples and said, “It is not desirable for us to neglect the word of God in order to serve tables. <sup>3</sup> “Therefore, brethren, select from among you seven men of good reputation, full of the Spirit and of wisdom, whom we may put in charge of this task. <sup>4</sup> “But we will devote ourselves to prayer and to the ministry of the word.” (Acts 6:2-4)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>The “ministry of the word” most likely refers to the message preached, the things proclaimed by the apostles. This is, in fact, the ministry of the word of God. This is confirmed for us in <strong>1 Thessalonians 2:13.</strong></p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">For this reason we also constantly thank God that when you received the word of God which you heard from us, you accepted <em>it </em>not <em>as </em>the word of men, but <em>for </em>what it really is, the word of God, which also performs its work in you who believe. (1 Thess. 2:13)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Kruger comments on this text as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Paul emphasizes that the apostolic message borne by the apostles was to be received as the authoritative word of God . . . Although this message was certainly passed along orally by the apostles, it is clear that Paul expected his written letters to bear the same weight as his words spoken in the Thessalonians’ presence. Second Thessalonians 2:15 says, “Stand firm and hold to the traditions that you were taught by us, <em>either by our spoken word or by our letter.”</em> It is difficult to imagine that the Thessalonians would have understood Paul’s letters in any other way than as the authoritative apostolic message that demanded their submission and obedience.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>The apostles realized their message was God’s message in light of the sufferings and glory of our Lord. It was God’s message through them, something communicated by Christ in them by virtue of the promise and ministry of the Spirit. Our Lord had prepared them to expect this.</p>
<p>The following words by the Lord to the disciples prior to his death and resurrection apply to them in a unique way as apostles.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">These things I have spoken to you while abiding with you. <sup>26</sup> “But the Helper, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in My name, He will teach you all things, and bring to your remembrance all that I said to you. (John 14:25-26)</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;">When the Helper comes, whom I will send to you from the Father, <em>that is </em>the Spirit of truth who proceeds from the Father, He will testify about Me, <sup>27</sup> and you <em>will </em>testify also, because you have been with Me from the beginning. (John 15:26-27)</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;">“But when He, the Spirit of truth, comes, He will guide you into all the truth; for He will not speak on His own initiative, but whatever He hears, He will speak; and He will disclose to you what is to come. <sup>14</sup> “He will glorify Me, for He will take of Mine and will disclose <em>it </em>to you. <sup>15</sup> “All things that the Father has are Mine; therefore I said that He takes of Mine and will disclose <em>it </em>to you. (John 16:13-15)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>These promises set the background for the apostolic ministry. The apostolic ministry includes both speaking and writing on behalf of Christ in fulfillment of these very words.</p>
<p>The apostles have left the church with what has been termed apostolic tradition. These apostolic traditions were first spoken by the apostles and then written for us in the New Testament. This means that some things done by the early churches prior to the writing of the New Testament were based on the authoritative spoken word of the apostles (e.g., the Lord’s Supper in Corinth [1 Cor. 10 and 11]; the presence and function of teachers of the word in Galatia [Gal. 6:6]; the presence and function of overseers and deacons in Philippi [Phil. 1:1]; and the presence and function of laborers who oversee and instruct in Thessalonica [1 Thess. 5:12-13]). It is important to note, as Kruger asserts, the authoritative tradition that the New Testament speaks of is not human tradition or ecclesiastical tradition, but apostolic tradition.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a> It is also important to realize that what was first spoken was subsequently written and canonized. As Kruger acknowledges:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Although this apostolic tradition was initially delivered orally as the apostles preached, taught, and visited churches (2 Thess. 2:15), it very soon began to be preserved and passed along in written form. Of course, this transition did not happen all at once—oral apostolic tradition and written apostolic tradition would have existed side by side for a period of time.<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #666666;">In sum, the New Testament documents can be understood as the written expression of the authoritative, foundational, and eyewitness tradition delivered by the apostles of Jesus Christ.<a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Oral apostolic tradition is assumed and further explicated by written apostolic tradition.</p>
<p>What does the discussion above about apostolic tradition have to do with the fact that Christ rose from the dead on the first day of the week? The resurrection of our Lord is not left as a self-interpreting act of God. Its theological and practical implications were brought to the early church by the apostles via both oral and written apostolic tradition. Though we do not necessarily possess the oral apostolic tradition in the exact words in which it was first delivered, the written assumes the oral and builds upon it. This being the case, if the New Testament indicates that the church met on the first day for public worship (i.e., practice), that it did so due to the first-day resurrection of our Lord (i.e., redemptive-historical basis), and that this practice was approved by an apostle or apostles (i.e., authoritative approval), is it too difficult to conclude that first-day meetings of the church for worship were also ordained by Christ through the apostles (i.e., dominical and apostolic sanction)? Just as the Book of Acts and the Epistles do not command the Lord’s Supper to be instituted, neither do they command the churches to meet on the first day of the week. Just as the Lord’s Supper is assumed by the Epistles, so the Lord’s Day is assumed as well. The churches addressed in the New Testament, <em>and the things they practiced</em>, existed prior to letters being written to them. As we shall see in our discussion of 1 Corinthians 16:1-2, first-day church meetings at Corinth are assumed to be in place, just as the Lord’s Supper is assumed to be in place, and both prior to the writing of 1 Corinthians. The importance of the discussion on apostolic tradition will become more evident in the discussion which follows.</p>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-4-of-8/"><strong>Part 4 </strong></a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 186-87; emphasis original.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> See Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 177. As understood and explained by Kruger, apostolic tradition is categorically different from Roman Catholic tradition.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 179.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 181.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 3 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 2 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 13:35:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1st day of the week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[First Day of the Week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lord's Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7332</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright &#169; 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. (This is part 2 of 8. &#160;Read part 1 here.) One interesting aspect of the book of Acts and the Epistles is there are points at which it [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 2 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright &copy; 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p>(This is part 2 of 8. &nbsp;Read <a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">part 1</a> here.)</p>
<p>One interesting aspect of the book of Acts and the Epistles is there are points at which it may be observed that the early Christians did certain things that are assumed as already in practice prior to the written record concerning the practice. For example, in 1 Corinthians 10:21, Paul writes about &#8220;the cup of the Lord&#8221; and &#8220;the table of the Lord.&#8221; Then in 1 Corinthians 11:20 he reduces those phrases to the phrase &#8220;the Lord&#8217;s Supper.&#8221; In 1 Corinthians 11:23-25, he recounts the words of the first institution of the Supper by our Lord. It is obvious that the Corinthians did not first partake of the Lord&#8217;s Supper after Paul wrote 1 Corinthians. He wrote to them to correct their thinking and practice, not to institute something never before practiced. In other words, the Corinthians knew about the Lord&#8217;s Supper and were in fact abusing it prior to Paul writing to them about it. This indicates that the practice of the Lord&#8217;s Supper predates Paul&#8217;s corrective concerning it. In 1 Corinthians 11:23, Paul says, &#8220;For I received from the Lord that which I also delivered to you . . .&#8221; This pertains to the Lord&#8217;s Supper. Paul had already delivered to the Corinthians the words of institution and their practical significance for the Corinthian church. Interestingly, in 1 Corinthians 11:2, Paul says, &#8220;Now I praise you because you remember me in everything and hold firmly to the traditions, just as I delivered them to you.&#8221; In context, it seems inescapable that one of those apostolic traditions is the Lord&#8217;s Supper. This is an instance where what is recorded for us in the Gospels (i.e., our Lord&#8217;s words of institution) is brought by an apostle to a local church by means of theological and practical implications. But when did Paul first bring the theological and practical implications of the institution of the Supper by our Lord to the Corinthians? The answer is he did so prior to writing 1 Corinthians, and he did so in the form of authoritative apostolic tradition.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> Paul does not say, however, &#8220;By the way, I am an apostle. The traditions I delivered to you as a church are the theological and practical implications of the redemptive-historical acts of God in Christ. Just as the events recorded for us in the Pentateuch form the historical and theological basis for the rest of the Old Testament and from which the writers of the Old Testament draw out theological and practical inferences for the people of God, so it goes with the events connected to our Lord&#8217;s sufferings and glory and the church of the inaugurated new covenant.&#8221; Though he does not say this, it is the best way to account for what took place in the first century. The Lord&#8217;s Supper did not start with Paul. It was instituted by our Lord and put into practice by other apostles prior to Paul&#8217;s conversion, and even prior to the writing of any New Testament books. When was it first called &#8220;the Lord&#8217;s Supper&#8221;? Though we cannot pinpoint an exact date, we know that it at least predates the writing of 1 Corinthians. Most likely, it goes back either to our Lord himself prior to his ascension or to the apostles prior to Paul. Why do I assert this?</p>
<p>Recall that the eleven were addressed by our Lord after his resurrection. The event to which I am referring is recorded for us in Luke 24:44-49.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Now He said to them, &#8220;These are My words which I spoke to you while I was still with you, that all things which are written about Me in the Law of Moses and the Prophets and the Psalms must be fulfilled.&#8221; <sup>45</sup> Then He opened their minds to understand the Scriptures, <sup>46</sup> and He said to them, &#8220;Thus it is written, that the Christ would suffer and rise again from the dead the third day, <sup>47</sup> and that repentance for forgiveness of sins would be proclaimed in His name to all the nations, beginning from Jerusalem. <sup>48</sup> &#8220;You are witnesses of these things. <sup>49</sup> &#8220;And behold, I am sending forth the promise of My Father upon you; but you are to stay in the city until you are clothed with power from on high.&#8221; (Luke&nbsp;24:44-49)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Our Lord could have instructed them about the Lord&#8217;s Supper and called it such at this time (or before), though we cannot know for certain.</p>
<p>The Book of Acts (written by Luke) informs us of other post-resurrection appearances by our Lord to the apostles. We read in Acts 1:1-4 the following:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The first account I composed, Theophilus, about all that Jesus began to do and teach, <sup>2</sup> until the day when He was taken up <em>to heaven</em>, after He had by the Holy Spirit given orders to the apostles whom He had chosen. <sup>3</sup> To these He also presented Himself alive after His suffering, by many convincing proofs, appearing to them over <em>a period of </em>forty days and speaking of the things concerning the kingdom of God. <sup>4</sup> Gathering them together, He commanded them not to leave Jerusalem, but to wait for what the Father had promised, &#8220;Which,&#8221; <em>He said</em>, &#8220;you heard of from Me; . . .&#8221; (Acts&nbsp;1:1-4)</span></p></blockquote>
<p>The &#8220;first account&#8221; (v. 1) refers to the Gospel of Luke. The words &#8220;all that Jesus began to do and teach&#8221; imply the Book of Acts concerns what Jesus continued to do and teach after his resurrection. Alan J. Thompson says:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Luke tells Theophilus in the first verse in Acts that his first book was all about what Jesus began to do and teach. The implication of these opening words in Acts is that he is now going to write about all that Jesus <em>continues</em> to do and teach.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Thompson adds, &#8220;Acts 1:1 indicates that the book is going to be about what Jesus is continuing to do and teach; therefore, the &#8216;Acts of the Risen Lord Jesus&#8217; would be a better title.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a> Before Christ&#8217;s ascension, he &#8220;had given orders to the apostles . . .&#8221; He appeared &#8220;to them over <em>a period of </em>forty days and&#8221; spoke &#8220;of the things concerning the kingdom of God.&#8221; He also reminded them of what Luke records for us in Luke 24 (see Acts 1:4). They were to wait in Jerusalem for Pentecost, at which time they would receive a special pneumatic endowment, equipping them for apostolic ministry while Christ was in heaven.</p>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-3-of-8/">Part 3</a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> See the compelling discussion on apostolic tradition in Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited</em>, 174-94.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Alan J. Thompson, <em>The Acts of the Risen Lord Jesus: Luke&#8217;s account of God&#8217;s unfolding plan</em>, New Studies in Biblical Theology (Downers Gove, IL: InterVarsity Press, 2011), 48; emphasis original. Thompson&#8217;s book is highly recommended.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Thompson, <em>The Acts of the Risen Lord Jesus</em>, 49.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 2 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 1 of 8)</title>
		<link>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2017 11:28:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[First Day of the Week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Getting the Garden Right]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lord's Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7318</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This discussion comes from Getting the Garden Right, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission. Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved. It will serve us well to be reminded of the uniqueness of the first day of the week in the New Testament. The concept of a unique day [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 1 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: large;">This discussion comes from <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>, coming soon from Founders Press. It is used with permission.</span></strong><br />
<span style="font-size: xx-small;">Copyright © 2017 Richard C. Barcellos. All rights reserved.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">It will serve us well to be reminded of the uniqueness of the first day of the week in the New Testament. The concept of a unique day of the week is not novel to the New Testament. What is novel is the uniqueness of the first day of the week. In order to identify that the first day is unique in the New Testament, why it is so, and what implications for Christians entail in light of it, the following will be examined: 1) the fact that Christ rose from the dead on the first day; 2) the prominence of the first day immediately subsequent to our Lord’s resurrection; 3) that the New Testament Christians met on the first day; and 4) identifying the reason for such first-day meetings. This will display that the uniqueness of the first day of the week in the New Testament is rooted in the epoch-changing, redemptive-historical event of the resurrection of our Lord Jesus Christ.</span></p>
<p>Conservative biblical scholars admit the first-day resurrection of our Lord. The prominence of the first day of the week immediately after our Lord’s resurrection is an indisputable phenomenon in the New Testament, as is the fact that the early Christians met on the first day of the week. The debate comes when seeking to determine the reason for and the implications of first-day meetings of the church. If the reason is mere convenience, then there is nothing significant in the resurrection of Christ in terms of directing orthopraxy or conduct with respect to public church worship on the first day of the week. If the reason is redemptive-historical, however, there is a theological basis for first-day church meetings that transcends the first century and ought to shape our conduct. If the reason is convenience, then anyone who mandates a particular day for churches to gather and conduct public worship has violated the law of Christ. If the reason is redemptive-historical, and therefore theological, then first-day church meetings for worship are rooted in the act of Christ and we should expect the apostles and writers of the New Testament to reflect this. These are important issues which we need to think through carefully. We will come back to the issue of the basis for first-day meetings in the discussion below.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: large;"><em>Christ Rose from the Dead on the First Day of the Week</em></span></strong></p>
<p>The New Testament is clear: the Lord Christ rose from the dead on the first day of the week. The first day is the day “after the Sabbath . . . the first <em>day</em> of the week” (Matt. 28:1; see Luke 24:1; John 20:1, 19), “when the Sabbath was over” (Mark 16:1). Several passages testify of Christ’s first-day resurrection (Matt. 28:1-8; Mark 16:1-11; Luke 24:1-12; John 20:1-23). Jesus rose from the dead early on the first day of the week (Mark 16:2, 9). Five times the Gospels mention this fact (Matt. 28:1; Mark 16:1; Luke 24:1; John 20:1, 19). Sam Waldron comments on this unique phenomenon, suggesting a reason why:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">Is this five-fold re-occurrence of the phrase “the first day of the week” merely an interesting detail or is it of religious significance? The singular importance of this repeated reference to the first day of the week may be seen by asking the question, How many times are days of the week mentioned by their number in the New Testament? The answer is not once. The third day after Christ’s death is mentioned. The Lord’s Day is also mentioned. The preparation day for the Sabbath is mentioned. Yet, there is no other reference to a day of the week by its number in the entire New Testament. This being the case it is difficult to think that the mention of “the first day of the week” five times by the evangelists is incidental. We are constrained to think that it has religious significance. But what is that significance? It appears to be recorded to show the origin of the church’s practice of observing the first day. There is no other natural explanation of this peculiar insistence on the “first day of the week” in the resurrection account.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Most conservative biblical scholars agree that the New Testament church met on the first day of the week because Christ rose from the dead on that day. What Waldron is asking is how should we understand the repeated phenomena of the Gospels mentioning the fact of Christ’s first-day resurrection? Is it merely historical accounting with no theological and practical entailments? Or could it be that the accounting of redemptive history in the Gospels lays a basis for theological and practical significance which awaits further revelation for its explanation? Let’s explore this a bit before continuing the discussion. It is very important to consider.</p>
<p>We have seen that historical acts of God subsequently recorded for us in narrative accounts are often the basis from which further explanation of their significance is teased out by the human agents of said subsequent written revelation. Could this be the case with Christ’s resurrection? If this is the case (and I think it is), we should not demand or even expect the Gospel accounts to draw out the theological and practical implications of the resurrection of our Lord for the church of the inaugurated new covenant. The Gospels record the redemptive-historical acts of God in the sufferings and glory of Christ. It is left up to divine revelation via divinely appointed agents to draw out the implications of these redemptive-historical acts. We have this in the apostles and the other books of the New Testament (i.e., Acts-Revelation). The theological and practical implications of Christ’s first-day resurrection are not left up to us to interpret on our own. God has acted in Christ’s sufferings and glory recorded for us in the Gospels. God also interprets those acts through his divinely ordained agents, drawing out the implications for us in the rest of the New Testament. As Michael J. Kruger says:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">God did not simply perform redemptive acts and then leave the announcement and promulgation of those redemptive acts to chance or to random movements of human history. Instead, God established the authority structure of his apostolate to be the foundation of his church for generations to come.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-2-of-8/"><strong>Part 2 </strong></a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Samuel E. Waldron, <em>Lectures on the Lord’s Day</em>, unpublished.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Michael J. Kruger, <em>Canon Revisited: Establishing the Origins and Authority of the New Testament Books</em> (Wheaton, IL: Crossway, 2012), 174-75.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/">The First Day of the Week in the New Testament (part 1 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-first-day-of-the-week-in-the-new-testament-part-1-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (VI)</title>
		<link>/wells-sabbath-chap-three-vi/</link>
					<comments>/wells-sabbath-chap-three-vi/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 05:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lord's Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Christian and the Sabbath review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Wells]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1034</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A detailed examination of all the passages in the Gospels where Christ discusses the issue of the Sabbath will show that he never predicted its abolition, nor did he ever profane it.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-sabbath-chap-three-vi/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (VI)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/06/1030/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (V)</a></p>
<p><strong>Conclusion: <strong>Gospel Texts on Sabbath-Keeping</strong></strong></p>
<p>A detailed examination of all the passages in the Gospels where Christ discusses the issue of the Sabbath will show that he never predicted its abolition, nor did he ever profane it. If fact, he could not profane it, nor advocate its profanation by others, without sinning. He was born under the law, not to profane it, but to keep it (Gal. 4:5). If Christ violated the Sabbath, then he sinned and would not be a suitable Savior for others. Instead, he advocated works of necessity (Matt. 12:1-8; Mk. 2:23-28; Lk. 6:1-5), mercy (Matt. 12:9-14; Mk. 3:1-6; Lk. 4:31-41; 6:6-11; 13:10-17; 14:1-6; Jn. 5:8-10; 7:23; 9:13-16), and piety (Matt. 12:9; Mk. 6:2; Lk. 4:16; 6:6; Jn. 7:22-23) on the Sabbath by his teaching and example. He never violated it, advocated its violation by others, or prophesied its soon demise. In fact, Mk. 2:27-28 prophesies the perpetuity of the Sabbath under his lordship as Son of Man.</p>
<p>Both Matt. 12:1-14 and Mk. 2:27-28 contain transcovenantal principles relating to the Sabbath. Works of mercy and necessity are lawful on the Sabbath, linking Jesus’ teaching with revelation given prior to his earthly ministry (i.e., the OT). Jesus as Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath, linking the Sabbath and its Lord with future revelation (i.e., the NT). Jesus’ teaching on the Sabbath leaves us with the expectation that he will execute his lordship over the Sabbath in the future, during the inter-advental days of the new covenant. His teaching on the Sabbath is related to antecedent revelation (explicitly) and subsequent revelation (implicitly). It establishes a basis for its basic ethical perpetuity and yet in such a way as to expect changes in application due to the redemptive-historical shift that takes place due to his entrance into glory (i.e., resurrection/ascension).</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-sabbath-chap-three-vi/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (VI)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/wells-sabbath-chap-three-vi/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (V)</title>
		<link>/1030-2/</link>
					<comments>/1030-2/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2011 05:37:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reveiw of Tom Wells The Christian and the Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wells]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1030</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Tom Wells&#8217; book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (IV) Mark 2:23-28 narrates another incident between Jesus and his disciples and the Pharisees. Jesus was &#8220;passing through the grainfields on the Sabbath, and His disciples began to make their way along while picking the heads of grain&#8221; (Mk. 2:23). The Pharisees said, &#8220;Look, why are they [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/1030-2/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (V)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/05/wells-on-sabb-chapt-three-iv/">Tom Wells&#8217; book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (IV)</a></p>
<p>Mark 2:23-28 narrates another incident between Jesus and his disciples and the Pharisees. Jesus was &#8220;passing through the grainfields on the Sabbath, and His disciples began to make their way along while picking the heads of grain&#8221; (Mk. 2:23). The Pharisees said, &#8220;Look, why are they doing what is not lawful on the Sabbath?&#8221; (Mk. 2:24). This is the regulating question Jesus answers in this passage. According to the Pharisees&#8217; understanding, Christ&#8217;s disciples were violating the law of God by doing that which was, in their words, &#8220;not lawful on the Sabbath&#8221; (Mk. 2:24). Christ, as in Matt. 12:3-4, brings up the example of David and his companions entering the house of God and doing that &#8220;which [was] not lawful&#8230;&#8221; (Mk. 2:26). In Matt. 12:7, he pronounced his disciples innocent. In Matt. 12:12, Jesus said, &#8220;So then, it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath.&#8221; Though he does not pronounce his disciples innocent in Mark 2, he uses David and his companions as an example of someone in Scripture doing a similar thing his disciples were doing. It seems obvious that if his disciples were innocent in one text (Matt. 12), they are innocent in another (Mk. 2).[1] But how were they innocent? Did they, in fact, do that which was not lawful on the Sabbath? Obviously, Jesus did not think so in Matthew 12 or here. In Jesus&#8217; mind, they did that which was lawful. It was lawful because God desires compassion or mercy over sacrifice (cf. Matt. 12:7). In other words, Jesus makes a distinction between aspects of the Old Testament&#8217;s laws. Mercy overrules the positive aspects of the Sabbath under the old covenant.[2]</p>
<p>In Mk. 2:27, Jesus does as Paul and Moses do elsewhere. He draws a principle from creation that is germane to mankind (cf. Exod. 20:8-11 and 1 Tim. 2:12-13). Mark 2:27-28 says, &#8220;And He said to them, &#8216;The Sabbath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath. Therefore the Son of Man is also Lord of the Sabbath.&#8217;&#8221; <em>First</em>, note that both man and Sabbath are said to be made. The verb used by Mark in v. 27, evge,neto (&#8220;made&#8221;), comes from gi,nomai, which means &#8216;to become&#8217; or &#8216;to be.&#8217; It is the same verb used in Jn. 1:3, where it is translated &#8220;made.&#8221; There it refers to the creation of all things through the Word. What Jesus is saying in Mk. 2:27 is that, in the past, both man and the Sabbath came into being (i.e., &#8216;were made&#8217;) and that coming into being is described by one verb. This leads us to the conclusion that man and Sabbath were made at the same time. It would be quite clumsy to separate the making of man and the making of the Sabbath by hundreds and maybe even thousands of years by placing the Sabbath&#8217;s birth after Israel&#8217;s deliverance from Egypt in Exod. 16 or 20. Since we know that man was created (i.e., &#8216;came into being&#8217;) according to Gen. 1 and 2 in the Garden of Eden, Christ would have us to conclude that the Sabbath, as he refers to it here, was made at the same time and in the same place (cf. Exod. 20:11). This relates Christ&#8217;s teaching on the Sabbath with previous revelation.</p>
<p><em>Second</em>, both Sabbath and man are singular and articular in the Greek text (To. sa,bbaton&#8230; to.n a;nqrwpon [&#8220;the Sabbath&#8230;the man&#8221;]). Both words occur twice in this verse and both words are preceded by an article each time. This is one way to emphasize both Sabbath and man. Jesus did not say &#8220;The Sabbath was made for the Jews&#8221; or &#8220;the Sabbaths[3] were made for the Jews.&#8221; He said &#8220;the Sabbath&#8221; was made for &#8220;the man.&#8221; &#8220;The man&#8221; refers either to Adam as the head of the human race or mankind. Either way, it is clear that Christ goes back to the creation account and sees both man and the Sabbath being made. In context, Christ not only corrects the Pharisees for misunderstanding the Sabbath (Mk. 2:23-24), he, in effect, rebukes their narrow-minded and unbiblical approach to this issue. Jesus teaches us that the Sabbath is not unique to the Jews. God caused it to come into being as he caused Adam and all mankind to come into being for his glory and their good. The Sabbath is as old as man, according to Christ, not merely as old as the Jews. Again, this relates Christ&#8217;s teaching with previous revelation.</p>
<p><em>Third</em>, the Sabbath is said to have been &#8220;made for man, and not man for the Sabbath.&#8221; Two observations are worthy to consider. <em>First</em>, &#8220;[t]he Sabbath was made <em>for</em> man.&#8221; It was not made for God. God does not need a Sabbath. We do. It was made by God for our good. <em>Second</em>, man was not made &#8220;for the Sabbath.&#8221; Man existed first. His needs existed before the Sabbath did. The Sabbath came into being to serve man&#8217;s needs to be like God and to enjoy him. We don&#8217;t serve the Sabbath, it serves us so we can serve God better. Again, this relates Christ&#8217;s teaching with previous revelation.</p>
<p><em>Fourth</em>, Christ puts his stamp of Messianic lordship on the Sabbath that was made at creation. &#8220;Therefore the Son of Man is also Lord of the Sabbath&#8221; (Mk. 2:28). This provides us with the expectation that the Sabbath will abide under his lordship and will take on characteristics appropriate to this lordship under the new covenant (cf. Rev. 1:10). John Murray comments:</p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p>What the Lord is affirming is that the Sabbath has its place within the sphere of his messianic lordship and that he exercises lordship over the Sabbath because the Sabbath was made for man. Since he is Lord of the Sabbath it is his to guard it against those distortions and perversions with which Pharisaism had surrounded it and by which its truly beneficent purpose has been defeated. But he is also its Lord to guard and vindicate its permanent place within that messianic lordship which he exercises over all things&#8211;he is Lord of the Sabbath, too. And he is Lord of it, not for the purpose of depriving men of that inestimable benefit which the Sabbath bestows, but for the purpose of bringing to the fullest realization on behalf of men that beneficent design for which the Sabbath was instituted. If the Sabbath was made for man, and if Jesus is the Son of man to save man, surely the lordship which he exercises to that end is not to deprive man of that which was made for his good, but to seal to man that which the Sabbath institution involves. Jesus is Lord of the Sabbath&#8211;we dare not tamper with his authority and we dare not misconstrue the intent of his words.[4]</p>
<p>It is clear from the text in Daniel, where the phrase &#8220;Son of Man&#8221; comes from, that it refers to Christ in the posture of enthronement, immediately following his ascension into glory and is a title appropriate for him during the days in which he is given a kingdom and the nations become his.</p>
<p>I was watching in the night visions, And behold, <em>One </em>like the Son of Man, Coming with the clouds of heaven! He came to the Ancient of Days, And they brought Him near before Him. Then to Him was given dominion and glory and a kingdom, That all peoples, nations, and languages should serve Him. His dominion <em>is </em>an everlasting dominion, Which shall not pass away, And His kingdom <em>the one </em>Which shall not be destroyed. (Dan. 7:13-14)</p>
<p>In other words, Christ administrates the Sabbath as the Son of Man during the whole interadvental period&#8211;the days of the new covenant. This relates Chris&#8217;s teaching on the Sabbath with both previous and future revelation. Christ&#8217;s lordship over the Sabbath also implies Christ&#8217;s deity. The Sabbath is God&#8217;s (Isa. 56:4; 58:13). Since Christ is Lord of the Sabbath as Son of Man and since this title is his during the inter-advental days of the new covenant, then we should not be shocked if the Sabbath bears unique characteristics of his lordship under the new covenant. Patrick Fairbairn says:</p>
<p>He is Lord of the Sabbath, and, as such, has a right to order everything concerning it, so as to make it, in the fullest sense, a day of blessing for man&#8211;a right, therefore, if He should see fit, to transfer its observance from the last day of the week to the first, that it might be associated with the consummation of His redemptive work, and to make it, in accordance with the impulsive life and energy thereby brought in, more than in the past, a day of active and hallowed employment for the good of men.[5]</p>
<p>Jesus (Matt. 19:4-5 [and Mk. 2:27-28]), Paul (1 Tim. 2:12-13), and Moses (Exod. 20:11) argue in similar fashion. Each of them goes back to the creation account for the basis of ethics in terms of marriage, divorce, male/female roles in the church, and Sabbath. They all apply the same reasoning, though to different issues. If the basis for their argument is creation, and if creation transcends covenants and cultures, how can we not conclude that what they are arguing for applies to all men at all times, though dependant upon revelation from God in terms of specific application at any given point in redemptive history? In other words, though the application may vary due to various redemptive-historical situations (i.e., divorce permitted due to the entrance of sin, 7<sup>th</sup> day Sabbath to 1<sup>st</sup> day Sabbath/Lord&#8217;s Day, etc.), the principle itself stands. And the reason why it stands is due to the order and ethical implications of creation drawn out by the Bible itself.</p>
<p>If the principle applies to marriage, divorce, and male/female roles in the church, then doesn&#8217;t it still apply to the Sabbath as well? If it does not apply to the Sabbath, upon what grounds is the principle dismissed? If one says, &#8220;The Sabbath was an ordinance for the Jews only. It was theirs&#8217; as God&#8217;s old covenant people to apply to their culture alone in the Promised Land,&#8221; then couldn&#8217;t someone argue the same for male/female roles in the church? They could say, &#8220;Paul was dealing with a culture-relative issue. His reasoning applied to that culture alone. Women, therefore, may have authority over men in the church and may teach and preach to them. Women may be pastors.&#8221; Some in our day argue this way. But when the Bible bases ethics upon creation, the principle applies to all cultures at all times. And until this age gives way to the fullness of the age to come, creation-based ethics (i.e., creation ordinances) are moral laws for all men.</p>
<hr size="1">[1] If Matthew utilized Mark, it could be that he filled out the incident for his own purposes. If Mark used Matthew, it could be that he trimmed the incident because he knew Matthew had dealt with it in detail. If the Gospel writers wrote independent of each other based on eye-witness accounts, each one wrote what they did for authorial purposes. Either way, both texts were inspired by God and can and ought to be used to interpret each other.</p>
<p>[2] See the <em>Second London Baptist Confession</em>, 22:7, where it acknowledges that the Sabbath is &#8220;a positive moral, and perpetual commandment&#8230;&#8221; I take this to mean that the Sabbath can and does take upon itself temporary aspects (i.e., positive laws) during the history of redemption, which can and do change, yet its essence is moral or perpetual. This means that its positive aspects may give way to the moral or perpetual aspects of God&#8217;s law.</p>
<p>[3] The Jews under the old covenant had both a weekly Sabbath and other non-weekly Sabbaths.</p>
<p>[4] John Murray, <em>Collected Writings of John Murray, </em>Vol. I<em> </em>(Edinburgh: The Banner of Truth Trust, 1976), 208.</p>
<p>[5] Fairbairn, <em>Revelation of Law</em>, 238.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/1030-2/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (V)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/1030-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brief survey of the history of hermeneutics – 12. Post-Reformation Reformed Orthodoxy (I)</title>
		<link>/surv-hist-herms-12-post-ref-ref-orth-i/</link>
					<comments>/surv-hist-herms-12-post-ref-ref-orth-i/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2011 12:47:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[history of hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-Reformation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed orthodoxy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1026</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The theological methodology of the post-Reformation Reformed orthodox was, in the first place, exegetical.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/surv-hist-herms-12-post-ref-ref-orth-i/">Brief survey of the history of hermeneutics – 12. Post-Reformation Reformed Orthodoxy (I)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/05/surv-of-hist-herm-ren-ref/">Brief survey of the history of hermeneutics &#8211; 11. Renaissance and Reformation</a></strong></p>
<p><strong>The theological methodology of the post-Reformation Reformed orthodox: </strong>The theological methodology of the post-Reformation Reformed orthodox was, in the first place, exegetical. In order to get a firmer grip on their methodology, we will examine it from the vantage point of <em>what it is not </em>&#8211; 1. a hyper-syllogistic method; 2. an Aristotelian, rationalistic method; and 3. a universal method &#8211; and <em>what it is </em>&#8211; 4. a pre-critical method; 5. an exegetically-based method; 6. a redemptive-historically sensitive method; and 7. a multi-sourced method. The last four mentioned methodological characteristics are especially visible in the writings of John Owen, one of the premiere post-Reformation Reformed scholastics.[1]<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Not a Hyper-Syllogistic Method: </strong>Their method was not reduced to syllogistic argumentation <em>ad nauseam</em>. In fact, Muller claims that &#8220;[f]ew of the orthodox or scholastic Protestants lapsed into constant or exclusive recourse to syllogism as a method of exposition.&#8221;[2] Syllogistic argumentation was utilized, but mostly in polemic contexts and not as an exegetical tool. Logic&#8211;the science of necessary inference&#8211;was utilized by the Reformed orthodox in the drawing out of good and necessary conclusions from the text of Scripture,[3] but it was a servant and not lord of the interpreter. Muller says that &#8220;the drawing of logical conclusions appears as one of the final hermeneutical steps in the [Reformed orthodox exegetical] method&#8230;&#8221;[4]<strong></strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;<strong>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Not an Aristotelian, Rationalistic Method: </strong>The Protestant scholasticism of the post-Reformation era must be distinguished from rationalism. The Reformed orthodox did not place human reason above, or even equal to, divine revelation.[5] The place and function of reason was subordinate to the authority of Scripture. Reason was an instrument not an axiomatic principle.[6] The Protestant scholastics utilized a modified (or Christian) Aristotelianism &#8220;that had its beginnings in the thirteenth century.&#8221;[7] Muller explains:<strong></strong></p>
<p>It is important to recognize what this use entailed and what it did not. The Christian Aristotelianism of the Protestant orthodox drew on rules of logic and devices such as the fourfold causality in order to explain and develop their doctrinal formulae&#8212;and only seldom, if ever, to import a full-scale rational metaphysics or physics into their theology. Contrary to what is sometimes claimed, the fourfold causality (i.e., first, formal, material, and final causes) does not imply a particular metaphysic. Specifically, it is not by nature &#8220;determinis&shy;tic.&#8221; One can use the model to delineate the soteriological patterns of the eternal decree of God and its execution in time; one can also use the model to describe the sources and effects of human sinfulness and human moral conduct; or one can use the model to explain how a car&shy;penter makes a table. The large-scale result of Christian Aristotelianism was not, in other words, a fundamentally Aristotelian Christianity: Aristotle would have disowned this hybrid philosophy with its infinite God who created the world out of nothing! There was, certainly, less imposition of rational metaphysics on theology in the seventeenth-century orthodox affirmations of divine eternity, omniscience, and immutability than there is in the twentieth-century claims of a changing God whose very being is in flux and who lacks foreknowledge of future contingency![8]</p>
<p>Van Asselt says, &#8220;[the] facile equation of Scholasticism and Aristotelianism is no longer tenable.&#8221;[9]</p>
<p><strong>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Not a Universal Method: </strong>As well, simply because an author utilized the scholastic method in some of his writings did not mean he used it in all of them. For instance, Muller offers Beza as an example.[10] Elsewhere, Muller says, &#8220;In the cases of Perkins, Ames, Voetius, and Baxter, works of piety and works of scholastic theology emanated from the same pens.&#8221;[11] Muller goes on to say:<strong></strong></p>
<p>&#8230;there is no clear division between Protestant scholasticism and federal theology. Theologians who wrote works of piety that followed a &#8220;positive&#8221; or &#8220;catechetical&#8221; method also wrote more technical and academic works using the scholastic method &#8211; and many of the scholastic, as well as &#8220;positive&#8221; works were covenantal in their theology.[12]</p>
<p>This observation applies to Johannes Cocceius and John Owen. Owen utilized the scholastic method in some treaties and a more practical, pastoral approach in others. Both Cocceius and Owen utilized the federal model as well as the <em>loci</em> model. Also, within the body of Owen&#8217;s <em>Biblical Theology</em>, he utilizes the scholastic method but also ridicules it.[13] This obviously shows that Owen could use a method he fully realized was abused by others and that the scholastic method was just that&#8211;a method and not a theology.</p>
<p>&nbsp;<strong>4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>A Pre-Critical Method: </strong>The Reformed orthodox obviously predate the Enlightenment and the critical assault on the Holy Scriptures. The Enlightenment gave birth to, among other things, a rationalistic approach to the interpretation of Scripture. This can be seen, for instance, in the early developments of biblical theology.[14] Typical Enlightenment rationalism and anti-supernaturalism is evidenced in the following statements made by Benjamin Jowett, a Greek professor at Oxford in the mid-nineteenth century. David C. Steinmetz quotes Jowett and comments:<strong></strong></p>
<p>Jowett argued that &#8220;Scripture has one meaning&#8211;the meaning which it had in the mind of the Prophet or Evangelist who first uttered or wrote, to the hearers or readers who first received it.&#8221;[15] Scripture should be interpreted like any other book and the later accretions and venerated traditions surrounding its interpretation should, for the most part, either be brushed aside or severely discounted. &#8220;The true use of interpretation is to get rid of interpretation, and leave us alone in company with the author.&#8221;[16]</p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p>Jowett obviously reduces meaning to the intent of the human author alone. In critical hermeneutical theory, there was no room whatsoever for the medieval concept of &#8220;double literal sense&#8221;[17] or for the Reformation and post-Reformation concepts of <em>sensus literalis</em> (literal sense), <em>analogia Scripturae </em>(analogy of Scripture), <em>analogia fidei </em>(analogy of faith), and <em>scopus Scripturae </em>(scope of Scripture).[18] In post-modern thought, man, the reader, is king of interpretation; in the modern/Enlightenment theory man, the author, was. In the Middle Ages, however, and in the Reformation and post-Reformation eras, though through differing hermeneutical principles, the meaning of Scripture was not determined by the human author&#8217;s intent alone or the reader. Ultimately, the meaning of Scripture was determined by God, the author of Scripture.[19]</p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>5.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>An Exegetically-Based Method<strong>[20]</strong>: </strong>Though the Reformed orthodox were confessionally one in a historical sense (i.e., the <em>Belgic Confession</em>, the <em>Heidelberg Catechism</em>, the <em>Canons of Dordt</em>, and in Britain in the Westminster Assembly&#8217;s <em>Confession of Faith and Larger and Shorter Catechisms</em>, <em>Savoy Declaration</em>, <em>Second London Confession of Faith</em>), this did not mean they viewed the exegetical task as complete and, therefore, unnecessary, nor that there was no room for disagreement over the exegesis of individual texts. Muller comments:<strong></strong></p>
<p>the biblicism of the seventeenth-century orthodox must not be read as an era of dogmatizing exegesis devoid of careful textual analysis and devoid of any variety in interpretation among those of an orthodox confessional persuasion. Instead, the age ought to be viewed as the great age of Protestant linguistic study and Judaica, of the textual analysis that led to such monumental productions as the London Polyglot Bible. &#8230;the Protestant orthodoxy must be recognized as producing highly varied and diverse exegetical works and commentaries, ranging from text-critical essays, to textual annotations, theological annotations, linguistic commentaries based on the study of cognate languages and Judaica, doctrinal and homiletical commentaries, and, indeed, all manner of permutations and combinations of these several types of effort.[21]</p>
<p>Biblical exegesis, in fact, experienced a revival of sorts within the Reformed orthodox of the seventeenth century. Muller says:</p>
<p>Contrary to much of the &#8220;received wisdom&#8221; concerning the seventeenth century, the era of orthodoxy was a time of great exegetical, textual, and linguistic development in Protestantism&#8211;and, indeed, it was the orthodox exegetes who were responsible for the major monuments to biblical scholarship.[22]</p>
<p>Carl R. Trueman says, &#8220;&#8230;the seventeenth century witnessed a remarkable flourishing of linguistic and exegetical studies, driven by both the positive and the polemical exigencies of Protestantism&#8217;s commitment to scripture, in the original languages, as being the very Word &#8211; and words &#8211; of God.&#8221;[23] Trueman continues elsewhere:</p>
<p>A high view of the authority and integrity of the biblical text as God&#8217;s word written was [a] major factor in fuelling the development of careful attention both to the biblical languages and other cognate tongues, and to issues of textual history and criticism. The idea that the seventeenth-century Reformed were interested neither in careful exegesis nor in the literary and linguistic contexts of the Bible is simply untrue. Indeed, the linguistic and exegetical work of this century was far more elaborate than that which had marked the earlier Reformation. &#8230;the exegesis of the Reformed Orthodox is far from the dogmatically-driven Procusteanism[24] [<em>sic</em>] of popular mythology.[25]</p>
<p>&nbsp;<strong>6.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>A Redemptive-Historically Sensitive Method: </strong>Not only were the Reformed orthodox exegetically driven, their hermeneutic was a whole-Bible hermeneutic, evidenced in such concepts as their highly nuanced view of <em>sensus literalis</em> (literal sense), <em>analogia Scripturae </em>(analogy of Scripture), <em>analogia fidei </em>(analogy of faith), and <em>scopus Scripturae </em>(scope of Scripture).[26] It is of vital importance to understand the nuances involved with these concepts in order to properly understand the Reformed orthodox. We will explore these concepts in our next post.</p>
<hr size="1">[1] We will discuss Owen below.</p>
<p>[2] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; I:369.</p>
<p>[3] Cf. Muller, <em>PRRD</em>, II:497-500 for a discussion of the use of logic in interpretation.</p>
<p>[4] Muller, <em>PRRD</em>, II:501.</p>
<p>[5] Cf. <em>WCF</em> 1:10 for confessional embodiment to this conviction.</p>
<p>[6] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; I:374.</p>
<p>[7] Muller, &#8220;Sources of Reformed Orthodoxy,&#8221; 55. Cf. van Asselt, &#8220;The Fundamental Meaning of Theology,&#8221; 322, where he says that the Reformed theology of the late sixteenth century (<em>i.e</em>., Franciscus Junius) critically received the Christian tradition.</p>
<p>[8] Muller, &#8220;Sources of Reformed Orthodoxy,&#8221; 55.</p>
<p>[9] van Asselt, &#8220;The Fundamental Meaning of Theology,&#8221; 329, n. 42.</p>
<p>[10] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; I:370.</p>
<p>[11] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; II:145.</p>
<p>[12] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; II:146.</p>
<p>[13] Cf. Rehnman<em>, Divine Discourse</em>, Chapter 4, &#8220;Faith and Reason,&#8221; especially the sections &#8220;The Abuse of Reason in Theology&#8221; and &#8220;A Contextual Line of Explanation,&#8221; 119-28 and the &#8220;Conclusion&#8221; to my dissertation.</p>
<p>[14] See below.</p>
<p>[15] Benjamin Jowett, &#8220;On the Interpretation of Scripture,&#8221; <em>Essays and Reviews</em>, 7<sup>th</sup> ed. (London: Longman, Green, Longman and Roberts, 1861), 378, quoted in David C. Steinmetz, &#8220;The Superiority of Pre-Critical Exegesis,&#8221; <em>Theology Today</em> (April 1980): 27.</p>
<p>[16] Steinmetz is quoting Jowett, &#8220;On the Interpretation of Scripture,&#8221; 384. Cf. Steinmetz, &#8220;The Superiority of Pre-Critical Exegesis,&#8221; 27.</p>
<p>[17] Steinmetz, &#8220;The Superiority of Pre-Critical Exegesis,&#8221; 31.</p>
<p>[18] We will discuss these below.</p>
<p>[19] This, of course, does not imply that pre-critical exegesis always arrived at God&#8217;s meaning of the text. Cf. Packer, <em>Quest for Godliness</em>, 98, for a brief discussion of the Puritans as pre-modern exegetes.</p>
<p>[20] Cf. Muller, &#8220;Sources of Reformed Orthodoxy,&#8221; 46-48; Muller, <em>PRRD</em>, II:482ff; Packer, <em>Quest for Godliness</em>, 98; and Thomas D. Lea, &#8220;The Hermeneutics of the Puritans,&#8221; <em>JETS</em> 39/2 (June 1996): 273.</p>
<p>[21] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; II:132-33.</p>
<p>[22] Muller, &#8220;Sources of Reformed Orthodoxy,&#8221; 46.</p>
<p>[23] Trueman, <em>John Owen</em>, 8-9.</p>
<p>[24] Tending to produce conformity by violent or arbitrary means.</p>
<p>[25] Trueman, <em>John Owen</em>, 37; Cf. Muller, <em>PRRD</em>, II:482ff. for a fascinating discussion of the practice of exegesis among the Reformed orthodox.</p>
<p>[26] Packer lists six governing principles of interpretation for the English Puritans: 1. Interpret Scripture <em>literally</em> <em>and</em> <em>grammatically</em>. 2. Interpret Scripture <em>consistently</em> <em>and</em> <em>harmonistically</em>. 3. Interpret Scripture <em>doctrinally</em> <em>and</em> <em>theocentrically</em>. 4. Interpret Scripture <em>christologically</em> <em>and</em> <em>evangelically</em>. 5. Interpret Scripture <em>experimentally and practically.</em> 6. Interpret Scripture <em>with a faithful and realistic application</em>. Cf. Packer, <em>Quest for Godliness</em>, 101-5. Cf. Barry Howson, &#8220;The Puritan Hermeneutics of John Owen: A Recommendation,&#8221; <em>WTJ</em> 63 (2001): 354-57.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/surv-hist-herms-12-post-ref-ref-orth-i/">Brief survey of the history of hermeneutics – 12. Post-Reformation Reformed Orthodoxy (I)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/surv-hist-herms-12-post-ref-ref-orth-i/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
