<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Historical Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/historical-theology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 16:24:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Historical Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 2 of 2]: Analysis and Conclusion</title>
		<link>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/</link>
					<comments>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 15:51:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15601</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ben CarlsonBen has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 2 of 2]: Analysis and Conclusion</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_0 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_0">
								<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_0  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_0  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><em>This is part 2 of a 2 part series on Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology. You can read part 1 <a href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/">here</a></em>.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>II.) Analysis of Calvin’s Teaching on Natural Theology</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>1.) Calvin clearly distinguishes between natural revelation and natural theology.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

For Calvin, there is a substantial difference between the reality of the knowledge of God in the universe and the use of the knowledge of God by sinful man. The reality that God clearly and continually reveals Himself to man as Creator within him and around him is called natural or general revelation. The interpretation and use of that knowledge by men, who in this fallen world are enslaved in sin, is called natural theology. This is their creaturely attempt to interpret and understand general revelation (the knowledge of God in creation) without the help or aid of special revelation (the knowledge of God in Scripture). It is important to highlight the differences if we would correctly understand Calvin’s thought.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>2.) Calvin teaches that since natural revelation is so distorted and corrupted by fallen man, natural theology is a futile endeavor that leads one to a throng of feigned gods but never to the true God.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

God’s revelation of Himself in creation is meant to be a teacher and guide to men to point out the right way (1:5:15). Ideally, all image bearers of God would rightly respond to this knowledge. Yet Calvin is clear that because of sin, man lacks the ability to come to a knowledge of God worthy of the name. With only natural reasoning and common understanding as his guide, sinful man poisons and corrupts natural revelation to such an extent that by itself it only produces the worst possible fruits in him. According to Calvin, no matter if one is chieftain of the whole tribe of philosophers or the worst of the vulgar folk, the best that natural theology can do is lead one to the worship of an unknown god. Therefore, the true knowledge of God cannot be grasped by fallen man on the basis of natural revelation. There must be another way.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>3.) Calvin teaches that special revelation, or the Scriptures, is necessary not only to properly understand the knowledge of God in salvation but also to properly understand the knowledge of God in creation.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

The Bible not only teaches us about God the Redeemer. It also teaches us about God the Creator. In addition to the Book of Nature, the Scriptures are another and better help “which direct us aright to the very Creator of the Universe” and “clearly shows us the true God” (1:6:1). In fact, without their aid and assistance, “the human mind because of its feebleness can in no way attain to God” (1:6:4). In order to do this, we need the spectacles of special revelation (1:6:1). As Calvin says, “We must come, I say, to the Word, where God is truly and vividly described to us from his works, while these very works are appraised not by our depraved judgment but by the rule of eternal truth. If we turn aside from the Word, as I have just now said, though we may strive with strenuous haste, yet, since we have got off the track, we shall never reach the goal. For we should so reason that the splendor of the divine countenance, which even the apostle calls ‘unapproachable’ [I Tim. 6:16], is for us like an inexplicable labyrinth unless we are conducted into it by the thread of the Word; so that it is better to limp along this path than to dash with all speed outside it” (1:6:3). And, “Now, in order that true religion may shine upon us, we ought to hold that it must take its beginning from heavenly doctrine and that no one can get even the slightest taste of right and sound doctrine unless he be a pupil of Scripture” (1:6:2).

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>4.) Calvin teaches that using evidences apart from Scripture as proofs for God’s existence is unnecessary.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

Since men do not need to be taught about God in the classroom but are masters of divinity from their mothers’ wombs (1:3:3), and since men suppress any knowledge of God they do possess by nature, the attempt to prove the existence of God from natural theology is unnecessary.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

We see that no long or toilsome proof is needed to elicit evidences that serve to illuminate and affirm the divine majesty; since from the few we have sampled at random, whithersoever you turn, it is clear that they are so very manifest and obvious that they can easily be observed with the eyes and pointed out with the finger. (1:5:9)

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

What is necessary, however, is faith.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

It is therefore in vain that so many burning lamps shine for us in the workmanship of the universe to show forth the glory of its Author. Although they bathe us wholly in their radiance, yet they can of themselves in no way lead us into the right path. Surely they strike some sparks, but before their fuller light shines forth these are smothered. For this reason, the apostle, in that very passage where he calls the worlds the images of things invisible, adds that through faith we understand that they have been fashioned by God’s word [Heb. 11:3]. He means by this that the invisible divinity is made manifest in such spectacles, but that we have not the eyes to see this unless they be illumined by the inner revelation of God through faith. (1:5:14)

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>III.) Conclusion from Calvin’s Teaching on Natural Theology</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

After surveying the evidence, Calvin is highly critical of any teaching that ascribes to sinful man sound reasoning concerning the knowledge of God. He cannot be any plainer in his assessment: “Human reason, therefore, neither approaches, nor strives toward, nor even takes a straight aim at, this truth: to understand who the true God is or what sort of God he wishes to be toward us” (2:2:18). Yet the natural theology propounded by the medieval scholastics teaches that human reason can do just that. How biblical this teaching is should be addressed exegetically from the relevant passages of Scripture. But from a historical standpoint, it seems clear from Calvin’s own critique of natural theology that it was not consistent with the views of Reformed theology, especially with the teaching on man’s fallen and depraved state.

<!-- /wp:paragraph --></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->			
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->		
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 2 of 2]: Analysis and Conclusion</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 1 of 2]: Summary</title>
		<link>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/</link>
					<comments>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 20:11:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15583</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ben Carlson Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 1 of 2]: Summary</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_1 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_1">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_1  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_1  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p><em>This is part 1 of a 2 part series on Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology. You can read part 2 <a href="http://calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/">here</a></em>.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>What was Calvin’s view of natural theology? That is an important question to ask today, especially in light of the discussions and debates taking place concerning the legitimacy of natural theology within Reformed epistemology and apologetics.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>One of the clearest places in the <em>Institutes</em> where Calvin’s evaluation of natural theology can be found is in Book 1, Chapter 5, Section 12. There he states, “Yet hence it appears that if men were taught only by nature, they would hold to nothing certain or solid or clear-cut, but would be so tied to confused principles as to worship an unknown god [cf. Acts 17:23].”</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>John T. McNeill, the editor of Ford Lewis Battles’ translation of the <em>Institutes</em>, makes this noteworthy remark in a footnote after Calvin’s words: “Natural theology (human reasoning about God, under the conditions of sin, unaided by special revelation) has been the subject of this chapter through section 12. All scholars agree that the above words present Calvin’s verdict upon it, held consistently in all his writings.”</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>In this brief essay, I will attempt to lay out Calvin’ critique of natural theology by first summarizing his teaching on the subject from the first six chapters of Book 1, second by analyzing his teaching, and third by offering a concluding thought. As “the theologian” of the Reformation, Calvin gives us a pivotal perspective concerning natural theology that aligns with his teachings on the doctrines of God, man, sin, Scripture, and grace. Therefore, his evaluation needs to be carefully read and understood.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>I.) Summary of Calvin’s Teaching on Natural Theology</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>1.) Calvin states that natural revelation is unmistakably and unfailingly clear to man.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Calvin argues that natural revelation, or the knowledge of God as Creator, Governor, and Judge of the world, is both inscribed on man’s heart and proclaimed throughout the universe.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>First, Calvin says that all men have an awareness of divinity, seed of religion, sense of deity, sort of divinity, and signs of immorality implanted and inscribed by God in their souls. This is the innate, inward, undeniable, and indelible knowledge of God as Creator. All men undoubtedly know Him as such and have no excuse to claim ignorance.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>There is within the human mind, and indeed by natural instinct, an awareness of divinity. This we take to be beyond controversy. To prevent anyone from taking refuge in the pretense of ignorance, God himself has implanted in all men a certain understanding of his divine majesty. (1:3:1)</p>
<p>And they who in other aspects of life seem least to differ from brutes still continue to retain some seed of religion. (1:3:1)</p>
<p>Therefore, since from the beginning of the world there has been no region, no city, in short, no household that could do without religion, there lies in this a tacit confession of a sense of deity inscribed in the hearts of all. (1:3:1)</p>
<p>Men of sound judgment will always be sure that a sense of divinity which can never be effaced is engraved upon men’s minds. (1:3:2)</p>
<p>.  . . that there is some God, is naturally inborn in all, and is fixed deep within, as it were in the very marrow. (1:3:3)</p>
<p>From this we conclude that it is not a doctrine that must first be learned in school, but one which each of us is master from his mother’s womb and which nature itself permits no one to forget, although many strive with every nerve to this end. (1:3:3)</p>
<p>As experience shows, God has sown a seed of religion in all men. (1:4:1)</p>
<p>Yet that seed remains which can in no wise be uprooted: that there is some sort of divinity. (1:4:4)</p>
<p>From this, my present contention is brought out with greater certainty, that a sense of divinity is by nature engraven on human hearts. (1:4:4)</p>
<p>These are unfailing signs of divinity in man. (1:5:5)</p>
<p>What ought we to say here except that the signs of immortality which have been implanted in man cannot be effaced? (1:5:5)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Second, Calvin states that all men are constantly confronted with the knowledge of God as Creator from the dazzling theater of His glory (1:5:8) that He has placed them in as spectators (1:6:2).</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>The final goal of the blessed life, moreover, rests in the knowledge of God [cf. John 17:3]. Lest anyone, then, be excluded from access to happiness, he not only sowed in men’s minds that seed of religion of which we have spoken but revealed himself and daily discloses himself in the whole workmanship of the universe. As a consequence, men cannot open their eyes without being compelled to see him. . . . But upon his individual works he has engraved unmistakable marks of his glory, so clear and so prominent that even unlettered and stupid folk cannot plead the excuse of ignorance. (1:5:1)</p>
<p>Yet, in the first place, wherever you cast your eyes, there is no spot in the universe wherein you cannot discern at least some sparks of his glory. (1:5:1)</p>
<p>There are innumerable evidences both in heaven and on earth that declare his wonderful wisdom; . . . Even the common folk and the most untutored, who have been taught only by the aid of the eyes, cannot be unaware of the excellence of divine art, for it reveals itself in this innumerable and yet distinct and well-ordered variety of the heavenly host. It is, accordingly, clear that there is no one to whom the Lord does not abundantly show his wisdom. (1:5:2)</p>
<p>Therefore, however fitting it may be for man seriously to turn his eyes to contemplate God’s works, since he has been placed in this most glorious theater to be a spectator of them, . . . (1:6:2)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>2.) Calvin states that natural revelation should teach man to fear, love, trust, and hope in God.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Calvin is clear that the knowledge of God in creation has a purpose, and that purpose is to greatly benefit man.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>For this sense of the powers of God is for us a fit teacher of piety, from which religion is born. I call “piety” that reverence joined with love of God which the knowledge of his benefits induces. (1:2:1)</p>
<p>Rather, our knowledge should serve first to teach us fear and reverence; secondly, with it as our guide and teacher, we should learn to seek every good from him, and, having received it, to credit it to his account. . . . Again, you cannot behold him clearly unless you acknowledge him to be the fountainhead and source of every good. From this too would arise the desire to cleave to him and trust in him . . . (1:2:2)</p>
<p>Knowledge of this sort, then, ought not only to arouse us to the worship of God but also to awaken and encourage us to the hope of the future life. (1:5:10)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>3.) Calvin states that natural revelation is unprofitable for sinful man.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Although the knowledge of God as Creator in creation should greatly benefit man, Calvin states that in a fallen world it does no such thing because of man’s sinfulness and blindness to the truth. Instead, with it man falls into superstitions, deserts God, or lives hypocritically. No matter the person, fallen man’s interpretation and response to natural revelation “corrupt by vanity the pure truth of God” (1:5:11) and “seduce[] his mind from rightly seeking him” (1:2:2).</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>But although the Lord represents both himself and his everlasting Kingdom in the mirror of his works with very great clarity, such is our stupidity that we grow increasingly dull toward so manifest testimonies, and they flow away without profiting us. (1:5:11)</p>
<p>Besides while some may evaporate in their own superstitions and others deliberately and wickedly desert God, yet all degenerate from the true knowledge of him. And so it happens that no real piety remains in the world. (1:4:1)</p>
<p>They see such exquisite workmanship in their individual members, from mouth and eyes even to their very toenails. Here also they substitute nature for God. (1:5:4)</p>
<p>Finally, they entangle themselves in such a huge mass of errors that blind wickedness stifles and finally extinguishes those sparks which once flashed forth to show them God’s glory. Yet that seed remains which can in no wise be uprooted: that there is some sort of divinity; but this seed is so corrupted that by itself it produces only the worst fruits. (1:5:4)</p>
<p>Sometimes we are driven by leading and direction of these things to contemplate God; this of necessity happens to all men. Yet after we rashly grasp a conception of some sort of divinity, straightway we fall back into the ravings or evil imaginings of our flesh, and corrupt by our vanity the pure truth of God. In one respect we are indeed unalike, because each one of us privately forges his own particular error; yet we are very much alike in that, one and all, we forsake the one true God for prodigious trifles. Not only the common folk and dull-witted men, but also the most excellent and those otherwise endowed with keen discernment, are infected with this disease. In this regard how volubly has the whole tribe of philosophers shown their stupidity and silliness! (1:5:11)</p>
<p>It is therefore in vain that so many burning lamps shine for us in the workmanship of the universe to show forth the glory of its Author. Although they bathe us wholly in their radiance, yet they can of themselves in no way lead us into the right path. Surely they strike some speaks, but before their fuller light shines forth these are smothered. (1:5:14)</p>
<p>Therefore, although the Lord does not want for testimony while he sweetly attracts men to the knowledge of himself with many and varied kindnesses, they do not cease on this account to follow their own ways, that is, their fatal errors. (1:5:14)</p>
<p>But, however that may be, yet the fact that men soon corrupt the seed of the knowledge of God, sown in their minds out of the wonderful workmanship of nature (thus preventing it from coming to a good and perfect fruit), must be imputed to their own failing; (1:5:15)</p>
<p>For at the same time as we have enjoyed a slight taste of the divine from contemplation of the universe, having neglected the true God, we raise up in his stead dreams and specters of our own brains, and attribute to anything else than the true source the praise of righteousness, wisdom, goodness, and power. Moreover, we so obscure or overturn his daily acts by wickedly judging them that we snatch away from them their glory and from their Author his due praise. (1:5:15)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>4.) Calvin states that natural theology is useless for sinful man.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Calvin argues that sinful man can never attain the true and pure knowledge of God with his depraved understanding. In other words, natural theology, or the ability of man to truly know and positively respond to God’s natural revelation, in a fallen world leads only to confused principles and a diversity of opinions about God, none of which are correct.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>But among the philosophers who have tried with reason and learning to penetrate into heaven, how shameful is the diversity! (1:5:12)</p>
<p>. . . but no mortal ever contrived anything that did not basely corrupt religion. (1:5:12)</p>
<p>But since all confess that there is nothing concerning which the learned and the unlearned at the same time disagree so much, hence one may conclude that the minds of men which thus wander in their search after God are more than stupid and blind in the heavenly mysteries. (1:5:12)</p>
<p>Yet hence it appears that if men were taught only by nature, they would hold to nothing certain or solid or clear-cut, but would be so tied to confused principles as to worship an unknown god [cf. Acts 17:23]. (1:5:12)</p>
<p>In short, even if not all suffered under crass vice, or fell into open idolatries, yet there was no pure and approved religion, found upon common understanding alone. For even though few persons did not share in the madness of the common herd, there remains the firm teaching of Paul that the wisdom of God is not understood by the princes of this world [I Cor. 2:8]. But if even the most illustrious wander in darkness, what can we say of the dregs? (1:5:13)</p>
<p>But although we lack the natural ability to mount up unto the pure and clear knowledge of God, all excuse is cut off because the fault of dullness is within us. (1:5:15)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>In the next post, I will present some analysis of Calvin&#8217;s teaching on Natural Theology.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 1 of 2]: Summary</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Crux of the Free Offer of the Gospel</title>
		<link>/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/</link>
					<comments>/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 18:53:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Course offerings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Offer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Offer of the Gospel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hyper-Calvinism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[well-meant offer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7876</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The following is Dr. Sam Waldron&#8217;s introduction to his lectures for our upcoming module: Hyper-Calvinism &#38; the Free Offer of the Gospel In the historic documents which brought to its climax the confessional development sparked by the Reformation&#8212;the Westminster Confession (1644-46), the Savoy Declaration (1658), and the 1689 Baptist Confession&#8212;the free offer of the gospel [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/">The Crux of the Free Offer of the Gospel</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The following is Dr. Sam Waldron&#8217;s introduction to his lectures for our upcoming module:
</p>
<h2><a href="/hyper-calvinism/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>Hyper-Calvinism &amp; the Free Offer of the Gospel</strong></a></h2>
<p>In the historic documents which brought to its climax the confessional development sparked by the Reformation&#8212;the Westminster Confession (1644-46), the Savoy Declaration (1658), and the 1689 Baptist Confession&#8212;the free offer of the gospel is confessed in each in chapter 7 and in identical language.&nbsp; The Westminster Confession and its daughter and grand-daughter confessions each speak of &#8220;the covenant of grace, wherein he freely offereth unto sinners, life and salvation by Jesus Christ.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></p>
<p>It is both the conviction and assumption of these lectures that the crux of the doctrine of the free offer of the gospel is <em>God&#8217;s Indiscriminate Desire for the Salvation of Sinners</em>.&nbsp; To put this in other words, at the core of the free offer of the gospel is what is called the &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer of the gospel.&nbsp; Though it may be well to speak of the &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer of the gospel for the sake of doctrinal clarity, I am jealous to affirm here that this is both the natural and necessary implication of the &#8220;free&#8221; offer confessed by the climactic Reformation confessions.</p>
<p>My conviction is that the &#8220;free&#8221; offer in the confessional documents is and must be understood as a &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer.&nbsp; Though this affirmation may be defended at length (and will be by Dr. Daniel in his historical treatment in this course, it may be proper here for me to briefly mention the grounds upon which my conviction is based.&nbsp; I maintain that the &#8220;free&#8221; offer in the confessional documents is and must be understood as a &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer for a number of reasons.</p>
<ul>
<li>It is, I think, the logical and necessary implication of speaking of a free offer. In fact, it seems to me that this is the implication of both the word, offer, and the word, free.&nbsp; &#8220;Offer&#8221; contains in it the notion of a proposal presented to someone which the one presenting it desires for him to accept.&nbsp; An offer not presented with such intent or desire would be regarded as insincere.&nbsp; What man proposes marriage to a woman without a desire that she should accept his proposal?&nbsp; What woman would regard such a proposal as authentic or genuine if it was not accompanied by the desire of the man for it to be accepted.&nbsp; The word, free, however, emphasizes the notion of a desire that one should take the offer presented.&nbsp; An offer is presented with the desire that it should be taken by the one to whom it is presented.&nbsp; A &#8220;free&#8221; offer accentuates such desire and the &#8220;well-meant&#8221; character of the offer by providing an extra incentive for the proposal to be accepted.</li>
<li>That this is the meaning and implication of a &#8220;free offer&#8221; was generally recognized by the modern opponents of the free offer in the controversy over common grace in the Christian Reformed denomination in the controversy that came to its denominational culmination in 1924. The Protestant Reformed Churches denied the free offer because they properly understood that a free offer was a well-meant offer&#8212;an offer that contained common grace.&nbsp; So much is this the case that Herman Hanko referencing the first point of common grace adopted by the Christian Reformed Church at the synod of 1924 and writing in the official journal of the Protestant Reformed Churches can write:</li>
</ul>
<p>In the discussions which followed the adoption of this statement of doctrine, the reference to the free offer was often called, &#8220;het puntje van het eerste punt.&#8221;&nbsp; (The main point of the first point.)&nbsp; While it is our intention to deal more specifically with this question at a later date, the point we wish to make now is that a denial of the free offer of the gospel is a part of the doctrinal confession of the Protestant Reformed Churches from their very beginning.&nbsp; This denial of the free offer of the gospel by the Protestant Reformed Churches has set them apart from almost every ecclesiastical fellowship.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></p>
<ul>
<li>That by the confessional free offer was intended a well-meant offer is the necessary conclusion to be reached from the historical backdrop of the climactic Reformed confessions. The high points of this backdrop (Calvin and the Canons of Dort) teach a free and well-meant offer.&nbsp; This is not the place for a detailed presentation of the evidence for this. Dr. Daniel will be providing such a presentation.&nbsp; It may be good, however, to illustrate the truth of this assertion.&nbsp; Perhaps the classic affirmation of the Free Offer by Calvin comes in a letter to Melancthon.&nbsp; There he says:</li>
</ul>
<p>And it cannot be attributed to hallucination, that you, a man acute and wise, and deeply versed in Scripture, confound the election of God with His promises, which are universal.&nbsp; For nothing is more certain than that the gospel is addressed to all promiscuously, but that the Spirit of faith is bestowed on the elect alone, by peculiar privilege.&nbsp; The promises are universal.&nbsp; How does it happen, therefore, that their efficacy is not equally felt by all?&nbsp; For this reason, because God does not reveal His arm to all.&nbsp; Indeed, among men but moderately skilled in Scripture, this subject needs not to be discussed, seeing that the promises of the Gospel make offer of the grace of Christ equally to all; and God, by the external call, invites all who are willing to accept of salvation.<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></p>
<ul>
<li>The classic assertion of the free and well-meant offer of the gospel by the Canons of Dort comes in The Second Head of Doctrine, Article 5 and The Third and Fourth Heads of Doctrine, Articles 6-8. The second reference bears comment.&nbsp; In Articles 6 and 7 gospel preaching and calls given to many who are not elect are described as &#8220;grace&#8221; and &#8220;so great and so gracious a blessing.&#8221;&nbsp; Article 8 then asserts, &#8220;As many as are called by the gospel, are unfeignedly called.&nbsp; For God hath most earnestly and truly declared in His Word, what will be acceptable to him; namely, that all who are called, should comply with the invitation.&#8221; &nbsp;If this language does not assert a free and well-meant offer, one wonders how such an idea could be stated without using the exact or precise words.</li>
</ul>
<p>To all this needs to be added a comment about the more recent history of Reformed truth.&nbsp; The resurgence of Reformed theology beginning in the 50&#8217;s and 60&#8217;s of the 20<sup>th</sup> Century can be traced in large part to Banner of Truth Trust; a Westminster Theological Seminary dominated by Cornelius Van Til and John Murray; and the revival of interest in the writing of Charles H. Spurgeon.&nbsp; In so far as this is true it is right to say that this resurgence of Calvinism was committed to the free and well-meant offer of the gospel.</p>
<p>In spite of all this and with the blossoming of wider interest in Reformed theology, there has come a denial of the well-meant offer of the gospel in recent years.&nbsp; It is this resurgence of a denial of the free and well-meant offer which has given birth in my mind to the necessity of this course and these lectures.</p>
<p>My lectures are not intended strictly speaking as a supplement to those of Dr. Daniel.&nbsp; It seemed better for us both to follow our own track in opening up this subject.&nbsp; I think we are of single mind on the subject, but perhaps such duplication as there may be between us will serve the student.&nbsp; Perhaps as well, whatever differences of emphasis there may be will also be of value to the student.</p>
<h2><strong>Outline of Dr. Waldron&#8217;s Lectures</strong></h2>
<p>Part 1:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Scriptural Exposition (from John 5:34)</p>
<p>Part 2:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Biblical Confirmation</p>
<p>Part 3:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Confessional Position</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Explicit Assertion</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Implicit Affirmation</p>
<p>Part 4:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Doctrinal Implications</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Love of God</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Will of God</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 3:&nbsp; The Mystery of God</p>
<p>Part 5:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Major Objections</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Objection from the Doctrine of Election</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Objection from the Doctrine of Simplicity</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 3:&nbsp; The Objection from the Fact of Anthropopathisms</p>
<p>Part 6:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Practical Applications</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Warning against Rationalism</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Warrant of Faith</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 3:&nbsp; The Way of Preaching</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">It&#8217;s not too late to register! &nbsp;<a href="/hyper-calvinism/"><strong>Register Here</strong></a></span></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a>This language is found in chapter 7, paragraph 2, in the 1689, but in chapter 7 paragraph 3 in the Savoy and Westminster.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a>Herman Hanko, <em>The History of the Free Offer</em>, accessed on the Internet July 21, 2017 <a href="http://www.prca.org/pamphlets/Free%20Offer/Introduction.htm">http://www.prca.org/pamphlets/Free%20Offer/Introduction.htm</a>.&nbsp; Further confirmation of the Protestant Reformed denial of the free offer of the gospel may be seen in David Engelsma, <em>Hyper-Calvinism and the Call of the Gospel: An Examination of the Well-Meant of the Gospel</em> (The Reformed Free Publishing Company: Jenison, MI, 2014).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a>Calvin, John, <em>Selected Works of John Calvin</em>, ed. by Henry Beveridge, trans. by Jules Bonnet (Grand Rapids: Baker Book House, 1983), vol. V, p. 379f.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/">The Crux of the Free Offer of the Gospel</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our Seventh and Eighth Lessons</title>
		<link>/true-conversion-augustine-7-8/</link>
					<comments>/true-conversion-augustine-7-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Augustine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conversion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1445</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We must never allow church history in general or any part of church history in particular to exercise a divine authority over our faith. Nevertheless, there are some persons and events of church history that are so close to the core of what historical Christianity is that to deny their legitimacy seems close to denying [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/true-conversion-augustine-7-8/">Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our Seventh and Eighth Lessons</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We must never allow church history in general or any part of church history in particular to exercise a divine authority over our faith. Nevertheless, there are some persons and events of church history that are so close to the core of what historical Christianity is that to deny their legitimacy seems close to denying the faith. One such event might be the conversion of Luther via his understanding of justification by faith alone. Another such event is the conversion of Augustine. We may well say, “If Augustine was not a Christian, and if his conversion was not true conversion, then whose conversion is?” Thus, we may well ask, indeed, we must ask, What lessons about true conversion can we learn from Augustine’s conversion?</p>
<p><strong>Our Seventh Lesson: The Reality of the Mixture of Error in Conversion</strong></p>
<p>Another important practical truth about all true conversion illustrated by the conversion of Augustine is that we must expect a mixture of misconception and error both in doctrine and practice in true conversions. Of course, this is not to say that such error is a matter of indifference or justifiable, but it is to say that in a fallen world and in an imperfectly redeemed church such error must be expected to be mixed in with even true conversions. Such error, assuming it is not an error which overthrows the foundation of the Christian faith, does not mean that the conversion in question is false. We know of two such serious errors which accompanied Augustine’s conversion.</p>
<p><em>Misconception about the Necessity of Celibacy</em></p>
<p>It was the example of St. Antony and the Egyptian monks which fired his imagination and deepened his conviction. It is clear that Augustine could contemplate no Christian life for himself which did not involve a commitment to celibacy. It is clear that he did not make this a standard for everyone else, but he certainly required it of himself. By rights his teachers and his conscience should have told him to go find Adeodatus’ mother and marry her! Sadly, this was not even on Augustine’s radar. This glorification of the monastic ideal including celibacy was not Christian, but it colored Augustine’s vision of Christianity.</p>
<p><em>Misconception about the Sovereignty of Grace</em></p>
<p>As becomes clear in the anti-Pelagian writings of Augustine, and as we will see in a later lecture, Augustine later confesses that he was not at first clear about the sovereignty of grace in salvation. While Augustine had never been Pelagian, he will tell us that he was for a while as a Christian semi-Pelagian in his views. That is to say, he believed, if we only take the first step, then the grace of God will intervene for our salvation. Of course, Augustine should have known that this was wrong from his own experience. It was, however, only his gradually maturing understanding of grace that showed him the error of semi-Pelagianism.</p>
<p>I have spoken to certain Christians who think that an Arminian cannot be a Christian. I have been asked by others who wonder if Arminians can be saved. Much can be said in response to those with such questions and such views. It is, however, certainly important to realize that the first Christian to affirm the sovereignty of grace in salvation and predestination in unmistakable terms was not himself a believer in these things when he himself was converted.</p>
<p>All of this teaches us the requirement of divine forbearance and mercy in the conversion of every sinner. Every sinner comes into the Christian faith with many misconceptions about both doctrine and practice from which he must be weaned by progressive sanctification. If God exercises such merciful forbearance towards his children, then so must we.</p>
<p><strong>Our Eighth Lesson: The Consequence of the Seal of Baptism in Conversion</strong></p>
<p>Paedobaptists will, of course, find all sorts of ways to explain away the fact that Augustine was not baptized as an infant. It is, however, clear that he was only baptized as a believer some months after the time of his conversion and only after a period careful instruction in the Christian faith had been completed.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/true-conversion-augustine-7-8/">Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our Seventh and Eighth Lessons</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/true-conversion-augustine-7-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our Fourth, Fifth, and Sixth Lessons</title>
		<link>/true-conversion-augustine-4-5-6/</link>
					<comments>/true-conversion-augustine-4-5-6/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2013 17:00:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Augustine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conversion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1441</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We must never allow church history in general or any part of church history in particular to exercise a divine authority over our faith. Nevertheless, there are some persons and events of church history that are so close to the core of what historical Christianity is that to deny their legitimacy seems close to denying [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/true-conversion-augustine-4-5-6/">Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our Fourth, Fifth, and Sixth Lessons</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We must never allow church history in general or any part of church history in particular to exercise a divine authority over our faith. Nevertheless, there are some persons and events of church history that are so close to the core of what historical Christianity is that to deny their legitimacy seems close to denying the faith. One such event might be the conversion of Luther via his understanding of justification by faith alone. Another such event is the conversion of Augustine. We may well say, &#8220;If Augustine was not a Christian, and if his conversion was not true conversion, then whose conversion is?&#8221; Thus, we may well ask, indeed, we must ask, What lessons about true conversion can we learn from Augustine&#8217;s conversion?</p>
<p><strong>Our Fourth Lesson: The Centrality of the Word of God in Conversion</strong></p>
<p>The words from Augustine&#8217;s <em>Confessions</em> <a title="True Conversion Augustine: Lessons 2 and 3" href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1438">cited previously</a> remind us of another universal feature of all true conversion. They remind us of the centrality of the Word of God as the instrument of true conversion. It was the Word of God and specifically Romans 13:13-14 that God used to renew and speak peace to the soul of Augustine. Augustine&#8217;s conversion shows (in the language of Scripture) that men are born again (as 1 Peter 1:23 teaches) &#8220;not of seed which is perishable but imperishable, that is, through the living and enduring word of God.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Our Fifth Lesson:&nbsp;The Sovereignty of the Grace of God in Conversion</strong></p>
<p>Another great truth about true conversion underscored in Augustine&#8217;s conversion and to Augustine himself is the fact of the sovereignty of God in all true conversion. Augustine&#8217;s experience of his own helplessness in the face of his bondage to sexual sin made clear to Him that only the direct intervention of God in power and grace could free him from his sin. I think it is clear that this prepared the way for his later, mature views of the sovereignty of God&#8217;s grace and predestination. It was first in His conversion that Augustine learned the truth of Jesus&#8217; words in John 6:44: &#8220;No one can come to Me unless the Father who sent Me draws him; and I will raise him up on the last day.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>Our Sixth Lesson: The Reality of the Change of Lordship in Conversion</strong></p>
<p>What I am saying under this heading is really a truism. Conversion means conversion! That is, true conversion always involves a radical renewal of the life and conduct of the one converted. Augustine&#8217;s conversion is again paradigmatic in this regard. Augustine would have had no peace and no sense of having been saved without the confident awareness that in the moment of his salvation God had delivered him from bondage to his sins and especially the bondage he felt to his sexual sins. This liberation and release from bondage was essential to his conversion and it is essential to every true conversion. Yes, it may be that the outward manifestations of inward repentance may struggle for a period to fully take possession of the life. Yes, it is true that Christians struggle throughout life with the principle of sin, but this sin does not reign over them. It only remains in them. This is why the modern so-called free grace movements which deny that conversion entails such repentance and transformation are fundamentally at odds with true Christian conversion. The Christian doctrine of conversion is found in the famous words of Jesus in Matthew 7:13-14: &#8220;Enter through the narrow gate; for the gate is wide and the way is broad that leads to destruction, and there are many who enter through it. For the gate is small and the way is narrow that leads to life, and there are few who find it.&#8221;</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/true-conversion-augustine-4-5-6/">Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our Fourth, Fifth, and Sixth Lessons</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/true-conversion-augustine-4-5-6/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our Second and Third Lessons</title>
		<link>/true-conversion-augustine-2-3/</link>
					<comments>/true-conversion-augustine-2-3/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 17:00:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Augustine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conversion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1438</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We must never allow church history in general or any part of church history in particular to exercise a divine authority over our faith. Nevertheless, there are some persons and events of church history that are so close to the core of what historical Christianity is that to deny their legitimacy seems close to denying [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/true-conversion-augustine-2-3/">Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our Second and Third Lessons</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We must never allow church history in general or any part of church history in particular to exercise a divine authority over our faith. Nevertheless, there are some persons and events of church history that are so close to the core of what historical Christianity is that to deny their legitimacy seems close to denying the faith. One such event might be the conversion of Luther via his understanding of justification by faith alone. Another such event is the conversion of Augustine. We may well say, &#8220;If Augustine was not a Christian, and if his conversion was not true conversion, then whose conversion is?&#8221; Thus, we may well ask, indeed, we must ask, What lessons about true conversion can we learn from Augustine&#8217;s conversion?</p>
<p><strong>Our Second Lesson: The Necessity of the Conviction of Sin in Conversion</strong></p>
<p>The pages of Augustine&#8217;s <em>Confessions</em> which lead up to the account of his conversion reek of sin and the conviction of sin. The increasingly overpowering sense of his<br />
bondage under sexual sin is underscored by the tragic account of the sending away of his much loved concubine because of the marriage arranged for him with an under-age heiress. One can sense Augustine&#8217;s crushing sense of moral failure in the astonishing account of his procuring a second concubine because he could not wait the two years till his under-age bride could marry. The deep insight which his experience gave him of the depravity or evil of sin can be read in Augustine&#8217;s account of how he and his buddies vandalized the pear tree of a neighbor and did it, as Augustine came to believe, for the sheer evil of it. The profane saying of wicked men about doing something &#8220;just for the hell of it&#8221; is more true than such men realized, Augustine was convinced. Augustine came to be deeply convinced of both the evil and the power of sin by his own experience. This experience prepared the way for his later insights.</p>
<p><strong>Our Third Lesson: The Over-ruling of the Providence of God in Conversion</strong></p>
<p>Here are Augustine&#8217;s remarks about the immediate circumstances of his conversion:
</p>
<blockquote><p>So was I speaking and weeping in the most bitter contrition of my heart, when, lo! I heard from a neighboring house a voice, as of boy or girl, I know not, chanting, and oft repeating, &#8220;Take up and read; Take up and read.&#8221; Instantly, my countenance altered, I began to think most intently whether children were wont in any kind of&nbsp;play to sing such words: nor could I remember ever to have heard the like. So checking the torrent of my tears, I arose; interpreting it to be no other than a command from God to open the book, and read the first chapter I should find. For I had heard of Antony, that coming in during the reading of the Gospel, he received the admonition, as if what was being read was spoken to him: Go, sell all that thou hast, and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven, and come and follow me: and by such oracle he was forthwith converted unto Thee. Eagerly then I returned to the place where Alypius was sitting; for there had I laid the volume of the Apostle when I arose thence I seized, opened, and in silence read that section on which my eyes first fell: Not in rioting and drunkenness, not in chambering and wantonness, not in strife and envying; but put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make not provision for the flesh, in concupiscence. No further would I read; nor needed I: for instantly at the end of this sentence, by a light as it were of serenity infused into my heart, all the darkness of doubt vanished away.</p></blockquote>
<p>We are not to learn from the example of Augustine the foolish method of seeking God&#8217;s will by opening the Bible at random and putting our finger on a verse. This is what Augustine did, but we are not to imitate his superstition. We are, however, to marvel at the kindness of an over-ruling providence which in spite of the folly of such a practice used it and the striking providence of the child&#8217;s chant of &#8220;take up and read.&#8221; In His kind providence God used things to lead Augustine to the exact Words of Scripture which God used to convert His soul to Himself.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/true-conversion-augustine-2-3/">Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our Second and Third Lessons</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/true-conversion-augustine-2-3/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our First Lesson</title>
		<link>/true-conversion-augustine-1/</link>
					<comments>/true-conversion-augustine-1/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2013 17:00:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Augustine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conversion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1435</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We must never allow church history in general or any part of church history in particular to exercise a divine authority over our faith. Nevertheless, there are some persons and events of church history that are so close to the core of what historical Christianity is that to deny their legitimacy seems close to denying [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/true-conversion-augustine-1/">Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our First Lesson</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignright size-full wp-image-1436" title="Augustine Portrait" src="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/250px-Saint_Augustine_Portrait.jpg" alt="" width="250" height="340">We must never allow church history in general or any part of church history in particular to exercise a divine authority over our faith. Nevertheless, there are some persons and events of church history that are so close to the core of what historical Christianity is that to deny their legitimacy seems close to denying the faith. One such event might be the conversion of Luther via his understanding of justification by faith alone. Another such event is the conversion of Augustine. We may well say, &#8220;If Augustine was not a Christian, and if his conversion was not true conversion, then whose conversion is?&#8221; Thus, we may well ask, indeed, we must ask, What lessons about true conversion can we learn from Augustine&#8217;s conversion?</p>
<p><strong>Our First Lesson: The Importance of the Use of Means in Conversion</strong></p>
<p>There is a debate in some Reformed circles over views of conversion which emphasize the importance of nurture in conversion and views which emphasize that conversion is a sudden event which often takes place without previous preparation in the context of revival. Now without getting deeply involved in that debate, it is clear that the use of means were vitally important to Augustine&#8217;s conversion.</p>
<p><em>The Means of Prayer&#8212;Monica</em></p>
<p>There may be no famous instance in the history of Christianity of the importance of parental nurture, but especially of parental prayers than the example of Monica. From this we learn that persevering prayer which never gives up on praying for the object of one&#8217;s concern is a mighty means in the conversion of sinners. We should never give up on the possibility of God answering our prayers in the conversion of our loved ones.</p>
<p><em>The Means of Preaching&#8212;Ambrose</em></p>
<p>The instruction from Ambrose which Augustine received in the years immediately preceding his conversion, and especially His preaching, is a strong encouragement to<br />
bring our children faithfully, and others as we can persuade them, under the faithful ministry of the Word of God. It is plain that through the preaching of Ambrose Augustine experienced both an increasingly clear understanding of the truthfulness of the Christian religion and an increasingly deep conviction of sin. These things plainly led to (were the means of) his conversion.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/true-conversion-augustine-1/">Lessons about True Conversion to Be Learned from Augustine’s Conversion: Our First Lesson</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/true-conversion-augustine-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whatever Happened to the Covenant of Works?</title>
		<link>/covenant-of-works/</link>
					<comments>/covenant-of-works/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 23:00:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Covenant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covenant of works]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Covenant Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1369</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Central to the theology of the Reformation is the contrast between the covenant of works and the covenant of grace.  The two concepts or structures go together, and it is in the light of them that the Reformed doctrine of justification and salvation as a whole is to be understood.  But the covenant of works [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/covenant-of-works/">Whatever Happened to the Covenant of Works?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Central to the theology of the Reformation is the contrast between the covenant of works and the covenant of grace.  The two concepts or structures go together, and it is in the light of them that the Reformed doctrine of justification and salvation as a whole is to be understood.  But the covenant of works has fallen on bad days and is widely denied even among evangelicals.  That is why it is crucial for us to have a clear understanding of the covenant of works and its biblical basis.  And that is why I asked the question in this message, <a title="Whatever Happened to the Covenant of Works" href="http://www.sermonaudio.com/sermoninfo.asp?SID=121132010515" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Whatever Happened to the Covenant of Works?</a></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/covenant-of-works/">Whatever Happened to the Covenant of Works?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/covenant-of-works/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brief survey of the history of hermeneutics – 12. Post-Reformation Reformed Orthodoxy (I)</title>
		<link>/surv-hist-herms-12-post-ref-ref-orth-i/</link>
					<comments>/surv-hist-herms-12-post-ref-ref-orth-i/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2011 12:47:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[history of hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[post-Reformation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed orthodoxy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1026</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The theological methodology of the post-Reformation Reformed orthodox was, in the first place, exegetical.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/surv-hist-herms-12-post-ref-ref-orth-i/">Brief survey of the history of hermeneutics – 12. Post-Reformation Reformed Orthodoxy (I)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/05/surv-of-hist-herm-ren-ref/">Brief survey of the history of hermeneutics &#8211; 11. Renaissance and Reformation</a></strong></p>
<p><strong>The theological methodology of the post-Reformation Reformed orthodox: </strong>The theological methodology of the post-Reformation Reformed orthodox was, in the first place, exegetical. In order to get a firmer grip on their methodology, we will examine it from the vantage point of <em>what it is not </em>&#8211; 1. a hyper-syllogistic method; 2. an Aristotelian, rationalistic method; and 3. a universal method &#8211; and <em>what it is </em>&#8211; 4. a pre-critical method; 5. an exegetically-based method; 6. a redemptive-historically sensitive method; and 7. a multi-sourced method. The last four mentioned methodological characteristics are especially visible in the writings of John Owen, one of the premiere post-Reformation Reformed scholastics.[1]<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Not a Hyper-Syllogistic Method: </strong>Their method was not reduced to syllogistic argumentation <em>ad nauseam</em>. In fact, Muller claims that &#8220;[f]ew of the orthodox or scholastic Protestants lapsed into constant or exclusive recourse to syllogism as a method of exposition.&#8221;[2] Syllogistic argumentation was utilized, but mostly in polemic contexts and not as an exegetical tool. Logic&#8211;the science of necessary inference&#8211;was utilized by the Reformed orthodox in the drawing out of good and necessary conclusions from the text of Scripture,[3] but it was a servant and not lord of the interpreter. Muller says that &#8220;the drawing of logical conclusions appears as one of the final hermeneutical steps in the [Reformed orthodox exegetical] method&#8230;&#8221;[4]<strong></strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;<strong>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Not an Aristotelian, Rationalistic Method: </strong>The Protestant scholasticism of the post-Reformation era must be distinguished from rationalism. The Reformed orthodox did not place human reason above, or even equal to, divine revelation.[5] The place and function of reason was subordinate to the authority of Scripture. Reason was an instrument not an axiomatic principle.[6] The Protestant scholastics utilized a modified (or Christian) Aristotelianism &#8220;that had its beginnings in the thirteenth century.&#8221;[7] Muller explains:<strong></strong></p>
<p>It is important to recognize what this use entailed and what it did not. The Christian Aristotelianism of the Protestant orthodox drew on rules of logic and devices such as the fourfold causality in order to explain and develop their doctrinal formulae&#8212;and only seldom, if ever, to import a full-scale rational metaphysics or physics into their theology. Contrary to what is sometimes claimed, the fourfold causality (i.e., first, formal, material, and final causes) does not imply a particular metaphysic. Specifically, it is not by nature &#8220;determinis&shy;tic.&#8221; One can use the model to delineate the soteriological patterns of the eternal decree of God and its execution in time; one can also use the model to describe the sources and effects of human sinfulness and human moral conduct; or one can use the model to explain how a car&shy;penter makes a table. The large-scale result of Christian Aristotelianism was not, in other words, a fundamentally Aristotelian Christianity: Aristotle would have disowned this hybrid philosophy with its infinite God who created the world out of nothing! There was, certainly, less imposition of rational metaphysics on theology in the seventeenth-century orthodox affirmations of divine eternity, omniscience, and immutability than there is in the twentieth-century claims of a changing God whose very being is in flux and who lacks foreknowledge of future contingency![8]</p>
<p>Van Asselt says, &#8220;[the] facile equation of Scholasticism and Aristotelianism is no longer tenable.&#8221;[9]</p>
<p><strong>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Not a Universal Method: </strong>As well, simply because an author utilized the scholastic method in some of his writings did not mean he used it in all of them. For instance, Muller offers Beza as an example.[10] Elsewhere, Muller says, &#8220;In the cases of Perkins, Ames, Voetius, and Baxter, works of piety and works of scholastic theology emanated from the same pens.&#8221;[11] Muller goes on to say:<strong></strong></p>
<p>&#8230;there is no clear division between Protestant scholasticism and federal theology. Theologians who wrote works of piety that followed a &#8220;positive&#8221; or &#8220;catechetical&#8221; method also wrote more technical and academic works using the scholastic method &#8211; and many of the scholastic, as well as &#8220;positive&#8221; works were covenantal in their theology.[12]</p>
<p>This observation applies to Johannes Cocceius and John Owen. Owen utilized the scholastic method in some treaties and a more practical, pastoral approach in others. Both Cocceius and Owen utilized the federal model as well as the <em>loci</em> model. Also, within the body of Owen&#8217;s <em>Biblical Theology</em>, he utilizes the scholastic method but also ridicules it.[13] This obviously shows that Owen could use a method he fully realized was abused by others and that the scholastic method was just that&#8211;a method and not a theology.</p>
<p>&nbsp;<strong>4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>A Pre-Critical Method: </strong>The Reformed orthodox obviously predate the Enlightenment and the critical assault on the Holy Scriptures. The Enlightenment gave birth to, among other things, a rationalistic approach to the interpretation of Scripture. This can be seen, for instance, in the early developments of biblical theology.[14] Typical Enlightenment rationalism and anti-supernaturalism is evidenced in the following statements made by Benjamin Jowett, a Greek professor at Oxford in the mid-nineteenth century. David C. Steinmetz quotes Jowett and comments:<strong></strong></p>
<p>Jowett argued that &#8220;Scripture has one meaning&#8211;the meaning which it had in the mind of the Prophet or Evangelist who first uttered or wrote, to the hearers or readers who first received it.&#8221;[15] Scripture should be interpreted like any other book and the later accretions and venerated traditions surrounding its interpretation should, for the most part, either be brushed aside or severely discounted. &#8220;The true use of interpretation is to get rid of interpretation, and leave us alone in company with the author.&#8221;[16]</p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p>Jowett obviously reduces meaning to the intent of the human author alone. In critical hermeneutical theory, there was no room whatsoever for the medieval concept of &#8220;double literal sense&#8221;[17] or for the Reformation and post-Reformation concepts of <em>sensus literalis</em> (literal sense), <em>analogia Scripturae </em>(analogy of Scripture), <em>analogia fidei </em>(analogy of faith), and <em>scopus Scripturae </em>(scope of Scripture).[18] In post-modern thought, man, the reader, is king of interpretation; in the modern/Enlightenment theory man, the author, was. In the Middle Ages, however, and in the Reformation and post-Reformation eras, though through differing hermeneutical principles, the meaning of Scripture was not determined by the human author&#8217;s intent alone or the reader. Ultimately, the meaning of Scripture was determined by God, the author of Scripture.[19]</p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>5.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>An Exegetically-Based Method<strong>[20]</strong>: </strong>Though the Reformed orthodox were confessionally one in a historical sense (i.e., the <em>Belgic Confession</em>, the <em>Heidelberg Catechism</em>, the <em>Canons of Dordt</em>, and in Britain in the Westminster Assembly&#8217;s <em>Confession of Faith and Larger and Shorter Catechisms</em>, <em>Savoy Declaration</em>, <em>Second London Confession of Faith</em>), this did not mean they viewed the exegetical task as complete and, therefore, unnecessary, nor that there was no room for disagreement over the exegesis of individual texts. Muller comments:<strong></strong></p>
<p>the biblicism of the seventeenth-century orthodox must not be read as an era of dogmatizing exegesis devoid of careful textual analysis and devoid of any variety in interpretation among those of an orthodox confessional persuasion. Instead, the age ought to be viewed as the great age of Protestant linguistic study and Judaica, of the textual analysis that led to such monumental productions as the London Polyglot Bible. &#8230;the Protestant orthodoxy must be recognized as producing highly varied and diverse exegetical works and commentaries, ranging from text-critical essays, to textual annotations, theological annotations, linguistic commentaries based on the study of cognate languages and Judaica, doctrinal and homiletical commentaries, and, indeed, all manner of permutations and combinations of these several types of effort.[21]</p>
<p>Biblical exegesis, in fact, experienced a revival of sorts within the Reformed orthodox of the seventeenth century. Muller says:</p>
<p>Contrary to much of the &#8220;received wisdom&#8221; concerning the seventeenth century, the era of orthodoxy was a time of great exegetical, textual, and linguistic development in Protestantism&#8211;and, indeed, it was the orthodox exegetes who were responsible for the major monuments to biblical scholarship.[22]</p>
<p>Carl R. Trueman says, &#8220;&#8230;the seventeenth century witnessed a remarkable flourishing of linguistic and exegetical studies, driven by both the positive and the polemical exigencies of Protestantism&#8217;s commitment to scripture, in the original languages, as being the very Word &#8211; and words &#8211; of God.&#8221;[23] Trueman continues elsewhere:</p>
<p>A high view of the authority and integrity of the biblical text as God&#8217;s word written was [a] major factor in fuelling the development of careful attention both to the biblical languages and other cognate tongues, and to issues of textual history and criticism. The idea that the seventeenth-century Reformed were interested neither in careful exegesis nor in the literary and linguistic contexts of the Bible is simply untrue. Indeed, the linguistic and exegetical work of this century was far more elaborate than that which had marked the earlier Reformation. &#8230;the exegesis of the Reformed Orthodox is far from the dogmatically-driven Procusteanism[24] [<em>sic</em>] of popular mythology.[25]</p>
<p>&nbsp;<strong>6.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>A Redemptive-Historically Sensitive Method: </strong>Not only were the Reformed orthodox exegetically driven, their hermeneutic was a whole-Bible hermeneutic, evidenced in such concepts as their highly nuanced view of <em>sensus literalis</em> (literal sense), <em>analogia Scripturae </em>(analogy of Scripture), <em>analogia fidei </em>(analogy of faith), and <em>scopus Scripturae </em>(scope of Scripture).[26] It is of vital importance to understand the nuances involved with these concepts in order to properly understand the Reformed orthodox. We will explore these concepts in our next post.</p>
<hr size="1">[1] We will discuss Owen below.</p>
<p>[2] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; I:369.</p>
<p>[3] Cf. Muller, <em>PRRD</em>, II:497-500 for a discussion of the use of logic in interpretation.</p>
<p>[4] Muller, <em>PRRD</em>, II:501.</p>
<p>[5] Cf. <em>WCF</em> 1:10 for confessional embodiment to this conviction.</p>
<p>[6] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; I:374.</p>
<p>[7] Muller, &#8220;Sources of Reformed Orthodoxy,&#8221; 55. Cf. van Asselt, &#8220;The Fundamental Meaning of Theology,&#8221; 322, where he says that the Reformed theology of the late sixteenth century (<em>i.e</em>., Franciscus Junius) critically received the Christian tradition.</p>
<p>[8] Muller, &#8220;Sources of Reformed Orthodoxy,&#8221; 55.</p>
<p>[9] van Asselt, &#8220;The Fundamental Meaning of Theology,&#8221; 329, n. 42.</p>
<p>[10] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; I:370.</p>
<p>[11] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; II:145.</p>
<p>[12] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; II:146.</p>
<p>[13] Cf. Rehnman<em>, Divine Discourse</em>, Chapter 4, &#8220;Faith and Reason,&#8221; especially the sections &#8220;The Abuse of Reason in Theology&#8221; and &#8220;A Contextual Line of Explanation,&#8221; 119-28 and the &#8220;Conclusion&#8221; to my dissertation.</p>
<p>[14] See below.</p>
<p>[15] Benjamin Jowett, &#8220;On the Interpretation of Scripture,&#8221; <em>Essays and Reviews</em>, 7<sup>th</sup> ed. (London: Longman, Green, Longman and Roberts, 1861), 378, quoted in David C. Steinmetz, &#8220;The Superiority of Pre-Critical Exegesis,&#8221; <em>Theology Today</em> (April 1980): 27.</p>
<p>[16] Steinmetz is quoting Jowett, &#8220;On the Interpretation of Scripture,&#8221; 384. Cf. Steinmetz, &#8220;The Superiority of Pre-Critical Exegesis,&#8221; 27.</p>
<p>[17] Steinmetz, &#8220;The Superiority of Pre-Critical Exegesis,&#8221; 31.</p>
<p>[18] We will discuss these below.</p>
<p>[19] This, of course, does not imply that pre-critical exegesis always arrived at God&#8217;s meaning of the text. Cf. Packer, <em>Quest for Godliness</em>, 98, for a brief discussion of the Puritans as pre-modern exegetes.</p>
<p>[20] Cf. Muller, &#8220;Sources of Reformed Orthodoxy,&#8221; 46-48; Muller, <em>PRRD</em>, II:482ff; Packer, <em>Quest for Godliness</em>, 98; and Thomas D. Lea, &#8220;The Hermeneutics of the Puritans,&#8221; <em>JETS</em> 39/2 (June 1996): 273.</p>
<p>[21] Muller, &#8220;Calvin and the &#8220;Calvinists&#8221;,&#8221; II:132-33.</p>
<p>[22] Muller, &#8220;Sources of Reformed Orthodoxy,&#8221; 46.</p>
<p>[23] Trueman, <em>John Owen</em>, 8-9.</p>
<p>[24] Tending to produce conformity by violent or arbitrary means.</p>
<p>[25] Trueman, <em>John Owen</em>, 37; Cf. Muller, <em>PRRD</em>, II:482ff. for a fascinating discussion of the practice of exegesis among the Reformed orthodox.</p>
<p>[26] Packer lists six governing principles of interpretation for the English Puritans: 1. Interpret Scripture <em>literally</em> <em>and</em> <em>grammatically</em>. 2. Interpret Scripture <em>consistently</em> <em>and</em> <em>harmonistically</em>. 3. Interpret Scripture <em>doctrinally</em> <em>and</em> <em>theocentrically</em>. 4. Interpret Scripture <em>christologically</em> <em>and</em> <em>evangelically</em>. 5. Interpret Scripture <em>experimentally and practically.</em> 6. Interpret Scripture <em>with a faithful and realistic application</em>. Cf. Packer, <em>Quest for Godliness</em>, 101-5. Cf. Barry Howson, &#8220;The Puritan Hermeneutics of John Owen: A Recommendation,&#8221; <em>WTJ</em> 63 (2001): 354-57.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/surv-hist-herms-12-post-ref-ref-orth-i/">Brief survey of the history of hermeneutics – 12. Post-Reformation Reformed Orthodoxy (I)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/surv-hist-herms-12-post-ref-ref-orth-i/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brief survey of the history of hermeneutics – 11. Renaissance and Reformation</title>
		<link>/surv-of-hist-herm-ren-ref/</link>
					<comments>/surv-of-hist-herm-ren-ref/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2011 00:52:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[history of hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reformation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[renaissance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1023</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>What the Renaissance gave to the Reformation, then, was an academic climate of questioning the status quo and seeking to arrive at conclusions based on primary documents.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/surv-of-hist-herm-ren-ref/">Brief survey of the history of hermeneutics – 11. Renaissance and Reformation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>The Renaissance: </strong>The Renaissance was a very complex humanist movement within Europe during the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries. Two of the most important contributions it gave to the Reformation were a return to critical scholarship and philology. What the Renaissance gave to the Reformation, then, was an academic climate of questioning the <em>status quo</em> and seeking to arrive at conclusions based on primary documents. Pelikan comments:</p>
<p>The insistence of humanistic scholars on an understanding of the biblical text based on a fresh reading of the Hebrew and Greek originals &#8230;acted as a catalyst in the reconsideration of the doctrine of authority during the age of the Reformation.[1]</p>
<p>This insistence led to the study of Hebrew and Greek grammar, the study of Augustine, and most importantly, the study of Paul and the Bible.</p>
<p><strong>The Reformation:</strong> The Reformation was both a break with the negative elements of the past (especially the late medieval doctrine of ecclesiastical authority and the system of human merit theology) and a continuation of the discussion that had been taking place from the beginning. The Bible took center stage at the Reformation due, in part, to the influence of the Renaissance. With this came a renewed interest in Bible interpretation and historical theology, both from primary sources. The maxim <em>ad fontes</em>[2] produced intensified study in the original sources of the Christian tradition &#8211; the Bible first and foremost and, secondarily, the Apostolic Fathers, Patristics, and Augustine.</p>
<p>Neither Luther nor Calvin invented or discovered doctrines that had never been discussed before.[3] Luther&#8217;s discovery of the gospel of justification <em>sola fide</em> was, first and foremost, a biblical doctrine and a doctrine that all true Christians had believed from the beginning. It had been eclipsed by a system of human merit theology and sacerdotalism, but this does not mean that it never existed prior to Luther.</p>
<p>Calvin was no innovator himself. He built his system of theology on his understanding of Christian Scripture controlled by &#8220;the rule of faith.&#8221; He produced commentaries that are still influential in our day. The Reformers saw themselves as part of a long line of Christian interpreters, utilizing what they could from previous generations and repudiating, sometimes viciously, what they could not. Though Calvin sought to be a corrector of what he viewed as wrong with elements of the past, on the main, he assumed into his interpretive method the method handed down to him by his university professors &#8211; the scholastic method, in distinction from scholastic theology (more on this below).</p>
<p>Mention has been made of how some view the history of Christian interpretation in a mostly negative light. This assessment is, primarily, a post-Enlightenment phenomenon. David Steinmetz, in his book <em>Calvin in Context</em>, discusses Calvin&#8217;s interpretation of Isaiah 6:1ff. in the light of the history of interpretation prior to Calvin.[4] Prior to his discussion of the history of interpretation and Isaiah&#8217;s text, he notes this about F. W. Farrar.</p>
<p>In 1885 Frederic W. Farrar, chaplain to Queen Victoria and later Dean of Canterbury, delivered the Bampton Lecutres at Oxford on the subject of the history of interpretation. The book is a triumph of what the late Sir Herbert Butterfield of Cambridge called &#8220;Whig&#8221; historiography. Farrar admired about the past precisely those elements in it most like the present and regarded the present, indeed, as the inevitable culmination of all that was best in the past. The history of exegesis became for Farrar the history of &#8220;more or less untenable&#8221; conceptions of the Bible, &#8220;a history of false suppositions slowly and progressively corrected.&#8221; Not surprisingly, Farrar admired Antioch over Alexandria, Luther over Thomas Aquinas, Calvin over Luther, and the moderns [Enlightenment/post-Enlightenment interpreters] over all. Farrar catalogued with obvious delight every strained allegory, every factual inaccuracy, every philological howler committed by precritical exegetes in the name of biblical interpretation. While he admitted that ancient commentaries are full of practical instruction aimed at moral and spiritual edification and that much of this instruction is &#8220;of the highest intrinsic value,&#8221; he nevertheless warned that frequently such material &#8220;has but a slender connexion with the text on which it is founded.&#8221;[5]</p>
<p>Steinmetz goes on to show that Calvin&#8217;s exegesis of the Isaiah pericope is very similar to the history of interpretation on this text and even goes so far as to say, &#8220;While the precritical exegesis of Isaiah 6 is not an exegesis we can simply adopt, it is still not accurate to regard it as arbitrary and strained, of value only for its homiletical asides.&#8221;[6] Steinmetz interacts with Farrar after his discussion of Calvin on Isaiah 6 and the history of precritical interpretation on this text:</p>
<p>It is difficult to recognize the exegesis of Isaiah 6 we have just examined in the general description of the history of exegesis which Farrar offered. To be sure, it is true that the older consensus on the historical-critical setting of Isaiah 6 would find few supporters among modern commentators, but the older discussion of these questions does not seem arbitrary or strained, even by modern standards. The judgment of Christian commentators that Isaiah saw the glory of Christ was an exegetical conclusion forced on the commentators by the New Testament itself, though there was a tendency on the part of some commentators&#8211;including Calvin&#8211;to soften the hard edges of that exegesis.[7]</p>
<p>Farrar assumed critical, Enlightenment categories while interpreting the history of interpretation. This gave his history a slant or bias in a certain direction and explains his overly negative assessment of most of what took place prior to the modern era. Steinmetz concludes:</p>
<p>It is no answer to Farrar to point out that there is a good deal in ancient commentaries which is surprisingly modern even from a historical-critical or philological viewpoint, or to argue that the modern reader can find insight into the &#8220;literal&#8221; sense of the text in precritical commentaries. That is to admit his principle that precritical exegesis is good in the proportion that it anticipates or agrees with modern exegesis. Nor is it an answer to reply with a <em>tu quoque</em> [Latin, &#8220;thou also&#8221;] and to list the exegetical atrocities which have been committed from time to time in the name of the historical-critical method, though such a list is disquietingly easy to compile.</p>
<p>The principal value of precritical exegesis is that it is not modern exegesis; it is alien, strange, sometimes even, from our perspective, comic and fantastical. Precisely because it is strange, it provides a constant stimulus to interpreters, offering exegetical suggestions they would never think of or find in any modern book, forcing them again and again to a rereading and reevaluation of the text. But if they immerse themselves not only in the text but also in these alien approaches to the text, they may learn in time to see with eyes not their own sights they could scarcely have imagined and may learn to hear with ears not their own voices too soft for their own ears to detect.[8]</p>
<p>Not only has this modern, Enlightenment mindset infected Farrar it has infected others who look down upon, not only the Reformers, but the post-Reformation Reformed orthodox, as we shall see next.</p>
<hr size="1">[1] Jaroslav Pelikan, <em>Reformation of Church and Dogma</em> (Chicago and London, University of Chicago Press, 1985), 8.</p>
<p>[2] Latin for <em>to the sources</em>.</p>
<p>[3] Cf. David C. Steinmetz, <em>Luther in Context</em> (Grand Rapids: Baker Books, 1995) and David C. Steinmetz, <em>Calvin in Context</em> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1995).</p>
<p>[4] Steinmetz, <em>Calvin in Context</em>, 95-109.</p>
<p>[5] Steinmetz, <em>Calvin in Context</em>, 95. Steinmetz is quoting from Fredric W. Farrar, <em>History of Interpretation</em> (Grand Rapids: Baker Book House, 1979).</p>
<p>[6] Steinmetz, <em>Calvin in Context</em>, 107.</p>
<p>[7] Steinmetz, <em>Calvin in Context</em>, 107.</p>
<p>[8] Steinmetz, <em>Calvin in Context</em>, 107.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/surv-of-hist-herm-ren-ref/">Brief survey of the history of hermeneutics – 11. Renaissance and Reformation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/surv-of-hist-herm-ren-ref/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
