<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Podcast 7: A Christian Sabbath?	</title>
	<atom:link href="/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 22:03:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: A Christian Sabbath? Podcast#7 from Midwest Center for Theological Studies &#124; 1689reformed baptist/1689bautista reformada		</title>
		<link>/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/#comment-131</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[A Christian Sabbath? Podcast#7 from Midwest Center for Theological Studies &#124; 1689reformed baptist/1689bautista reformada]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 22:03:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=566#comment-131</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[...] http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/01/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/ [...]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] <a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/01/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/" rel="nofollow ugc">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/01/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/</a> [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Stephen		</title>
		<link>/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/#comment-130</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2011 17:44:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=566#comment-130</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I know that in church History different understandings and applications of keeping the Christian Sabbath have existed, The Puritans for example had very rigorious activities the whole day. I think I would be considered a Sabbath breaker by many from that time because I generally take a good nap in between services. I read a little or try to preach at one of our outside ministries. I also seek to council younger Brethren and teach when asked a question bt them. Is this keeping the Sabbath,I say yes to all I have mentioned. I also quite simply enjoy being with my Brethren and they with me, I hope. Before coming into reformed circles I sort of kept the day seperate from the other six days of the week,no movies sports events malls and so on. But I would go fishing after church or hike a little just to marvel and enjoy a lazzy Sunday and I had peace in my soul doing it this way. Much in my understanding has changed do to teaching on it but not everything. The Sabbath is for man to delight im it&#039;s Lord for He is Lord of the Sabbath. I hope the reason so many Brethren get upset about the idea of a Christian Sabbath is not because they simply want to enjoy the things the world does, Sports,The Movies,The Malls etc. If you sincerely don&#039;t see and uderstand why we do call it a Christian Sabbath and strive to keep it as we see it a Moral Command then please don&#039;t judge us for keeping His command and we will seek not to judge you for not keeping it,though we believe you should. A parting comment I will make, how much harm is done to us who strive to focus in heartfelt worship to GOD the whole day and how much spiritual good is done to you who spend most of the day in lawful amusements of the world?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I know that in church History different understandings and applications of keeping the Christian Sabbath have existed, The Puritans for example had very rigorious activities the whole day. I think I would be considered a Sabbath breaker by many from that time because I generally take a good nap in between services. I read a little or try to preach at one of our outside ministries. I also seek to council younger Brethren and teach when asked a question bt them. Is this keeping the Sabbath,I say yes to all I have mentioned. I also quite simply enjoy being with my Brethren and they with me, I hope. Before coming into reformed circles I sort of kept the day seperate from the other six days of the week,no movies sports events malls and so on. But I would go fishing after church or hike a little just to marvel and enjoy a lazzy Sunday and I had peace in my soul doing it this way. Much in my understanding has changed do to teaching on it but not everything. The Sabbath is for man to delight im it&#8217;s Lord for He is Lord of the Sabbath. I hope the reason so many Brethren get upset about the idea of a Christian Sabbath is not because they simply want to enjoy the things the world does, Sports,The Movies,The Malls etc. If you sincerely don&#8217;t see and uderstand why we do call it a Christian Sabbath and strive to keep it as we see it a Moral Command then please don&#8217;t judge us for keeping His command and we will seek not to judge you for not keeping it,though we believe you should. A parting comment I will make, how much harm is done to us who strive to focus in heartfelt worship to GOD the whole day and how much spiritual good is done to you who spend most of the day in lawful amusements of the world?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Richard Barcellos		</title>
		<link>/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/#comment-129</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2011 20:42:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=566#comment-129</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My take on Is. 56 as it relates to a Sabbath under the New Covenant:


Isaiah 56:1-8
Isaiah 56:1-8 says:

Thus says the LORD: “Keep justice, and do righteousness, for My salvation is about to come, and My righteousness to be revealed. Blessed is the man who does this, and the son of man who lays hold on it; who keeps from defiling the Sabbath, and keeps his hand from doing any evil.” Do not let the son of the foreigner who has joined himself to the LORD speak, saying, “The LORD has utterly separated me from His people”; nor let the eunuch say, “Here I am, a dry tree.” For thus says the LORD: “To the eunuchs who keep My Sabbaths, and choose what pleases Me, and hold fast My covenant, even to them I will give in My house and within My walls a place and a name better than that of sons and daughters; I will give them an everlasting name that shall not be cut off. Also the sons of the foreigner who join themselves to the LORD, to serve Him, and to love the name of the LORD, to be His servants -- everyone who keeps from defiling the Sabbath, and holds fast My covenant -- even them I will bring to My holy mountain, and make them joyful in My house of prayer. Their burnt offerings and their sacrifices will be accepted on My altar; for My house shall be called a house of prayer for all nations.” The Lord GOD, who gathers the outcasts of Israel, says, “Yet I will gather to him others besides those who are gathered to him.” (Is. 56:1-8)

Several observations will assist us in understanding how this passage prophesies explicitly the perpetuity and continuation of the Sabbath under the New Covenant. First, the section of the book of Isaiah starting at chapter 40 and ending with chapter 66 is pointing forward to the days of Messiah and in some places to the eternal state. This section includes language pointing forward to the time primarily between the two comings of Christ, the interadvental days of the New Covenant. It is understood this way by the New Testament in several places (see Mt. 3:3; 8:16, 17; 12:15-21; and Acts 13:34).
Second, Isaiah 56:1-8 speaks prophetically of a day in redemptive history in which God will save Gentiles (see esp. vv. 7 and 8). The language of “all nations” in verse 7 reminds us of the promise given to Abraham concerning blessing all nations through his seed (see Gen. 12:3 and Gal. 3:8, 16). This Abrahamic promise is pursued by the great commission of Matthew 28:18-20. Isaiah is speaking about New Covenant days.
Third, in several New Testament texts, the language of Isaiah 56:1-8 (and the broader context) is applied to the days between Christ’s first and second coming in the motif of fulfillment (Mt. 21:12-13; Acts 8:26-40; Eph. 2:19; and 1 Tim. 3:15). Compare Matthew 21:13, “My house shall be called a house of prayer,” with Isaiah 56:7, “For My house shall be called a house of prayer for all nations.” This anticipates the inclusion of Gentiles in the house of God, a common New Testament phenomenon. Compare Acts 8:26-40 (notice a eunuch was reading from Isaiah) with Isaiah 56:3-5, which says:

Do not let the son of the foreigner who has joined himself to the LORD Speak, saying, “The LORD has utterly separated me from His people”; nor let the eunuch say, “Here I am, a dry tree.” For thus says the LORD: “To the eunuchs who keep My Sabbaths, and choose what pleases Me, and hold fast My covenant, even to them I will give in My house and within My walls a place and a name better than that of sons and daughters; I will give them an everlasting name that shall not be cut off. (Is. 56:3-5)

The Old Covenant placed restrictions on eunuchs. Deuteronomy 23:1 says, “He who is emasculated by crushing or mutilation shall not enter the assembly of the LORD.” Isaiah is prophesying about a day in redemptive history when those restrictions no longer apply.
In Ephesians 2:19 the church is called the “household of God” and in 1 Timothy 3:15 it is called “the house of God…” The context of 1 Timothy 3:15 includes 1 Timothy 2:1-7, where Paul outlines regulations for church prayer. Now listen to Isaiah 56:7, which says:

Even them [i.e., the foreigners (Gentiles) of v. 6a] I will bring to My holy mountain, and make them joyful in My house of prayer. Their burnt offerings and their sacrifices will be accepted on My altar; for My house shall be called a house of prayer for all nations. (Is. 56:7)

The New Testament sees Isaiah’s prophecy as fulfilled under the New Covenant. However, the privileges, responsibilities, and the people of God foretold here (Is. 56) are transformed to fit the conditions brought in by the New Covenant. The people of God are transformed due to the New Covenant; the house of God is transformed due to the New Covenant; the burnt offerings, sacrifices, and altar are transformed due to the New Covenant; and the Sabbath (as well shall see) is transformed due to the New Covenant. Isaiah, as with other Old Testament prophets, accommodates his prophecy to the language of the Old Covenant people, but its New Testament fulfillment specifies exactly what his prophesy looks like when being fulfilled. We saw Jeremiah do this with the promise of the New Covenant. What was promised to “the house of Israel” and “the house of Judah” (Jer. 31:31), is fulfilled in the Jew-Gentile church, the New Covenant people of God, the transformed Israel of Old Testament prophecy.
With these considerations before us, it seems not only plausible but compelling to conclude that between the two advents of Christ, when the Old Covenant law restricting eunuchs no longer restricts them, and when the nations (i.e., Gentiles) are becoming the Lord’s and frequenting His house, which is His Church, a Sabbath (see Isaiah 56:2, 4, 6) yet remains. Isaiah is speaking prophetically of Sabbath keeping in New Covenant days. The English Puritan John Bunyan, commenting on Isaiah 56, said, “Also it follows from hence, that the sabbath that has a promise annexed to the keeping of it, is rather that which the Lord Jesus shall give to the churches of the Gentiles.” 
The essence of the Sabbath transcends covenantal bounds, as we have seen and see here once again. Its roots are in creation, not the Old Covenant alone. It transcends covenants and cultures because the ethics of creation are trans-covenantal and trans-cultural. The Sabbath is part of God’s Moral Law.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My take on Is. 56 as it relates to a Sabbath under the New Covenant:</p>
<p>Isaiah 56:1-8<br />
Isaiah 56:1-8 says:</p>
<p>Thus says the LORD: “Keep justice, and do righteousness, for My salvation is about to come, and My righteousness to be revealed. Blessed is the man who does this, and the son of man who lays hold on it; who keeps from defiling the Sabbath, and keeps his hand from doing any evil.” Do not let the son of the foreigner who has joined himself to the LORD speak, saying, “The LORD has utterly separated me from His people”; nor let the eunuch say, “Here I am, a dry tree.” For thus says the LORD: “To the eunuchs who keep My Sabbaths, and choose what pleases Me, and hold fast My covenant, even to them I will give in My house and within My walls a place and a name better than that of sons and daughters; I will give them an everlasting name that shall not be cut off. Also the sons of the foreigner who join themselves to the LORD, to serve Him, and to love the name of the LORD, to be His servants &#8212; everyone who keeps from defiling the Sabbath, and holds fast My covenant &#8212; even them I will bring to My holy mountain, and make them joyful in My house of prayer. Their burnt offerings and their sacrifices will be accepted on My altar; for My house shall be called a house of prayer for all nations.” The Lord GOD, who gathers the outcasts of Israel, says, “Yet I will gather to him others besides those who are gathered to him.” (Is. 56:1-8)</p>
<p>Several observations will assist us in understanding how this passage prophesies explicitly the perpetuity and continuation of the Sabbath under the New Covenant. First, the section of the book of Isaiah starting at chapter 40 and ending with chapter 66 is pointing forward to the days of Messiah and in some places to the eternal state. This section includes language pointing forward to the time primarily between the two comings of Christ, the interadvental days of the New Covenant. It is understood this way by the New Testament in several places (see Mt. 3:3; 8:16, 17; 12:15-21; and Acts 13:34).<br />
Second, Isaiah 56:1-8 speaks prophetically of a day in redemptive history in which God will save Gentiles (see esp. vv. 7 and 8). The language of “all nations” in verse 7 reminds us of the promise given to Abraham concerning blessing all nations through his seed (see Gen. 12:3 and Gal. 3:8, 16). This Abrahamic promise is pursued by the great commission of Matthew 28:18-20. Isaiah is speaking about New Covenant days.<br />
Third, in several New Testament texts, the language of Isaiah 56:1-8 (and the broader context) is applied to the days between Christ’s first and second coming in the motif of fulfillment (Mt. 21:12-13; Acts 8:26-40; Eph. 2:19; and 1 Tim. 3:15). Compare Matthew 21:13, “My house shall be called a house of prayer,” with Isaiah 56:7, “For My house shall be called a house of prayer for all nations.” This anticipates the inclusion of Gentiles in the house of God, a common New Testament phenomenon. Compare Acts 8:26-40 (notice a eunuch was reading from Isaiah) with Isaiah 56:3-5, which says:</p>
<p>Do not let the son of the foreigner who has joined himself to the LORD Speak, saying, “The LORD has utterly separated me from His people”; nor let the eunuch say, “Here I am, a dry tree.” For thus says the LORD: “To the eunuchs who keep My Sabbaths, and choose what pleases Me, and hold fast My covenant, even to them I will give in My house and within My walls a place and a name better than that of sons and daughters; I will give them an everlasting name that shall not be cut off. (Is. 56:3-5)</p>
<p>The Old Covenant placed restrictions on eunuchs. Deuteronomy 23:1 says, “He who is emasculated by crushing or mutilation shall not enter the assembly of the LORD.” Isaiah is prophesying about a day in redemptive history when those restrictions no longer apply.<br />
In Ephesians 2:19 the church is called the “household of God” and in 1 Timothy 3:15 it is called “the house of God…” The context of 1 Timothy 3:15 includes 1 Timothy 2:1-7, where Paul outlines regulations for church prayer. Now listen to Isaiah 56:7, which says:</p>
<p>Even them [i.e., the foreigners (Gentiles) of v. 6a] I will bring to My holy mountain, and make them joyful in My house of prayer. Their burnt offerings and their sacrifices will be accepted on My altar; for My house shall be called a house of prayer for all nations. (Is. 56:7)</p>
<p>The New Testament sees Isaiah’s prophecy as fulfilled under the New Covenant. However, the privileges, responsibilities, and the people of God foretold here (Is. 56) are transformed to fit the conditions brought in by the New Covenant. The people of God are transformed due to the New Covenant; the house of God is transformed due to the New Covenant; the burnt offerings, sacrifices, and altar are transformed due to the New Covenant; and the Sabbath (as well shall see) is transformed due to the New Covenant. Isaiah, as with other Old Testament prophets, accommodates his prophecy to the language of the Old Covenant people, but its New Testament fulfillment specifies exactly what his prophesy looks like when being fulfilled. We saw Jeremiah do this with the promise of the New Covenant. What was promised to “the house of Israel” and “the house of Judah” (Jer. 31:31), is fulfilled in the Jew-Gentile church, the New Covenant people of God, the transformed Israel of Old Testament prophecy.<br />
With these considerations before us, it seems not only plausible but compelling to conclude that between the two advents of Christ, when the Old Covenant law restricting eunuchs no longer restricts them, and when the nations (i.e., Gentiles) are becoming the Lord’s and frequenting His house, which is His Church, a Sabbath (see Isaiah 56:2, 4, 6) yet remains. Isaiah is speaking prophetically of Sabbath keeping in New Covenant days. The English Puritan John Bunyan, commenting on Isaiah 56, said, “Also it follows from hence, that the sabbath that has a promise annexed to the keeping of it, is rather that which the Lord Jesus shall give to the churches of the Gentiles.”<br />
The essence of the Sabbath transcends covenantal bounds, as we have seen and see here once again. Its roots are in creation, not the Old Covenant alone. It transcends covenants and cultures because the ethics of creation are trans-covenantal and trans-cultural. The Sabbath is part of God’s Moral Law.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Richard Barcellos		</title>
		<link>/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/#comment-128</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2011 20:39:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=566#comment-128</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[James, that is certainly a fair question. Since the death penalty in the OT for Sabbath violations, then wouldn&#039;t it be the same under the NT? And if not, where does the NT say so? I hope that fairly represents your question.

My view is that the Sabbath was instituted on the seventh day of creation and yet the death penalty for violating it was not instituted until the Old Covenant came. There was a Sabbath in Exodus 16, for instance, prior to Mt. Sinai, and it did not have the death penalty attached to it for violations of it. In other words, a Sabbath can be in place without the death penalty in place. I also think that the OT prophesies a Sabbath under the New Covenant. Jer. 31:33 implies it (&quot;I will write My law on their hearts&quot;) and Isaiah 56 explicitly prophesies it. I will post my take on Is. 56 ASAP.

In the mean time, here is something I have written about the Sabbath and the death penalty issue you brought up:


•	The Sabbath had the death penalty attached to it under the Old Covenant, which implies that it was ceremonial and for Israel in the Promised Land alone.

Exodus 31:13-14 says:

Speak also to the children of Israel, saying: “Surely My Sabbaths you shall keep, for it is a sign between Me and you throughout your generations, that you may know that I am the LORD who sanctifies you. You shall keep the Sabbath, therefore, for it is holy to you. Everyone who profanes it shall surely be put to death; for whoever does any work on it, that person shall be cut off from among his people.” (Ex. 31:13-14)

Some may want to claim that since capital punishment is attached to Sabbath breaking, then the Sabbath is merely ceremonial and for Israel alone as God’s Old Covenant nation in the Promised Land. It cannot be proven, however, that if a commandment has the death penalty attached to it under the Old Covenant it is, therefore, merely ceremonial and for Israel under the Old Covenant alone. For instance, the third commandment has the sanction of capital punishment attached to it under the Old Covenant as well (Lev. 20:1-3). No one, however, argues against the perpetuity of the third commandment due to this. The fifth commandment also has the sanction of capital punishment attached to it under the Old Covenant (Ex. 21:12; Lev. 20:9; Dt. 21:18-21). No one, however, argues against the perpetuity of the fifth commandment due to this. The seventh commandment has the sanction of capital punishment attached to it under the Old Covenant also (Lev. 20:10; Dt. 22:21-22). Again, no one argues against the perpetuity of the seventh commandment due to this. The Decalogue formed the heart of Old Covenant Israel’s law. It had various appendages added to it to administrate the unique redemptive-historical circumstances it was given in. These redemptive-historical appendages were added to the Decalogue under the Old Covenant “until the time of reformation” (Heb. 9:10b). Simply because some commands of the Decalogue have the sanction of capital punishment attached to them under the Old Covenant does not mean they cannot function in other eras of redemptive history without those sanctions. The New Testament bears this out amply.
But this brings rise to a very important question: Does the Bible abrogate the death penalty for various offenses that were capital crimes under the Old Covenant? And if so, how? I believe it does, even while maintaining some of the very same laws under the New Covenant. This can be seen if we consider the unique character of Old Covenant Israel’s law, the abrogation of the Old Covenant law according to Old Testament prophecy and New Testament fulfillment, and the functions of the Decalogue in redemptive history.
First, consider that the Old Covenant’s law was given to ancient Israel to be applied in the Promised Land. Several Old Testament passages teach this very clearly.

Now, O Israel, listen to the statutes and the judgments which I teach you to observe, that you may live, and go in and possess the land which the LORD God of your fathers is giving you. You shall not add to the word which I command you, nor take from it, that you may keep the commandments of the LORD your God which I command you. Your eyes have seen what the LORD did at Baal Peor; for the LORD your God has destroyed from among you all the men who followed Baal of Peor. But you who held fast to the LORD your God are alive today, every one of you. Surely I have taught you statutes and judgments, just as the LORD my God commanded me, that you should act according to them in the land which you go to possess. (Dt. 4:1-5)

And the LORD commanded me at that time to teach you statutes and judgments, that you might observe them in the land which you cross over to possess. (Dt. 4:14)

But as for you, stand here by Me, and I will speak to you all the commandments, the statutes, and the judgments which you shall teach them, that they may observe them in the land which I am giving them to possess. Therefore you shall be careful to do as the LORD your God has commanded you; you shall not turn aside to the right hand or to the left. You shall walk in all the ways which the LORD your God has commanded you, that you may live and that it may be well with you, and that you may prolong your days in the land which you shall possess. Now this is the commandment, and these are the statutes and judgments which the LORD your God has commanded to teach you, that you may observe them in the land which you are crossing over to possess, that you may fear the LORD your God, to keep all His statutes and His commandments which I command you, you and your son and your grandson, all the days of your life, and that your days may be prolonged. Therefore hear, O Israel, and be careful to observe it, that it may be well with you, and that you may multiply greatly as the LORD God of your fathers has promised you – ‘a land flowing with milk and honey.’ (Dt. 5:31-6:3)

These texts make it very clear that the whole of the Old Covenant’s law was given for Old Covenant Israel in the Promised Land. All the laws of the Old Covenant are not necessarily trans-covenantal or trans-cultural–some are but not all of them. 
Second, consider the fact that the Old Testament itself prophesies the abrogation of the Old Covenant. We have seen this above in Jeremiah 31:31ff. Hosea 2:11 clearly prophesies that “all her [Old Covenant Israel’s] appointed feasts” will cease when the New Covenant days of which Hosea is speaking come.
Third, consider the New Testament teaching on the abrogation of the Old Covenant. As was stated above, the New Testament announces the abrogation of the Old Covenant in many places. For instance, 2 Corinthians 3:7-18; Galatians 3-4; Ephesians 2:14-16; and Hebrews 8-10 (cf. esp. 8:6-7, 13; 9:9-10, 15; 10:1, 15-18) are clear that the Old Covenant has been abrogated.
Fourth, consider the various functions of the Decalogue in redemptive history. As we have seen, the Decalogue functions as the basic, fundamental law of Old Covenant Israel, the basic, fundamental law of the New Covenant, and the basic, fundamental law for all men–the Moral Law. The essence of the Decalogue is both trans-covenantal and trans-cultural. It can function one way under the Old Covenant, with temporary appendages added to it, and other ways in other eras of redemptive history as well, without those appendages. We have seen this very phenomenon several times in our studies thus far.
These considerations lead us to the conclusion that since the Old Covenant has gone, so has its sanctions for capital punishment. Those laws were laws for Old Covenant Israel while in the Promised Land and since they fulfilled their purpose, they were abrogated when the New Covenant was inaugurated. These laws were covenantally conditioned, as are baptism and the Lord’s Supper, for instance, under the New Covenant. They were positive laws added to the Moral Law and given for a specific purpose, for a specific time, for a specific nation, under a specific covenant.
It does not follow, then, that since the Sabbath under the Old Covenant had the sanction of capital punishment attached to it, it is therefore ceremonial and a temporary law for ancient Israel alone. Other commands of the Decalogue, as we have seen, have the same sanction attached to them under the Old Covenant and they are not ceremonial and temporary. They are moral because based on God’s character as our creator and man as God’s image bearer. The same applies to the essence of the fourth commandment. The basis for these commands is not merely the Old Covenant but creation itself. And, as we have seen, creation-based ethics are age-long ethics, both trans-covenantal and trans-cultural.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>James, that is certainly a fair question. Since the death penalty in the OT for Sabbath violations, then wouldn&#8217;t it be the same under the NT? And if not, where does the NT say so? I hope that fairly represents your question.</p>
<p>My view is that the Sabbath was instituted on the seventh day of creation and yet the death penalty for violating it was not instituted until the Old Covenant came. There was a Sabbath in Exodus 16, for instance, prior to Mt. Sinai, and it did not have the death penalty attached to it for violations of it. In other words, a Sabbath can be in place without the death penalty in place. I also think that the OT prophesies a Sabbath under the New Covenant. Jer. 31:33 implies it (&#8220;I will write My law on their hearts&#8221;) and Isaiah 56 explicitly prophesies it. I will post my take on Is. 56 ASAP.</p>
<p>In the mean time, here is something I have written about the Sabbath and the death penalty issue you brought up:</p>
<p>•	The Sabbath had the death penalty attached to it under the Old Covenant, which implies that it was ceremonial and for Israel in the Promised Land alone.</p>
<p>Exodus 31:13-14 says:</p>
<p>Speak also to the children of Israel, saying: “Surely My Sabbaths you shall keep, for it is a sign between Me and you throughout your generations, that you may know that I am the LORD who sanctifies you. You shall keep the Sabbath, therefore, for it is holy to you. Everyone who profanes it shall surely be put to death; for whoever does any work on it, that person shall be cut off from among his people.” (Ex. 31:13-14)</p>
<p>Some may want to claim that since capital punishment is attached to Sabbath breaking, then the Sabbath is merely ceremonial and for Israel alone as God’s Old Covenant nation in the Promised Land. It cannot be proven, however, that if a commandment has the death penalty attached to it under the Old Covenant it is, therefore, merely ceremonial and for Israel under the Old Covenant alone. For instance, the third commandment has the sanction of capital punishment attached to it under the Old Covenant as well (Lev. 20:1-3). No one, however, argues against the perpetuity of the third commandment due to this. The fifth commandment also has the sanction of capital punishment attached to it under the Old Covenant (Ex. 21:12; Lev. 20:9; Dt. 21:18-21). No one, however, argues against the perpetuity of the fifth commandment due to this. The seventh commandment has the sanction of capital punishment attached to it under the Old Covenant also (Lev. 20:10; Dt. 22:21-22). Again, no one argues against the perpetuity of the seventh commandment due to this. The Decalogue formed the heart of Old Covenant Israel’s law. It had various appendages added to it to administrate the unique redemptive-historical circumstances it was given in. These redemptive-historical appendages were added to the Decalogue under the Old Covenant “until the time of reformation” (Heb. 9:10b). Simply because some commands of the Decalogue have the sanction of capital punishment attached to them under the Old Covenant does not mean they cannot function in other eras of redemptive history without those sanctions. The New Testament bears this out amply.<br />
But this brings rise to a very important question: Does the Bible abrogate the death penalty for various offenses that were capital crimes under the Old Covenant? And if so, how? I believe it does, even while maintaining some of the very same laws under the New Covenant. This can be seen if we consider the unique character of Old Covenant Israel’s law, the abrogation of the Old Covenant law according to Old Testament prophecy and New Testament fulfillment, and the functions of the Decalogue in redemptive history.<br />
First, consider that the Old Covenant’s law was given to ancient Israel to be applied in the Promised Land. Several Old Testament passages teach this very clearly.</p>
<p>Now, O Israel, listen to the statutes and the judgments which I teach you to observe, that you may live, and go in and possess the land which the LORD God of your fathers is giving you. You shall not add to the word which I command you, nor take from it, that you may keep the commandments of the LORD your God which I command you. Your eyes have seen what the LORD did at Baal Peor; for the LORD your God has destroyed from among you all the men who followed Baal of Peor. But you who held fast to the LORD your God are alive today, every one of you. Surely I have taught you statutes and judgments, just as the LORD my God commanded me, that you should act according to them in the land which you go to possess. (Dt. 4:1-5)</p>
<p>And the LORD commanded me at that time to teach you statutes and judgments, that you might observe them in the land which you cross over to possess. (Dt. 4:14)</p>
<p>But as for you, stand here by Me, and I will speak to you all the commandments, the statutes, and the judgments which you shall teach them, that they may observe them in the land which I am giving them to possess. Therefore you shall be careful to do as the LORD your God has commanded you; you shall not turn aside to the right hand or to the left. You shall walk in all the ways which the LORD your God has commanded you, that you may live and that it may be well with you, and that you may prolong your days in the land which you shall possess. Now this is the commandment, and these are the statutes and judgments which the LORD your God has commanded to teach you, that you may observe them in the land which you are crossing over to possess, that you may fear the LORD your God, to keep all His statutes and His commandments which I command you, you and your son and your grandson, all the days of your life, and that your days may be prolonged. Therefore hear, O Israel, and be careful to observe it, that it may be well with you, and that you may multiply greatly as the LORD God of your fathers has promised you – ‘a land flowing with milk and honey.’ (Dt. 5:31-6:3)</p>
<p>These texts make it very clear that the whole of the Old Covenant’s law was given for Old Covenant Israel in the Promised Land. All the laws of the Old Covenant are not necessarily trans-covenantal or trans-cultural–some are but not all of them.<br />
Second, consider the fact that the Old Testament itself prophesies the abrogation of the Old Covenant. We have seen this above in Jeremiah 31:31ff. Hosea 2:11 clearly prophesies that “all her [Old Covenant Israel’s] appointed feasts” will cease when the New Covenant days of which Hosea is speaking come.<br />
Third, consider the New Testament teaching on the abrogation of the Old Covenant. As was stated above, the New Testament announces the abrogation of the Old Covenant in many places. For instance, 2 Corinthians 3:7-18; Galatians 3-4; Ephesians 2:14-16; and Hebrews 8-10 (cf. esp. 8:6-7, 13; 9:9-10, 15; 10:1, 15-18) are clear that the Old Covenant has been abrogated.<br />
Fourth, consider the various functions of the Decalogue in redemptive history. As we have seen, the Decalogue functions as the basic, fundamental law of Old Covenant Israel, the basic, fundamental law of the New Covenant, and the basic, fundamental law for all men–the Moral Law. The essence of the Decalogue is both trans-covenantal and trans-cultural. It can function one way under the Old Covenant, with temporary appendages added to it, and other ways in other eras of redemptive history as well, without those appendages. We have seen this very phenomenon several times in our studies thus far.<br />
These considerations lead us to the conclusion that since the Old Covenant has gone, so has its sanctions for capital punishment. Those laws were laws for Old Covenant Israel while in the Promised Land and since they fulfilled their purpose, they were abrogated when the New Covenant was inaugurated. These laws were covenantally conditioned, as are baptism and the Lord’s Supper, for instance, under the New Covenant. They were positive laws added to the Moral Law and given for a specific purpose, for a specific time, for a specific nation, under a specific covenant.<br />
It does not follow, then, that since the Sabbath under the Old Covenant had the sanction of capital punishment attached to it, it is therefore ceremonial and a temporary law for ancient Israel alone. Other commands of the Decalogue, as we have seen, have the same sanction attached to them under the Old Covenant and they are not ceremonial and temporary. They are moral because based on God’s character as our creator and man as God’s image bearer. The same applies to the essence of the fourth commandment. The basis for these commands is not merely the Old Covenant but creation itself. And, as we have seen, creation-based ethics are age-long ethics, both trans-covenantal and trans-cultural.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: James		</title>
		<link>/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/#comment-127</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2011 05:21:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=566#comment-127</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Since God gave a clear definition of the Sabbath being the 7th day and showed it was attached to the exact 7th day of creation and also God made it deadly clear that if this sabbath was broken then Jew that break it should die.
 
Then what is the New testaments clear definition of a new sabbath? Since God is deadly clear in the OT then I would expect the same God, that doesn&#039;t change, to give a clear new definition. Peoples lives are at stake.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Since God gave a clear definition of the Sabbath being the 7th day and showed it was attached to the exact 7th day of creation and also God made it deadly clear that if this sabbath was broken then Jew that break it should die.</p>
<p>Then what is the New testaments clear definition of a new sabbath? Since God is deadly clear in the OT then I would expect the same God, that doesn&#8217;t change, to give a clear new definition. Peoples lives are at stake.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Richard Barcellos		</title>
		<link>/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/#comment-126</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2011 18:54:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=566#comment-126</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[James,

We were discussing elements of a book entitled &quot;The Christian and the Sabbath.&quot; We hold that there is a Sabbath for Christians, the author of the book we were discussing does not. The issues we discussed are foundational to a Christian Sabbath.

I hope this helps.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>James,</p>
<p>We were discussing elements of a book entitled &#8220;The Christian and the Sabbath.&#8221; We hold that there is a Sabbath for Christians, the author of the book we were discussing does not. The issues we discussed are foundational to a Christian Sabbath.</p>
<p>I hope this helps.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: James		</title>
		<link>/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/#comment-125</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2011 16:20:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=566#comment-125</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There was NO discussion about Christian Sabbath. Why is it labeled &quot;A Christian Sabbath?&quot;]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There was NO discussion about Christian Sabbath. Why is it labeled &#8220;A Christian Sabbath?&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Rich Barcellos		</title>
		<link>/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/#comment-124</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rich Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2011 18:26:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=566#comment-124</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Doug,

Great question! Col. 2:16 is a very important text in this discussion. Here (below) is something I wrote elsewhere, which attempts to put the triad of Col. 2:16 in a wider biblical/canonical context. I think this is crutial in order to understnd what Paul means in Col. 2:16.

&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;
The OT clearly prophesies the abrogation and cessation of ancient Israel’s Sabbaths. It does so in Hos. 2:11, which says, “I will also cause all her mirth to cease, her feast days, her New Moons, her Sabbaths--all her appointed feasts.” We will make several observations that bear this out. First, Hosea’s prophecy is dealing with the days of the New Covenant. The phrase “in that day” (vv. 16, 18, 21) is used prophetically of New Covenant days in Is. 22:20. Revelation 3:7 quotes Is. 22:22 and applies it to Christ. The prophecy in Is. 22:20 mentions the Lord’s servant, who is Christ. Isaiah 22:20-22 says:

Then it shall be in that day, that I will call My servant Eliakim the son of Hilkiah; I will clothe him with your robe and strengthen him with your belt; I will commit your responsibility into his hand. He shall be a father to the inhabitants of Jerusalem and to the house of Judah. The key of the house of David I will lay on his shoulder; so he shall open, and no one shall shut; and he shall shut, and no one shall open. (Is. 22:20-22)

Revelation 3:7, quoting Is. 22:22, says:

And to the angel of the church in Philadelphia write, “These things says He who is holy, He who is true, He who has the key of David, He who opens and no one shuts, and shuts and no one opens.” (Rev. 3:7)

The phrase, “in that day,” refers to the days of Christ–the days of the New Covenant. Paul references Hos. 1:10 and 2:23 in Rom. 9:25, applying them to Christians. “As He says also in Hosea: ‘I will call them My people, who were not My people, and her beloved, who was not beloved’” (Rom. 9:25). Peter references Hos. 1:9-10 and 2:23 in 1 Pet. 2:10 and applies them to Christians as well. He says, “who once were not a people but are now the people of God, who had not obtained mercy but now have obtained mercy” (1 Pet. 2:10). Hosea is clearly speaking of New Covenant days. According to the NT usage of Hosea, he is speaking of the time in redemptive history when God will bring Gentiles and Jews into a saving relationship with himself. Much of the NT deals with this very issue.
Second, Hos. 2:11 clearly prophesies the abrogation of Old Covenant Israel’s Sabbaths, along with “all her appointed feasts.” Hosea uses a triad of terms (“feast days, New Moons, Sabbaths”) that is used many places in the OT (1 Chron. 23:31; 2 Chron. 2:4; 31:3; Neh. 10:33; and Is. 1:13-14). Clearly, he is speaking of the abrogation of Old Covenant ceremonial laws. When the Old Covenant goes, Israel’s feast days, New Moons, Sabbaths, and all her appointed feasts go with it.
Third, the NT confirms this understanding of Hos. 2:11. It uses this triad of terms in Col. 2:16, which says, “So let no one judge you in food or in drink, or regarding a festival or a new moon or Sabbaths.” In the context, Paul is combating those who were attempting to impose Old Covenant ceremonial law on New Covenant Christians. So Col. 2:16 is clear NT language that sees Hosea’s prophecy as fulfilled. It is of interest to note that Paul uses the plural for Sabbath in Col. 2:16 (sabba,twn). It is not too hard to assume that Paul had the OT triad in mind and Hosea’s prophecy while penning these words. The NT announces the abrogation of the Old Covenant in many places. For instance, 2 Cor. 3:7-18; Gal. 3-4; Eph. 2:14-16; and Heb. 8-10 (cf. esp. 8:6-7, 13; 9:9-10, 15; 10:1, 15-18) are clear that the Old Covenant has been abrogated.

But now He [Christ] has obtained a more excellent ministry, inasmuch as He is also Mediator of a better covenant [the New Covenant], which was established on better promises. For if that first covenant [the Old Covenant] had been faultless, then no place would have been sought for a second. (Heb. 8:6-7)

In that He says, “A new covenant,” He has made the first obsolete. Now what is becoming obsolete and growing old is ready to vanish away. (Heb. 8:13)

It was symbolic for the present time in which both gifts and sacrifices are offered which cannot make him who performed the service perfect in regard to the conscience--concerned only with foods and drinks, various washings, and fleshly ordinances imposed until the time of reformation. (Heb. 9:9-10)

And for this reason He is the Mediator of the new covenant, by means of death, for the redemption of the transgressions under the first covenant, that those who are called may receive the promise of the eternal inheritance. (Heb. 9:15)

For the law, having a shadow of the good things to come, and not the very image of the things, can never with these same sacrifices, which they offer continually year by year, make those who approach perfect. (Heb. 10:1)

But the Holy Spirit also witnesses to us; for after He had said before, “This is the covenant that I will make with them after those days, says the LORD: I will put My laws into their hearts, and in their minds I will write them,” then He adds, “Their sins and their lawless deeds I will remember no more.” Now where there is remission of these, there is no longer an offering for sin. (Heb. 10:15-18)

The Old Covenant and all its ceremonies are obsolete and have vanished away (Heb. 8:13). Taking these passages and Col. 2:16 together, they clearly teach that when the Old Covenant goes, the triad of Col. 2:16 goes as well.
&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;

After arguing that the Old Testament also prophesies the perpetuity and continuation of a Sabbath under the New Covenant I concluded with the words below:

&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;
The OT teaches us that Old Covenant Israel’s Sabbaths will one day pass away because the Old Covenant will pass away. But it also presents us with a Sabbath for the New Covenant. The Sabbath, therefore, functions under different eras of redemptive history. This should not shock us since we have seen that the Sabbath has its roots in that which does not change–creation and its ethical implications for man created in God’s image. Geerhardus Vos agrees, when he says:

It must be remembered that the Sabbath, though a world-aged observance, has passed through the various phases of the development of redemption, remaining the same in essence but modified as to its form, as the new state of affairs at each point might require. The Sabbath is not only the most venerable, it is likewise the most living of all the sacramental realities of our religion. It has faithfully accompanied the people of God on their march though the ages. 

Granting the validity of our findings, the question of a Sabbath under the New Covenant is settled. The issue now becomes, what does the New Covenant’s Sabbath look like? Since the Old Covenant’s Sabbath took on unique, redemptive-historical elements, can we not expect the New Covenant’s Sabbath to do the same? Since Christ, as the Son of Man, is Lord of the Sabbath, should we not expect the Sabbath to bear distinct marks of his lordship? These are crucial questions but beyond the scope of this article. It is hoped that this study has provided an OT redemptive-historical grid through which the breadth and diversity of the subject of the Sabbath can be viewed and with which the NT can now be properly examined.
&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;&#062;

I hope this helps.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Doug,</p>
<p>Great question! Col. 2:16 is a very important text in this discussion. Here (below) is something I wrote elsewhere, which attempts to put the triad of Col. 2:16 in a wider biblical/canonical context. I think this is crutial in order to understnd what Paul means in Col. 2:16.</p>
<p>&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;<br />
The OT clearly prophesies the abrogation and cessation of ancient Israel’s Sabbaths. It does so in Hos. 2:11, which says, “I will also cause all her mirth to cease, her feast days, her New Moons, her Sabbaths&#8211;all her appointed feasts.” We will make several observations that bear this out. First, Hosea’s prophecy is dealing with the days of the New Covenant. The phrase “in that day” (vv. 16, 18, 21) is used prophetically of New Covenant days in Is. 22:20. Revelation 3:7 quotes Is. 22:22 and applies it to Christ. The prophecy in Is. 22:20 mentions the Lord’s servant, who is Christ. Isaiah 22:20-22 says:</p>
<p>Then it shall be in that day, that I will call My servant Eliakim the son of Hilkiah; I will clothe him with your robe and strengthen him with your belt; I will commit your responsibility into his hand. He shall be a father to the inhabitants of Jerusalem and to the house of Judah. The key of the house of David I will lay on his shoulder; so he shall open, and no one shall shut; and he shall shut, and no one shall open. (Is. 22:20-22)</p>
<p>Revelation 3:7, quoting Is. 22:22, says:</p>
<p>And to the angel of the church in Philadelphia write, “These things says He who is holy, He who is true, He who has the key of David, He who opens and no one shuts, and shuts and no one opens.” (Rev. 3:7)</p>
<p>The phrase, “in that day,” refers to the days of Christ–the days of the New Covenant. Paul references Hos. 1:10 and 2:23 in Rom. 9:25, applying them to Christians. “As He says also in Hosea: ‘I will call them My people, who were not My people, and her beloved, who was not beloved’” (Rom. 9:25). Peter references Hos. 1:9-10 and 2:23 in 1 Pet. 2:10 and applies them to Christians as well. He says, “who once were not a people but are now the people of God, who had not obtained mercy but now have obtained mercy” (1 Pet. 2:10). Hosea is clearly speaking of New Covenant days. According to the NT usage of Hosea, he is speaking of the time in redemptive history when God will bring Gentiles and Jews into a saving relationship with himself. Much of the NT deals with this very issue.<br />
Second, Hos. 2:11 clearly prophesies the abrogation of Old Covenant Israel’s Sabbaths, along with “all her appointed feasts.” Hosea uses a triad of terms (“feast days, New Moons, Sabbaths”) that is used many places in the OT (1 Chron. 23:31; 2 Chron. 2:4; 31:3; Neh. 10:33; and Is. 1:13-14). Clearly, he is speaking of the abrogation of Old Covenant ceremonial laws. When the Old Covenant goes, Israel’s feast days, New Moons, Sabbaths, and all her appointed feasts go with it.<br />
Third, the NT confirms this understanding of Hos. 2:11. It uses this triad of terms in Col. 2:16, which says, “So let no one judge you in food or in drink, or regarding a festival or a new moon or Sabbaths.” In the context, Paul is combating those who were attempting to impose Old Covenant ceremonial law on New Covenant Christians. So Col. 2:16 is clear NT language that sees Hosea’s prophecy as fulfilled. It is of interest to note that Paul uses the plural for Sabbath in Col. 2:16 (sabba,twn). It is not too hard to assume that Paul had the OT triad in mind and Hosea’s prophecy while penning these words. The NT announces the abrogation of the Old Covenant in many places. For instance, 2 Cor. 3:7-18; Gal. 3-4; Eph. 2:14-16; and Heb. 8-10 (cf. esp. 8:6-7, 13; 9:9-10, 15; 10:1, 15-18) are clear that the Old Covenant has been abrogated.</p>
<p>But now He [Christ] has obtained a more excellent ministry, inasmuch as He is also Mediator of a better covenant [the New Covenant], which was established on better promises. For if that first covenant [the Old Covenant] had been faultless, then no place would have been sought for a second. (Heb. 8:6-7)</p>
<p>In that He says, “A new covenant,” He has made the first obsolete. Now what is becoming obsolete and growing old is ready to vanish away. (Heb. 8:13)</p>
<p>It was symbolic for the present time in which both gifts and sacrifices are offered which cannot make him who performed the service perfect in regard to the conscience&#8211;concerned only with foods and drinks, various washings, and fleshly ordinances imposed until the time of reformation. (Heb. 9:9-10)</p>
<p>And for this reason He is the Mediator of the new covenant, by means of death, for the redemption of the transgressions under the first covenant, that those who are called may receive the promise of the eternal inheritance. (Heb. 9:15)</p>
<p>For the law, having a shadow of the good things to come, and not the very image of the things, can never with these same sacrifices, which they offer continually year by year, make those who approach perfect. (Heb. 10:1)</p>
<p>But the Holy Spirit also witnesses to us; for after He had said before, “This is the covenant that I will make with them after those days, says the LORD: I will put My laws into their hearts, and in their minds I will write them,” then He adds, “Their sins and their lawless deeds I will remember no more.” Now where there is remission of these, there is no longer an offering for sin. (Heb. 10:15-18)</p>
<p>The Old Covenant and all its ceremonies are obsolete and have vanished away (Heb. 8:13). Taking these passages and Col. 2:16 together, they clearly teach that when the Old Covenant goes, the triad of Col. 2:16 goes as well.<br />
&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;</p>
<p>After arguing that the Old Testament also prophesies the perpetuity and continuation of a Sabbath under the New Covenant I concluded with the words below:</p>
<p>&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;<br />
The OT teaches us that Old Covenant Israel’s Sabbaths will one day pass away because the Old Covenant will pass away. But it also presents us with a Sabbath for the New Covenant. The Sabbath, therefore, functions under different eras of redemptive history. This should not shock us since we have seen that the Sabbath has its roots in that which does not change–creation and its ethical implications for man created in God’s image. Geerhardus Vos agrees, when he says:</p>
<p>It must be remembered that the Sabbath, though a world-aged observance, has passed through the various phases of the development of redemption, remaining the same in essence but modified as to its form, as the new state of affairs at each point might require. The Sabbath is not only the most venerable, it is likewise the most living of all the sacramental realities of our religion. It has faithfully accompanied the people of God on their march though the ages. </p>
<p>Granting the validity of our findings, the question of a Sabbath under the New Covenant is settled. The issue now becomes, what does the New Covenant’s Sabbath look like? Since the Old Covenant’s Sabbath took on unique, redemptive-historical elements, can we not expect the New Covenant’s Sabbath to do the same? Since Christ, as the Son of Man, is Lord of the Sabbath, should we not expect the Sabbath to bear distinct marks of his lordship? These are crucial questions but beyond the scope of this article. It is hoped that this study has provided an OT redemptive-historical grid through which the breadth and diversity of the subject of the Sabbath can be viewed and with which the NT can now be properly examined.<br />
&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;</p>
<p>I hope this helps.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jim Butler		</title>
		<link>/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/#comment-123</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jim Butler]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2011 16:59:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=566#comment-123</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Doug,

The standard works on the Christian Sabbath deal with Col 2:16.  As well, commentaries by confessional men also explain Col 2:16 with reference to the Christian Sabbath.

jim]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Doug,</p>
<p>The standard works on the Christian Sabbath deal with Col 2:16.  As well, commentaries by confessional men also explain Col 2:16 with reference to the Christian Sabbath.</p>
<p>jim</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Doug Skiles		</title>
		<link>/podcast-7-a-christian-sabbath/#comment-122</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Doug Skiles]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2011 01:55:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=566#comment-122</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Interesting discussion, but unless I missed it, Colossians 2:16 was not mentioned,&quot;Do not let anyone judge you with regard to a Sabbath Day&quot;. Comments?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Interesting discussion, but unless I missed it, Colossians 2:16 was not mentioned,&#8221;Do not let anyone judge you with regard to a Sabbath Day&#8221;. Comments?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
