<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Sermons | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/sermons/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 May 2011 14:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Sermons | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 5 of 5)</title>
		<link>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-5/</link>
					<comments>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-5/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2011 14:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sermons]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bin Laden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[osama]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=935</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>What practical conclusions should we draw from Proverbs 11:10 (you can also listen to or download my message on Bin Laden from our church’s web site)? Proverbs 11:10 When it goes well with the righteous, the city rejoices, And when the wicked perish, there is joyful shouting. (1) Men rejoice and ought to rejoice in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-5/">Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 5 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What practical conclusions should we draw from Proverbs 11:10 (<a title="Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden is Dead - Or Not? Sermon" href="http://www.hbcowensboro.org/sermon/the-death-of-osama-bin-laden/" target="_self" rel="noopener">you can also listen to or download my message on Bin Laden from our church’s web site</a>)?</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Proverbs 11:10</strong> When it goes well with the righteous, the city rejoices, And when the wicked perish, there is joyful shouting.</p></blockquote>
<p><em><strong>(1)	Men rejoice and ought to rejoice in the judgment of the wicked.</strong></em></p>
<p>This is why a blanket or general condemnation of all rejoicing over the killing of Osama Bin Laden is not biblical or balanced.  The Bible teaches that God’s judgment of the wicked and the freedom it gives us from their oppression and danger ought to make us praise God.  It is both unnatural and unrighteous if it does not.</p>
<p><em><strong>(2)	This delight in the judgment of the wicked justice confirms the justice and righteousness of God’s judgment of the wicked.</strong></em></p>
<p>Rejoicing, being glad, and feeling satisfaction at the judgment of the wicked is the natural, instinctive, and necessary response of creatures made in the image of God of justice to the demise of men like Hitler, Stalin, and Bin Laden.  It cannot be repressed and ought not to be suppressed.  This satisfaction and joy is the inner and self-attesting confirmation that God’s judgment on wicked is both righteous and just.</p>
<p>Those newspaper headlines which read something like, <em>Rot in hell</em>, may be public and published violations of the command not to rejoice in the fall of our enemies.  I think they are!  But they are also something else.  Here’s what they make me want to say:  <em>Oh, so now we believe in hell!  We believe in hell for Osama Bin Laden.  So now the question is not whether hell is just.  Now we admit that hell is just for some people.  Now the only question is not whether there is a hell, but who should go there?</em></p>
<p>So our innate response of satisfaction at justice being done on Bin Laden ought not to be condemned or repressed, but it ought to make us admit that we do believe in hell.  There is something deep and indelible in our natures which affirms that hell is just and right.</p>
<p><em><strong>(3)	This innate sense of the justice of God’s judgment on the wicked confirms the propriety of our sense of guilt when we know ourselves to be sinful.</strong></em></p>
<p>But now let me come even closer to us personally.  This undeniable sense of satisfied justice that we feel in the killing of Bin Laden means that our own feelings of guilt for our sins are not false feelings of guilt.  They are the authentic expressions of the work of the law written on our hearts.  When your heart tells you that you deserve punishment for sins you have committed, when it accuses you of not loving God and not loving your neighbor in all sorts of clear and flagrant sins, listen to it!  It is literally the voice of God to you.  It is not feelings of false guilt.  It is the echo of the justice of almighty God.</p>
<p><em><strong>(4)	All this confirms that we understand by nature the necessity of a substitionary curse-bearer if we are ever to be saved.</strong></em></p>
<p>This just sense of guilt and condemnation is a primary assertion of our natures as made in the image of God.  This indelible sense of guilt tells us that we need someone to bear the punishment and curse of our sins if we are ever to be saved.  We do not know the gospel by nature.  We do not know that there is such a substitutionary curse-bearer by nature.  We could never hope that there is such a Savior from nature.  But we do know by nature that we need such a Savior, such a curse-bearer, such a substitute, and such a gospel.  The great news is that such a Savior exists and will receive us if we will to Him acknowledging your guilt and need.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-5/">Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 5 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 4 of 5)</title>
		<link>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-4/</link>
					<comments>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-4/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2011 14:00:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sermons]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bin Laden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[osama]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=933</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Under my third heading I want to consider the teaching and lessons we may gain from the verses (you can also listen to or download my message on Bin Laden from our church’s web site). I think it will be best to do this in reverse order. We will consider, first, Proverbs 24:17 and then, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-4/">Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 4 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Under my third heading I want to consider the teaching and lessons we may gain from the verses (<a title="Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden is Dead - Or Not? Sermon" href="http://www.hbcowensboro.org/sermon/the-death-of-osama-bin-laden/" target="_self" rel="noopener">you can also listen to or download my message on Bin Laden from our church’s web site</a>).  I think it will be best to do this in reverse order.  We will consider, first, Proverbs 24:17 and then, Proverbs 11:10.</p>
<p>What practical conclusions should we draw from Proverbs 24:17?</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Proverbs 24:17</strong> Do not rejoice when your enemy falls, And do not let your heart be glad when he stumbles</p></blockquote>
<p><em><strong>(1)	Proverbs 24:17 warns us never to be guilty of rejoicing out of a vengeful, vindictive, and bitter spirit toward our enemies.</strong></em></p>
<p>I am convinced that there is a lot of imbalanced thinking with regard to the issue of forgiveness in our day.  On the basis of some of this imbalanced thinking we should even have had to feel obligated to forgive Osama Bin Laden while he was in the very process of planning further assaults on our country.  I believe the Bible requires no such thing and that repentance is the necessary condition of forgiveness both in our relation with God and with other human beings.</p>
<p>This does not mean, however, that we are ever allowed to entertain bitter and vengeful feelings toward our enemies.  Vengeance in any hands but God’s and His ministers is hard-hearted sadism.  While we cannot actually forgive our enemies, we must stand ready to forgive our enemies and love them just as God loves His enemies.  In this way we must be perfect as our Father in heaven.</p>
<p>This is what Paul so clearly commands in Romans 12:19-21.</p>
<blockquote><p>Never take your own revenge, beloved, but leave room for the wrath of God, for it is written, &#8220;VENGEANCE IS MINE, I WILL REPAY,&#8221; says the Lord. &#8220;BUT IF YOUR ENEMY IS HUNGRY, FEED HIM, AND IF HE IS THIRSTY, GIVE HIM A DRINK; FOR IN SO DOING YOU WILL HEAP BURNING COALS ON HIS HEAD.&#8221; Do not be overcome by evil, but overcome evil with good.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is, in fact, the secret to dealing with the deep hurts the sins of others can cause us in this life and with the indignation those hurts provoke in us.  My brother or sister, leave room for the wrath of God.  Here is what you do with your hurt and anger.  Take it in your spiritual hands and place it in the hands of God.  Every in justice will receive from Him a just recompense.  God will judge those sins either at the day of judgment, or He has judged those sins at the cross of Christ. Either way the vengeance taken should be more than enough to turn your feelings vengeance into feelings of pity that will enable you to love your enemy.</p>
<p><em><strong>(2)	Proverbs 24:17 warns us never to be guilty of rejoicing out of a self-righteous or self-sufficient attitude toward our enemies.</strong></em></p>
<p>We do not rejoice and we must never rejoice out of any sense that we are better than the wicked.  We are not better in wisdom, or in righteousness, or in power than those upon whose God’s judgments have fallen.  This is what is properly called “gloating,” and we must never be guilty of it.  Rather, we must admit that we might have been guilty—perhaps we have been guilty of the very folly, ungodliness, and weakness for which God has now judged the wicked.  We cannot but rejoice that we are freed from their danger and oppression, but we must never rejoice as if we were better than they.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-4/">Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 4 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 3 of 5)</title>
		<link>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-3/</link>
					<comments>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-3/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2011 14:30:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sermons]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bin Laden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[osama]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=930</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We are looking at two verses which provide a balanced, biblical response to the death of Bin Laden (you can also listen to or download my message on Bin Laden from our church&#8217;s web site). In this blog post I want to compare and contrast the two verses. This will help us, I hope, reconcile [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-3/">Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 3 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We are looking at two verses which provide a balanced, biblical response to the death of Bin Laden (<a title="Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden is Dead - Or Not? Sermon" href="http://www.hbcowensboro.org/sermon/the-death-of-osama-bin-laden/" target="_self" rel="noopener">you can also listen to or download my message on Bin Laden from our church&#8217;s web site</a>).  In this blog post I want to compare and contrast the two verses.  This will help us, I hope, reconcile their teaching.  Having in the previous post cast aside a superficial way of reconciling of the two verses, let us see if there is not a better way to release the tension we feel between them.
</p>
<blockquote><p><strong></strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong>II.	The Verses Compared</strong></p>
<p>We ought not to shy away from difficulties in the Bible.  Nor should we feel that genuine Christianity requires that we check our brain at the door.  True lovers of the Bible will find in tensions and difficulties like those we now face an opportunity to lay aside superficial views of Scripture and go more deeply into the truth of the Word of God.  In seeking to go deeper into the Word there is no substitute for extended meditation on the Word of God.  As I thought about it, three helpful thoughts occurred to me in the comparison of Proverbs 11:10 with 24:17.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Proverbs 11:10</strong> When it goes well with the righteous, the city rejoices, And when the wicked perish, there is joyful shouting.<br />
<strong>Proverbs 24:17</strong> Do not rejoice when your enemy falls, And do not let your heart be glad when he stumbles</p></blockquote>
<p>I see here one similarity and three contrasts.</p>
<p><em><strong>The first thought:  The emotion described in the two verses is the same</strong></em>.  There is no escape from the tension between the two verses	by trying to contrast the emotions commanded in the two verses.  Yes, the words for joy and the expression of joy are different, but they convey the same concept of exultant joy.  The words used for joy and joyful shouting found in these two verses are synonyms and describe fundamentally the same human emotion.  They are clearly parallel and synonymous words in the Hebrew Bible and are used in parallel in many places in the Old Testament.  There is no distinction between the two verses at this point.</p>
<p>Emotions are not in themselves good or bad.  I believe I could show you in the Bible if time permitted that every human emotion may be either good or bad depending on its situation and motivation.  It is the situation and motivation of human emotions that make them good and bad&#8212;not the emotion itself.  Exultant joy may be very good, or it may be very bad.  It must be one or the other, but it may be either.</p>
<p>Take the emotion of anger.  We may be angry at the man who murdered 3000 thousand innocent lives on 9/11.  We may be angry that this wicked man has now been brought to justice.  It is the same emotion, but in the one case it is good, while in the other case it is bad.  Even so it is with the emotion of joy.</p>
<p><em><strong>The second thought:  The rejoicing in Proverbs 11:10 is public, while the rejoicing in Proverbs 24:17 is private</strong></em>.  The first text (Proverbs 11:10) speaks of a public, corporate, and civil rejoicing.  Look at it closely.  Who is rejoicing in the first text?  <em><strong>The city!</strong></em> The second text is in striking contrast to this.  Let me give you an expanded Waldron Literal translation of Proverbs 24:17:   <em>In fall of your (singular) enemy not shall you (singular) rejoice; and in his overthrow not shall your (singular) heart shout with joy. </em>All of the pronouns here are singular.  This text speaks of a private and individual rejoicing.  The difference or contrast is clear.</p>
<p>In American football there are rules against excessive celebration after scoring a touchdown.  These rules, however, apply against the player on the field and not against the crowd in the stands.  Even so the rejoicing in Proverbs 11:10 is by the crowd in the stands and not by the player on the field.  We can hardly even imagine it, but suppose one of the Navy Seals who killed Bin Laden had done a little jig over his body and chanted <em>You&#8217;re dead!  You&#8217;re dead!</em> That is a very different thing than the couple whose son was killed in the tragedy of 9/11 sitting silent on their couch with a sense of exultant joy and relief filling their hearts.</p>
<p><em><strong>The third thought: The rejoicing in Proverbs 11:10 has a moral cause, while the rejoicing in Proverbs 24:17 has a personal cause</strong></em>.  Again the contrast is clear.   Proverbs 11:10 speaks of rejoicing over the destruction of <em><strong>the wicked (who are contrasted with the righteous)</strong></em>.  Proverbs 24:17 speaks of rejoicing over the destruction of <em><strong>your enemy</strong></em>.  Notice the personal character of this rejoicing seems emphasized by the very next verse, Proverbs 24:18.  &#8220;Or the LORD will see it and be displeased, And turn His anger away from him.&#8221;  It may be true that your enemy is also wicked.  But is your rejoicing over his fall because of his wickedness of because of your enmity?  That is the great question.  That is one main thing that distinguishes Proverbs 11:10 from Proverbs 24:17.</p>
<p>I need to qualify this last point.  It is not wrong to feel a sense of gladness and shout for joy when God judges an enemy who was an imminent threat to you, your family, or your nation.  This is a different thing than merely rejoicing that old scores of no present consequence were settled and that old enemies of no present danger are destroyed.</p>
<p><em><strong>The fourth thought:  The rejoicing in Proverbs 11:10 is over the perishing of the wicked, while the rejoicing in Proverbs 24:17 is over our enemy&#8217;s merely stumbling. </strong></em></p>
<p>Proverbs 24:18 makes clear that the calamity which overtakes our enemy is not complete or irreversible.  While the perishing of the wicked in Proverbs 11:10 is final, the stumbling of our enemy is not.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Proverbs 24:17-18</strong> Do not rejoice when your enemy falls, And do not let your heart be glad when he stumbles; Or the LORD will see it and be displeased, And turn His anger away from him.</p></blockquote>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-3/">Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 3 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-3/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 2 of 5)</title>
		<link>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-2/</link>
					<comments>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 15:00:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sermons]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bin Laden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[osama]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=922</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In this blog series we are looking to provide a balanced, biblical response to Bin Laden&#8217;s death (you can also listen to or download my message on Bin Laden from our church&#8217;s web site). I want to introduce the verses under my first heading: I. The Verses Contemplated Here are the two verses. I want [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-2/">Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 2 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this blog series we are looking to provide a balanced, biblical response to Bin Laden&#8217;s death  (<a title="Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden is Dead - Or Not? Sermon" href="http://www.hbcowensboro.org/sermon/the-death-of-osama-bin-laden/" target="_self" rel="noopener">you can also listen to or download my message on Bin Laden from our church&#8217;s web site</a>). I want to introduce the verses under my first heading:</p>
<p><strong>I.	The Verses Contemplated</strong></p>
<p>Here are the two verses.  I want you simply to contemplate or look at them for a few moments.  Here they are in the NASB
</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Proverbs 11:10</strong> When it goes well with the righteous, the city rejoices, And when the wicked perish, there is joyful shouting.<br />
<strong>Proverbs 24:17</strong> Do not rejoice when your enemy falls, And do not let your heart be glad when he stumbles</p></blockquote>
<p>Here they are in the New English Translation</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Proverbs 11:10</strong> When the righteous do well, the city rejoices; when the wicked perish, there is joy.<br />
<strong>Proverbs 24:17</strong> Do not rejoice when your enemy falls, and when he stumbles do not let your heart rejoice</p></blockquote>
<p>Here they are in the ESV:</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Proverbs 11:10</strong> When it goes well with the righteous, the city rejoices, and when the wicked perish there are shouts of gladness.<br />
<strong>Proverbs 24:17</strong> Do not rejoice when your enemy falls, And do not let your heart be glad when he stumbles</p></blockquote>
<p>Finally, here they are in the Waldron Literal Translation:</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Proverbs 11:10</strong> In good of righteous ones rejoices a city and in destroying of wicked ones shouts (of joy)<br />
<strong>Proverbs 24:17</strong> In fall of your enemy not shall you rejoice; and in his overthrow not shall your heart shout with joy</p></blockquote>
<p>As you can see, there is no difficulty with the translation with these verses.  Each of the above translations render them so as to produce the same thoughts.  The problem is not with the translation of these verses, but with the meaning of them.  It is especially with how both verses can be true.  The problem is how the Bible can affirm both these things.</p>
<p>There is one possibility which may occur to some of you and which might appear to remove the difficulty.  The first verse (Proverbs 11:10) is simply descriptive.  That is, it directly commands nothing.  It simply states what is the case.  Someone might argue conceivably that the text is merely descriptive and not normative.  They might say that it simply affirms what is and not what should be.  They might interpret the verse like this:  <em>&#8230;when the wicked perish, there is joyful shouting, but there should not be&#8230;</em></p>
<p>This would provide a satisfying resolution of the tension we feel as we look at the two verses together&#8212;if it were true.  I am convinced, however, that it is not.  Here is why.  I have three reasons.</p>
<p>First, Proverbs 11:10 itself suggests that it not merely descriptive.  Look at it again.  The first half of the verse says:  <em>When it goes well with the righteous, the city rejoices&#8230;</em> Should we understand this to mean similarly, <em>When it goes well with the righteous, the city rejoices, but they should not!</em> I don not think so.</p>
<p>Second, the following verse suggests that this rejoicing is properly motivated and thus not to be reproached.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Proverbs 11:11</strong> By the blessing of the upright a city is exalted, But by the mouth of the wicked it is torn down.</p></blockquote>
<p>Third, other texts in the Bible teach us to rejoice when the wicked are judged.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Psalm 52:5-7</strong> But God will break you down forever; He will snatch you up and tear you away from your tent, And uproot you from the land of the living. Selah. The righteous will see and fear, And will laugh at him, saying, &#8220;Behold, the man who would not make God his refuge, But trusted in the abundance of his riches And was strong in his evil desire.&#8221;<br />
<strong>Psalm 58:9-11</strong> Before your pots can feel the fire of thorns He will sweep them away with a whirlwind, the green and the burning alike. The righteous will rejoice when he sees the vengeance; He will wash his feet in the blood of the wicked. And men will say, &#8220;Surely there is a reward for the righteous; Surely there is a God who judges on earth!&#8221;<br />
<strong>Revelation 18:19-20</strong> &#8220;And they threw dust on their heads and were crying out, weeping and mourning, saying, &#8216;Woe, woe, the great city, in which all who had ships at sea became rich by her wealth, for in one hour she has been laid waste!&#8217; Rejoice over her, O heaven, and you saints and apostles and prophets, because God has pronounced judgment for you against her.&#8221;<br />
<strong>Revelation 19:1-3</strong> After these things I heard something like a loud voice of a great multitude in heaven, saying, &#8220;Hallelujah! Salvation and glory and power belong to our God; BECAUSE HIS JUDGMENTS ARE TRUE AND RIGHTEOUS; for He has judged the great harlot who was corrupting the earth with her immorality, and HE HAS AVENGED THE BLOOD OF HIS BOND-SERVANTS ON HER.&#8221; And a second time they said, &#8220;Hallelujah! HER SMOKE RISES UP FOREVER AND EVER.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>There is no relief from the tension and difficulty we feel between these two verses in this way.  Though Proverbs 11:10 is descriptive, it is not merely descriptive.  It tells us what the righteous will do&#8212;what in some sense the righteous must do when the wicked are judged.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-2/">Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 2 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 1 of 5)</title>
		<link>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-1/</link>
					<comments>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-1/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 14:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sermons]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bin Laden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[osama]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=916</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Where were you when you heard the news? I was sitting on my living room couch about 10:30 pm. The phone rang. It was my son, Nate. He said, &#8220;Dad, did you hear the news, they got Bin Laden.&#8221; Usually nothing beside the weather channel gets watched on the Lord&#8217;s Day at our house, but [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-1/">Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 1 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Where were you when you heard the news?  I was sitting on my living room couch about 10:30 pm.  The phone rang.  It was my son, Nate.   He said,  &#8220;Dad, did you hear the news, they got Bin Laden.&#8221;  Usually nothing beside the weather channel gets watched on the Lord&#8217;s Day at our house, but that news seemed important enough to turn on one of the news stations.  Shortly, President Obama was on with his short speech confirming the reports that US military had killed Osama Bin Laden.</p>
<p>All during this time the news channel kept cutting away to the growing crowd outside the White House and in Times Square in New York City celebrating the news of Bin Laden&#8217;s death.  Clearly, people felt a need to celebrate the death of public enemy number one.  Other things caught my eye this week.  There was the couple whose son was killed on 9/11 who sat in silent celebration for 20 minutes after they heard the news.  There were the newspaper headlines which voiced what surely were the feelings of many.  They simply read:  <em>Rot in Hell</em>!</p>
<p>To not a few Christians all of this seems entirely inappropriate.  When I asked one of my religion classes at KWC if Christians should rejoice that Bin Laden was killed, the general sentiment was that Christians should not rejoice.  One Christian organization seems to agree and put out these thoughts:</p>
<blockquote><p>Gloating over death and destruction of an enemy is not the proper response.  It should never be the Christian response. While our nation sought and accomplished justice with Osama bin Laden, it is unfitting to celebrate.</p></blockquote>
<p>I suspect, however, that this level of Christianity may seem a little difficult to attain for some of us.  Even though we wonder if we should feel this way, we are glad that <em>they finally got him</em>!</p>
<p>Last Lord&#8217;s Day evening I preached on Osama&#8217;s death  (<a title="Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden is Dead - Or Not? Sermon" href="http://www.hbcowensboro.org/sermon/the-death-of-osama-bin-laden/" target="_self" rel="noopener">you can listen to or download my message from our church&#8217;s web site</a>).  Even though I am not much of an occasional preacher, Mark Redfern, one of my fellow pastors, suggested it to me and I followed his counsel and even took the verses he suggested as my text.  They provide a balanced, biblical response to the killing of Osama Bin Laden.  In these blogs I will look at these verses as follows:  I.  The Verses Contemplated; II.  The Verses Compared;  III.  The Verses Considered.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-1/">Rejoice that Osama Bin Laden Is Dead—Or Not? (Part 1 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/rejoice-that-osama-bin-laden-is-dead-or-not-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sermon notes: The Reformation and the Election &#8211; Ephesians 1:4</title>
		<link>/sermon-notes-the-reformation-and-the-election-ephesians-14/</link>
					<comments>/sermon-notes-the-reformation-and-the-election-ephesians-14/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2010 19:08:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sermons]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/?p=294</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Reformation and the Election &#8211; Ephesians 1:4 A sermon preached on Lord&#8217;s Day, October 31, 2010 I.&#160;&#160;&#160;INTRODUCTION A. Today, October 31, marks the 493rd anniversary of a significant even to us, but not to those who were living at the time or even to those who might have witnessed it. An unknown and insignificant [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/sermon-notes-the-reformation-and-the-election-ephesians-14/">Sermon notes: The Reformation and the Election &#8211; Ephesians 1:4</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>The Reformation and the Election &#8211; Ephesians 1:4</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>A sermon preached on Lord&#8217;s Day, October 31, 2010</strong></p>
<p><strong>I.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong><strong>INTRODUCTION</strong></p>
<p>A. Today, October 31, marks the 493<sup>rd</sup> anniversary of a significant even to us, but not to those who were living at the time or even to those who might have witnessed it. An unknown and insignificant Roman Catholic priest, Martin Luther, tacked a series of 95 statements on a church door in Germany. In those days, the way a subject for debate among priests and theologians occurred was when someone like Luther pinned his concerns on a church door. But Luther&#8217;s concerns, slowly but surely, would change the world. The result of this seemingly insignificant act by a relatively unknown man is what we call the Protestant Reformation. October 31, 1517 is when the Reformation of the Christian church began and the world has never been the same.</p>
<p>B. During the Reformation of the 16<sup>th</sup> century, the Bible took its rightful place &#8211; front and center. And God raised-up two main leaders, Martin Luther and John Calvin, who changed the face of the church and of the Western world.</p>
<p><strong>1. Luther and Calvin were different men:</strong> But Martin Luther and John Calvin were very different men.</p>
<p>a. Luther was an ex-monk who, at the age of 42, married an apostate nun, Katherine. Luther really needed to get married. He once said, &#8220;Before I was married the bed was not made for a whole year and became foul with sweat&#8221; (Bainton, <em>Here I Stand</em>, 226). But here what he says next, &#8220;But I worked so hard and was weary I tumbled in [bed] without noticing it&#8221; (Bainton, <em>Here I Stand</em>, 226). <strong>PT. </strong>What drove Luther to work so hard?</p>
<p>b. Luther was quite the character. He sent out many invitations to his wedding. There was a man named Leonard Kopp who had helped some nuns escape from their convent (Luther&#8217;s soon-to-be wife being one of them). Here&#8217;s how the invitation to Kopp read, &#8220;I am to be married on Thursday. My lord Katie and I invite you to send a barrel of the best &#8230;beer, and if it is not good you will have to drink it all yourself&#8221; (Bainton, <em>Here I Stand</em>, 226). Calvin was much more refined than Luther; he drank wine.</p>
<p><strong>2. Luther and Calvin, though they were different men, they believed some of the same things:</strong> Though Luther and Calvin were very different in terms of their personalities, Luther and Calvin agreed on many things. And this is what fueled the Reformation &#8211; not the <strong><em>great men</em></strong>, but the <strong><em>great truths</em></strong> they held in common. This is vital to understand! <strong>PT. </strong>It is the truth that sets souls free not strong leaders or unique personalities! The Gospel was unleashed at the time of the Reformation and the world became different as a result!</p>
<p><strong>3. Luther and Calvin and the Five Solas:</strong> Luther and Calvin, and the first wave of Protestants, all believed in what we call the five solas of the Reformation &#8211; <em>Sola Scriptura (the Bible is above the Church not under it)</em>, <em>Sola Gratia (to be right with God is based on God&#8217;s grace not our works)</em>, <em>Sola Fidei (salvation from sin comes to a soul through the instrument of faith and faith alone!)</em>, <em>Solus Christus (Christ and Christ alone as the object of ones faith saves)</em> and the last Sola is, <em>Soli Deo Gloria</em> &#8211; to God along be the glory in all things (Rom. 11:36). It&#8217;s all about Him, not us. The universe isn&#8217;t tethered around us; its&#8217; tethered around God. Everything exists for Him. All that is, is, for Him.</p>
<p>C. Transition: Protestants all over the world are remembering the Reformation today. And to help us understand why the truths rediscovered at the time of the Reformation were so life-changing, I want you to turn to Ephesians 1:4 as we consider the Reformation and the Election.</p>
<p><strong>II.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong><strong>BODY</strong></p>
<p><strong>Introduction: </strong>What I would like to do with this text is to show you that it is one of many NT passages that justify the <em>solas</em> of the Reformation. I will first explain the text, deal with some common objections, and then draw some practical applications.<strong></strong></p>
<p>A. Exposition</p>
<p>1. Notice the context of the verse: 1:3-14 is an anthem of praise to God for the blessings of salvation. Paul&#8217;s soul explodes with praise to God the Father for the fact and way He saves sinners.</p>
<p>a. Praise to God the Father for election &#8211; 1:4-6</p>
<p>b. Praise to God the Father for redemption in the Beloved one &#8211; 1:7-12</p>
<p>c. Praise to God the Father for sealing by the Holy Spirit &#8211; 1:13-14</p>
<p><strong>PT. </strong>Notice how each section ends with a <em>soli Deo gloria</em> type of statement!</p>
<p>2. Notice the teaching of the verse</p>
<p>a. The <strong><em>author</em></strong> of election: <em>He</em></p>
<p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This refers back to verse 3.</p>
<p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <em>He</em> is God the Father.</p>
<p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; God the Father is the author of election. He is the elector.</p>
<p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The Father is depicted in Scripture as the divine fountain-head from which salvation ultimately begins (cf. <strong><em>Eph. 1:5, 9, 11 [His will, His purpose]; Col.</em></strong> <strong><em>1:12). </em></strong>The work of salvation is divided between the Persons of the <strong><em>Godhead </em></strong>&#8211; the Father <strong><em>plans</em></strong> redemption, the Son <strong><em>purchases</em></strong> redemption, the Spirit <strong><em>applies</em></strong> redemption. The redemptive stewardship of the <strong><em>Father</em></strong> lies mainly in the realm of the planning of salvation, in election and predestination.</p>
<p>b. The <strong><em>fact</em></strong> of election: <em>chose</em></p>
<p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To chose for one self</p>
<p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To chose or select or elect out of a group</p>
<p>c. The <strong><em>objects</em></strong> of election: <em>us</em></p>
<p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The &#8220;us&#8221; is Paul and the believers in Christ to whom he was writing. Election is personal. It refers to individuals.</p>
<p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; But notice with me how Paul describes the &#8220;us&#8221; in 2:1-3. This is before they believed the gospel.</p>
<p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The &#8220;us&#8221; are chosen <strong><em>to be</em></strong> holy, not <strong><em>because</em></strong> they were holy.</p>
<p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; IOW, elect people are first sinful people. Election is necessary because we are sinners. If there were no election, there would be no salvation! Since there is election, we can be sure that there is salvation!</p>
<p><strong>ILLUSTRATION: </strong>This election is very unlike Tuesday&#8217;s election. In political elections, if you run a great campaign, chances are better that you will be elected. But the election of Eph. 1:4 has no campaign slogans that will work. Not only do we have nothing to offer God to make us fit for election, we can&#8217;t come up with a slogan that will cause Him to overlook our faults and choose us anyway.</p>
<p>d. The <strong><em>sphere</em></strong> of election: <em>in Him</em></p>
<p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We are not told by Paul just exactly what being chosen &#8220;in Him&#8221; means.</p>
<p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; I think Charles Hodge, a 19<sup>th</sup>-century Presbyterian theologian says it well: &#8220;It was in Christ as their head and representative they were chosen to holiness and eternal life, and therefore in virtue of what he was to do in their behalf. There is a federal (or covenantal) union with Christ which [comes before] all actual union [which comes by faith], and is the source of it. God gave a people to his Son in the covenant of redemption [before the world began]&#8230; It is, therefore, in Christ, i. e. as untied to him in the covenant of redemption [before the world began], that the people of God are elected to eternal life and to all the blessings [connected to it]&#8221; (Hodge, <em>Eph</em>., 31).</p>
<p>e. The <strong><em>timing</em></strong> of election: <em>before the foundation of the world</em></p>
<p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Paul uses this kind of language elsewhere. For instance, <strong><em>2 Timothy 1:9</em></strong>, &#8220;[God] saved us and called us with a holy calling, not according to our works, but according to His own purpose and grace which was granted us in Christ Jesus from all eternity,&#8221; And <strong><em>2 Thess. 2:13</em></strong>, &#8220;&#8230;we should always give thanks to God for you, brethren beloved by the Lord, because God has chosen you from the beginning for salvation through sanctification by the Spirit and faith in the truth.&#8221; Here <strong><em>Acts 13:48</em></strong>, &#8220;When the Gentiles heard this, they began rejoicing and glorifying the word of the Lord; ans as many as had been appointed to eternal life believed.&#8221;</p>
<p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; So the Bible teaches us that before the foundation of the world, something was going on between God the Father and God the Son concerning the salvation of souls!</p>
<p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Jesus knew these things to be true: <strong><em>Jn. 6:35-40; 17:2</em></strong>.</p>
<p>f. The <strong><em>goal</em></strong> of election: <em>to be holy</em></p>
<p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Not God chose us because we were holy.</p>
<p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Not God chose us because we promised to be holy.</p>
<p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; But God chose us to a goal we were <strong><em>not pursuing</em></strong> and could <strong><em>never, ever attain</em></strong> &#8211; holiness and blamelessness in the presence of God. I think Paul is referring to the same thing Jude alerts to in <strong><em>Jude 24</em></strong>, &#8220;Now to Him who is able to keep you from stumbling, and to make you stand in the presence of His glory blameless with great joy&#8221;!</p>
<p><strong>PT. </strong>Ephesians 1:4ff. teaches that God chose some he viewed as sinners to be holy in His presence (or saved), before the foundation of the world, in the plan of redemption between the Father and the Son and all according to the kind intention of His will, to the praise of the glory of His grace. <em>Sola gratia and soli Deo Gloria</em>!</p>
<p>B. Objections</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Stated:</strong> I&#8217;ve got a real problem with this. This does not seem to be just. You claim that God is just, yet this sure does not seem to display justice. <strong>Answered:</strong> Well, I must say that I agree with you. Election does not display justice; it displays mercy, grace, kindness, and love. That&#8217;s why it&#8217;s so amazing! If you want God to be just alone, then no one will be saved, &#8220;for all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God&#8221; (Rom. 3:23). That one soul is elected is staggering to the mind, considering how holy and just God is and how sinful we are. But there are millions upon millions of elect sinners!</li>
<li><strong>Stated:</strong> If election is true the way you have explained it, this would mean that man has no say in the matter. <strong>Answered:</strong> Our having a say in the matter is our problem not the solution! Our hearts are not naturally inclined to say yes to God, yes to His law, yes to His Son, yes to the Gospel, and yes to holiness, selflessness, sacrifice, and obedience against all odds. Man&#8217;s will is one of the things that man needs to be saved from. <strong><em>Rom. 8:8 </em></strong>[in our natural state we are] <strong><em>not able to please God!</em></strong></li>
</ol>
<p>C. Applications/Observations</p>
<p>1. For the lost and unbelieving.</p>
<p><strong>a. A warning:</strong> Don&#8217;t leave here playing the unjust card against God. Spurgeon said, &#8220;I will not attempt to prove the justice of God in having thus elected some and left others. It is not for me to vindicate my Master. He will speak for himself, and he does so&#8230;&#8221; (Election, 11). Listen to Rom. 9:14-24. Don&#8217;t turn things upside down and become God&#8217;s judge instead of He being ours. Everything God does is just, simply because He does it.</p>
<p><strong>b. An encouragement:</strong> If you affirm with the Bible that election is of grace, that justice requires punishment, and that you are both <strong><em>unworthy</em></strong> of election and <strong><em>worthy</em></strong> of punishment, then you are in a good state of mind. As Spurgeon told and audience over 100 years ago, &#8220;&#8230;take courage, take hope, O thou sinner, that there is election!&#8221; If there were no election, there would be no hope of salvation. But, since election is, salvation is. So, take God&#8217;s word for it, and come to Jesus Christ and live! You&#8217;ve already got election down; now get the gospel right and come! You will not be more sinful if you do so. In fact, Christ is your only hope to know if you are elect. If you want salvation, take Christ. And if you do, you will know that you are elect! Not only is election true, but all who come to Christ acknowledging their sins and trusting Him are received by Him! You need Him; only Him, all of Him, and nothing but Him!</p>
<p>2. For the saved and believing.</p>
<p>a. Always remember that this teaching on election comes in a context of praise and thanksgiving, not polemics. Understanding election should move us to worship not argument. <strong><em>Eph. 1:3; 2 Thess. 2:13</em></strong>. Hymn #95: <strong><em>Not one of all the chosen race, But shall to heaven attain, Partake on earth the purposed grace, And then with Jesus reign</em></strong>!</p>
<p>b. This doctrine of election strips believers of boasting in themselves and directs their boasts exclusively to the<strong><em> </em></strong>Lord!<strong><em> Tis not that I did choose Thee, For, Lord, that could not be; This heart would still refuse Thee, Hadst Thou not chosen me. </em></strong>It is by God&#8217;s doing that anyone is in Christ. Let him who boars, boast in the Lord!</p>
<p>c. This doctrine of election reminds us of the truths embodied in the <em>solas</em> of the Reformation: Salvation is by sovereign and electing grace alone (<em>sola gratia</em>), through the instrument of faith alone (<em>sola fidei),</em> in Christ alone as offered in the gospel and nothing but Christ (<em>solus Christus</em>), and all for the glory of God &#8211; <em>soli Deo Gloria</em>! May our cry ever be <strong><em>Free grace alone, from the first to the last, Hath won my affection and bound my soul fast! </em></strong>Amen.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/sermon-notes-the-reformation-and-the-election-ephesians-14/">Sermon notes: The Reformation and the Election &#8211; Ephesians 1:4</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/sermon-notes-the-reformation-and-the-election-ephesians-14/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
