<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>admin | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/author/admin/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2015 19:00:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>admin | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Fall Update from Dr. Sam Waldron</title>
		<link>/waldron-fall-update/</link>
					<comments>/waldron-fall-update/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2015 19:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1733</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dear Brothers, Much has been happening here at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary over the last few months which is cause for giving of thanks and the seeking of your prayerful support. We are thankful for the ongoing transition in our administrator position.&#160; Our much appreciated administrator, John Divito, continues to raise support for the African [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/waldron-fall-update/">Fall Update from Dr. Sam Waldron</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dear Brothers,</p>
<p>Much has been happening here at <a href="/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a> over the last few months which is cause for giving of thanks and the seeking of your prayerful support.</p>
<p>We are thankful for the ongoing transition in our administrator position.&nbsp; Our much appreciated administrator, John Divito, continues to raise support for the <a href="http://africanpastors.missionsplace.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">African Pastors&#8217; Conferences</a>&nbsp;conference manager position to which he has been called.&nbsp; At the same time, our brother, Rex Semrad, has begun employment as our full-time administrator.&nbsp; He is right now being trained by John in all the various responsibilities of that position.&nbsp; I would like your prayers for both John and Rex and their various needs during this time of transition.</p>
<p>We are also thankful for significant opportunities emerging for CBTS in South America.&nbsp; We are organizing a modular course of studies in Bogota, Colombia with our brother&nbsp;Guillermo Gomez and the church there.&nbsp; We expect 60 students to begin studies in the first of these courses in late March.&nbsp; The course of study will consist of 14 modular courses which, when completed, will provide those students who already have bachelor&#8217;s degrees with what we are calling a Master&nbsp;of Arts in Reformed Theology Degree.&nbsp; Those with English competency who complete this course of study in CBTS Bogota will be welcomed to transfer the credits earned and continue their studies at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary.&nbsp; Commitments have been made which provide for all the funds needed for 12 out of the 14 modular courses.&nbsp; We are in need of $3,000 for two courses to be taught by Spanish-speaking Reformed Baptist pastors whose churches are located in Latin America.&nbsp;They are sacrificially saving for the airfare necessary to go, but we want to provide these funds ($1,500 for each course).&nbsp;This money provides for the housing and feeding of the students at each course which is not covered by the fees already charged to each of the students.&nbsp;I would be glad to talk to anyone interested in helping these two brothers.</p>
<p>We are also considering responding affirmatively to a similar plea which has come to us from the emerging Reformed Baptist movement in Ecuador.&nbsp; They are asking for help to organize a similar course of studies there.&nbsp; If our board approves this endeavor, we will organize these two centers of study as CBTS South America!</p>
<p>Let me share another burden which I hope you will consider.&nbsp;Grace Reformed Baptist Church here in Owensboro is both the host church for the seminary and the home to a growing number of residential students.&nbsp; One of these has so commended himself to the church in the several years he has been with us that our church voted to raise support for him to be a full-time student.&nbsp;We are endeavoring to raise the money needed to set him apart to finish his course of study by the end of 2017.&nbsp;We also want him to have the benefit of summer internships in sister Reformed Baptist churches.&nbsp;I would be happy to discuss this encouraging student with any of you and how you might be involved with us in stewarding the gift he may be to our churches.</p>
<p>I could go on about other needs and opportunities, but suffice to say there is a great work to be done. Please pray and consider how God might want you to be a part of what God is doing here at CBTS.</p>
<p>The Lord Reigns,<br />
Dr. Sam Waldron<br />
Dean, Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/waldron-fall-update/">Fall Update from Dr. Sam Waldron</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/waldron-fall-update/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CBTS is Now an Affiliate Member of ARTS</title>
		<link>/cbts-affiliate-member-of-arts/</link>
					<comments>/cbts-affiliate-member-of-arts/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2015 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1685</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>As Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary begins our fall semester, God continues to bless us with exciting developments. Our latest news is that we have become an affiliate member of the&#160;Association of Reformed Theological Seminaries&#160;(ARTS). &#160;Our involvement in ARTS is a strategic move toward institutional progress, and we look forward to&#160;developing academic relationships with theologically like-minded [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/cbts-affiliate-member-of-arts/">CBTS is Now an Affiliate Member of ARTS</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary begins our fall semester, God continues to bless us with exciting developments. Our latest news is that we have become an affiliate member of the&nbsp;<a href="http://artseminaries.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Association of Reformed Theological Seminaries</a>&nbsp;(ARTS). &nbsp;Our involvement in ARTS is a strategic move toward institutional progress, and we look forward to&nbsp;developing academic relationships with theologically like-minded seminaries. Please join with us in thanking God for this development and pray that our affiliation will be mutually beneficial for the glory of Christ.</p>
<p><center></center></p>
<div><em>Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary is an Affiliate institution of the Association of Reformed Theological Seminaries. As such, it participates in and contributes to collegial and professional development activities of the Association, and is committed to the quality of education ARTS promotes. Affiliate status does not, however, constitute, imply, or presume ARTS Commission on Accreditation accredited status at present or in the future.</em></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/cbts-affiliate-member-of-arts/">CBTS is Now an Affiliate Member of ARTS</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/cbts-affiliate-member-of-arts/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Announcing an Exciting New Partnership</title>
		<link>/exciting-new-partnership/</link>
					<comments>/exciting-new-partnership/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2015 22:00:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1683</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary is excited to announce a new partnership with the&#160;Association of Reformed Baptist Churches&#160;of Qu&#233;bec. Together with the the association&#8217;s CERB (Centre d&#8217;&#233;tudes r&#233;form&#233;es baptistes), we will be equipping men in French-speaking Canada to rightly handle the Word of Truth (2 Timothy 2:15). Please join us in prayer as we move forward [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/exciting-new-partnership/">Announcing an Exciting New Partnership</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary is excited to announce a new partnership with the&nbsp;<a href="http://cbtseminary.us7.list-manage.com/track/click?u=11118de60955d83b1e4e6bea8&amp;id=153b9b7f80&amp;e=b2a6109dc6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Association of Reformed Baptist Churches&nbsp;of Qu&eacute;bec</a>. Together with the the association&#8217;s CERB (Centre d&#8217;&eacute;tudes r&eacute;form&eacute;es baptistes), we will be equipping men in French-speaking Canada to rightly handle the Word of Truth (2 Timothy 2:15). Please join us in prayer as we move forward with this wonderful opportunity!</p>
<p><em>The CERB (Centre d&#8217;&eacute;tudes r&eacute;form&eacute;es baptistes) is happy to announce its partnership with Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. We would like to thank Dr. Samuel Waldron (Dean) as well as our brother John Divito (Administrator) who did not save any effort in order to accommodate our needs. One of our students has already registered and more are to come. We expect a long and blessed collaboration with CBTS in our common goal to train ministers for the Kingdom of God.</em></p>
<p><em>Pro Rege,<br />
Raymond Perron Ph.D.<br />
Ministre de l&#8217;&eacute;vangile<em></em></em></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/exciting-new-partnership/">Announcing an Exciting New Partnership</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/exciting-new-partnership/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Letter from CBTS Graduate</title>
		<link>/letter-from-cbts-graduate/</link>
					<comments>/letter-from-cbts-graduate/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 20:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Student Profiles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1681</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Eric Coher is a recent graduate of&#160;Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary, having received our&#160;Master of Arts in Theological Studies&#160;degree. In the letter below, Eric writes about his studies with us. Dear Prayer Partners and Supporters, As I reflect back over the past few years of my theological training at&#160;Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary&#160;(CBTS), I am both humbled [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/letter-from-cbts-graduate/">A Letter from CBTS Graduate</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Eric Coher is a recent graduate of&nbsp;<a href="/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>, having received our&nbsp;<a href="/academics/program-offerings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Master of Arts in Theological Studies</a>&nbsp;degree. In the letter below, Eric writes about his studies with us.</em></p>
<p>Dear Prayer Partners and Supporters,</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="" src="https://ci5.googleusercontent.com/proxy/SnGEiWpFPMFF0C7B2_k5GYknv5XTg5TS9r0JD3uXYoEJcx81Af0YW1N77Mlo5noAfZicVKK4AOcFuPFNg1eLSiV7TRmFFIwT00Cu2_MMsiOt0Boufng0D5Vx-haj2nAkS7GFPh2QMtPujXxIYsl9ZGAXXyXFLDqZH-3X_Ww=s0-d-e1-ft#https://gallery.mailchimp.com/11118de60955d83b1e4e6bea8/images/4e13d5e6-c784-498a-8ba0-c1082ac6a3f5.jpg" width="175" height="175" align="right">As I reflect back over the past few years of my theological training at&nbsp;<a href="/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>&nbsp;(CBTS), I am both humbled and immensely blessed by the instruction that I received. As a full-time pastor, I was unable to uproot my family and leave my church to pursue seminary. Consequently, I was thrilled to learn that there was an institution right in my &#8220;backyard&#8221; that was theologically orthodox, distinctively reformed, and academically rigorous. CBTS provided an opportunity for me to pursue a theological education while simultaneously serving in the local church. This meant that not only did I benefit from what I was learning, but the sparks of my education fell on those who sat under my teaching, preaching, counseling, and discipleship.</p>
<p>While CBTS was the vehicle for my theological training, it was the men who invested in my education for which I am most grateful.&nbsp; Each professor, resident or visiting, that I had the privilege of learning from sought to equip my mind, challenge my heart, encourage my soul, and better prepare me to shepherd the flock of God. They deeply cared for, intentionally thought for, and loved me well in very tangible ways. Being surrounded by men who passionately love Christ, valiantly uphold the truth of the gospel, and desire to see the Church rooted, built up, and established has served crystalize my calling, chisel my theological convictions, hone my spiritual gifts. In short, I am a better husband, father, pastor, shepherd, teacher, counselor, disciple-maker, and friend as a result of my seminary training at CBTS!</p>
<p>At the end of the day, having a degree on the wall or letters following my name is insignificant. What is significant, on the other hand, is the sharpening that I received through my studies at CBTS. The instruction that I received will help me to better fulfill Paul&#8217;s exhortation, &#8220;Him we proclaim, warning everyone and teaching everyone with all wisdom, that we may present everyone mature in Christ&#8221; (Colossians 1:28 ESV).</p>
<p>For the glory of Christ and the beauty of His Bride,<br />
Eric C. Coher,&nbsp;Associate Pastor<br />
<a href="http://fbcevansville.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Faith Bible Church</a><br />
Evansville, IN</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/letter-from-cbts-graduate/">A Letter from CBTS Graduate</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/letter-from-cbts-graduate/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reformation Preaching Conference</title>
		<link>/reformation-conference/</link>
					<comments>/reformation-conference/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 18:00:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1677</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Plan now to join Dr. Sam Waldron and Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary at this year&#8217;s Reformation Preaching Conference in Elizabethtown, Kentucky on October 9-10, 2015. adminCBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/reformation-conference/">Reformation Preaching Conference</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Plan now to join Dr. Sam Waldron and Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary at this year&#8217;s <a href="http://www.reformedconference.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Reformation Preaching Conference</a> in Elizabethtown, Kentucky on October 9-10, 2015.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/reformation-conference/">Reformation Preaching Conference</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/reformation-conference/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Another Encouraging Letter from CBTS Student</title>
		<link>/letter-from-cbts-student/</link>
					<comments>/letter-from-cbts-student/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2015 19:30:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student Profiles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1662</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dear Prayer Partners and Supporters, In God&#8217;s good providence, being a distance learning student at&#160;Covenant Baptist&#160;Theological Seminary&#160;has helped me grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ in ways that I would have never imagined otherwise. If I could summarize into one concrete thought what the seminary has done for my soul [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/letter-from-cbts-student/">Another Encouraging Letter from CBTS Student</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dear Prayer Partners and Supporters,</p>
<p>In God&#8217;s good providence, being a distance learning student at&nbsp;<a href="http://goo.gl/yDzNo4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Covenant Baptist&nbsp;Theological Seminary</a>&nbsp;has helped me grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ in ways that I would have never imagined otherwise. If I could summarize into one concrete thought what the seminary has done for my soul it would be this &#8211;<em>it has made my soul abound with love for the bride of Christ, the church</em>. She is ruddy but beautiful and she is being adorned by her Lord with splendor, majesty, and glory. He is making her the fragrance of Christ to the world (Song 4:7, 16; 2 Cor. 2:15).&nbsp;Hallelujah!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignright" alt="" src="https://gallery.mailchimp.com/11118de60955d83b1e4e6bea8/images/20a0d6c2-704f-471b-bf94-f371559dfb5f.jpg" width="175" height="177" align="right">My soul has come to see these truths more vividly through the seminary&#8217;s&nbsp;<a href="http://goo.gl/KpUV2t" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Basic Training Program</a>. This program has helped me step into seminary life at a pace that isn&#8217;t intimidating, but rather encouraging. The program is designed to give aspiring pastors a taste for what seminary studies are like and to aid in discerning the will of the Lord regarding education. I have found the material refreshing, challenging, edifying and encouraging. Every book recommended for course material is a keeper. Every professor is worth his weight in gold. Best of all, the orthodoxy of the courses is supplemented by the orthopraxy required of the program in the local church. This has tended to keep me balanced with regard to learning at the seminary level, and it gives me an outlet for the things I am learning to be used in the building up of the body.</p>
<p>Distance learning from a technical standpoint for some can be intimidating, but CBTS has streamlined this processing using a&nbsp;<a href="http://www.cbtspathway.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">step-by-step path</a>&nbsp;for prerecorded material, and simple&nbsp;<a href="http://new.livestream.com/cbtseminary" target="_blank" rel="noopener">video streaming</a>&nbsp;for live courses. If you can navigate the popular video sharing websites out there you can easily work your way through the courses.</p>
<p>Recently my local fellowship partnered with CBTS in their&nbsp;<a href="http://goo.gl/zoj4Em" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Church Partnership Program</a>&nbsp;which has, by God&#8217;s good grace, relieved me of many seminary costs. Imagine that! Top notch Reformed Baptist studies paid for once your church partners with the seminary. The cost for partnership is extremely reasonable, by the way. Praise God for His infinite, matchless grace! If there are men in your congregation that are aspiring to the ministry then the Church Partnership Program is an excellent way to receive godly instruction at a great price. It also opens the door up for your church to receive material to use in instructing the church (great options for deeper studies).</p>
<p>At CBTS it is truly informed scholarship with a pastoral heart. Someone once said that burning hearts are not nourished by empty heads. If your heart is burning to learn Christ, in whom are hidden all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge, then there is no better place to set your mind on things that are above.</p>
<p>Grace and Peace to You All,<br />
Scott Autry<br />
<a href="http://www.rockdalecommunitychurch.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Rockdale Community Church</a><br />
Conyers, GA</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/letter-from-cbts-student/">Another Encouraging Letter from CBTS Student</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/letter-from-cbts-student/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reformed Baptist Covenant Theology with Dr. Fred Malone</title>
		<link>/reformed-baptist-covenant-theology/</link>
					<comments>/reformed-baptist-covenant-theology/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2014 16:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Covenant Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fred Malone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1626</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In just a few short months, we will be hosting our next modular course with Dr. Fred Malone&#8212;Reformed Baptist Covenant Theology.&#160;Dr. Malone is an&#160;Adjunct Professor of New Testament Studies as well as pastor of&#160;First Baptist Church&#160;in Clinton, Louisiana and the author of&#160;The Baptism of Disciples Alone. As a Baptist pastor who was a&#160;former Presbyterian minister, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/reformed-baptist-covenant-theology/">Reformed Baptist Covenant Theology with Dr. Fred Malone</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><center></center></p>
<p>In just a few short months, we will be hosting our next modular course with Dr. Fred Malone&#8212;<a href="http://goo.gl/mft0KG" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Reformed Baptist Covenant Theology</a>.&nbsp;Dr. Malone is an&nbsp;Adjunct Professor of New Testament Studies as well as pastor of&nbsp;<a href="http://www.fbcclintonla.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">First Baptist Church</a>&nbsp;in Clinton, Louisiana and the author of&nbsp;<a href="http://press.founders.org/shop/the-baptism-of-disciples-alone/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>The Baptism of Disciples Alone</em></a>. As a Baptist pastor who was a&nbsp;former Presbyterian minister, he provides an insightful summary of the issues surrounding covenant theology.&nbsp;Dr. Malone explains the need for this course:</p>
<blockquote><p>The study of Reformed Baptist Covenant Theology is greatly needed today. Historically, many Baptists have held to Covenant Theology, especially those associated with the 1689 Second London Baptist Confession and its clones (Philadelphia, Charleston, etc.). With the rise of dispensationalism in the Twentieth Century, many Baptists have jettisoned that original historical theology, often ignorant of its very existence in Baptist history. The revival of Reformed Theology in the last 50 years has attracted many Baptists again. However, often being told that Covenant Theology requires the acceptance of paedobaptism, many have either rejected Covenant Theology or have been attracted toward paedobaptist churches. The purpose of this course is to teach the Covenant Theology which Baptists have held in the past, both biblically and historically. Modern-day issues which affect Covenantal Baptists today will be examined in due course: paedobaptism, paedocommunion, theonomy, hypercovenantalism, the New Perspective, New Covenant Theology, etc. The implications for a robust Reformed Baptist Covenant Theology will be explored in matters of evangelism, sanctification, ecclesiology, sacraments, eschatology, pastoral ministry, etc.</p></blockquote>
<p>To hear more about our upcoming course, the latest episode of the Confessing Baptist Podcast features Dr. Waldron interviewing Dr. Malone. If you have the opportunity,&nbsp;<a href="http://confessingbaptist.com/interview067/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">we encourage you to listen to this informative interview</a>.</p>
<p>So don&#8217;t miss out on this unique opportunity to learn more about Baptist Covenant Theology from Dr. Fred Malone on our campus in Owensboro, Kentucky.&nbsp;<strong><em><a href="/news-events/event-registration/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sign up now to attend!</a></em></strong>&nbsp;For those who are not students, you can still participate by simply paying a low $100 auditing fee. Additionally, in order to keep the costs down for our distance students and visiting auditors, we plan to offer places to stay (limited housing is available). With this in mind, if you&nbsp;have any questions about this exciting course, please contact our Administrator/Registrar by email at&nbsp;<a href="mailto:registrar@cbtseminary.org?subject=Reformed%20Baptist%20Covenant%20Theology" target="_blank" rel="noopener">registrar@cbtseminary.org</a>&nbsp;or by phone at 270.925.6992. We look forward to an enriching and edifying study together.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/reformed-baptist-covenant-theology/">Reformed Baptist Covenant Theology with Dr. Fred Malone</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/reformed-baptist-covenant-theology/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dr. Sam Waldron Video on the 1689 Baptist Confession and Baptist Distinctives</title>
		<link>/waldron-1689-baptist-distinctives/</link>
					<comments>/waldron-1689-baptist-distinctives/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2014 17:00:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1689 Confession]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1613</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In light of the upcoming conference Baptists, Confessionalism and the Providence of God, Dr. Sam Waldron has recorded a series of brief videos on the topics that he will be addressing. Here is the second video: adminCBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced degree in their field of instruction, and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/waldron-1689-baptist-distinctives/">Dr. Sam Waldron Video on the 1689 Baptist Confession and Baptist Distinctives</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In light of the upcoming conference <a href="http://www.1689conference.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Baptists, Confessionalism and the Providence of God</a>, Dr. Sam Waldron has recorded a series of brief videos on the topics that he will be addressing. Here is the second video:</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/106547907" height="281" width="500" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0"></iframe></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/waldron-1689-baptist-distinctives/">Dr. Sam Waldron Video on the 1689 Baptist Confession and Baptist Distinctives</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/waldron-1689-baptist-distinctives/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dr. Sam Waldron Video on the 1689 Baptist Confession and Reformed Theology</title>
		<link>/waldron-1689-confession-reformed-theology/</link>
					<comments>/waldron-1689-confession-reformed-theology/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2014 14:00:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1689 Confession]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1602</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In light of the upcoming conference Baptists, Confessionalism and the Providence of God, Dr. Sam Waldron has recorded a series of brief videos on the topics that he will be addressing. Here is the second video: adminCBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced degree in their field of instruction, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/waldron-1689-confession-reformed-theology/">Dr. Sam Waldron Video on the 1689 Baptist Confession and Reformed Theology</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In light of the upcoming conference <a href="http://www.1689conference.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Baptists, Confessionalism and the Providence of God</a>, Dr. Sam Waldron has recorded a series of brief videos on the topics that he will be addressing. Here is the second video:</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/106540549" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/waldron-1689-confession-reformed-theology/">Dr. Sam Waldron Video on the 1689 Baptist Confession and Reformed Theology</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/waldron-1689-confession-reformed-theology/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dr. Sam Waldron Video on the Outline of the 1689 Confession</title>
		<link>/dr-sam-waldron-video-on-the-outline-of-the-1689-confession/</link>
					<comments>/dr-sam-waldron-video-on-the-outline-of-the-1689-confession/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2014 14:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1689 Confession]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1583</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In light of the upcoming conference Baptists, Confessionalism and the Providence of God, Dr. Sam Waldron has recorded a series of brief videos on the topics that he will be addressing. Here is the first video: adminCBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced degree in their field of instruction, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/dr-sam-waldron-video-on-the-outline-of-the-1689-confession/">Dr. Sam Waldron Video on the Outline of the 1689 Confession</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In light of the upcoming conference <a href="http://www.1689conference.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Baptists, Confessionalism and the Providence of God</a>, Dr. Sam Waldron has recorded a series of brief videos on the topics that he will be addressing. Here is the first video:</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/106488293" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/dr-sam-waldron-video-on-the-outline-of-the-1689-confession/">Dr. Sam Waldron Video on the Outline of the 1689 Confession</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/dr-sam-waldron-video-on-the-outline-of-the-1689-confession/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
