<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Sam Waldron | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/author/sam-waldron/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 17:44:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Sam Waldron | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>A Post-Logue to #DatPostmil? Blog Posts</title>
		<link>/a-post-log-to-datpostmil-blog-posts/</link>
					<comments>/a-post-log-to-datpostmil-blog-posts/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 17:34:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Civil Government]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=19297</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>It is always a humbling and learning experience to read the responses to a blog series on a controversial subject. Iron does sharpen iron, as the Bible says, and I learn much from those responses. Some postmils have taken a little umbrage at my description of Postmillennialism as a millennium involving a distinct, golden age following the one in which we live.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-post-log-to-datpostmil-blog-posts/">A Post-Logue to #DatPostmil? Blog Posts</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_0 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_0">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_0  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_0  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p><em>This post is a follow-up to a 5 part series on &#8220;#datpostmil?&#8221; View: <span style="color: #0a0808;"><a href="/datpostmil-a-friendly-and-reluctant-response-to-james-white-and-all-my-postmillennial-friends/" style="color: #0a0808;" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 1</span></a>, <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="/datpostmil-2-a-present-evil-age/" style="color: #0a0808; text-decoration: underline;" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2,</a></span><a href="/datpostmil-4-does-the-growth-of-the-kingdom-require-postmillennialism/(opens%20in a new tab)" style="color: #0a0808; text-decoration: underline;"></a> <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="/datpostmil-3-the-postmillennial-doctrine-of-bifurcation-two-ages-in-the-gospel-age/" style="color: #0a0808; text-decoration: underline;" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3,</a></span> <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="/datpostmil-4-does-the-growth-of-the-kingdom-require-postmillennialism/" style="color: #0a0808; text-decoration: underline;" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4</a>, <span><a href="/datpostmil-5-the-problem-with-preterism/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 5</a></span></span></span></em></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">It is always a humbling and learning experience to read the responses to a blog series on a controversial subject. Iron does sharpen iron, as the Bible says, and I learn much from those responses.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">In the case of my posts on Postmillennialism, I have been reminded of something that I already knew but did not make as clear as I should have. A number of the more recent, self-proclaimed postmillennialists have departed from what I think is properly called the older Postmillennialism and adopted the view that the entire inter-adventual period is the millennium. I have observed this view in Gary North’s defense of Postmillennialism. Thus, some postmils have taken a little umbrage at my description of Postmillennialism as a millennium involving a distinct, golden age following the one in which we live. Here is the way a friend of mine described his understanding of their views in an email to me. This friend is actually neither amillennial nor postmillennial, but an historic premillennialist. Nevertheless, I think he has stated their view accurately.</span><span style="font-size: 14px;"> </span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">Their version of postmillennialism seems to be an interesting mix of beliefs. If I understand it correctly, they believe that the millennium stretches between the first and second comings of Christ like amillennialism and do not divide between an age of humility and an age of glory. But they argue for a social/cultural sanctification process through this age similar to a personal sanctification process in our lives. So the gospel is successful through this millennial age of Christianizing the world.</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">Another correspondent who is postmillennial has described his view this way. He begins by quoting me:</span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">&#8220;To maintain its millennial hope for a golden age, of necessity, it must conceive of the gospel age—the period between Christ’s First and Second Advents—as divided into two distinct periods. The first period is the humiliation of the church. The second period is the triumph of the church. There is the time of the persecuted church and the time of the triumphant church.&#8221;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;"><br /> I know that, at least for me and many others, this is not how I conceive of the millennium AT ALL. If I had to draw a parallel image, it would be of the process of sanctification. I am a &#8220;New Creation&#8221;, but I don&#8217;t conceive of my existence as a &#8216;new creation&#8217; as divided into two distinct periods after the New Birth: a period where I am alive in Christ but living an awful, sinful, and ungrateful life and a period where I suddenly start living like an awesome, totally devoted, and pure Christian. No, my sanctification is a gradual process, life growing up from infancy to adulthood. I don&#8217;t stay as an infant and then one day, TA-DA! now I&#8217;m a fully grown, matured man. No, first infancy, then toddler, adolescent, a young man, a middle aged man, and finally an old man.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;"></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;"></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;"></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;"></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;"></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;"></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;"><br /> So too is it for the millennium. Just as the New Creation (me) is slowly, but surely sanctified throughout my life according to God&#8217;s divine plan, so too are the New Heavens and New Earth sanctified throughout its existence according to God&#8217;s divine plan. When I die, I will have been sanctified as such that I am much closer to God then when I was first born again &#8211; but I will not be perfectly sanctified. When Christ returns, the nations will have been discipled, baptized, and taught obedience &#8211; and it will be glorious, but it will not be perfect. It is then that the final enemy, Death, will be destroyed.</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">Now, I freely admit that my presentation did not do justice to this sort of postmillennial theory. It should have. I was aware of North and others with this viewpoint. Nevertheless, I do have a kind of defense and restatement of my view in light of this pushback. Let me provide it now.</span></p>
<p><strong style="font-size: medium;"><em>First, allow me to say that this view is a clear movement in the direction of Amillennialism and away from the way which most historic postmillennialists thought of the millennium.</em></strong><span style="font-size: medium;"> In embracing that the whole gospel age is a single era with the same, continuing characteristics, they have really embraced one of the main perspectives of Amillennialism. They have also changed significantly the definition of the millennium held by historic postmils.</span></p>
<p><strong style="font-size: medium;"><em>Second, allow me to say consequently that, in adopting this view of the gospel age, contemporary postmils have given us a system which is very difficult to distinguish from Amillennialism and especially my form of optimistic Amillennialism.</em></strong><span style="font-size: medium;"> Amillennialists like myself believe in the growth of the kingdom and the building of the church throughout the world. We do not believe in the victory of evil in this age or that the only reality is that “evil men grow worse and worse.”</span></p>
<p><strong style="font-size: medium;"><em>Third, I do have to take exception to the analogy of the personal sanctification process and the millennial conquest of this age by the Word of God. Just as the Christian is gradually sanctified, so also this age is gradually Christianized by the gospel and law of God.</em></strong><span style="font-size: medium;"> This is the analogy; and I need to say that it does not work. Why? It does not work because the sanctification process assumes a regenerate person. One cannot make an analogy here with the present age, because it is not a regenerate age. It is an evil age ruled by Satan. Sanctification can only take place where there is an original and radical break from evil in regeneration. But this age has not been regenerated. As I pointed out in my previous posts, it is an evil age ruled by Satan, the god of this age, and dominated by the sons of this age and not the sons of light. To be conformed to this age’s thinking and to walk according to this age is to live under the dominion of evil. This age cannot be gradually sanctified because it is not regenerate. Rather, it is evil.</span></p>
<p><strong style="font-size: medium;"><em>Fourth, I guess that is the preterist hermeneutic which is being utilized by those who reject my reasoning here.</em></strong><span style="font-size: medium;"> The personal correspondent I mentioned earlier actually did say:</span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">And no, I don’t think that this Age is ruled by the Evil One, as Waldron suggests. Rather it is Christ who rules it and has sovereignly ordaining that all enemies will be subdued under His feet in these New Heavens and New Earth.</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">I rather think that we have here a clue as to how contemporary postmils would respond to what I have just said. It comes back to their preterist hermeneutic. What the New Testament asserts and asserts plainly about this age is no longer true because it only obtained before the destruction of Jerusalem in AD 70. Now we are in the new heavens and new earth. It is, thus, no longer true that this is an evil age. Allow me to quote what I said previously:</span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">The proposition here is, in other words, that the basic character of this age will always be morally evil.  A number of the key passages where the two-age terminology is used require this conclusion. Luke 16:8 speaks of evil men as the sons of this age and contrasts them with the sons of light.  Mark 10:30 teaches that those who have left all for Christ must always expect persecutions in this age.  As long as this age lasts, then, persecution will be the lot of the true Christian.  Romans 12:2 is Paul’s exhortation to Christians not to be conformed to this age. Such language plainly assumes that this age will always be an evil age.  2 Corinthians 4:4 asserts that Satan is “the god of this age”.  It is, therefore, necessarily evil.  Galatians 1:4 is Paul’s description of this age as a “present, evil age” from which the elect are to be delivered by the death of Christ. Ephesians 2:2 describes the former, wicked lives of Ephesian believers as a “walking according to the age of this world.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;"><br /> Such passages as these presuppose and assume that this present age is, and always will be, evil.  If this were not the case, there might come a day when the persecution of Christians would cease, when it would not be wrong to be conformed to this age, when Satan would not be its god, when Paul&#8217;s description of it as evil would cease to be true, and when one could walk according to the age of this world and be righteous.  All this would defy, however, the plain implications of these passages. </span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">It appears that contemporary postmils use their Preterism to refer such passages to another age or dispensation. They no longer describe “these New Heavens and New Earth.” It is just this result of Preterism which I so fervently reject. In a way not so different than Dispensationalism, it refers passages which describe our present life and duty to another period of human history and empty them of their significance for us. I think that even though fine men have adopted this preterist view in the past, they have deviated seriously from a reasonable interpretation of key passages of Scripture. See my blog series: <a href="/john-owen-a-caveat-parts-1-13/">John Owen—A Caveat</a>.</span></p>
<p><strong style="font-size: medium;"><em>Fifth, while admitting that my presentation was not clear with regard to some, contemporary postmillennialism, I have a difficult time regarding my criticism of a bifurcation in the present age as off-base.</em></strong><span style="font-size: medium;"> Let me quote Rex Semrad’s response to one correspondent on this point.</span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">I cannot tell for certain from what you wrote whether or not you believe that for some period of time before Christ returns the majority of people in the world will be converted and nations will be governed by Christian principles. If you don’t believe this, I don’t know why you would consider yourself a postmillennialist, so I assume that is what you believe. … A period of time in which the majority of people are saved and the nations are governed by Christian principles would certainly be clearly differentiated from the world as it now is and has been since Christ ascended to His throne. One would have every reason to consider this a “golden age.” It would also be quite difficult to call it a “present evil age” to which we are not to be conformed (Gal. 1:4, Rom. 12:2). It is also hard to understand how all who seek to live godly in Christ Jesus will suffer persecution in such an age (2 Tim. 3:12). This is the bifurcation of which Dr. Waldron speaks, and it is certainly still there whether it comes about gradually or in a single generation.</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong style="font-size: medium;"><em>Sixth, it does seem to me that there is a focus on the “sanctification” of the world in contemporary Postmillennialism which does not reflect the biblical focus.</em></strong><span style="font-size: medium;"> One friend remarked on this in private correspondence to me:</span></p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">In any case, I am wondering if the biggest distinction between their theonomic postmillennialism and other millennial views has to do with the nature of Christ&#8217;s kingdom. They explicitly deny two kingdoms doctrine, which leads to problematic conclusions.</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: medium;">I think this is correct. Though it is true that the world is under the authority of Christ and the moral law ought to be the basis for all rule in the world today, yet the nations of the world—all of them—are Gentile kingdoms. They are not—any of them—potential theocracies. It is God’s will that church and state not be joined as it was in the theocracy in the world today. These Gentile kingdoms are simply the interim, civil authorities which God has appointed until … “the return of the king!</span></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_1 et_pb_with_background et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_1">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_1  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_0">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737507/ref=sr_1_1?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165840&#038;sr=8-1" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-1" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg 224w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1-194x300.jpg 194w" sizes="(max-width: 224px) 100vw, 224px" class="wp-image-16337" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_2  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_1">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MORE-End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737698/ref=sr_1_3?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165862&#038;sr=8-3" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-2" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg 336w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2-202x300.jpg 202w" sizes="(max-width: 336px) 100vw, 336px" class="wp-image-16339" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_3  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_2">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MacArthurs-Millennial-Manifesto-Samuel-Waldron/dp/098021792X/ref=pd_bxgy_img_3/132-2520012-4634739?_encoding=UTF8&#038;pd_rd_i=098021792X&#038;pd_rd_r=ac9f0afa-68d3-4ac2-8ef6-f5b4cadc19cd&#038;pd_rd_w=2dSwU&#038;pd_rd_wg=0rs7V&#038;pf_rd_p=f325d01c-4658-4593-be83-3e12ca663f0e&#038;pf_rd_r=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7&#038;psc=1&#038;refRID=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-3" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg 333w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 333px) 100vw, 333px" class="wp-image-16341" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-post-log-to-datpostmil-blog-posts/">A Post-Logue to #DatPostmil? Blog Posts</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-post-log-to-datpostmil-blog-posts/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Owen—A Caveat, parts 1-13</title>
		<link>/john-owen-a-caveat-parts-1-13/</link>
					<comments>/john-owen-a-caveat-parts-1-13/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 13:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Owen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[partial-preterism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=19132</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Sam WaldronDr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-owen-a-caveat-parts-1-13/">John Owen—A Caveat, parts 1-13</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_2 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_2">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_4  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_1  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p> </p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 1</span></p>
<p>Caveat comes from the Latin cavere.  The verb in Latin means to be on guard.  I am using its English descendant caveat to mean a warning or caution.  Such is my esteem for John Owen that I prefer the softer idea of caution.</p>
<p>John Owen has attained (and not without warrant) a high status among Reformed Baptists in our day.  This status derives from many things, I suppose.  He is certainly a profound and faithful expositor of the Reformed faith.  He is also a progenitor of the Reformed Baptist movement as a Congregationalist Puritan and one of the authors of that confession from which the mass of the 1689 is immediately drawn, the Savoy Declaration of Faith.  The views articulated in the Savoy are only a kind of half step from the positions regarding baptism and the church found in the 1689.  1689 Federalism has publicized the idea that Owen’s views of covenant theology articulate a covenant theology amenable to and even foundational for Reformed Baptist views of covenant theology.</p>
<p>For all of these reasons, to cite Owen is almost to cite Scripture in Reformed books and blogs.  Do we have a celebrity theologian of our own in John Owen? This is a question, I think, worth considering.  Christian realism and spiritual sanity require, I think, that we admit that all men have spiritual and exegetical feet of clay.  I think this is true of John Owen, and in the posts that follow I will point out a place at which I am convinced Owen does have feet of clay.  It is also an exegetical place about which, in my opinion, we may no longer entertain his views without opening ourselves to serious error.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><span style="font-size: x-large;"><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 2</span></span></span></p>
<p>My first post on this subject, I must confess, was a deliberate “teaser.” It was a deliberate attempt to attract interest in my subject and get you to “stay tuned” and come back next week to the same time and channel. Now I must ‘fess up and tell you without further ado what my concern is about Owen. It is found in Book 9 page 134 of his Works. My general area of concern is eschatological. My specific concern is the Preterist interpretation of 2 Peter 3 which Owen adopts. Some of you may not have Owen’s works. Of course, this may at some level and for some people undermine your very credibility as a Reformed Baptist. (Pardon my humor, please!) Yet for those of you who do not have his Works here is what Owen says:</p>
<p>“On this foundation I affirm, that the heavens and earth intended in this prophecy of Peter, the coming of the Lord, the day of judgment and perdition of ungodly men, mentioned in the destruction of that heaven and earth, do all of them relate, not to the last and final judgment of the world, but to that utter desolation and destruction that was to be made of the Judaical church and state; …”</p>
<p>Owen goes on to offer two reasons (which he says are among many that could be offered) for this view. In the posts that follow I will provide a critique both of Owen’s reasoning and several (what I believe to be) conclusive arguments against the exegetical ground he occupies in his interpretation of this key, eschatological passage.</p>
<p>Before I close this present post, I simply want to identify what the position is that Owen is taking. He is quite obviously taking the partial preterist approach to New Testament prophecy and to 2 Peter 3. I gladly acknowledge that, since he speaks of the last and final judgment of the world, he is not defending the full preterist view. That is to say, his view is that some but not all of the prophecies of the New Testament are fulfilled at the destruction of Jerusalem and the events surrounding it. This is partial preterism, not its heretical evil twin, full or hyper-preterism.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 3</span></p>
<p>In my last post I quoted Owen’s statement of his partial preterist view of 2 Peter 3. I believe this view to be seriously misguided in the exegesis of 2 Peter 3 and also burdened with serious, practical consequences. Let me hasten to add that these serious, practical consequences were probably not as visible nor even as serious in Owen’s day as they are in ours.</p>
<p>In defense of his partial preterist view of the prophecy of 2 Peter 3 Owen says that “I shall offer these two reasons, of many that might be insisted on from the text.” Here is the first of those two reasons.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Because whatever is here mentioned was to have its peculiar influence on the men of that generation. He speaks of that wherein both the profane scoffers and those scoffed at were concerned, and that as Jews;–some of them believing, others opposing the faith. Now, there was no particular concernment of that generation in that sin, nor in that scoffing, as to the day of judgment in general; but there was a peculiar relief for the one and a peculiar dread of the other at hand, in the destruction of the Jewish nation; and, besides, an ample testimony, both to the one and the other, of the power and dominion of the Lord Jesus Christ;–which was the thing in question between them.” (Works, 9:134)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a remarkable assertion. It assumes an identification of the false teaching with which Peter was dealing which will need to be examined. It also asserts that “there was no particular concernment of that generation in that sin, nor in that scoffing, as to the day of judgment in general.” This assertion also needs to be questioned.</p>
<p>But here is Owen’s second reason for his view. It contains assertions that are, if anything, even more troubling.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Peter tells them, that, after the destruction and judgment that he speaks of, verse 13, “We, according to his promise, look for new heavens and a new earth,” etc. They had this expectation. But what is that promise? Where may we find it? Why, we have it in the very words and letter, Isa. Lxv. 17. Now, when shall this that God will create these “new heavens and new earth, wherein dwelleth righteousness?” Saith Peter, “It shall be after the coming of the Lord, after that judgment and destruction of ungodly men, who obey not the gospel, that I foretell.” But now it is evident, from this place of Isaiah, with chap. Lxvi. 21, 22, that this is a prophecy of gospel times only; and that the planting of these new heavens is nothing but the creation of gospel ordinances, to endure for ever. The same thing is so expressed, Heb. Xii. 26-28.” (Works, 9:134, 135)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We must begin to explore the validity of these arguments and their truly massive implications in the next post.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 4</span></p>
<p>Owen’s way of reading 2 Peter 3 is so alien to most Christians in our day that there may be some doubt about what he is actually saying and implying. In this post I want to emphasize both the explicit and the implicit significance of the way Owen interprets 2 Peter 3. My hope is that the results of this survey will by themselves raise significant doubt about the propriety of Owen’s exegesis.</p>
<h3><strong>The Explicit Extent of Owen’s Argument</strong></h3>
<p>Owen takes Luke 21:34, 36 as a reference to the destruction of Jerusalem (page 138). Here is what he says speaking of the “dissolution” of “the Judaical church and state”:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“As it was foretold and threatened by Christ. How were believers cautioned to be ready for it with eminent holiness and watchfulness therein! So Luke xxi. 34, 36, “Take heed to yourselves; watch, therefore.” Why so? “Christ is coming,” verse 27. When? “Why in this generation,” verse 32. What to do? “Why, to dissolve heaven and earth,” verse 25; to “dissolve the Jewish church and state. Watch, therefore, give all diligence.” So also Matt. Xxiv. 42.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Owen takes the words of 2 Peter 3:4 (“the promise of His Parousia”) as a reference to Jesus’ coming at the destruction of Jerusalem in AD 70. Thus, it is not just a coming, but the Parousia which is said to occur at the destruction of Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Owen takes Isaiah 65:17f. as exclusively a reference to the present gospel age (page 135). Remember his words: “this is a prophecy of gospel times only; and that the planting of these new heavens is nothing but the creation of gospel ordinances…” It would be one thing if Owen maintained that this was a promise anticipated or even partly fulfilled in the gospel age. His words, however, are clear. They are exclusively fulfilled in the gospel age— “nothing but the creation of gospel ordinances.”</p>
<p>I find this interpretation deeply troubling in itself for a number of reasons, but what I find even more troubling are its implications or consequences. I will point out those consequences in my next post.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 5</span></p>
<p>In my last post I attempted to emphasize several of the explicit assertions of Owen regarding 2 Peter 3. In this post I want to suggest that there are several natural inferences or implications of Owen’s argument that need to be carefully weighed.</p>
<h3><strong>The Inferential Implications of Owen’s Argument</strong></h3>
<p>Here is the first one. If Owen is right, then it follows that the whole Olivet Discourse speaks only of the coming of Jesus for the destruction of Jerusalem. Peter’s words allude to Matthew 24. There is a seamless web between Matthew 24 and 25. Thus, Matthew 25:31-46, the passage which speaks of Jesus coming in glory to judge all nations and consign the sheep to eternal life and the goats to eternal punishment, must rather refer to the coming of Jesus at the destruction of Jerusalem. This passage which speaks so clearly of day of judgment would appear to be nothing more than a prophecy of the destruction of Jerusalem.</p>
<p>Another inference which may naturally be drawn from Owen is that the other references to the coming of Christ in 1 Peter and 2 Peter must be thought as references to the coming of Christ at the destruction of Jerusalem. I refer to passages such as these:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“so that the proof of your faith, being more precious than gold which is perishable, even though tested by fire, may be found to result in praise and glory and honor at the revelation of Jesus Christ;” (1 Pet. 1:7 NAU)</p>
<p>“Therefore, prepare your minds for action, keep sober in spirit, fix your hope completely on the grace to be brought to you at the revelation of Jesus Christ.” (1 Pet. 1:13 NAU)</p>
<p>“The end of all things is near; therefore, be of sound judgment and sober spirit for the purpose of prayer.” (1 Pet. 4:7 NAU)</p>
<p>“but to the degree that you share the sufferings of Christ, keep on rejoicing, so that also at the revelation of His glory you may rejoice with exultation.” (1 Pet. 4:13 NAU)</p>
<p>“And when the Chief Shepherd appears, you will receive the unfading crown of glory.” (1 Pet. 5:4 NAU)</p>
<p>“for in this way the entrance into the eternal kingdom of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ will be abundantly supplied to you.” (2 Pet. 1:11 NAU)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now let me be clear that I do not know how Owen may have interpreted these passages. I am only asserting that upon the exegetical grounds he takes in 2 Peter 3 all of them may be so interpreted as to refer merely to the destruction of Jerusalem.</p>
<p>I have already admitted that Owen here seems clearly to be adopting a partial preterist position. It also needs to be said, however, that upon Owen’s principles of interpretation it is difficult to find a clear text in the New Testament that teaches the Second Coming of Christ in glory at the end of the age. This is surely a consequence of his exegesis that must be carefully weighed.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 6</span></p>
<p>In my last couple of posts I tried to lay out fairly what I understand both the explicit extent of Owen’s argument for a preterist interpretation of 2 Peter 3 and also the inferential implications of that argument. My purpose, I admit, was not only to help my readers understand Owen, but to share what are to me the troubling implications of his exegesis. In this post and the following I want to turn to a number of serious objections to his view.</p>
<h3><strong>The Conclusive Case against Owen’s Interpretation</strong></h3>
<p>The first argument in my case against Owen is the lack of analogy between Owen’s view of the new heavens and earth in verse 13 and the whole thrust and movement of Peter’s argument in 2 Peter 3. As I have documented in my End Times Made Simple, Peter’s eschatological teaching in this passage is broadly speaking built around three worlds divided by two destructions. There is the old world which was created by God and destroyed by water (verses 5-6). There is the present or now world that is reserved for fire (verse 7). There is the new heaven and new earth (v. 13).</p>
<p>I think this structure is absolutely inconsistent with a preterist view of new heavens and earth. The reason should be clear. The original heavens and earth were the physical universe created by God in the beginning and destroyed in the universal flood. This pointedly suggests that the new heavens and new earth must also be that same universe remade in the resurrection glory of the sons of God (Romans 8:19-23). Furthermore, the water which destroyed the world in the flood was literal water. This directly leads to the conclusion that the fire of the greater judgment was a fire which reduces the world to ashes. It is not a spiritual fire which destroyed the Judaical system. Yes, I know that some fire was used in the destruction of Jerusalem, but it certainly does not qualify for the kind of fiery destruction of which 2 Peter 3 speaks—if it is taken literally.</p>
<p>The second argument is really a kind of exegetical focusing of the first. The focus of which I speak is the movement from destruction of the old world in the flood in verse 6 to the preservation of the present heavens and earth for destruction by fire in verse 7. Look at these two verses once more: “through which the world at that time was destroyed, being flooded with water. But by His word the present heavens and earth are being reserved for fire, kept for the day of judgment and destruction of ungodly men.” Here the present heavens and earth are contrasted with the world that was destroyed by water. Of course, this included the religious and civil structures—whatever they were–of that world, but it certainly included much more. There was a massive upheaval of the physical surface of the world.” This destruction took place by physical water. To say that the counterpart of this physical water was the spiritual fire that destroyed Judaism simply defies the analogy instituted by Peter.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 7</span></p>
<p>In the last post I mentioned the first two points of my case against Owen’s preterist interpretation of 2 Peter 3, here I add a further argument in my case.</p>
<h3><strong>The Conclusive Case against Owen’s Interpretation Continued</strong></h3>
<p>Owen takes Luke 21:34, 36 as a reference to the destruction of Jerusalem (page 138). Let me remind you of his exact words:</p>
<p>“As it was foretold and threatened by Christ. How were believers cautioned to be ready for it with eminent holiness and watchfulness therein! So Luke xxi. 34, 36, “Take heed to yourselves; watch, therefore.” Why so? “Christ is coming,” verse 27. When? “Why in this generation,” verse 32. What to do? “Why, to dissolve heaven and earth,” verse 25; to “dissolve the Jewish church and state. Watch, therefore, give all diligence.” So also Matt. Xxiv. 42.”</p>
<p>It is perfectly evident from this that Owen takes the coming of which Luke 21:27 speaks as a spiritual coming of Christ at the destruction of Jerusalem. The problem with this becomes evident when one reads the context of these verses and what they say about the coming of Christ there described.</p>
<p>Consider Luke 21:23-27</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Woe to those who are pregnant and to those who are nursing babies in those days; for there will be great distress upon the land and wrath to this people; 24 and they will fall by the edge of the sword, and will be led captive into all the nations; and Jerusalem will be trampled underfoot by the Gentiles until the times of the Gentiles are fulfilled. 25 “There will be signs in sun and moon and stars, and on the earth dismay among nations, in perplexity at the roaring of the sea and the waves. 26 men fainting from fear and the expectation of the things which are coming upon the world; for the powers of the heavens will be shaken. 27 “Then they will see THE SON OF MAN COMING IN A CLOUD with power and great glory.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It is evident that the coming of which this passage speaks does not take place at the destruction of Jerusalem. The order is explicit. There is (1) the actual destruction of Jerusalem ending with the words “they will fall by the edge of the sword (vv. 23-24a) (2) the exile of the Jews into all the nations (v. 24b) (3) Jerusalem trampled down by the Gentiles until the times of the Gentiles are fulfilled (v. 24c) (4) signs in the sun, moon, and stars, and on the earth dismay among the nations etc. (v. 26) (5) Then the coming of the Son of man (v. 27). Plainly, this coming does not take place at, or anywhere near, the time of the destruction of Jerusalem.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 8</span></p>
<p>So far I have covered three points in my case against John Owen’s preterist view of 2 Peter 3. Let’s add a fourth in this post.</p>
<h3><strong>The Conclusive Case against Owen’s Interpretation Continued</strong></h3>
<p>Owen takes the words of verse 4 (“the promise of His Parousia”) as a reference to Jesus’ coming at the destruction of Jerusalem in AD 70. My emphasis is on the fact that verse 4 speaks of the Parousia of Christ. It does not speak merely of a coming of Christ, but of His Parousia.</p>
<p>The word, Parousia, means arrival or presence or being present. One lexicon (Friberg) goes on to add that it is the opposite of apousia which is absence or being away. This word is used 24 times in the New Testament. In 6 of those occurrences the reference is to the coming or arrival and presence of someone other than Christ. The other 18 occurrences in all sorts of ways clearly and exclusively refer to the Second Coming of Christ in glory at the end of the age. Let me mention and comment on a few of these usages.</p>
<p>Matthew 24:27 “For just as the lightning comes from the east and flashes even to the west, so will the coming of the Son of Man be.” While preterists take all of the references to the coming of Christ in Matthew 24 as references to the coming of Christ at the destruction of Jerusalem, the difficulty with so understanding this text is obvious. The “coming” of Christ at the destruction of Jerusalem was not obvious in the Americas nor in China, for instance. The Parousia, however, is obvious from one end of heaven to the other like a flash of lightning.</p>
<p>1 Corinthians 15:23 “But each in his own order: Christ the first fruits, after that those who are Christ’s at His coming…” Here the resurrection of Christ’s people is coincident with His Parousia. Did this take place at the destruction of Jerusalem. Hyper-preterists say so, but I do not think that partial preterists want to assert this.</p>
<p>1 Thessalonians 4:15 “For this we say to you by the word of the Lord, that we who are alive and remain until the coming of the Lord, will not precede those who have fallen asleep.” This is the classic text on Christ’s Second Coming and it uses the term, Parousia, to describe that coming. The Parousia here is associated with meeting the Lord in the air. Verse 17 contains Paul’s famous assertion that believers will meet the Lord in the air. Pretribulationists assume that this statement implies that after this meeting, Christ and the church return together to heaven. Actually, this is neither stated, nor implied. In fact the word in the original (apantesis) implies exactly the opposite. F. F. Bruce says: “When a dignitary paid an official visit or parousia to a city in Hellenistic times, the action of the leading citizens in going out to meet him and escorting him on the final stage of his journey was called the apantesis….” Gundry aptly comments on the implication of this word: “This connotation points toward our rising to meet Christ in order to escort Him immediately back to earth.” This meaning of meeting (apantesis) is confirmed by its two other uses in the New Testament. Matt. 25:6 speaks of the ten virgins who were waiting to go out and meet the bridegroom and then return with him to the wedding feast. Even more clearly Acts 28:15 speaks of how the brethren came out to meet Paul and accompanied him on the final leg of his journey to Rome. If this is the meaning and implication of the word, then it is utterly inconsistent with the Pretribulational theory. It is also clearly inconsistent with a preterist interpretation of the Parousia.</p>
<p>There is one New Testament use of Parousia which is capable of being interpreted as not a reference to Christ’s final coming in glory. That passage is found in 2 Peter itself.</p>
<p>2 Peter 1:16 “For we did not follow cleverly devised tales when we made known to you the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but we were eyewitnesses of His majesty.” Because of the association of these words with the transfiguration, some have assumed that Parousia here is a reference to that event. If so, it is the only use of the word to refer to that event to be found in the New Testament. It is preferable by far to understand that the transfiguration is here viewed as substantiating the Apostle Peter’s claims (1) that Jesus was the supernatural Son of God and (2) that Jesus would come again in glory.</p>
<p>In the context of the New Testament the Parousia of Christ is always a reference to the Second Coming of Christ in glory. It is not suggestive of a preterist interpretation anywhere and certainly not in 2 Peter 3:4.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 9</span></p>
<p>So far, I have covered three points in my case against John Owen’s preterist view of 2 Peter 3. Let me add a fourth in this post.</p>
<h3><strong>The Conclusive Case against Owen’s Interpretation Continued</strong></h3>
<p>Owen takes Isaiah 65:17f. as a reference to the present gospel age exclusively (page 135). Let me quote what he says again: “this is a prophecy of gospel times only; and that the planting of these new heavens is nothing but the creation of gospel ordinances…” It would be one thing if Owen maintained that this was a promise anticipated or even partly fulfilled in the gospel age. His words, however, are clear. They are exclusively fulfilled in the gospel age— “nothing but the creation of gospel ordinances.”</p>
<p>Owen here takes what seems to me to be an indefensibly one-sided view of Old Testament prophecy. Jesus makes clear in Matthew 13 that the mystery of the coming of the kingdom is that it comes in two stages. The grand prophecies of the return of the kingdom of God to our world are fulfilled both in the events of Christ’s first advent but fully and finally in the events that accompany and follow Christ’s Second Advent in glory. This matter of the already and not yet is really a matter of settled perspective among most Reformed exegetes today. While I am not saying that Owen would have been wholly unaware of such a perspective, I am saying that he chooses to adopt a totally preterist view of the New Heavens and New Earth in his exegesis of 2 Peter 3.</p>
<p>This is questionable enough in itself, but it is even more questionable in light of the way in which the other passage in the New Testament which alludes to Isaiah 65:17f. does so. There are clear allusions to the language of Isaiah 65:17f. in Revelation 21:1-4. Look at that passage: “Then I saw a new heaven and a new earth; for the first heaven and the first earth passed away, and there is no longer any sea. 2 And I saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, made ready as a bride adorned for her husband. 3 And I heard a loud voice from the throne, saying, “Behold, the tabernacle of God is among men, and He will dwell among them, and they shall be His people, and God Himself will be among them, 4 and He will wipe away every tear from their eyes; and there will no longer be any death; there will no longer be any mourning, or crying, or pain; the first things have passed away.”</p>
<p>There are multiple allusions to Isaiah 65:17f. in these verses. First, there is the reference to the new heavens and new earth which is a clear quotation of Isaiah 65:17f. and Isaiah 66:22f. Second, there is the reference to the holy city which is also mentioned in Isaiah 65:18-19. Third, there is the affirmation of the end of weeping and crying in Isaiah 65:17f. Kraugei in the LXX of Isaiah 65:19 is translated crying in the NASB and is used in Revelation 21:4. Ponos, the word translated pain in Revelation 21:4 is used in the LXX of Isaiah 65:22. The closing words of Revelation 21:4 (the first things have passed away.) also appear to allude to the words of Isaiah 65:17 “And the former things will not be remembered or come to mind.” Fourth, the condition of which Isaiah speaks is eternal (Isaiah 65:17-18). This means that it is the eternal state that is in view. Fifth, the condition contemplated in Isaiah 65:17f. is one in which there is an absence of evil. “The wolf and the lamb will graze together, and the lion will eat straw like the ox; and dust will be the serpent’s food. They will do no evil or harm in all My holy mountain,” says the LORD.” This is parallel to the assertions of Revelation 21:8 and 27.</p>
<p>There is an indisputable reference to Isaiah 65:17f. in Revelation 21:1-4. I understand that some preterists even take Revelation 21:1-14 as a reference to the gospel age. I can only say that, if they do refer to this, I do not know how to understand their significance. Personally, I think such an interpretation of Revelation lacks credibility.</p>
<p>But something more needs to be said about the phrase, new heavens and new earth. While I admit that an already/not yet grid has to be applied to Old Testament prophecy. I believe that this particular phrase and these particular passages show that the emphasis if not the exclusive meaning of these phrases is on the eternal state. Certainly, Isaiah 66:22-24 seems to emphasize the eternal state. I have also argued elsewhere against Premillennialism that Isaiah 65:17f. must be understood as a prophecy of the eternal state, and the language which suggests death in the state contemplated is to be taken as a promise of the end of calamity and figuratively speaking of what Revelation 21:4 calls “no longer any death.” See my End Times Made Simple and my critique of Matt Waymeyer published in JIRBS.</p>
<p>Something else must be considered. It is that the phrase in verse 13 which is descriptive of the new heavens and new earth, “in which righteousness dwells,” alludes to other prophecies in later Isaiah which appear to speak of the eternal state. Cf. Isaiah 11:9; 52:1; 54:13-14; 60:21.</p>
<p>The notion that 2 Peter 3:13 refers only to the gospel age simply lacks credibility.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 10</span></p>
<p>So far, I have covered five points in my case against John Owen’s preterist view of 2 Peter 3. Let me add another argument in this post. Here is my sixth objection to Owen’s exegesis.</p>
<h3><strong>The Conclusive Case against Owen’s Interpretation Continued</strong></h3>
<p>Owen takes 2 Peter 3:4 as concerning Jews only and only relevant to the men of that generation (page 134). The words of Owen are: “Because whatever is here mentioned was to have its peculiar influence on the men of that generation. He speaks of that wherein both the profane scoffers and those scoffed at were concerned, and that as Jews;—some of them believing, others opposing the faith. Now, there was no particular concernment of that generation in that sin, nor in that scoffing, as to the day of judgment in general; but there was a peculiar relief for the one and a peculiar dread of the other at hand, in the destruction of the Jewish nation; and, besides, an ample testimony, both to the one and the other, of the power and dominion of the Lord Jesus Christ; —which was the thing in question between them.” (Works, 9:134)</p>
<p>To state the problem briefly, such an approach to the imminence of Christ’s return suggests that Christ’s Second Coming in glory is not relevant for this early generation of the Christian era. The problem is that, if there is any evidence for the Second Coming in the New Testament, it is always accompanied by exhortations that it is near and that we are to stay awake, be alert, not fall asleep. However we explain the imminence and relevance of Christ’s long awaited return for that generation, it is clearly relevant to them. This doubt arises in light of Owen’s exegesis: how could any passage which speaks of a coming of Christ that is relevant for that generation of Jews, actually be a reference to His future return in glory?</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 11</span></p>
<p>So far, I have covered six points in my case against John Owen’s preterist view of 2 Peter 3. Let me add another argument in this post. Here is my seventh objection to Owen’s exegesis.</p>
<h3><strong>The Conclusive Case against Owen’s Interpretation Continued</strong></h3>
<p>Owen assumes that the false teachers of 2 Peter are a reference to the Jews who clung to the Old Testament institutions and the legalism that had grown up around them. Here is Owen once more: “He speaks of that wherein both the profane scoffers and those scoffed at were concerned, and that as Jews; —some of them believing, others opposing the faith. Now, there was no particular concernment of that generation in that sin, nor in that scoffing, as to the day of judgment in general; but there was a peculiar relief for the one and a peculiar dread of the other at hand, in the destruction of the Jewish nation; and, besides, an ample testimony, both to the one and the other, of the power and dominion of the Lord Jesus Christ; —which was the thing in question between them.” (Works, 9:134)</p>
<p>This account of the false teachers with whom Peter was contending is out of sync with the whole presentation of them in 2 Peter. These men were not legalistic defenders of the Old Judaism. Peter makes clear that they had been and perhaps still were professing Christians (2 Peter 2:1-2, 20-22) who distorted the teaching of the Apostle Paul (2 Peter 3:16) and (far from being legalists) were antinomians in their views and practice (2 Peter 2:12-18).</p>
<p>To sum up: the false teachers of 2 Peter 2 and 3 were not Jews opposing Christ, but antinomians who had professed Christ and followed Paul, but who had distorted Christian truth to their own destruction. Cf. Matthew 24:48 for the background of Peter’s thought which predicts every feature of these false teachers.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 12</span></p>
<p>So far, I have covered seven points in my case against John Owen’s preterist view of 2 Peter 3. Let me add another argument in this post. Here is my eighth objection to Owen’s exegesis.</p>
<h3><strong>The Conclusive Case against Owen’s Interpretation Continued</strong></h3>
<p>The whole Olivet Discourse speaks (according to Owen) only of the coming of Jesus for the destruction of Jerusalem. Peter’s words allude to Matthew 24. We have repeatedly noted the insistence of Owen on this fact.</p>
<p>My objection is that this straightforwardly and directly implies that the account of the judgment found in Matthew 25:31-46 must refer to the coming of Jesus at the destruction of Jerusalem. There is a seamless web of references to Christ’s coming between Matthew 24 and 25. Thus, Matthew 25:31-46 must refer to the coming of Jesus at the destruction of Jerusalem. But this requires a preterist understanding of the words of Matthew 25:31-32: “But when the Son of Man comes in His glory, and all the angels with Him, then He will sit on His glorious throne. 32 “All the nations will be gathered before Him; and He will separate them from one another, as the shepherd separates the sheep from the goats.” It also requires that Matthew 25:46 be a reference to an event that happened at the destruction of Jerusalem: “These will go away into eternal punishment, but the righteous into eternal life.” Not only is such an understanding of Matthew 25:31-46 unlikely to the point of impossibility, it is also dangerous in a broader way</p>
<p>Upon Owen’s interpretation, what are we to think of the other references to the coming of Christ throughout 1 and 2 Peter? Must they not be thought of as references to the coming of Christ at the destruction of Jerusalem? It would seem so. Thus, for instance, are we to take a preterist interpretation on 1 Peter 5:4? “And when the Chief Shepherd appears, you will receive the unfading crown of glory.”</p>
<p>This brings us, then, to the most serious challenge and difficulty for orthodox preterists like Owen. They have to show how their views can be held without leading directly down a slippery slope to Hyper-preterism? Upon Owen’s interpretation, it seems to me, it is difficult to find any clear text in the New Testament that teaches the Second Coming of Christ in glory at the end of the age.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Part 13</span></p>
<h3><strong>Conclusion</strong></h3>
<p>If Owen was indeed wrong as we have seen, what can we learn from this fact? It is to answer this question that I have taken so much time to firmly disagree with the properly revered John Owen. I believe there is something to be learned from the serious exegetical mistake he makes with 2 Peter 3. I think there are important lessons to be learned.</p>
<p>First, this shows that no one—not even the man who is probably the greatest of the Puritan and Reformed Scholastics—may be given an almost infallible status by us. The fact is that in some places—it has appeared to me—that if Owen said it, that was the end of all discussion. That is certainly not true with regard to his preterist interpretation of 2 Peter 3. It may not be true in other places.</p>
<p>Second, this shows that we may not fix one period of church history, and one group of theologians in that history, as the standard of orthodoxy for all times. The Bible teaches a developmental or progressivist view of church history. That means that, not only was there progressive revelation in the Bible, there is progressive enlightenment of the church during this inter-adventual period. This is the straightforward implication of the parables of Jesus regarding the wheat and weeds, the mustard seed, the leaven, and the seed growing by itself.</p>
<p>As much as we love the Puritans and as much as we love our Baptist forefathers, church history did not end with them. Nor did the church’s insight into the Scriptures cease developing. Valuable as is our honored confession of faith, it is a human document which reflects the best understanding of the Scriptures by the church at a certain point in time in that development. Personally, I do not think that we have come to the place where it is good to think of attempting an expansion or refinement of that great document. But in principle we must admit that such a place could come in a future era of the church.</p>
<p>Third, let me finally express my view that it is particularly in the doctrinal area where Owen goes wrong that we must be ready for further light upon Scripture to have been given to the church since the 17th century. There have been vast and important developments in eschatological thought since Owen wrote. There was the prevalence of postmillennialism for a time, followed by the rise of historic premillennialism and dispensational premillennialism in reaction to postmillennialism. There has been the long critique of Dispensationalism by Amillennialism, the splintering of Dispensationalism as a result, and the rise of a new and wiser form of Amillennialism. I think this history is significant. I think it has presented us with an alternative to Owen’s preterism which is vastly to be preferred.</p>


<p></p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-owen-a-caveat-parts-1-13/">John Owen—A Caveat, parts 1-13</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/john-owen-a-caveat-parts-1-13/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>#DatPostmil? #5: The Problem with Preterism</title>
		<link>/datpostmil-5-the-problem-with-preterism/</link>
					<comments>/datpostmil-5-the-problem-with-preterism/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=17393</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Preterism is one of a number of different methods of prophetic interpretation that have been adopted and defended by various biblical intepreters. A little background may be helpful before I come to my discussion of preterism in particular.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/datpostmil-5-the-problem-with-preterism/">#DatPostmil? #5: The Problem with Preterism</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_3 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_3">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_5  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_2  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p><em>This is part 5 of a 5 part series on &#8220;#datpostmil?&#8221; View: <span style="color: #0a0808;"><a href="/datpostmil-a-friendly-and-reluctant-response-to-james-white-and-all-my-postmillennial-friends/" style="color: #0a0808;" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 1</span></a>, <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="/datpostmil-2-a-present-evil-age/" style="color: #0a0808; text-decoration: underline;" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2,</a></span><a href="/datpostmil-4-does-the-growth-of-the-kingdom-require-postmillennialism/(opens%20in a new tab)" style="color: #0a0808; text-decoration: underline;"></a> <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="/datpostmil-3-the-postmillennial-doctrine-of-bifurcation-two-ages-in-the-gospel-age/" style="color: #0a0808; text-decoration: underline;" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3,</a></span> <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="/datpostmil-4-does-the-growth-of-the-kingdom-require-postmillennialism/" style="color: #0a0808; text-decoration: underline;" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4</a></span></span></em></p>
<p><strong></strong></p>
<h2><strong><em>The Problem with Preterism</em></strong></h2>
<p>Preterism is one of a number of different methods of prophetic interpretation that have been adopted and defended by various biblical intepreters. A little background may be helpful before I come to my discussion of preterism in particular.</p>
<p>These contrasting methods of biblical interpretation often are used to speak of how various schools interpret the Book of Revelation. Common today is the futurist school which thinks that the Revelation beginning with chapter 4 speaks of a future time of tribulation and what happens afterward. Common in past centuries and especially around the time of the Reformation and afterward is the historicist school which viewed the Revelation as a symbolic, consecutive, chronological account of the history of the gospel age and afterward. It is noteworthy that this view is associated with the notion that the institution of the papacy was (and is) the antichrist. Becoming more common today is the preterist school which see the Revelation as written prior to the destruction of Jerusalem in A. D. 70. It sees its prophecies as fulfilled mainly in that event and the events leading up to it. There is a close association historically and currently between Postmillennialism and Preterism.</p>
<p>Truth in advertising requires me to say that I hold none of these views. Rather, I hold to a fourth view which may be called idealism. Though idealism is sometimes associated with a liberal approach to the Revelation, I hold to a redemptive-historical, modified form of idealism which sees the prophecies of the Book of Revelation as cycling through various apocalyptic pictures of the gospel age and what follows.</p>
<p>Each of these views has also been applied by the various schools to other of the prophetic portions of Scripture. Here I am particularly concerned with the preterist method which has been applied to 2 Peter 3, 2 Thessalonians 2, and Matthew 24. John Owen, on the basis of preterism, thought that the new heavens and new earth of 2 Peter 3 was the gospel age. B. B. Warfield suspected that 2 Thessalonians 2 was fulfilled in current events taking place in and around the destruction of Jerusalem in A. D. 70. J. Marcellus Kik and many others regard Matthew 24 as fulfilled by the destruction of Jerusalem.</p>
<p>One other piece of background to my discussion of preterism is this. What I have called “orthodox preterism” has an evil twin which I will call Hyper-preterism. The difference between the two views is important. Orthodox preterism believes that <em>many or most</em> prophecies were fulfilled in the past by the events surrounding the destruction of Jerusalem. Hyper-preterism believes that they <em>all</em> were. Thus, the Second Coming of Christ and the resurrection of the dead took place in A. D. 70. Hyper-preterism is, in my view, straightforwardly heretical. I do not use the word lightly!</p>
<p>I want to focus on the interpretation of Matthew 24 and the Olivet Discourse by orthodox preterism. (I offer another and what I think is a superior interpretation of Matthew 24 in my book, <em>More of the End Times Made Simple</em>. It is based on the wonderful interpretation of the Olivet Discourse by John Murray in the second volume of His <em>Collected Works</em> which is entitled, “The Interadventual Period<em>.</em>” I hope you will read either Murray or me if you are attracted by the preterist interpretation.) The simple fact is that orthodox preterists take language like the following as referring to a figurative or spiritual coming of Christ at the destruction of Jerusalem:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Matthew 24:27 &#8220;For just as the lightning comes from the east and flashes even to the west, so will the coming of the Son of Man be.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Matthew 24:29 &#8220;But immediately after the tribulation of those days THE SUN WILL BE DARKENED, AND THE MOON WILL NOT GIVE ITS LIGHT, AND THE STARS WILL FALL from the sky, and the powers of the heavens will be shaken. 30 &#8220;And then the sign of the Son of Man will appear in the sky, and then all the tribes of the earth will mourn, and they will see the SON OF MAN COMING ON THE CLOUDS OF THE SKY with power and great glory. 31 &#8220;And He will send forth His angels with A GREAT TRUMPET and THEY WILL GATHER TOGETHER His elect from the four winds, from one end of the sky to the other.</p>
<p>Matthew 24:36 &#8220;But of that day and hour no one knows, not even the angels of heaven, nor the Son, but the Father alone.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As I have said previously, they also commonly take the language of 2 Peter 3 and 2 Thessalonians 2 as referring to the same figurative or spiritual coming of Christ in A. D. 70. Yes, the reference to the new heavens and new earth brought in by the day of the Lord and Parousia of Christ in 2 Peter 3:3-13 refers according to preterists to this “coming” of Christ in A. D. 70. Yes, the Parousia which destroys the man of sin is also a reference to this same coming.</p>
<p>Here, then, is the problem with orthodox preterism. I do not see how orthodox preterism does not become hyper-preterism. There is a hermeneutical slippery slope here. If such language in such passages may refer to the coming of Christ in A. D. 70, what language teaching the Second Coming of Christ in the New Testament cannot (on the basis of the same hermeneutical principles) be explained away? Orthodox preterism is in constant danger of becoming its evil and heretical twin.</p>
<p>Do not misunderstand me. I know orthodox preterists do not come to this hyper-preterist conclusion. I know orthodox preterists do not want to come to this conclusion. I am simply saying that I do not know how orthodox preterists avoid coming to this conclusion. Their hermeneutic logically brings them there—if even against their will.</p>
<p>How is this relevant to Postmillennialism? It is relevant simply because many, if not most, Postmillennialists have adopted orthodox preterism as the hermeneutic most amenable to their position. I think they have been right to do so in the sense that the other views (with the possible exception of historicism) are not consistent with their views.</p>
<p>I believe that there have also been historicist Postmillennialists. This was probably Jonathan Edwards’ approach. The fact is that historicist interpretations of Revelation have been proven so frequently and wildly wrong in their interpretations that—at least for me—they have even less credibility than preterism. This is certainly true of the historicism of both Jonathan Edwards and Thomas Goodwin.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --> </p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_4 et_pb_with_background et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_4">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_6  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_3">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737507/ref=sr_1_1?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165840&#038;sr=8-1" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-1" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg 224w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1-194x300.jpg 194w" sizes="(max-width: 224px) 100vw, 224px" class="wp-image-16337" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_7  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_4">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MORE-End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737698/ref=sr_1_3?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165862&#038;sr=8-3" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-2" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg 336w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2-202x300.jpg 202w" sizes="(max-width: 336px) 100vw, 336px" class="wp-image-16339" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_8  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_5">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MacArthurs-Millennial-Manifesto-Samuel-Waldron/dp/098021792X/ref=pd_bxgy_img_3/132-2520012-4634739?_encoding=UTF8&#038;pd_rd_i=098021792X&#038;pd_rd_r=ac9f0afa-68d3-4ac2-8ef6-f5b4cadc19cd&#038;pd_rd_w=2dSwU&#038;pd_rd_wg=0rs7V&#038;pf_rd_p=f325d01c-4658-4593-be83-3e12ca663f0e&#038;pf_rd_r=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7&#038;psc=1&#038;refRID=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-3" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg 333w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 333px) 100vw, 333px" class="wp-image-16341" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/datpostmil-5-the-problem-with-preterism/">#DatPostmil? #5: The Problem with Preterism</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/datpostmil-5-the-problem-with-preterism/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>DatPostmil? #4: Does the Growth of the Kingdom Require Postmillennialism?</title>
		<link>/datpostmil-4-does-the-growth-of-the-kingdom-require-postmillennialism/</link>
					<comments>/datpostmil-4-does-the-growth-of-the-kingdom-require-postmillennialism/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 18:12:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=17384</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Sam Waldron Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/datpostmil-4-does-the-growth-of-the-kingdom-require-postmillennialism/">DatPostmil? #4: Does the Growth of the Kingdom Require Postmillennialism?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_5 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_5">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_9  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_3  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p><em>This is part 4 of a 5 part series on &#8220;#datpostmil?&#8221; View: <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="color: #0a0707;"><a href="/datpostmil-a-friendly-and-reluctant-response-to-james-white-and-all-my-postmillennial-friends/" style="color: #0a0707; text-decoration: underline;" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1</a></span></span>,<span style="text-decoration: underline; color: #0a0909;"><a href="/datpostmil-2-a-present-evil-age/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> Part 2</a>, <a href="/datpostmil-3-the-postmillennial-doctrine-of-bifurcation-two-ages-in-the-gospel-age/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3</a></span></em></p>
<p><strong></strong></p>
<h2><strong><em>Does the Growth of the Kingdom Require Postmillennialism? </em></strong></h2>
<p>I mentioned in my last post that there are passages which the Postmillenialists might complain I am overlooking. Let me reassure my postmillennial friends that I am not. These passages are exactly the ones that make me an Optimistic Amillennialist. Let me explain.</p>
<p>I did not mention two of the seven, great Parables of the Kingdom in Matthew 13. They are the Parable of the Mustard Seed (Matt. 13:31; Mark 4:31; Luke 13:19) and the Parable of the Leaven (Matthew 13:33; Luke 13:21). Both of them teach (and in my view teach clearly) that there will be a vast growth of the kingdom during the gospel age.</p>
<p>Similar are the implications of the promises and predictions Christ’s makes in Matthew 16:16-19 with regard to both the building of the church and the prevailing of the church against the gates of Hades. These are glorious and encouraging promises of the success of the gospel through the church and beginning in this age.</p>
<p>Other passages add to this emphasis on the progress of the kingdom. There is the Parable of the Seed Growing by Itself in Mark 4:26-29. There is also the suggestion in Ephesians 4:12-15 of the maturation of the church throughout the gospel age. Once more in Colossians 1:6 such growth is suggested.</p>
<p>Dr. White sees the inevitable progress of the kingdom in Psalm 2, Psalm 110, Isaiah 42, and 1 Corinthians 15:20-28. Let me affirm this. I see it in those passages too.</p>
<p>Clearly, Postmillennialists will not argue against my seeing growth and progress for the kingdom in these passages. They will wonder, however, how I avoid what they think are the inevitable, postmillennial implications of these passages. I think that this question is reasonable. I also think that it is answerable. What is that answer?</p>
<h2><em>Both Grow Together</em></h2>
<p>Jesus gives us the answer Himself and nowhere more clearly than in the Parable of the Wheat and Weeds.</p>
<p>Here is the telling of the parable …</p>
<blockquote>
<p><sup>24</sup> Jesus presented another parable to them, saying, &#8220;The kingdom of heaven may be compared to a man who sowed good seed in his field. <sup>25</sup> &#8220;But while his men were sleeping, his enemy came and sowed tares among the wheat, and went away. <sup>26</sup> &#8220;But when the wheat sprouted and bore grain, then the tares became evident also. <sup>27</sup> &#8220;The slaves of the landowner came and said to him, &#8216;Sir, did you not sow good seed in your field? How then does it have tares?&#8217; <sup>28</sup> &#8220;And he said to them, &#8216;An enemy has done this!&#8217; The slaves said to him, &#8216;Do you want us, then, to go and gather them up?&#8217; <sup>29</sup> &#8220;But he said, &#8216;No; for while you are gathering up the tares, you may uproot the wheat with them. <sup>30</sup> &#8216;Allow both to grow together until the harvest; and in the time of the harvest I will say to the reapers, &#8220;First gather up the tares and bind them in bundles to burn them up; but gather the wheat into my barn.&#8221;&#8216;&#8221;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here is the interpretation of the parable (which comes a few verses later) …</p>
<blockquote>
<p><sup>36</sup> Then He left the crowds and went into the house. And His disciples came to Him and said, &#8220;Explain to us the parable of the tares of the field.&#8221;<sup>37</sup> And He said, &#8220;The one who sows the good seed is the Son of Man, <sup>38</sup> and the field is the world; and as for the good seed, these are the sons of the kingdom; and the tares are the sons of the evil one; <sup>39</sup> and the enemy who sowed them is the devil, and the harvest is the end of the age; and the reapers are angels. <sup>40</sup> &#8220;So just as the tares are gathered up and burned with fire, so shall it be at the end of the age. <sup>41</sup> &#8220;The Son of Man will send forth His angels, and they will gather out of His kingdom all stumbling blocks, and those who commit lawlessness, <sup>42</sup> and will throw them into the furnace of fire; in that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth. <sup>43</sup> &#8220;Then THE RIGHTEOUS WILL SHINE FORTH AS THE SUN in the kingdom of their Father. He who has ears, let him hear.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Jesus’s key statement is found in Matthew 13:30: “Allow both to grow together until the harvest; and in the time of the harvest I will say to the reapers, &#8220;First gather up the tares and bind them in bundles to burn them up; but gather the wheat into my barn.&#8221;&#8216;” This is the answer of the Lord of the Harvest to a question of His servants. To their query whether they should hoe up the weeds that the enemy had sown, He replies that both wheat and weeds should be allowed to <strong><em>grow together</em></strong> until the harvest.</p>
<p>The error of the postmillennial use of all the growth and progress passages is here exposed. They assume that the growth of the wheat (the sons of the kingdom) during the gospel age means the withering of the weeds (the sons of the evil one). This assumption seems obvious to them, of course, but it is contrary to the teaching and assumption of Jesus. Jesus thinks that both good and evil will keep growing and grow together till the end of the age.</p>
<p>This view seems strange to us. This logic is contrary to our limited logic. There is, however, a deep truth in it. Evil gets worse just because good gets better. Good must get better in response to the putrid evil of the wicked; or it will be overcome.</p>
<p>This growth of both good and evil together is also the implication of other passages. Allow me to set aside for now the Preterist interpretation of Matthew 24. I will deal with it later. Let me say only what seems obvious to me and many Christians. Somehow this passage speaks not just of the Destruction of Jerusalem, but also of the Second Coming of Christ and the whole “inter-adventual” period or gospel age. Understood in this way, the passage teaches that the gospel of the kingdom will be preached in all the world in the midst of the darkness, chaos, and turmoil of the present age predicted in Matthew 24:1-36. Matthew 24:14 reads: “This gospel of the kingdom shall be preached in the whole world as a testimony to all the nations, and then the end will come.”</p>
<p>Similarly, when Christ is on the throne, He has ascended in Revelation 5 and breaks the seals on the book which contains the end of the world. There is once more the progress of the gospel in the midst of trouble and chaos.</p>
<p>Though I make no claim to understand everything in the Book of Revelation, it seems to me that Revelation 5 and 6 do speak clearly of the enthronement of Christ at His resurrection. When in Revelation 6 you have the breaking of the seals on the book, it seems clearly to speak of the characteristics of this age. Yes, there is in the first seal Christ on the white horse winning gospel victories throughout the world, but these gospel victories do not appear to create a golden age in the period between Christ’s first and second advents. Rather, these gospel victories are gained in the midst of turmoil and distress. The second seal looses war on the world (Rev. 6:4). The third seal looses famine on the world (Rev. 6:5-6). The fourth seal looses mass death on the world (Rev. 6:7-8). The fifth seal returns to the plight of the saints in the gospel age and speaks of the reality of martyrdom (Rev. 6:9-11). The sixth seal speaks of the impending judgment which hangs over this age. The seventh seal brings us to the seven trumpets which warn of judgment and the next picture of this age. In the interim between the sixth and seventh seals there is perhaps a picture of the gathering of the elect, but there is no picture of millennial glory during or at the end of the gospel age.</p>
<p>Yes, the gospel wins victories throughout the world, but this does not create a golden age. Those victories are won in a day of darkness and difficulty.</p>
<h2><em>Get Off the Millennial Teeter-totter</em></h2>
<p>Postmillennialism is actually guilty of the equal and opposite error committed by Premillennialism and Pessimillennialism. Premillennialists look at all the passages that speak of the growth and progress of evil during this age. Evil men will get worse (2 Timothy 3:13). The mystery of iniquity already works (2 Thessalonians 2:7). The time of tribulation and the antichrist are coming at the very end of the age (2 Thessalonians 2:3, 8, 9; Revelation 20:9-10). They deduce from all this that dark days of apostasy are ahead for the church. They deduce from this that the church age will end in failure like all the other dispensations.</p>
<p>But they are wrong to think this way. The growth and progress of evil does not mean that the good seed stops growing or withers. <em>Both grow together until the harvest!</em></p>
<p>But in exactly the same way and for exactly the same reason the postmillennial deduction from the passages that teach growth and progress is wrong. The growth of the good seed does not mean the withering of the evil seed until a golden age of peace, prosperity, and righteousness dominates the world. <em>Both grow together until the harvest!</em></p>
<p>Yes, the kingdom will one day rule the world. Yes, Christ will defeat all of His enemies. But this final victory awaits His return. Only then is the last enemy destroyed. The teaching of the Bible is the progress of the kingdom in this age and the triumph of the kingdom in the age to come. <em>Both grow together until the harvest!</em></p>
<p>I am, then, an Optimistic Amillennialist. I am very optimistic about the progress of the gospel throughout the world. I am very optimistic about the church being built throughout the world. I am not optimistic about the world. It will suffer under the growing of the weeds until harvest comes. Then there will come a new world in which righteousness dwells, <em>but not until then</em>. Growth never brings harvest. Only harvest (and the glorious return of the Lord of the harvest) brings harvest.</p>
<p><strong><em>What does the key passage—Revelation 20—actually teach about the millennium? </em></strong></p>
<p>There is one and only one passage in the Bible which explicitly speaks of the millennium. It seems necessary, therefore, to ask what Revelation 20 actually teaches about it. Of course, it is true that this passage has been a crux of New Testament interpretation for 2000 years.</p>
<p>I think, however, that I may assume that my postmillennial friends with me reject the literalism and weirdness of the premillennial interpretation of this passage in all its forms. I think they must also agree with me that this passage is crucial for our understanding of the millennium. Therefore, we must ask, Is the millennium here a golden age at the end of the gospel age?</p>
<p>It is obvious to me that the thousand years is not a period at the end of the gospel age. <em>It is the gospel age.</em> The thousand years begins with the binding of Satan. Once the literalism of Premillennialists is rejected; once the necessity of interpreting this passage according to the analogy of Scripture is accepted; then it is obvious that this binding of Satan took place at the time of Christ’s first advent and resurrection. Matthew 12:28-29; Luke 10:17-19; John 12:31-32; Colossians 2:15; Hebrews 2:14-15; 1 John 3:8; Revelation 12:10-15—all of these passages lead to the interpretation which sees the binding of Satan as beginning the gospel age and the spread of the gospel throughout the world.</p>
<p>On the other hand, there is no parallel passage which suggests a future, interim binding of Satan. Let me say that again. There are zero passages in the whole Bible that suggest that in the future, for a temporary period of time, Satan will be bound. On the other hand, there are seven clear passages which teach that he was bound by the events of Christ’s first advent. And this observation spells doom for both Premillenialism and Postmillennialism.</p>
<p>In particular, this is true for Postmillennialism. This passage teaches that the millennium began with Christ’s resurrection and is not a future golden age before Christ comes back. Whatever the millennium is, the fact is that we have been in it for 2000 years! This is <strong><em>not</em></strong> the postmillennial understanding of the matter.</p>
<p>Yet further, I noticed that at the end of the millennium of Revelation 20 there was a little season characterized by the loosing of Satan and a worldwide assault on the church. I find this also in 2 Thessalonians 2. There are a number of interesting parallels between 2 Thessalonians 2 and Revelation 20. Both speak of the restraint of evil for a period. Both speak of the loosing of evil on the world at a future time just before the Second Coming of Christ. Both speak of this time as a period of terrible deception. Both speak of the final destruction of evil by Christ at His Second Coming. Thus, in both passages, there is a little season of trouble for the church. During this little season, the antichrist appears in the midst of a great rebellion or apostasy against God. This ending of the gospel age in a global persecution of the church under the man of lawlessness seems clear in these passages. It does not, it seems to me, comport with the picture of the future painted by Postmillennialists.</p>
<p>Now, at this point, I am quite certain that, if my postmillennial friends are still reading, they have some questions they want to ask me. I have implied something other than a preterist understanding of Matthew 24 and 2 Thessalonians 2. I will take that up in my next post where I discuss the problems with Orthodox Preterism.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --> </p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_6 et_pb_with_background et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_6">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_10  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_6">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737507/ref=sr_1_1?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165840&#038;sr=8-1" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-1" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg 224w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1-194x300.jpg 194w" sizes="(max-width: 224px) 100vw, 224px" class="wp-image-16337" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_11  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_7">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MORE-End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737698/ref=sr_1_3?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165862&#038;sr=8-3" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-2" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg 336w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2-202x300.jpg 202w" sizes="(max-width: 336px) 100vw, 336px" class="wp-image-16339" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_12  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_8">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MacArthurs-Millennial-Manifesto-Samuel-Waldron/dp/098021792X/ref=pd_bxgy_img_3/132-2520012-4634739?_encoding=UTF8&#038;pd_rd_i=098021792X&#038;pd_rd_r=ac9f0afa-68d3-4ac2-8ef6-f5b4cadc19cd&#038;pd_rd_w=2dSwU&#038;pd_rd_wg=0rs7V&#038;pf_rd_p=f325d01c-4658-4593-be83-3e12ca663f0e&#038;pf_rd_r=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7&#038;psc=1&#038;refRID=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-3" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg 333w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 333px) 100vw, 333px" class="wp-image-16341" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/datpostmil-4-does-the-growth-of-the-kingdom-require-postmillennialism/">DatPostmil? #4: Does the Growth of the Kingdom Require Postmillennialism?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/datpostmil-4-does-the-growth-of-the-kingdom-require-postmillennialism/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>#DatPostmil? #3: The Postmillennial Doctrine of Bifurcation—Two ages in the Gospel Age?</title>
		<link>/datpostmil-3-the-postmillennial-doctrine-of-bifurcation-two-ages-in-the-gospel-age/</link>
					<comments>/datpostmil-3-the-postmillennial-doctrine-of-bifurcation-two-ages-in-the-gospel-age/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 17:19:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=17360</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Sam Waldron Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/datpostmil-3-the-postmillennial-doctrine-of-bifurcation-two-ages-in-the-gospel-age/">#DatPostmil? #3: The Postmillennial Doctrine of Bifurcation—Two ages in the Gospel Age?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_7 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_7">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_13  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_4  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p><em>This is part 3 of a 5 part series on &#8220;#datpostmil?&#8221; View: <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="/datpostmil-a-friendly-and-reluctant-response-to-james-white-and-all-my-postmillennial-friends/">Part 1</a></span>, <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="/datpostmil-2-a-present-evil-age/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2</a></span> </em></p>
<p><strong></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong><em>The Postmillennial Doctrine of Bifurcation—Two ages in the Gospel Age?</em></strong></span></p>
<p>Let me pursue an aspect of the problem with Postmillennialism which I raised in my last post. I think, though my memory is dim with age, that this had a lot to do with my “apostasy” from Postmillennialism of my college years. Key to systematic Postmillennialism is the notion that we are not in the millennium, but that some day before Christ’s return the church will experience millennial glory. The persecution and humiliation that has been the portion of the church for the last 2000 years will be replaced by the triumph and glory of the millennial reign of the church on earth. Thus, there is an essential bifurcation of the gospel age into very different eras. This is not only necessary to Postmillennialism, but also it is its distinguishing mark.</p>
<h2><span style="font-size: x-large;"><em> The Absence of Evidence for the Doctrine of Bifurcation</em></span></h2>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">But in my desire to be postmillennial in my early years as a Reformed Christian here was the problem I encountered. I could not find any good evidence for such a bifurcation of the gospel age in the New Testament.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">I was rather confronted with phrases and verses that might possibly imply such a bifurcation, but I could find no clear evidence.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">Somewhere I saw Postmillennialism read into James 5:7: “Therefore be patient, brethren, until the coming of the Lord. The farmer waits for the precious produce of the soil, being patient about it, until it gets the early and late rains.” But the next verse does not sound postmillennial. James 5:8 speaks of Christ’s near coming: “You too be patient; strengthen your hearts, for the coming of the Lord is near.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">There is, of course, Romans 11. But again I encountered difficulty. First, even if you think a mass conversion of the Jewish nation in the future is taught there, that seems to be the last event before the Second Coming and not the beginning of the millennium. Romans 11:25-26 so interpreted seem to make the conversion of the Jews to follow the coming in of the fullness of the Gentiles and not to precede it. Second, I knew that many reputable Reformed theologians beginning with Calvin himself wholly rejected such a view. Gradually, I came to accept a version of Calvin’s interpretation of Romans 11.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"> <em>The Presence of Evidence against Bifurcation</em></span></p>
<p>Against this meagre evidence, I found many passages which taught clearly—it seemed to me—that the gospel age was not two eras but a single era with the same characteristics throughout.</p>
<p>I was impressed, of course, by the evidence presented in the last blog post that this age continues to be an evil age till its end. It is not an evil age for a while but then a good and golden age for a long era before Christ’s return.</p>
<p>The Parables of the Kingdom in Matthew 13 also taught me that the gospel age was a single era with a single character. They surely implied the same mixed and troubled character of this age. The Parable of the Soils taught that the gospel in this age would always encounter four types of soil. Only one of them would bear fruit. The Parables of the Wheat and Weeds taught that wheat and weeds would grow together until the end of the age. The Parables of the Treasure Hidden in the Field and the Pearl of Great Price both taught that great sacrifice (selling all that you have) would always be necessary in this age to have the kingdom.</p>
<p>The bottom-line for me was this. I saw no clear evidence for the bifurcation of the gospel age. On the other hand, I saw persuasive evidence against the postmillennial doctrine of bifurcation.</p>
<p>I anticipate that my postmillennial readers will feel that I have overlooked an important feature of the New Testament in what I have said so far. They want to ask, What about the New Testament teaching about the growth and progress of the gospel during this age? Does this not lead directly to postmillennial hopes and convictions? I will take up this teaching next time and show why it does not lead to Postmillennialism, but rather to Optimistic Amillennialism.</p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --> </p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_8 et_pb_with_background et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_8">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_14  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_9">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737507/ref=sr_1_1?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165840&#038;sr=8-1" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-1" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg 224w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1-194x300.jpg 194w" sizes="(max-width: 224px) 100vw, 224px" class="wp-image-16337" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_15  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_10">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MORE-End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737698/ref=sr_1_3?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165862&#038;sr=8-3" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-2" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg 336w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2-202x300.jpg 202w" sizes="(max-width: 336px) 100vw, 336px" class="wp-image-16339" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_16  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_11">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MacArthurs-Millennial-Manifesto-Samuel-Waldron/dp/098021792X/ref=pd_bxgy_img_3/132-2520012-4634739?_encoding=UTF8&#038;pd_rd_i=098021792X&#038;pd_rd_r=ac9f0afa-68d3-4ac2-8ef6-f5b4cadc19cd&#038;pd_rd_w=2dSwU&#038;pd_rd_wg=0rs7V&#038;pf_rd_p=f325d01c-4658-4593-be83-3e12ca663f0e&#038;pf_rd_r=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7&#038;psc=1&#038;refRID=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-3" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg 333w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 333px) 100vw, 333px" class="wp-image-16341" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/datpostmil-3-the-postmillennial-doctrine-of-bifurcation-two-ages-in-the-gospel-age/">#DatPostmil? #3: The Postmillennial Doctrine of Bifurcation—Two ages in the Gospel Age?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/datpostmil-3-the-postmillennial-doctrine-of-bifurcation-two-ages-in-the-gospel-age/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>#DatPostmil? #2: A Present Evil Age!</title>
		<link>/datpostmil-2-a-present-evil-age/</link>
					<comments>/datpostmil-2-a-present-evil-age/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=17315</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>It did not take me long after my college years to depart from my early postmil sympathies. I suppose there were many reasons for this “sad” departure. I will attempt to describe them in this and future posts. But as I look at things now, it is this bifurcation of the present gospel age into two radically different periods which is necessary to systematic Postmillennialism which I see as a premier reason to reject Postmillennialism. It simply does not fit with the two-age schema of biblical prophecy.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/datpostmil-2-a-present-evil-age/">#DatPostmil? #2: A Present Evil Age!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_9 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_9">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_17  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_5  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><h4><span style="font-size: small;"><em>This is part 2 of a 5 part series on &#8220;#datpostmil?&#8221; View <a href="/datpostmil-a-friendly-and-reluctant-response-to-james-white-and-all-my-postmillennial-friends/"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 1</span></a></em></span></h4>
<p><strong></strong></p>
<h2><strong><em>A Present Evil Age!</em></strong></h2>
<p> <span style="font-size: 14px;">I ended my first post in this friendly response to James White by arguing that it is the notion of a distinct, future millennial period before the return of Christ in glory that is the distinguishing feature of what I will call systematic Postmillennialism. It is this future golden age before Christ returns </span><em style="font-size: 14px;">and in which we do not already live</em><span style="font-size: 14px;"> that distinguishes Postmillennialism from Amillennialism. Subtract this idea from Postmillennialism and you might as well call all of us optimistic Amillennialists postmillennial. It is furthermore this idea of a distinct, future golden age which has usually distinguished Postmillennialists in the past in the present.</span></p>
<p>Perhaps it is good to insert here a confession. I once wanted to be postmil. I tried to be postmil. I had read Boettner’s <em>The Millennium</em>. I also loved John Murray’s interpretation of Romans 11 in which he argued for a future mass conversion of physical Israelites. This view of Murray’s does not mean that he or anyone else is necessarily postmil. One could hold it—in my opinion—in an optimistic amillennial scheme. I recall that some postmils actually reject the idea of a future mass conversion of the Jews. Yet, such a view of Romans 11 does certainly fit well within the postmillennial scheme.</p>
<p>It did not take me long after my college years to depart from my early postmil sympathies. I suppose there were many reasons for this “sad” departure. I will attempt to describe them in this and future posts. But as I look at things now, it is this bifurcation of the present gospel age into two radically different periods which is necessary to systematic Postmillennialism which I see as a premier reason to reject Postmillennialism. It simply does not fit with the two-age schema of biblical prophecy. I argue in <em>End Times Made Simple</em> for the prominence of this two-age scheme in the New Testament. I see it as the beating heart of biblical eschatology. And the simple truth is that this scheme is inconsistent with systematic Postmillennialism. Let me explain why.</p>
<p>Of the very many references to the two-age scheme in the New Testament Luke 20:34-36 is perhaps its classic, biblical statement. Here is what that passage says:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><sup>34</sup> Jesus said to them, &#8220;The sons of this age marry and are given in marriage, <sup>35</sup> but those who are considered worthy to attain to that age and the resurrection from the dead, neither marry nor are given in marriage; <sup>36</sup> for they cannot even die anymore, because they are like angels, and are sons of God, being sons of the resurrection.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It is clear from Jesus’ words that the history of the world is divided into two ages. Jesus calls them here “this age” and “that age.” Elsewhere the New Testament speaks of that age as “the age to come” (Matt. 12:32; Mk. 10:30; Lk. 18:30; Eph. 1:21; Heb. 6:5). It is also clear these two ages are radically different. Four major differences are mentioned in this key passage. (1) The sons of this age marry but the sons of that age do not. (2) The sons of this age die but the sons of that age do not. (3) In this age, the sons of this age and the sons of God are mixed together in the world but in the age to come there are only sons of God. (4) The sons of this age are natural men but the sons of the age to come are sons of the resurrection.</p>
<p>The New Testament makes clear that the age to come begins with the resurrection of the righteous and that the resurrection of the righteous begins with the Second Coming of Christ. Matthew 13:37-43 is closely parallel and makes this exact point.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><sup>37</sup> And He said, &#8220;The one who sows the good seed is the Son of Man, <sup>38</sup> and the field is the world; and as for the good seed, these are the sons of the kingdom; and the tares are the sons of the evil one; <sup>39</sup> and the enemy who sowed them is the devil, and the harvest is the end of the age; and the reapers are angels. <sup>40</sup> &#8220;So just as the tares are gathered up and burned with fire, so shall it be at the end of the age. <sup>41</sup> &#8220;The Son of Man will send forth His angels, and they will gather out of His kingdom all stumbling blocks, and those who commit lawlessness, <sup>42</sup> and will throw them into the furnace of fire; in that place there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth. <sup>43</sup> &#8220;Then THE RIGHTEOUS WILL SHINE FORTH AS THE SUN in the kingdom of their Father. He who has ears, let him hear.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here is the same viewpoint as that found in Luke 20. In this age, good and evil men are mixed together. At the harvest or judgment, they are separated. Then, in the coming age, there are only righteous men in the state of resurrection. Verse 43 refers to the resurrection as its quotation of Daniel 12:1-3 makes clear.</p>
<p>But my point is this. What event brings about the new age and the kingdom of the Father? It is the Second Coming in glory. Until then this present, natural age continues with good and evil men mixed together in the world. What this passage teaches the New Testament everywhere teaches. This age ends and the new age comes with the Second Coming of Christ and the resurrection of the righteous which is always associated with it. Cf. Matthew 24:3; 28:20; Luke 18:30; 1 Corinthians 15:23; 1 Thessalonians 4:13-18; 2 Thessalonians 2:1-3; Titus 2:12-13.</p>
<p>It is in this two-age scheme that we have the backbone of biblical eschatology. In my book I argue that this scheme makes Premillennialism impossible. Premillennialists can neither place Revelation 20 (as they interpret it) in this age (which ends with the resurrection and Second Coming of Christ); nor can they place their version of the millennium in the age to come (since their millennium is not a perfected condition with only resurrected and righteous men inhabiting that age of the world).</p>
<p>But my point here is that systematic Postmillennialism also does not fit with this two-age scheme of the New Testament. It is not just that there are only two ages and not the three which systematic Postmillennialism (substantially) presumes. No, there is a much deeper problem.</p>
<p>What is it? It is the way that the New Testament describes this age in other places. We already know that it is an age in which good and evil men are mixed together till the end. But when the New Testament speaks of the characteristics of this age it raises significant stumbling blocks for Postmillennialism. Why? It is because it teaches that <strong><em>t</em></strong><strong><em>his age is <u>and always will be</u> an evil age.  </em></strong></p>
<p>The proposition here is, in other words, that the basic character of this age will always be morally evil.  A number of the key passages where the two-age terminology is used require this conclusion. Luke 16:8 speaks of evil men as the sons of this <em>age</em> and contrasts them with the sons of light.  Mark 10:30 teaches that those who have left all for Christ must always expect persecutions in this age.  As long as this age lasts, then, persecution will be the lot of the true Christian.  Romans 12:2 is Paul’s exhortation to Christians not to be conformed to <em>this age</em>. Such language plainly assumes that this age will always be an evil age.  2 Corinthians 4:4 asserts that Satan is <em>“the god of this age”</em>.  It is, therefore, necessarily evil.  Galatians 1:4 is Paul’s description of this age as a <em>“present, evil age”</em> from which the elect are to be delivered by the death of Christ. Ephesians 2:2 describes the former, wicked lives of Ephesian believers as a <em>“walking according to the age of this world.”</em></p>
<p>Such passages as these presuppose and assume that this present age is, and always will be, evil.  If this were not the case, there might come a day when the persecution of Christians would cease, when it would not be wrong to be conformed to this age, when Satan would not be its god, when Paul&#8217;s description of it as evil would cease to be true, and when one could walk according to the age of this world and be righteous.  All this would defy, however, the plain implications of these passages. </p>
<p> <span style="font-size: 14px;">Such passages confront postmillennialism with a serious difficulty.  Postmillennialism teaches that good triumphs over evil in this age.  Righteousness and peace in this age overcome unrighteousness and hatred according to postmillennialism.  Postmillennialists may qualify their teaching by saying that they do not believe that this age will become perfect or that every single man will be converted.  Still and nonetheless, their contention remains that, in substance, good triumphs over evil in this age.  When the Bible, however, assumes that this age (that ends, as we have seen, only with the Second Coming of Christ) is and always will be evil, it teaches something that pointedly contradicts Postmillennialism. Let me conclude by trying to illustrate this with a diagram.</span></p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text --><div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_12">
				
				
				<span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/2-diagram-1.jpg" alt="" title="#2 diagram" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/2-diagram-1.jpg 790w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/03/2-diagram-1-480x326.jpg 480w" sizes="(min-width: 0px) and (max-width: 480px) 480px, (min-width: 481px) 790px, 100vw" class="wp-image-17339" /></span>
			</div><div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_6  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p><em></em></p>
<p>One more thing is necessary to say. I agree with Dr. White when he affirms that God will bring down everything that exalts itself against Christ. I agree with him that many of these defeats will come during this age. But the defeat of these enemies does not mean that a millennial golden age arises in their place. For 70 years the anti-God Communist ideology prevailed in the Soviet Union filling the world with terror. Christ brought the Soviet Union down! But this did not mean that a new Reformed and Evangelical Russia would rise in its place. Rather another dragon emerged out of the sea of this fallen world. The corrupt oligarchy led by Vladimir Putin came to power. My point is that the victories of Christ in this age are real, but they do not mean that a golden age is coming before the King Himself returns. They only mean that God preserves His people for the spread of His gospel and the building of the church. As Peter said in 2 Peter 2:9, “the Lord knows how to rescue the godly from temptation, and to keep the unrighteous under punishment for the day of judgment.” Messianic judgments are real and history-altering during this age, but they do not mean a millennium is coming before Christ returns in glory.</p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_10 et_pb_with_background et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_10">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_18  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_13">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737507/ref=sr_1_1?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165840&#038;sr=8-1" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-1" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg 224w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1-194x300.jpg 194w" sizes="(max-width: 224px) 100vw, 224px" class="wp-image-16337" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_19  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_14">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MORE-End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737698/ref=sr_1_3?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165862&#038;sr=8-3" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-2" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg 336w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2-202x300.jpg 202w" sizes="(max-width: 336px) 100vw, 336px" class="wp-image-16339" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_20  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_15">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MacArthurs-Millennial-Manifesto-Samuel-Waldron/dp/098021792X/ref=pd_bxgy_img_3/132-2520012-4634739?_encoding=UTF8&#038;pd_rd_i=098021792X&#038;pd_rd_r=ac9f0afa-68d3-4ac2-8ef6-f5b4cadc19cd&#038;pd_rd_w=2dSwU&#038;pd_rd_wg=0rs7V&#038;pf_rd_p=f325d01c-4658-4593-be83-3e12ca663f0e&#038;pf_rd_r=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7&#038;psc=1&#038;refRID=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-3" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg 333w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 333px) 100vw, 333px" class="wp-image-16341" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/datpostmil-2-a-present-evil-age/">#DatPostmil? #2: A Present Evil Age!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/datpostmil-2-a-present-evil-age/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>#datpostmil? A Friendly (and Reluctant) Response to James White (and All My Postmillennial Friends)</title>
		<link>/datpostmil-a-friendly-and-reluctant-response-to-james-white-and-all-my-postmillennial-friends/</link>
					<comments>/datpostmil-a-friendly-and-reluctant-response-to-james-white-and-all-my-postmillennial-friends/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 15:17:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=17210</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Sam Waldron Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/datpostmil-a-friendly-and-reluctant-response-to-james-white-and-all-my-postmillennial-friends/">#datpostmil? A Friendly (and Reluctant) Response to James White (and All My Postmillennial Friends)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_11 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_11">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_21  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_7  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><h4><span style="font-size: small;"><em>This is part 1 of a 5 part series on “#datpostmil?” View: <span><a href="/datpostmil-a-friendly-and-reluctant-response-to-james-white-and-all-my-postmillennial-friends/">Part 1</a>, <a href="/datpostmil-2-a-present-evil-age/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2,</a><a href="/datpostmil-4-does-the-growth-of-the-kingdom-require-postmillennialism/(opens%20in%20a%20new%20tab)"></a> <a href="/datpostmil-3-the-postmillennial-doctrine-of-bifurcation-two-ages-in-the-gospel-age/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3,</a> <a href="/datpostmil-4-does-the-growth-of-the-kingdom-require-postmillennialism/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4</a>, <a href="/datpostmil-5-the-problem-with-preterism/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 5</a>, <a href="/a-post-log-to-datpostmil-blog-posts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Post-Logue</a></span></em></span></h4>
<h2><strong><em></em></strong></h2>
<h2><strong><em>A Friendly (and Reluctant) Response to James White (and All My Postmillennial Friends)</em></strong></h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Reformed Christians who follow James White have been keeping the media buzzing recently with the news that, as of a couple weeks ago, he embraced Postmillennialism. You can hear his message on YouTube here: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KlS4vmHgtWA.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">I have been urged to respond to White. I do so in some ways quite reluctantly. James White has been a kind and useful friend to Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary of which I am President. More than that, he has been a highly influential force for the defense and spread of Reformed truth. Times I cannot number I have heard his name mentioned as one of the influences which brought our students to a Reformed way of thinking. I admire his ability to defend our faith in a debate context. Though I sometimes will take such a debate if I think it will serve the interests of truth, I am not a debater. But James White has that gift in great measure. I am thankful for it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">I am reluctant to respond to White on this subject for another reason. I have a number of other esteemed friends in the Reformed Baptist ministry who also embrace postmillennial views. I have no desire to offend or alienate those friends. I hope they do not take these blog posts as either offensive or as a sign of any alienation in my heart from them. They certainly are not so intended and mean no such thing.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">Finally, I am reluctant to respond (and emphasize that it is a friendly response) because it seems to me that too many in our camp are ready to anathematize those with whom they disagree on differences that are well within the bounds of both the orthodoxy of the Confession and the Reformed tradition. I think that the postmillennial view of eschatology is within those bounds. You will find no anathemas here. You may find warnings against errors that it could lead to in its ripple effects. You may find warnings against some views often associated with Postmillennialism. But you will not find name-calling or anathemas in these posts.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">But, of course, I have chosen to respond. No one is forcing me to do this. It is really a sense of obligation which makes me do so. It is a duty to the truth of God’s Word which (I hope) constrains me to write. It is the errors and ripple-effect dangers associated with postmillennial views that force me to write.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">Something else moves me. I hope I have a sense for the dangers of eschatological loose-thinking honed by reading eschatology for many years. I fear that such loose-thinking will derail the progress made over the last several centuries in the church’s understanding of eschatology. Progress should be an idea that is attractive to Postmillennialists. Yes, I have to admit that I view Postmillennialism as loose-thinking.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em style="font-size: 26px;"><strong>What is Postmillennialism?</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">Before we start arguing eschatology, it is important that we state some clear definitions and make some careful distinctions. Let me begin by saying that I follow the common paradigm which distinguishes four major eschatological positions that are within the general bounds of orthodoxy. They are Dispensational Premillennialism, Historic Premillennialism, Amillennialism, and Postmillennialism.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">Of course, by saying that they are all within the general bounds of orthodoxy, I do not at all mean that they are all equally correct or biblical. I only mean that, in my view, none of these views is per se heretical and outside the bounds of the Christian faith. There are views that are. The Liberal and Hyper-preterist denials of a future Second Coming are outside the bounds of orthodoxy and heretical, but the views I mentioned above are not outside the bounds.</span></p>
<p>And I must state another clarification, as well. I do not regard all these views as equally within the Reformed confessional tradition or as equally consistent with my own 1689 Baptist Confession. I happily grant confessional status to Postmillennialism and, of course, Amillennialism. Swallowing hard, I even grant it to Historic Premillennialism. I do not, however, regard Dispensationalism as consistent with confessional subscription. Leaving aside its views of prophecy, both its views of the law of God and the church of God contradict the Confession.</p>
<p>But all this brings me to a problem I have pointed out in my books on eschatology. It is a problem that simply has to be considered in the present context. Perhaps I am ill-informed, but the eschatological movement in his thinking to which James White confesses in his sermon is really a movement most recently, I think, from an amillennial view to a postmillennial perspective on eschatology. The problem is that in a certain sense <em>Amillennialism is postmillennial</em>.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">What do I mean? Simply this. Both views believe that the visible and bodily return of Christ to the world takes place after the thousand years (or millennium) described in Revelation 20:1-10. Amillennialism is, then, postmillennial in its view of the return of Christ. This being the case—if Postmillennialism and Amillennialism are to be distinguished—another and different distinguishing feature must be found to differentiate them. Without such a clear distinction, the whole discussion will be fruitless. Whether Postmillennialism is the correct eschatological view surely depends on a clear definition of what it is—and especially what it is in contradistinction to Amillennialism.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em style="font-size: 26px;"><strong>Postmillennialism … Amillennialism: What Is the Difference?</strong></em></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">I have said that any meaningful debate over the biblical merits of Postmillennialism as opposed to Amillennialism must assume a clear distinction between the two systems. I believe one exists. I hope now to make it clear.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">But perhaps I must first tell you what it is not. I do not believe that the distinction is merely in one’s level of optimism about the church and its future. Postmillennialists make points by decrying the </span><em style="font-size: 14px;">Pessimillennialists</em><span style="font-size: 14px;">. It is true of Premillennialism, and especially Dispensationalism, that it has been horrendously and destructively pessimistic about the future of the church in this age. I imagine—at least it is my opinion—that there have been some Amillennialists that have also fallen into what may fairly be called </span><em style="font-size: 14px;">Pessimillennialism</em><span style="font-size: 14px;">.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">But I think that there are many of us Amils who have not fallen into such a spirit of pessimism about the church. I happily describe myself as an “optimistic Amillennialist.” I am very optimistic about the future of the church. I want to say more about this in a future blog post. I should only add here that I do not think such optimism about the church entails optimism about the world in this age. The Bible teaches that it “lies in the power of the evil one” (1 John 5:19) during this age.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">But optimistic Amillennialism is not the same as Postmillennialism. At least, I have never thought so. Why? Because no clear theological or prophetic distinction between Amillennialism and Postmillennialism can be achieved by a psychological assessment of how optimistic one is!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">To get to a sound, theological distinction, let me point out an interesting thing about the term, millennium. This interesting ambiguity in the term may be seen in the Webster’s New World Dictionary. Under the entry on millennium it has three definitions:</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">1. A period of a thousand years 2.  In </span><em style="font-size: 14px;">theology</em><span style="font-size: 14px;">, the period during which Satan will be bound and Christ will reign on earth … Rev, 20:1-5 hence 3.  Any period of great happiness, peace, prosperity, etc. imagined golden age.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">Do you see the double meaning of millennium? Like many words </span><em style="font-size: 14px;">millennium </em><span style="font-size: 14px;">has both a denotation and a connotation. Its denotation or plain meaning is simply a thousand years and beyond that the thousand years mentioned in Revelation 20. Its connotation or “halo meaning” is that it speaks of a great golden age of happiness, peace, and prosperity (and we may add of righteousness).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">Why is this important? It is important because Amillennialists are postmillennial with regard to the denotation of millennium, but they are not postmillennial with regard to the connotation of millennium. That is, we amils believe that Christ is coming back after the thousand years. We do not, however, believe that this thousand years is what the millenarians conceive it to be. It is not a great golden age of happiness, peace, prosperity, and righteousness in which such blessedness is the dominant tone of the world and in which evil is subdued under these things.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">This brings us to a second and key distinguishing feature of Postmillennialism. This second key and crucial feature of Postmillennialism can be seen in this way. It is most obvious that the last 2000 years have not been such a golden age of righteousness, prosperity, and peace. Oh, of course, there have been great blessings bestowed on the church and even in common grace on the world! Certainly! But just glance at the 20</span><sup>th</sup><span style="font-size: 14px;"> Century of the Christian era and you will see that it is anything but a golden, millennial age. The names of Hitler, Stalin, Mao Tse Tung, and Pol Pot glare at us from the history books. The First World War, the Second World War, the Cold War and the threat of nuclear annihilation, the rise of secularism, naturalism, and the dominion of evolutionary views in science contradict our millennial hopes. All these things, furthermore, were instrumental in destroying the rosy optimism of the Postmillennialism of an earlier age.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">Yes, but the Postmil says, Christ will subdue these things and bring in the golden age before He returns. This is, of course, the postmillennial response to the contradiction of earlier postmillennial hopes. Despite earlier disappointments, a future is coming before the Second Coming of Christ which will bring the golden age long hoped for.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">I know that this is the postmillennial reply. To this reply my response is … Exactly! Here we come to the distinguishing feature of Postmillennialism. To maintain its millennial hope for a golden age, of necessity, it must conceive of the gospel age—the period between Christ’s First and Second Advents—as divided into two distinct periods. The first period is the humiliation of the church. The second period is the triumph of the church. There is the time of the persecuted church and the time of the triumphant church. These are successive periods which characterize the gospel age.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14px;">Such a distinction has been foundational to the thinking of many Postmillenialists in the past. It is crucial to any clear distinction between Amil and Postmil today! But is it biblical? That is the question to which we must now turn in posts to come.</span></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --><em>This is part 1 of a 5 part series.</em></p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_12 et_pb_with_background et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_12">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_22  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_16">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737507/ref=sr_1_1?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165840&#038;sr=8-1" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-1" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1.jpg 224w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-1-194x300.jpg 194w" sizes="(max-width: 224px) 100vw, 224px" class="wp-image-16337" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_23  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_17">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MORE-End-Times-Made-Simple/dp/1879737698/ref=sr_1_3?dchild=1&#038;keywords=the+end+times+made+simple&#038;qid=1616165862&#038;sr=8-3" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-2" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2.jpg 336w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-2-202x300.jpg 202w" sizes="(max-width: 336px) 100vw, 336px" class="wp-image-16339" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column --><div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_1_3 et_pb_column_24  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_18">
				
				
				<a href="https://www.amazon.com/MacArthurs-Millennial-Manifesto-Samuel-Waldron/dp/098021792X/ref=pd_bxgy_img_3/132-2520012-4634739?_encoding=UTF8&#038;pd_rd_i=098021792X&#038;pd_rd_r=ac9f0afa-68d3-4ac2-8ef6-f5b4cadc19cd&#038;pd_rd_w=2dSwU&#038;pd_rd_wg=0rs7V&#038;pf_rd_p=f325d01c-4658-4593-be83-3e12ca663f0e&#038;pf_rd_r=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7&#038;psc=1&#038;refRID=QTM9X6AR4VP3F909WXP7" target="_blank"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap "><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg" alt="" title="end-times-3" height="auto" width="auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3.jpg 333w, /wp-content/uploads/2016/10/End-Times-3-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 333px) 100vw, 333px" class="wp-image-16341" /></span></a>
			</div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/datpostmil-a-friendly-and-reluctant-response-to-james-white-and-all-my-postmillennial-friends/">#datpostmil? A Friendly (and Reluctant) Response to James White (and All My Postmillennial Friends)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/datpostmil-a-friendly-and-reluctant-response-to-james-white-and-all-my-postmillennial-friends/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Book Recommendation &#124; The Imperative of Preaching by John Carrick</title>
		<link>/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/</link>
					<comments>/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 16:20:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15520</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Recently in a discussion about hermeneutics and preaching, the chairman of the Board of CBTS, John Miller, recommended to us John Carrick’s book entitled, The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric. John Carrick is introduced on the Banner of Truth website as follows:&#160; John Carrick is a graduate of Oxford University (BA, 1973; [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/">Book Recommendation | The Imperative of Preaching by John Carrick</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Recently in a discussion about hermeneutics and preaching, the chairman of the Board of CBTS, John Miller, recommended to us John Carrick’s book entitled, <em>The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric.</em></p>



<p>John Carrick is introduced on the Banner of Truth website as follows:&nbsp;</p>



<p>John Carrick is a graduate of Oxford University (BA, 1973; Certificate in Education, 1974; MA, 1978) and studied at London Theological Seminary, 1978-1980. He holds a D.Min. from Westminster Theological Seminary in California (2002). He was formerly Minister of Cheltenham Evangelical Church (1979-1992), briefly Lecturer in the History of Philosophy &amp; Christian Thought at Reformed Theological Seminary, Charlotte, North Carolina (1993), and Minister of Matthews Orthodox Presbyterian Church, Matthews, NC (1992-1994).</p>



<p>He is the author of <em>The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric</em> and <em>The Preaching of Jonathan Edwards</em>, published by the Trust.</p>



<p>I was thinking of writing a review of the book myself, but I found the review of my esteemed friend, D. Scott Meadows online and feel no need to duplicate his fine review.&nbsp; I do want, however, to add my commendation of this book and urge you to read it.</p>



<p>I just finished reading Carrick’s short volume myself.&nbsp; The book is not long and is an easy read. (Even with the appendices, it is less than 200 pages.) It has been helpful to me in several respects. I want you men to be aware of this fine book and also receive help in your preaching from it.</p>



<p>Carrick’s interest is to discuss the biblical balance and relationship between the indicative and the imperative, especially as it affects our preaching.&nbsp; There are five main chapters of the book sandwiched between an introduction and conclusion. He spends the first three of these main chapters discussing the indicative and then two discussing the imperative.</p>



<p>Over the course of the three chapters on the indicative, Carrick discusses the indicative, the exclamative, and the interrogative and gives examples of great preaching from each. He argues in them that the exclamative and the interrogative are forms of the indicative. I found his emphasis on the importance the interrogative in preaching particularly helpful.</p>



<p>Carrick then comes to the beating heart of his book in his two chapters on the imperative. In the first chapter on the imperative, Carrick discusses the imperative generally, its relationship to the indicative, and finally its importance in preaching.&nbsp; In the second chapter, he dives into his critique of the redemptive-historical school of preaching and especially its more extreme forms. I found his historical survey of the controversy surrounding this school of preaching enlightening. I also found his critique of its deficiency with regard to the “imperative preaching” most timely and helpful. I urge you to read the book and give special attention to this chapter.</p>



<p>There it is. My recommended book of the day for you! Shortly, we will post D. Scott Meadows’ review of this fine book.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/">Book Recommendation | The Imperative of Preaching by John Carrick</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 7 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</title>
		<link>/9-john-mark/</link>
					<comments>/9-john-mark/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 21:32:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15515</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is the 9th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here:&#160;1,&#160;2,&#160;3,&#160;4,&#160;5,&#160;6,&#160;7, 8. Chapter 7 of John Mark&#8217;s Remarkable Career&#8212;His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark The unanimous testimony of the early church is that the Gospel of Mark was written by John Mark. The earliest [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/9-john-mark/">Chapter 7 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is the 9th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here:&nbsp;<a href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">1</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">2</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/mark-career-3/">3</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/chapter-3-mark/">4</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/john-mark-5/">5</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/6-john-mark/">6</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/7-john-mark/">7</a>, <a href="/8-john-mark/">8</a>.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2><strong>Chapter 7 of John Mark&#8217;s Remarkable Career&#8212;His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</strong></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The unanimous testimony of the early church is that the Gospel of Mark was written by John Mark. The earliest testimony to this comes from two well-known Christians of the second century.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The first is a man named Papias. His testimony likely comes from around the years 110-120. He said:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><em>Mark, the interpreter of Peter, wrote down carefully what he remembered, both the sayings and the deeds of the Christ, but not in chronological order, for he did not hear the Lord nor did he accompany him. At a later time, however, he did accompany Peter, who adapted his instructions to the needs, but not with the object of making a connected series of discourses of our Lord. So, Mark made no mistake in writing the individual discourses in the order in which he recalled them. His one concern was not to omit a single thing he had heard or to leave any untruth in this account.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The second significant testimony comes from the early church father, Irenaeus. Writing around 180, he said:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><em>Matthew also issued a written Gospel among the Hebrews in their own dialect, while Peter and Paul were preaching at Rome, and laying the foundations of the Church. After their departure, Mark, the disciple and interpreter of Peter, did also hand down to us in writing what had been preached by Peter. Luke also, the companion of Paul, recorded in a book the Gospel preached by him. Afterwards, John, the disciple of the Lord, who also had leaned upon His breast, did himself publish a Gospel during his residence at Ephesus in Asia.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The best and the necessary conclusion with regard to the authorship of the Gospel of Mark is summarized in the words of another scholar:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Though the author does not directly identify himself, there is still strong evidence to attribute the Gospel to John Mark. In addition to Markan composition, church fathers also state that Mark was the interpreter of Peter, which would give reason to believe that he wrote his Gospel under the guidance or assistance of the apostle &#8230; the title &#8220;According to Mark&#8221; (KATA MARKON) is found in the earliest manuscripts. &nbsp;[https://www.blueletterbible.org/study/intros/mark.cfm]</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>John Mark&#8212;that John Mark who abandoned Christ and deserted Barnabas and Saul and was the source of the scandal of the disagreement between Paul and Barnabas&#8212;that John Mark was so restored in Christ&#8217;s church that by the grace of Christ he rose to be one of the four evangelists who penned inspired chronicles of the life of Christ!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong><em>We learn that because of Christ people of smaller talents and lesser grace can still hold useful places of service in the kingdom of God!&nbsp; </em></strong>John Mark was surrounded throughout his life by giants. Barnabas, Paul, and Peter&#8212;such giant Christians no doubt constantly reminded him of how meager and small his own talent was.&nbsp; He no doubt would have called himself a one-talent man as he compared himself to such greats! But he did not make this a reason to bury his talent. He kept on. He kept plodding. He kept serving God. And one day he became the penman of one of the four gospels! What hope and consolation and encouragement this should give to the rest of us. We also see ourselves as people of small gift, but God may also make us eminently useful like John Mark if we will be faithful to use the gift we have been given.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong><em>We learn that because of Christ you can still be greatly useful in spite of your messing up in the past!&nbsp; </em></strong>Not only did John Mark see himself as possessing very meager gifts, he surely also saw himself as having royally messed up in his past.&nbsp; And it was true.&nbsp; There was no denying it.&nbsp; Yet, despite this, Mark became greatly useful! You must not allow your view of yourself be ruled by your past messes, but by Christ&#8217;s present graces!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/9-john-mark/">Chapter 7 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/9-john-mark/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</title>
		<link>/8-john-mark/</link>
					<comments>/8-john-mark/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 20:18:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15505</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is the 8th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter 1 Peter 5:13 reads: “She who is in Babylon, chosen together with you, sends you greetings, and so does my son, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/8-john-mark/">Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>This is the 8th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here: <a href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">1</a>, <a href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">2</a>, <a href="/mark-career-3/">3</a>, <a href="/chapter-3-mark/">4</a>, <a href="/john-mark-5/">5</a>, <a href="/6-john-mark/">6</a>, <a href="/7-john-mark/">7</a>.</em></p>



<h2><strong>Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</strong></h2>



<p>1 Peter 5:13 reads: “She who is in Babylon, chosen together with you, sends you greetings, and so does my son, Mark.” No serious doubt may be entertained that Peter here refers to the John Mark we have been studying.&nbsp; And he refers to him in the most affectionate terms. He calls him “his son.” Most conservative scholars date 1 Peter around AD 64-65. Thus, this remark of the Apostle Peter may have taken place a year or two before that of Paul’s remark in AD 67, but at about the same time.</p>



<p>We learn, then, that John Mark’s reputation had been rehabilitated not only with Paul and the wing of the church that he led.&nbsp; It had also been restored in the part of the church led by Peter. What a clear testimony to the renewed usefulness and respected status of John Mark in the early church!</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn that by the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ you can receive deliverance from past sins and not be doomed by your past mistakes!&nbsp; </em></strong>The example of John Mark ought to encourage those who live with a sneaking suspicion that they have forfeited God’s best for their lives. It should give hope to those who think that their past mistakes have condemned them to a useless life and sad existence. If deliverance could come through Christ to John Mark, it can come to you.</p>



<p>But this statement is not the greatest testimony to God’s restoring grace in John Mark’s remarkable career. That is rather his authoring of the Gospel of Mark. We will consider that in the next blog.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/8-john-mark/">Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/8-john-mark/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
