<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Biblical Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/biblical-theology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 16:20:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Biblical Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Book Recommendation &#124; The Imperative of Preaching by John Carrick</title>
		<link>/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/</link>
					<comments>/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 16:20:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15520</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Recently in a discussion about hermeneutics and preaching, the chairman of the Board of CBTS, John Miller, recommended to us John Carrick’s book entitled, The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric. John Carrick is introduced on the Banner of Truth website as follows:&#160; John Carrick is a graduate of Oxford University (BA, 1973; [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/">Book Recommendation | The Imperative of Preaching by John Carrick</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Recently in a discussion about hermeneutics and preaching, the chairman of the Board of CBTS, John Miller, recommended to us John Carrick’s book entitled, <em>The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric.</em></p>



<p>John Carrick is introduced on the Banner of Truth website as follows:&nbsp;</p>



<p>John Carrick is a graduate of Oxford University (BA, 1973; Certificate in Education, 1974; MA, 1978) and studied at London Theological Seminary, 1978-1980. He holds a D.Min. from Westminster Theological Seminary in California (2002). He was formerly Minister of Cheltenham Evangelical Church (1979-1992), briefly Lecturer in the History of Philosophy &amp; Christian Thought at Reformed Theological Seminary, Charlotte, North Carolina (1993), and Minister of Matthews Orthodox Presbyterian Church, Matthews, NC (1992-1994).</p>



<p>He is the author of <em>The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric</em> and <em>The Preaching of Jonathan Edwards</em>, published by the Trust.</p>



<p>I was thinking of writing a review of the book myself, but I found the review of my esteemed friend, D. Scott Meadows online and feel no need to duplicate his fine review.&nbsp; I do want, however, to add my commendation of this book and urge you to read it.</p>



<p>I just finished reading Carrick’s short volume myself.&nbsp; The book is not long and is an easy read. (Even with the appendices, it is less than 200 pages.) It has been helpful to me in several respects. I want you men to be aware of this fine book and also receive help in your preaching from it.</p>



<p>Carrick’s interest is to discuss the biblical balance and relationship between the indicative and the imperative, especially as it affects our preaching.&nbsp; There are five main chapters of the book sandwiched between an introduction and conclusion. He spends the first three of these main chapters discussing the indicative and then two discussing the imperative.</p>



<p>Over the course of the three chapters on the indicative, Carrick discusses the indicative, the exclamative, and the interrogative and gives examples of great preaching from each. He argues in them that the exclamative and the interrogative are forms of the indicative. I found his emphasis on the importance the interrogative in preaching particularly helpful.</p>



<p>Carrick then comes to the beating heart of his book in his two chapters on the imperative. In the first chapter on the imperative, Carrick discusses the imperative generally, its relationship to the indicative, and finally its importance in preaching.&nbsp; In the second chapter, he dives into his critique of the redemptive-historical school of preaching and especially its more extreme forms. I found his historical survey of the controversy surrounding this school of preaching enlightening. I also found his critique of its deficiency with regard to the “imperative preaching” most timely and helpful. I urge you to read the book and give special attention to this chapter.</p>



<p>There it is. My recommended book of the day for you! Shortly, we will post D. Scott Meadows’ review of this fine book.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/">Book Recommendation | The Imperative of Preaching by John Carrick</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dr. Richard Barcellos on Biblical Theology Now Available!</title>
		<link>/barcellos-biblical-theology-available/</link>
					<comments>/barcellos-biblical-theology-available/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2014 16:00:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1495</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We are excited to announce the online release of our latest course at the Midwest Center for Theological Studies! Dr. Richard Barcellos&#8217; class on Biblical Theology I is now available on MCTS Pathway: http://goo.gl/wYpQ3d In this course, Dr. Barcellos introduces Biblical Theology as a discipline. He covers its place and function in the encyclopedia of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/barcellos-biblical-theology-available/">Dr. Richard Barcellos on Biblical Theology Now Available!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We are excited to announce the online release of our latest course at the Midwest Center for Theological Studies! Dr. Richard Barcellos&#8217; class on Biblical Theology I is now available on MCTS Pathway: <a title="Barcellos Biblical Theology I Course" href="http://goo.gl/wYpQ3d" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://goo.gl/wYpQ3d</a></p>
<p>In this course, Dr. Barcellos introduces Biblical Theology as a discipline. He covers its place and function in the encyclopedia of theology, a brief history, a working definition, various models and practitioners, and hermeneutics.</p>
<p>Do you want to have a better understanding of the progressive unfolding of God&#8217;s redemptive plan as revealed in the Bible? Then consider registering for this course, which opens up a much richer reading of God&#8217;s Word.</p>
<p>To whet your appetite, here is a sample lecture video from Dr. Barcellos where he provides a brief sketch of God&#8217;s progressive revelation from Genesis through Revelation.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/89140585" width="600" height="337" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>You can also <a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/BT-11-Syllabus1.pdf">download the course syllabus</a> for more information.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/barcellos-biblical-theology-available/">Dr. Richard Barcellos on Biblical Theology Now Available!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/barcellos-biblical-theology-available/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MCTS Podcast 18: The Family Tree of Reformed Biblical Theology</title>
		<link>/mcts-podcast-18/</link>
					<comments>/mcts-podcast-18/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2011 15:00:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Divito]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1061</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Richard Barcellos discusses his doctoral dissertation in our latest video podcast, The Family Tree of Reformed Biblical Theology. admin CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-podcast-18/">MCTS Podcast 18: The Family Tree of Reformed Biblical Theology</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Richard Barcellos discusses his doctoral dissertation in our latest video podcast, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Family-Tree-Reformed-Biblical-Theology/dp/0980217954/">The Family Tree of Reformed Biblical Theology</a>.<br />
<object classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" width="398" height="299" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true"><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"><param name="src" value="http://vimeo.com/moogaloop.swf?clip_id=25910421&amp;server=vimeo.com&amp;show_title=0&amp;show_byline=0&amp;show_portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff&amp;fullscreen=1&amp;autoplay=0&amp;loop=0"></object></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-podcast-18/">MCTS Podcast 18: The Family Tree of Reformed Biblical Theology</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mcts-podcast-18/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (VI)</title>
		<link>/wells-sabbath-chap-three-vi/</link>
					<comments>/wells-sabbath-chap-three-vi/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 05:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lord's Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Christian and the Sabbath review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Wells]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1034</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A detailed examination of all the passages in the Gospels where Christ discusses the issue of the Sabbath will show that he never predicted its abolition, nor did he ever profane it.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-sabbath-chap-three-vi/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (VI)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/06/1030/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (V)</a></p>
<p><strong>Conclusion: <strong>Gospel Texts on Sabbath-Keeping</strong></strong></p>
<p>A detailed examination of all the passages in the Gospels where Christ discusses the issue of the Sabbath will show that he never predicted its abolition, nor did he ever profane it. If fact, he could not profane it, nor advocate its profanation by others, without sinning. He was born under the law, not to profane it, but to keep it (Gal. 4:5). If Christ violated the Sabbath, then he sinned and would not be a suitable Savior for others. Instead, he advocated works of necessity (Matt. 12:1-8; Mk. 2:23-28; Lk. 6:1-5), mercy (Matt. 12:9-14; Mk. 3:1-6; Lk. 4:31-41; 6:6-11; 13:10-17; 14:1-6; Jn. 5:8-10; 7:23; 9:13-16), and piety (Matt. 12:9; Mk. 6:2; Lk. 4:16; 6:6; Jn. 7:22-23) on the Sabbath by his teaching and example. He never violated it, advocated its violation by others, or prophesied its soon demise. In fact, Mk. 2:27-28 prophesies the perpetuity of the Sabbath under his lordship as Son of Man.</p>
<p>Both Matt. 12:1-14 and Mk. 2:27-28 contain transcovenantal principles relating to the Sabbath. Works of mercy and necessity are lawful on the Sabbath, linking Jesus’ teaching with revelation given prior to his earthly ministry (i.e., the OT). Jesus as Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath, linking the Sabbath and its Lord with future revelation (i.e., the NT). Jesus’ teaching on the Sabbath leaves us with the expectation that he will execute his lordship over the Sabbath in the future, during the inter-advental days of the new covenant. His teaching on the Sabbath is related to antecedent revelation (explicitly) and subsequent revelation (implicitly). It establishes a basis for its basic ethical perpetuity and yet in such a way as to expect changes in application due to the redemptive-historical shift that takes place due to his entrance into glory (i.e., resurrection/ascension).</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-sabbath-chap-three-vi/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (VI)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/wells-sabbath-chap-three-vi/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (V)</title>
		<link>/1030-2/</link>
					<comments>/1030-2/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2011 05:37:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reveiw of Tom Wells The Christian and the Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wells]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1030</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Tom Wells&#8217; book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (IV) Mark 2:23-28 narrates another incident between Jesus and his disciples and the Pharisees. Jesus was &#8220;passing through the grainfields on the Sabbath, and His disciples began to make their way along while picking the heads of grain&#8221; (Mk. 2:23). The Pharisees said, &#8220;Look, why are they [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/1030-2/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (V)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/05/wells-on-sabb-chapt-three-iv/">Tom Wells&#8217; book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (IV)</a></p>
<p>Mark 2:23-28 narrates another incident between Jesus and his disciples and the Pharisees. Jesus was &#8220;passing through the grainfields on the Sabbath, and His disciples began to make their way along while picking the heads of grain&#8221; (Mk. 2:23). The Pharisees said, &#8220;Look, why are they doing what is not lawful on the Sabbath?&#8221; (Mk. 2:24). This is the regulating question Jesus answers in this passage. According to the Pharisees&#8217; understanding, Christ&#8217;s disciples were violating the law of God by doing that which was, in their words, &#8220;not lawful on the Sabbath&#8221; (Mk. 2:24). Christ, as in Matt. 12:3-4, brings up the example of David and his companions entering the house of God and doing that &#8220;which [was] not lawful&#8230;&#8221; (Mk. 2:26). In Matt. 12:7, he pronounced his disciples innocent. In Matt. 12:12, Jesus said, &#8220;So then, it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath.&#8221; Though he does not pronounce his disciples innocent in Mark 2, he uses David and his companions as an example of someone in Scripture doing a similar thing his disciples were doing. It seems obvious that if his disciples were innocent in one text (Matt. 12), they are innocent in another (Mk. 2).[1] But how were they innocent? Did they, in fact, do that which was not lawful on the Sabbath? Obviously, Jesus did not think so in Matthew 12 or here. In Jesus&#8217; mind, they did that which was lawful. It was lawful because God desires compassion or mercy over sacrifice (cf. Matt. 12:7). In other words, Jesus makes a distinction between aspects of the Old Testament&#8217;s laws. Mercy overrules the positive aspects of the Sabbath under the old covenant.[2]</p>
<p>In Mk. 2:27, Jesus does as Paul and Moses do elsewhere. He draws a principle from creation that is germane to mankind (cf. Exod. 20:8-11 and 1 Tim. 2:12-13). Mark 2:27-28 says, &#8220;And He said to them, &#8216;The Sabbath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath. Therefore the Son of Man is also Lord of the Sabbath.&#8217;&#8221; <em>First</em>, note that both man and Sabbath are said to be made. The verb used by Mark in v. 27, evge,neto (&#8220;made&#8221;), comes from gi,nomai, which means &#8216;to become&#8217; or &#8216;to be.&#8217; It is the same verb used in Jn. 1:3, where it is translated &#8220;made.&#8221; There it refers to the creation of all things through the Word. What Jesus is saying in Mk. 2:27 is that, in the past, both man and the Sabbath came into being (i.e., &#8216;were made&#8217;) and that coming into being is described by one verb. This leads us to the conclusion that man and Sabbath were made at the same time. It would be quite clumsy to separate the making of man and the making of the Sabbath by hundreds and maybe even thousands of years by placing the Sabbath&#8217;s birth after Israel&#8217;s deliverance from Egypt in Exod. 16 or 20. Since we know that man was created (i.e., &#8216;came into being&#8217;) according to Gen. 1 and 2 in the Garden of Eden, Christ would have us to conclude that the Sabbath, as he refers to it here, was made at the same time and in the same place (cf. Exod. 20:11). This relates Christ&#8217;s teaching on the Sabbath with previous revelation.</p>
<p><em>Second</em>, both Sabbath and man are singular and articular in the Greek text (To. sa,bbaton&#8230; to.n a;nqrwpon [&#8220;the Sabbath&#8230;the man&#8221;]). Both words occur twice in this verse and both words are preceded by an article each time. This is one way to emphasize both Sabbath and man. Jesus did not say &#8220;The Sabbath was made for the Jews&#8221; or &#8220;the Sabbaths[3] were made for the Jews.&#8221; He said &#8220;the Sabbath&#8221; was made for &#8220;the man.&#8221; &#8220;The man&#8221; refers either to Adam as the head of the human race or mankind. Either way, it is clear that Christ goes back to the creation account and sees both man and the Sabbath being made. In context, Christ not only corrects the Pharisees for misunderstanding the Sabbath (Mk. 2:23-24), he, in effect, rebukes their narrow-minded and unbiblical approach to this issue. Jesus teaches us that the Sabbath is not unique to the Jews. God caused it to come into being as he caused Adam and all mankind to come into being for his glory and their good. The Sabbath is as old as man, according to Christ, not merely as old as the Jews. Again, this relates Christ&#8217;s teaching with previous revelation.</p>
<p><em>Third</em>, the Sabbath is said to have been &#8220;made for man, and not man for the Sabbath.&#8221; Two observations are worthy to consider. <em>First</em>, &#8220;[t]he Sabbath was made <em>for</em> man.&#8221; It was not made for God. God does not need a Sabbath. We do. It was made by God for our good. <em>Second</em>, man was not made &#8220;for the Sabbath.&#8221; Man existed first. His needs existed before the Sabbath did. The Sabbath came into being to serve man&#8217;s needs to be like God and to enjoy him. We don&#8217;t serve the Sabbath, it serves us so we can serve God better. Again, this relates Christ&#8217;s teaching with previous revelation.</p>
<p><em>Fourth</em>, Christ puts his stamp of Messianic lordship on the Sabbath that was made at creation. &#8220;Therefore the Son of Man is also Lord of the Sabbath&#8221; (Mk. 2:28). This provides us with the expectation that the Sabbath will abide under his lordship and will take on characteristics appropriate to this lordship under the new covenant (cf. Rev. 1:10). John Murray comments:</p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p>What the Lord is affirming is that the Sabbath has its place within the sphere of his messianic lordship and that he exercises lordship over the Sabbath because the Sabbath was made for man. Since he is Lord of the Sabbath it is his to guard it against those distortions and perversions with which Pharisaism had surrounded it and by which its truly beneficent purpose has been defeated. But he is also its Lord to guard and vindicate its permanent place within that messianic lordship which he exercises over all things&#8211;he is Lord of the Sabbath, too. And he is Lord of it, not for the purpose of depriving men of that inestimable benefit which the Sabbath bestows, but for the purpose of bringing to the fullest realization on behalf of men that beneficent design for which the Sabbath was instituted. If the Sabbath was made for man, and if Jesus is the Son of man to save man, surely the lordship which he exercises to that end is not to deprive man of that which was made for his good, but to seal to man that which the Sabbath institution involves. Jesus is Lord of the Sabbath&#8211;we dare not tamper with his authority and we dare not misconstrue the intent of his words.[4]</p>
<p>It is clear from the text in Daniel, where the phrase &#8220;Son of Man&#8221; comes from, that it refers to Christ in the posture of enthronement, immediately following his ascension into glory and is a title appropriate for him during the days in which he is given a kingdom and the nations become his.</p>
<p>I was watching in the night visions, And behold, <em>One </em>like the Son of Man, Coming with the clouds of heaven! He came to the Ancient of Days, And they brought Him near before Him. Then to Him was given dominion and glory and a kingdom, That all peoples, nations, and languages should serve Him. His dominion <em>is </em>an everlasting dominion, Which shall not pass away, And His kingdom <em>the one </em>Which shall not be destroyed. (Dan. 7:13-14)</p>
<p>In other words, Christ administrates the Sabbath as the Son of Man during the whole interadvental period&#8211;the days of the new covenant. This relates Chris&#8217;s teaching on the Sabbath with both previous and future revelation. Christ&#8217;s lordship over the Sabbath also implies Christ&#8217;s deity. The Sabbath is God&#8217;s (Isa. 56:4; 58:13). Since Christ is Lord of the Sabbath as Son of Man and since this title is his during the inter-advental days of the new covenant, then we should not be shocked if the Sabbath bears unique characteristics of his lordship under the new covenant. Patrick Fairbairn says:</p>
<p>He is Lord of the Sabbath, and, as such, has a right to order everything concerning it, so as to make it, in the fullest sense, a day of blessing for man&#8211;a right, therefore, if He should see fit, to transfer its observance from the last day of the week to the first, that it might be associated with the consummation of His redemptive work, and to make it, in accordance with the impulsive life and energy thereby brought in, more than in the past, a day of active and hallowed employment for the good of men.[5]</p>
<p>Jesus (Matt. 19:4-5 [and Mk. 2:27-28]), Paul (1 Tim. 2:12-13), and Moses (Exod. 20:11) argue in similar fashion. Each of them goes back to the creation account for the basis of ethics in terms of marriage, divorce, male/female roles in the church, and Sabbath. They all apply the same reasoning, though to different issues. If the basis for their argument is creation, and if creation transcends covenants and cultures, how can we not conclude that what they are arguing for applies to all men at all times, though dependant upon revelation from God in terms of specific application at any given point in redemptive history? In other words, though the application may vary due to various redemptive-historical situations (i.e., divorce permitted due to the entrance of sin, 7<sup>th</sup> day Sabbath to 1<sup>st</sup> day Sabbath/Lord&#8217;s Day, etc.), the principle itself stands. And the reason why it stands is due to the order and ethical implications of creation drawn out by the Bible itself.</p>
<p>If the principle applies to marriage, divorce, and male/female roles in the church, then doesn&#8217;t it still apply to the Sabbath as well? If it does not apply to the Sabbath, upon what grounds is the principle dismissed? If one says, &#8220;The Sabbath was an ordinance for the Jews only. It was theirs&#8217; as God&#8217;s old covenant people to apply to their culture alone in the Promised Land,&#8221; then couldn&#8217;t someone argue the same for male/female roles in the church? They could say, &#8220;Paul was dealing with a culture-relative issue. His reasoning applied to that culture alone. Women, therefore, may have authority over men in the church and may teach and preach to them. Women may be pastors.&#8221; Some in our day argue this way. But when the Bible bases ethics upon creation, the principle applies to all cultures at all times. And until this age gives way to the fullness of the age to come, creation-based ethics (i.e., creation ordinances) are moral laws for all men.</p>
<hr size="1">[1] If Matthew utilized Mark, it could be that he filled out the incident for his own purposes. If Mark used Matthew, it could be that he trimmed the incident because he knew Matthew had dealt with it in detail. If the Gospel writers wrote independent of each other based on eye-witness accounts, each one wrote what they did for authorial purposes. Either way, both texts were inspired by God and can and ought to be used to interpret each other.</p>
<p>[2] See the <em>Second London Baptist Confession</em>, 22:7, where it acknowledges that the Sabbath is &#8220;a positive moral, and perpetual commandment&#8230;&#8221; I take this to mean that the Sabbath can and does take upon itself temporary aspects (i.e., positive laws) during the history of redemption, which can and do change, yet its essence is moral or perpetual. This means that its positive aspects may give way to the moral or perpetual aspects of God&#8217;s law.</p>
<p>[3] The Jews under the old covenant had both a weekly Sabbath and other non-weekly Sabbaths.</p>
<p>[4] John Murray, <em>Collected Writings of John Murray, </em>Vol. I<em> </em>(Edinburgh: The Banner of Truth Trust, 1976), 208.</p>
<p>[5] Fairbairn, <em>Revelation of Law</em>, 238.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/1030-2/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (V)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/1030-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (IV)</title>
		<link>/wells-on-sabb-chapt-three-iv/</link>
					<comments>/wells-on-sabb-chapt-three-iv/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2011 18:56:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lord's Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mark 2:27-28]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Wells]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=979</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I found Wells&#8217; argument unconvincing and his method of argumentation, at this point, very sloppy.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-on-sabb-chapt-three-iv/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (IV)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/05/wells-on-the-sabbath-chap-three-iii/">Tom Wells&#8217; book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (III)</a></p>
<p><strong>Mark 2:27-28</strong></p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong>Wells discusses Mk. 2:27-28 (48-57). He claims, and rightly so, &#8220;There is no command in these verses&#8230;&#8221; (49). He continues, &#8220;&#8230;but an argument for Sabbath keeping has been drawn from each of them&#8221; (49). He states the argument this way:</p>
<p>The argument is twofold. First, if God at creation made the Sabbath a blessing for mankind, He certainly did not do so only to abolish it later. Second, when the Lord Jesus announces Himself as Lord of the Sabbath, it seems unlikely to suppose that He intended to exercise His Lordship over it by doing away with it. (49)</p>
<p>Dealing with this twofold argument, Wells assumes &#8220;that God commanded man to keep the Sabbath at the time of creation&#8221; (49), though he does not believe that to be the case. Discussing the first argument, he says:</p>
<p>The first argument implies the impossibility of God later abolishing anything that He made for mankind&#8217;s benefit at the creation. But is this sound reasoning? It may be true or it may be false, but it is certainly not obvious. Where is it written that if God once made something a blessing for mankind at large that He would never suspend it? (49)</p>
<p>He then gives examples of many things God has made for man&#8217;s benefit that he subsequently takes from man (i.e., the Garden of Eden, many wonderful fruits, extinct birds and animals, the benefits of family life for some believers in Christ, etc. [49-50]). What shall we say to this?</p>
<p>Wells asserts, without citing anyone, that &#8220;The first argument implies the impossibility of God later abolishing <em>anything</em> that He made for mankind&#8217;s benefit at the creation&#8221; (49; emphasis mine). Does the first argument imply this? Is this the way those Wells is arguing against state their position? I think the answer to both questions is a resounding, &#8220;No!&#8221; Do those who believe that God instituted some things for mankind&#8217;s good at creation also believe in &#8220;the impossibility of God later abolishing&#8221; those things? Again, Wells cites no one. In fact, he over-states his case. Claiming that God instituted some things for man&#8217;s good at creation does not <em>necessarily</em> imply the impossibility of God later abolishing those things. The Garden of Eden is a case in point, as Wells says.</p>
<p>The argument Wells set up (i.e., that &#8220;God at creation made the Sabbath a blessing for mankind&#8221;) needs additional elements to necessarily imply what he claims. Those who argue this would need to state that it is <em>impossible</em> for God to institute <em>anything</em> for man&#8217;s benefit at creation and then abolish it later. I don&#8217;t know of anyone who would argue this way, though someone who does may exist.</p>
<p>But there is another problem with Wells&#8217; response. The examples he uses of things instituted by God at creation for the benefit of man and later abolished are not identified as creation ordinances by those he is combating. Creation ordinances are not co-extensive with everything instituted by God for man in the Garden of Eden. Wells himself identifies what those who hold to creation ordinances identify as such. He says, &#8220;Often three are cited: marriage, labor and Sabbath&#8221; (26). In other words, for example, the Garden of Eden is not a creation ordinance in the minds of Wells&#8217; opponents. Even though it appears that Wells does not adhere to the doctrine of creation ordinances, he is disagreeing with those who do and should have seen the problem with arguing the way he did. In effect, he put words in the mouths of those he is critiquing and then shows those words to be impossible to square with Scripture. I found Wells&#8217; argument unconvincing and his method of argumentation, at this point, very sloppy.[1]</p>
<p>After extensive discussion, Wells denies that this verse teaches any sort of Sabbath perpetuity under the lordship of Christ as Son of Man. However, is it that simple? Let&#8217;s consider these verses in context in our next post.</p>
<p>[1] I am sure I have been guilty of the same thing.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-on-sabb-chapt-three-iv/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (IV)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/wells-on-sabb-chapt-three-iv/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is Christ the ultimate fulfillment of the Sabbath?</title>
		<link>/is-christ-the-ultimate-fulfillment-of-the-sabbath/</link>
					<comments>/is-christ-the-ultimate-fulfillment-of-the-sabbath/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2011 17:27:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christ is the Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=963</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Sabbath is not a symbol or type of Christ, strictly speaking; it is a symbol and type of that which Christ attains for us – the eschatological state.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/is-christ-the-ultimate-fulfillment-of-the-sabbath/">Is Christ the ultimate fulfillment of the Sabbath?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As far as Christ as the ultimate fulfillment of the Sabbath, I would say this…If the Sabbath as instituted at creation was a symbol and type of the eternal state, then the Sabbath between creation and consummation is at least that. The Sabbath is not a symbol or type of Christ, strictly speaking; it is a symbol and type of that which Christ attains for us – the eschatological state. And until that state comes in its fullness and finality, the Sabbath yet remains as its symbol and type. I think Hebrews 4 argues this.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/is-christ-the-ultimate-fulfillment-of-the-sabbath/">Is Christ the ultimate fulfillment of the Sabbath?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/is-christ-the-ultimate-fulfillment-of-the-sabbath/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (III)</title>
		<link>/wells-on-the-sabbath-chap-three-iii/</link>
					<comments>/wells-on-the-sabbath-chap-three-iii/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2011 02:51:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Wells]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=953</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Wells references Matt. 12:1-14 several times in chapter 3 but offers no exposition of the passage.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-on-the-sabbath-chap-three-iii/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (III)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/05/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/">Tom Wells&#8217; book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (II)</a></p>
<p><strong>Matthew 12:1-14&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Wells references Matt. 12:1-14 several times in chapter 3[1] but offers no exposition of the passage.[2] I will offer a brief exposition.</p>
<p>In Matt. 12, we are told that &#8220;Jesus went through the grainfields on the Sabbath. And His disciples were hungry, and began to pluck heads of grain and to eat&#8221; (Matt. 12:1). The Pharisees replied, &#8220;Look, Your disciples are doing what is not lawful to do on the Sabbath!&#8221; (Matt. 12:2). Jesus then offers two examples from the OT; &#8220;&#8230;David&#8230; and those who were with him&#8221; (Matt. 12:3) and &#8220;the priests in the temple&#8221; (Matt. 12:5).[3] Concerning the priests, he says, &#8220;Or have you not read in the law that on the Sabbath the priests in the temple profane the Sabbath, and are blameless?&#8221; (Matt. 12:5). Whatever the priests were doing, the Pharisees&#8217; logic implied it was a violation of the Sabbath. Their logic taught that the priests, David, and Christ&#8217;s disciples were profaning the Sabbath. But Jesus says the priests &#8220;&#8230;are blameless&#8221; (Matt. 12:5). Then he quotes Hos. 6:6. He says, &#8220;But if you had known what this means, &#8216;<em>I desire mercy and not sacrifice</em>,&#8217; you would not have condemned the guiltless&#8221; (Matt. 12:7).[4] He pronounces his disciples &#8220;guiltless&#8221; by referencing two OT examples. In the next section of Matt. 12, the Pharisees ask, &#8220;Is it lawful to heal on the Sabbath?&#8221; (Matt. 12:10). Jesus concludes in v. 12, &#8220;Therefore it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath.&#8221; This clearly teaches that healing on the Sabbath was lawful as was preserving the life of a sheep (vv. 10-12). His disciples ate because eating is necessary to sustain human life. All of these actions, according to Christ, were lawful on the Sabbath according to OT law. Jesus was correcting faulty thinking about the Sabbath by consulting prior revelation.</p>
<p>Someone might want to offer Matt. 12 as an example of Jesus abrogating the Sabbath (cf. Mk. 2:23-28 and Lk. 6:1-11).[5] They might claim that Jesus advocates Sabbath-breaking thereby proving that he was abolishing it. But does this text bear this out? Did Jesus, in fact, advocate Sabbath-breaking during his earthly ministry? We have just examined Matt. 12:1-14 and seen Christ justifying works of necessity and mercy and concluding in v. 12, &#8220;Therefore it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath.&#8221; The &#8220;good&#8221; in the context of Matt. 12 involved not only what his disciples did and what he did, but what David and those with him and the old covenant priests did. The supposed violation of the Sabbath in this passage (and others) is actually an upholding of the Sabbath and in accordance with OT revelation. Jesus never advocated Sabbath-breaking during his earthly ministry. Jesus&#8217; teaching upholds existing Sabbath law.</p>
<p>Those who offer this objection may claim that when Jesus says, &#8220;But I say to you that in this place there is One greater than the temple&#8221; (v. 6) and &#8220;For the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath&#8221; (v. 8), Jesus is claiming authority to abolish the Sabbath as he abolished the temple. In once sense, Christ did abolish the Sabbath. He abolished it in its various functions under the old covenant. And, in one sense, Christ abolished the temple. He did not, however, abolish the temple in all senses. His church is now God&#8217;s temple, where spiritual sacrifices are offered (Eph. 2:19-22; 1 Pt. 2:4-5). What does Jesus mean, when he says, &#8220;But I say to you that in this place there is One greater than the temple&#8221; (Mt. 12:6) and &#8220;For the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath&#8221; (Matt. 12:8; cf. Mk. 2:28)? Fairbairn offers this explanation:</p>
<p>The Temple, He had said, has claims of service, which it was no proper desecration of the Sabbath, but the reverse, to satisfy; and &#8216;a greater than the Temple was there.&#8217; &#8216;The Temple yields to Christ, the Sabbath yields to the Temple, therefore the Sabbath yields to Christ&#8217;&#8211;so the sentiment is syllogistically expressed by Bengel; but yields, it must be observed, in both cases alike, only for the performance of works not antagonistic, but homogeneous, to its nature. &#8230; He is Lord of the Sabbath, and, as such, has a right to order everything concerning it, so as to make it, in the fullest sense, a day of blessing for man&#8211;a right, therefore, if He should see fit, to transfer its observance from the last day of the week to the first, that it might be associated with the consummation of His redemptive work, and to make it, in accordance with the impulsive life and energy thereby brought in, more than in the past, a day of active and hallowed employment for the good of men.[6]</p>
<p>Just as the temple yields to Christ and is transformed to fit the redemptive-historical circumstances brought in by his death and resurrection/exaltation, so the Sabbath yields to Christ and is transformed to fit the redemptive-historical circumstances brought in by his death and resurrection/exaltation. The new covenant has both a temple and a Sabbath. This connects Christ&#8217;s teaching on the temple and the Sabbath with subsequent revelation.</p>
<p>Instead of Matt. 12 proving that Christ abolished the Sabbath, it actually argues that he upheld it and sought to correct the Pharisees&#8217; faulty interpretation of Sabbath law. Fairbairn says, &#8220;Jesus grasped, as usual, the real spirit of the institution; for we are to remember, He is explaining the law of the Sabbath as it then stood, not superseding it by another.&#8221;[7] Christ upheld the Sabbath, cleared it of Pharisaic encumbrances, and set the stage for further revelation about it.</p>
<p>This objection assumes that the Sabbath in all senses was temporary, ceremonial law. Ceremonial laws are temporary laws for old covenant Israel and were a shadow of things to come (Col. 2:16-17). They were all abrogated by the coming of Christ and the inauguration of the new covenant (2 Cor. 3:7-18; Gal. 3-4; Eph. 2:14-16; Col. 2:16; and Heb. 8-10 [cf. esp. 8:6-7, 13; 9:9-10, 15; 10:1, 9, 15-18]). If the Sabbath is ceremonial law in all senses, then it has been abrogated. But the Sabbath is not ceremonial law in all senses, as we have seen (cf. Gen. 2:2-3; Ex. 20:8-11; Is. 56:2, 4, 6; and Mk. 2:27). And if Jesus considered it as ceremonial only, one would think he would treat it like he did other ceremonial laws. Beckwith and Stott comment:</p>
<p>But if Jesus regarded the sabbath as purely ceremonial and purely temporary, it is remarkable that he gives so much attention to it in his teaching, and also that in all he teaches about it he never mentions its temporary character. This is even more remarkable when one remembers that he emphasizes the temporary character of other parts of the Old Testament ceremonial&#8211;the laws of purity in Mark 7:14-23 and Luke 11:39-41, and the temple (with its sacrifices) in Mark 13:2 and John 4:21. By contrast, &#8230;he seems&#8230;to speak of the sabbath as one of the unchanging ordinances for all mankind.[8]</p>
<p>Jesus neither abrogated the Sabbath in all senses in his earthly ministry nor did he predict its soon demise. He upheld it and gave evidence that it would continue under his lordship as the Son of Man (Mk. 2:27-28).</p>
<p>We will look at Mk. 2:27-28 in our next post.</p>
<hr size="1">[1] I counted 10.</p>
<p>[2] In fact, the book contains little exegesis. Wells cites many texts and makes many observations; but he does little exegesis or exposition of passages. There was much proof-texting surrounded by observations that put the reader in an interpretive strait-jacket. I found his theological-interpretive method not very sound.</p>
<p>[3] Notice that Jesus is referring to previous revelation.</p>
<p>[4] Here is another reference to previous revelation.</p>
<p>[5] I am not assuming Wells does this.</p>
<p>[6] Patrick Fairbairn, <em>The Revelation of Law in Scripture</em> (Phillipsburg, NJ: P&amp;R Publishing Company, 1996), 238.</p>
<p>[7] Fairbairn,<em> Revelation of Law</em>, 237.</p>
<p>[8] Roger T. Beckwith and Wilfrid Stott, <em>This is the Day: The Biblical Doctrine of the Christian Sunday in its Jewish and Early Christian Setting</em> (London: Marshall, Morgan &amp; Scott, 1978), 26.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-on-the-sabbath-chap-three-iii/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (III)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/wells-on-the-sabbath-chap-three-iii/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Covenant of Creation</title>
		<link>/the-covenant-of-creation/</link>
					<comments>/the-covenant-of-creation/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2011 17:35:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covenant of creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covenant of works]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roland S. Ward]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=943</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The guys at Reformed Forum discuss the Creation Covenant with Dr. Roland S. Ward.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-covenant-of-creation/">The Covenant of Creation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The guys at Reformed Forum discuss the Creation Covenant with Dr. Roland S. Ward. I highly recommend Ward&#8217;s book  <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Reformed-Theology-Creation-Covenant-Covenants/dp/095862416X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1305567192&amp;sr=1-1"><em>God &amp; Adam: Reformed Theology and the Creation Covenant</em>.</a> It is a wealth of information on this important issue.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-covenant-of-creation/">The Covenant of Creation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-covenant-of-creation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (II)</title>
		<link>/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/</link>
					<comments>/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 05:16:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Wells]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=911</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Gospels are full of allusions to and echoes of previous revelation. And the Gospels set the stage for further revelation which will explain both the redemptive acts and words of Jesus Christ (Jn. 14:26; 16:13-15).</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (II)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/05/tom-wells-sabbath-chapter-three-i/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (I)</a></p>
<p>Let me make a few necessary comments on the genre and interpretation of the Gospels. The Gospels contain narrative accounts of various aspects of Christ’s earthly ministry. He taught in a very distinct redemptive-historical context and the Gospel authors each had theological purposes for choosing what they narrated and what they commented upon. We must remind ourselves that OT and NT narratives do just that – they narrate, they tell us what happened, though with theological purpose.[1] We must grant that some of the teachings of Christ in the Gospels are perpetually binding and not to be left on the shelf of narrated history. I say some because Christ commanded things to individuals that are not meant to be perpetually binding on others (cf. Matt. 26:36, “Sit here while I go over there and pray.”). But to demand a distinct type of teaching in order to justify ethics (<a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/05/tom-wells-sabbath-chapter-three-i/">what Wells did in the previous post</a>) and then claim that the Gospel passages don’t contain that type of teaching is simply a wrong-headed, constricting hermeneutical procedure. What if there are other grounds for considering Christ’s teachings on the Sabbath as applicable to Christians? A much better approach would be to read the Gospels looking for teaching related to prior and subsequent revelation and then to determine ethical perpetuity based on how Christ’s teaching is related to its broader, canonical-ethical/redemptive-historical context. The Gospels are full of allusions to and echoes of previous revelation. And the Gospels set the stage for further revelation which will explain both the redemptive acts and words of Jesus Christ (Jn. 14:26; 16:13-15). We must never interpret the Gospels as an end in themselves. Two passages in the Gospels are especially instructive in light of this – Matt. 12:1-14 and Mk. 2:27-28. These texts both reach back in redemptive history, alluding to and echoing previous revelation, and set the stage for further revelation. We will look at each passage briefly in the next post.</p>
<hr size="1" />[1] This is not to suggest that OT narratives and the Gospels are one and the same genre on every level. Whether the Gospels are seen as theological biographies, covenantal treaty documents, or a complex of different genres the presence of narrative is still true.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (II)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
