<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>CBTSeminary | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/author/user/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 17:10:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>CBTSeminary | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>CBTS Statement on Sexuality and Sexual Ethics</title>
		<link>/cbts-statement-on-sexuality-and-sexual-ethics/</link>
					<comments>/cbts-statement-on-sexuality-and-sexual-ethics/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2021 22:26:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=16161</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Rev. 1.19.2021 Our confession, the London Baptist Confession of Faith of 1689, in summarizing the teaching of Scripture, clearly affirms in chapter 25, paragraph 1 that “Marriage is to be between one man and one woman; neither is it lawful for any man to have more than one wife, nor for any woman to have [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/cbts-statement-on-sexuality-and-sexual-ethics/">CBTS Statement on Sexuality and Sexual Ethics</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Rev. 1.19.2021</em></p>



<p>Our confession, the London Baptist Confession of Faith of 1689, in summarizing the teaching of Scripture, clearly affirms in chapter 25, paragraph 1 that “Marriage is to be between one man and one woman; neither is it lawful for any man to have more than one wife, nor for any woman to have more than one husband.”&nbsp; It seems necessary because of the present widespread degradation of sexual morality in our culture to state our views of this matter more specifically and formally.</p>



<ul><li>We believe that the term “marriage” has only one meaning, and that is marriage sanctioned by God, which joins one genetic male and one genetic female in a single, exclusive, covenantal union, as delineated in Scripture.</li><li>We believe that God intends sexual intimacy to only occur between one genetic male and one genetic female who are married to each other. We believe that God has commanded that no intimate sexual activity be engaged in outside of a marriage between a genetic male and a genetic female.</li><li>We believe that any form of sexual immorality, such as adultery, fornication, homosexual conduct, bisexual conduct, bestiality, incest, any use of pornography or any attempt to change one’s sex, or disagreement with one’s genetic sex, is sinful and offensive to God.</li><li>We believe that God offers redemption and restoration to all who confess and forsake their sin, seeking His mercy and forgiveness through Jesus Christ.</li><li>We believe that every person must be afforded compassion, love, kindness, respect, and dignity. Hateful and harassing behavior or attitudes directed toward any individual are to be repudiated and are not in accord with Scripture nor the doctrines of the church.&nbsp;</li><li>We believe, nevertheless, in spite of the kindness to be shown to sinners, impenitence in the aforementioned sins is inconsistent with a Christian’s biblical profession of faith and conduct. Therefore, any prospective or current student of CBTS must not profess belief or impenitently act in a manner incompatible with the 1689 Confession and the above statements at the risk of denial of entry or expulsion. Any prospective or current employee of CBTS will forfeit employment eligibility if they profess belief or impenitently act in a manner incompatible with the 1689 Confession and any of the above statements.</li></ul>



<p>Major portions of Scripture from which these beliefs are drawn are as follows:&nbsp; Genesis 1:27-28; Genesis 2:18-25; Exodus 20:14; Matthew 19:3-12; Romans 1:26-27; 1 Corinthians 6:9-20; Ephesians 5:22-33; Hebrews 13:4.</p>



<p>This statement has been adapted from Section 2 of the constitution of our host church, Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. For further exposition of Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary’s views on sexuality, including affirmations and denials, please see the Nashville Statement. (<a href="https://cbmw.org/nashville-statement">https://cbmw.org/nashville-statement</a>)</p>



<p>May God help us as we seek to remain faithful to Him in proclaiming His truth in this generation. </p>



<p>The Lord Reigns, </p>



<p>John Miller, Chairman of the Board<br>Jim Savastio, Board Member<br>Mike Spickard, Board Member<br>Mike Waters, Board Member<br>Christopher Sheffield, Board Member<br>Ron Miller, Board Member<br>Ben Carlson, Board Member<br>Tom Hicks, Board Member<br>Jorge Rodriguez, Board Member<br>John Divito, Board Member<br>Jon Hueni, Board Member<br>Fred Malone, Board Member<br>Sam Waldron, President and Academic Dean<br>Rex Semrad, Dean of Students and Director of Administration<br></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/cbts-statement-on-sexuality-and-sexual-ethics/">CBTS Statement on Sexuality and Sexual Ethics</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/cbts-statement-on-sexuality-and-sexual-ethics/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Imperative of Preaching Part II</title>
		<link>/scott-meadows-imp-2/</link>
					<comments>/scott-meadows-imp-2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 22:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15554</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This review was originally posted on HeraldofGrace.org and has been re-posted by the permission of the author. The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred RhetoricJohn CarrickBanner of Truth Presence and Implications of the Exemplary Imperative Carrick quotes other respected Reformed theologians on the matter who appear to share his concerns about EW-RHP&#8212;men like Jay [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/scott-meadows-imp-2/">The Imperative of Preaching Part II</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This review was originally posted on HeraldofGrace.org and has been re-posted by the permission of the author.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image {"align":"left","id":759,"linkDestination":"custom"} -->
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft"><a href="https://heraldofgrace.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Imperative_of_Preaching_John_Carrick1.jpg"><img src="https://heraldofgrace.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Imperative_of_Preaching_John_Carrick1.jpg" alt="Imperative" class="wp-image-759"></a></figure></div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="http://www.trinitybookservice.com/index.php/the-imperative-of-preaching-hardcover-by-john-carrick.html">The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric</a><br>John Carrick<br>Banner of Truth</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Presence and Implications of the Exemplary Imperative</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Carrick quotes other respected Reformed theologians on the matter who appear to share his concerns about EW-RHP&#8212;men like Jay Adams, Hendrik Krabbendam, John R. de Witt, John Frame, and J. Douma. More importantly, Carrick shows that the Apostle Paul used historical examples as the basis for exhorting his hearers (citing 1 Cor 10.1-14), a classic concern of the RH school. Exhorting from example is also found in Hebrews, as P. E. Hughes (Visiting Professor of New Testament at WTS) noted in his excellent commentary:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The simplest sense [of 11.4] remains the best sense, namely, that Abel by his example of faith and righteousness still speaks to us today, even though he has so long been dead. The spectacle of his trustful integrity, even in the face of violence, should inspire us to persevere and to overcome by the same means. His was certainly an example that the faltering readers of this epistle were in need of emulating (123).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Carrick also enlists Dr. Richard Gaffin, who is himself &#8220;unashamedly a passionate exponent of biblical theology&#8221; (144-145), for the cause of applicatory preaching by citing his observation that James 5.16b-18 uses Elijah&#8217;s example of prayer in 1 Kings 18, an &#8220;incidental aspect&#8221; and &#8220;quite subordinate point&#8221; in the OT passage, to make a primary point of application for New Testament believers. Then Carrick raises a provocative question. &#8220;Does the RH school regard James&#8217; reference to Elijah as atomistic and moralistic, or not? If it does, then clearly it is claiming to be wiser than the inspired authors of the Word of God itself; and if it does not, then it is conceding the very point at issue in the original controversy. One of the major problems [if true, an understatement!&#8212;DSM] with the charge made by some within the redemptive-historical school . . . is that this charge actually recoils upon James himself&#8212; it recoils upon the Holy Scriptures of God&#8221; (127-128). Even though this statement is in the middle of the book, I got the impression that Carrick considered it something of a climax comparable to checkmate, the burr under his saddle from which he sought relief, the book&#8217;s raison d&#8217;&ecirc;tre. Christ Himself (128) exhorts tersely from an OT historical example when He urged us to &#8220;remember Lot&#8217;s wife&#8221; (Luke 17.32). Thus, &#8220;Holy Scripture leads the way&#8221; for our method of preaching (quoting Huyser, a proponent of the exemplary approach in the original controversy in the Netherlands, 123).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The exclamation point for the exemplary imperative comes from the NT&#8217;s appeal to Christ as the believer&#8217;s great Example to follow. This comes out in His charge to the disciples when He washed their feet (John 13.15), and in Peter&#8217;s counsel to suffering Christians (1 Pet 2.21, 23-24). Christ is both our Savior and our Example, and so we must hold to Him in both His roles. The RH school in some instances has been paranoid about the exemplary approach because of its historical association with &#8220;liberal theology and its na&iuml;ve Pelagianism,&#8221; but such heresy is not intrinsic to it.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Without embracing the exemplary imperative, we have no satisfactory explanation for passages like Hebrews 11, 1 Corinthians 10, James 5, and Luke 17. Homiletical Christocentricity is a good thing, but EW-RHP has degenerated to Christomonism. [Monism is a theory or doctrine that denies the existence of a distinction or duality in some sphere; here, Christ as gracious Savior and moral Example.]</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Scripture joins the concepts of example and imperative. The letter of any particular example is generally in the indicative, but the spirit of it is always in the imperative, with an implied, &#8220;Go and do likewise!&#8221; for the positive examples, and a tacit warning with the negative ones. Therefore, we should not be surprised that when RHP is uncomfortable with the imperative in preaching, it is also skittish about using examples, as illustrated in the defective preaching of Klaas Schilder, an early RHP advocate.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Expos&eacute; and Indictment of EW-RHP</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Here Carrick gets most personal in assailing the errors of his contemporaries, particularly the Dennison brothers<sup>1</sup>&nbsp;and Lee Irons, all his fellow OPC ministers associated with Kerux: A Journal of Biblical-Theological Preaching, available free online.&nbsp;<sup>2</sup></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In this journal, Carrick observes a striking emphasis upon the double indicatives of Christianity, and a corresponding dearth of the double imperatives (132). He bolsters this with quotations of both Dennison&#8217;s which castigate application per se as &#8220;man-centered&#8221; rather than &#8220;God-centered.&#8221; This is another false antithesis (133).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>James Dennison appeals for support to Geerhardus Vos&#8217; inaugural address already cited (footnote 4), but Carrick notes three problems with this. 1) EW-RHP has an overemphasis on eschatology in preaching. Vos&#8217; statement that &#8220;eschatology is prior to soteriology&#8221; is ambiguous. Vos may only have meant that eschatology is logically prior (God first resolved to glorify Himself in eternity and therefore decreed to saves us), while Dennison presses the slogan to mean eschatology is more important than soteriology (137), another idea altogether. 2) EW-RHP also exhibits an underemphasis on the ethical in preaching which opposes the NT&#8217;s strong emphasis, not to mention Vos&#8217; own characterization of Pauline theology in terms of an &#8220;already&#8212;not yet&#8221; structure. Dennison&#8217;s revels in the &#8220;already&#8221; aspects (indicatives) to the neglect of &#8220;not yet&#8221; aspects (imperatives) in the kingdom of God. 3) EW-RHP idealizes, almost idolizes, Geerhardus Vos, and this is wrong. His preaching was too heavily theological, with sermons resembling essays. Even Dr. J. Gresham Machen had this opinion (source: biography by Stonehouse). Further, Vos&#8217; sermons were also sparse in application, though not as bad as EW-RHP represented in Kerux.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Survey Resumed and Concluded</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>A few sundry observations round out Carrick&#8217;s last chapter. First, biblical salvation is covenantal, and in a bilateral, not unilateral way. Both God and man are parties to the covenant. God reveals, and man responds. EW-RHP fails to appreciate the latter and exposes itself to a fair charge of &#8220;objectivism.&#8221; It is hard to know exactly what Carrick has in mind by this word since he does not explain it; it is related to the idea of &#8220;overlooking man&#8221; (139). EW-RHP exaggerates the concept of &#8220;progress&#8221; while giving short shrift to &#8220;concourse,&#8221; the relationship between God and man, and insight Carrick gleans from scholar C. Trimp.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Second, Carrick uses considerable space reviewing some of Gaffin&#8217;s helpful contributions to the topic, including 1) the relevance of the historia salutis and the ordo salutis and their correspondence to redemption accomplished and redemption applied, with the evident imbalance in EW-RHP, 2) the dual identity of OT characters as both types of Christ and examples for believers, 3) the irreversibility and inseparability of the indicative and imperative moods in Scripture and biblical preaching, and 4) the strong Reformed homiletical tradition of explicatio et applicatio verbi Dei (explication and application of God&#8217;s Word). Carrick concludes that a balance of the indicative and the imperative, of proclamation and appeal, is justified from all considerations, and that this is just what EW-RHP, a &#8220;homiletical innovation&#8221; (144), lacks. This is bound to lead to &#8220;distortions of a more or less serious character&#8221; (146).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>With stunning insight, R. L. Dabney almost seems to have anticipated the controversy and resolved it in 1870 before it erupted in the twentieth century.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>[Christianity&#8217;s] end and aim is holy living (Eph 1.4; Tit 2.14; et passim). Of this holy life, the law of God is the rule. The believer justified in Christ does not, indeed, look to the law for his redeeming merit; but he receives it as his guide to the obedience of faith and love, as fully as though he were still under a covenant of works. He therefore needs practical instruction, as really as the unbeliever. It must stimulate and direct him in the Christian race, and make him a &#8220;peculiar person, zealous of good works.&#8221; The exclusive preaching of doctrine [viz., the indicative&#8212;DSM] to professed Christians tends to cultivate an Antinomian Spirit. The exclusive inculcation of duties [viz., the imperative, or application&#8212;DSM] fosters self-righteousness. The edification of the Church, then, demands the diligent intermixture of both kinds. This precept may be confirmed by the remark, that, as the motives and obligations of all duties are rooted in the doctrines, so the best illustrations of the doctrines are by their application to the duties. The two are inseparably connected as grounds and conclusions, as means and end; and their systematic separation in your instructions would leave your hearers incapable of a correct understanding of either.<sup>3</sup></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This sounds amazingly like Carrick&#8217;s conclusion in the last chapter (146). He may have been influenced by Dabney, without remembering it (since Dabney is not cited), to think along these lines.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The conclusion (ch. 7) is mostly a succinct summary, with the addition of a parting shot: &#8220;It is a regrettable fact that much Reformed preaching operates in a virtual mono-mood&#8212;that of the indicative&#8212; to the virtual exclusion of the imperative&#8221; (151). Whether the charge is fair or a straw man, my limited exposure to contemporary Reformed preaching is not qualified to judge. Surely Carrick is right when he opines that the doctrinal must be balanced by the practical, the historical by the ethical, the historia salutis by the ordo salutis, and the work of Christ by the work of the Spirit (151). His final statement is, &#8220;It is absolutely essential that the great indicatives of Christ&#8217;s accomplishment of redemption be balanced by the great imperatives of the Spirit&#8217;s application of redemption&#8221; (151). May the Lord deliver His church from pulpits devoid of either.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Three appendixes supply further illustrations of the exclamative, the interrogative, and the imperative from Reformed preaching. They may be the most useful to readers who are relatively unfamiliar with the spiritual eloquence of our forefathers, as a provocation to read more of their sermons. I agree with Earl Blackburn&#8217;s two minor criticisms<sup>4</sup>&nbsp;that including illustrative examples from Calvin&#8217;s sermons alongside the five Carrick chose and an appendix dedicated to the indicative mood would have strengthened the book.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Whatever one&#8217;s familiarity with this topic or position taken, this book seems to be an important contribution worthy of consideration by all modern Reformed preachers, and so I recommend it with meek enthusiasm. Its head-on criticisms of some RHP will disturb adherents, but where the tool is sharpened sparks are bound to fly. Let us receive Carrick&#8217;s savory meat and leave any bones on the plate. A well-reasoned and specific response to this book by a worthy champion of RHP would also prove an interesting read and may shed more light upon this homiletical controversy.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>You may find interesting the attached brief report of Carrick debating a RHP proponent named William Dennison (yes, another brother) at the March 2002 theology conference sponsored by Greenville Presbyterian Theological Seminary, where Carrick teaches.<sup>5</sup>&nbsp;It may prove especially useful to us because in it the other side is not mute.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>1. James T. Dennison, Jr. (1943-present), Librarian and Lecturer in Church History at WTS in California from 1980- 2000, currently Professor of Church History and Academic Dean at Northwest Theological Seminary in Lynnwood, Washington; Charles G. Dennison (1945-1999), Pastor of Grace OPC of Sewickley, PA; Lee Irons (see footnote 6).<br>2. www.kerux.com<br>3. Lectures on Sacred Rhetoric, Lecture III, &#8220;Distribution of Subjects,&#8221; pp. 57-58.<br>4. See first review referenced in footnote 1.<br>5. http://www.banneroftruth.org/pages/articles/article_detail.php?119</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/scott-meadows-imp-2/">The Imperative of Preaching Part II</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/scott-meadows-imp-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: The Imperative of Preaching Part I &#124; D. Scott Meadows</title>
		<link>/scott-meadows-imp-1/</link>
					<comments>/scott-meadows-imp-1/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 14:25:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15541</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This review was originally posted on HeraldofGrace.org and has been re-posted by the permission of the author. The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric1John Carrick2Banner of Truth Book Review by D. Scott Meadows Introduction Since &#8220;imperative&#8221; can mean vital importance and urgency, the title of this book could signal a general defense of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/scott-meadows-imp-1/">Review: The Imperative of Preaching Part I | D. Scott Meadows</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-small-font-size"><em>This review was originally posted on HeraldofGrace.org and has been re-posted by the permission of the author. </em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="http://www.trinitybookservice.com/index.php/the-imperative-of-preaching-hardcover-by-john-carrick.html">The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric<sup>1</sup></a><br>John Carrick<sup>2</sup><br>Banner of Truth</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Book Review by D. Scott Meadows</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Introduction</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Since &#8220;imperative&#8221; can mean vital importance and urgency, the title of this book could signal a general defense of preaching&#8212;a welcome subject in our prevalent anti-preaching cultural milieu, but already addressed frequently in many other homiletical books.<sup>3</sup>Carrick&#8217;s concern is more narrow, yet also momentous. He devotes attention to the grammatical moods of biblical preaching with their theological significance, emphasizing the necessity of preaching in the imperative voice of command or exhortation. While he may not have intended the title as a double-entendre, in a curious way it is. Applicatory preaching is of vital importance today, not just preaching in general.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This book affected me in a way no other ever has. When I finished it in April 2003, my first thought was, &#8220;I wish I had written that!&#8221; The terse assessment I penciled at that time on the first page was, &#8220;One of the finest books on preaching I have ever read! Very helpful.&#8221; It is excellent in so many respects. It is clear and presents strong Scriptural support for its thesis. Carrick often quotes the New King James Version translation and the authoritative Oxford English Dictionary, which would have been my own choices. He has a style of writing that is engaging and confrontational without rancor. Besides giving serious preachers much pleasure, this book provokes thoughtful reflection on one&#8217;s own pulpit ministry, with much encouragement of continued reformation toward the biblical standard.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Proverbs 26.17 says, &#8220;He who passes by and meddles in a quarrel not his own is like one who takes a dog by the ears.&#8221; Let go of either ear and you get bitten! If the controversy raised by this book review did not belong to me, wisdom would preclude my involvement&#8212;but alas, as a Reformed preacher I have been sucked into it. We have the two ears of redemptive-historical preaching (RHP) and imperative-applicatory preaching, and I find myself holding onto both simultaneously, unwilling to release either. Some may charge me with hermeneutical and homiletical inconsistency. My own opinion is that the best Reformed preachers agree in the most important points, whichever side they take, and that the extreme elements in both may be legitimate causes of concern. Perhaps some ardent advocates of a particular perspective have been unnecessarily divisive from zeal to protect their Shibboleth (Judges 12.6). Did I pronounce that right? Let all things be done with love and unto the edification of the church.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Biblical Theology and Redemptive Historical Preaching</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>A brief description of RHP may prove helpful. It is that preaching which grows out of the emphasis on redemptive history in biblical theology (BT) in its technical sense, although some who espouse BT do not endorse all the distinctives of RHP (e.g., Gaffin, 145). Geerhardus Vos (1862-1949), champion and popularizer of BT, offered a terse definition. It is &#8220;the exhibition of the organic progress of supernatural revelation in its historic continuity and multiformity.&#8221;<sup>4</sup>&nbsp;It is distinguished from systematic theology in &#8220;that it discusses both the form and contents of revelation from the point of view of the revealing activity of God Himself.&#8221;<sup>5</sup></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Systematic theology pulls together within a circle all the biblical data on a given topic, with little regard to chronology, so that the truth is flattened. BT moves along a historical line, noting well the providential context of any salvation-event and anticipating its issue in the completion of God&#8217;s redemptive purpose through Christ. RHP, therefore, is typically sweepingly panoramic and conspicuously Christocentric.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Carrick&#8217;s book raises his concerns about some advocates and practitioners of RHP. He does not denounce RHP per se, nor does he advocate an approach to preaching in the name of power and relevance with the typical naivet&eacute; of evangelicals embracing an &#8220;application bridge&#8221; mentality, with its clumsy attempt to make Scripture relevant by ill-founded exhortations that miss the point of what the text really urges.<sup>6</sup></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>His &#8220;theology of sacred rhetoric&#8221; almost rises above the fray (except in chapter 6) to make keen and undeniable observations about the grammatical forms of homiletical statements both in Scripture and in the tradition of some of the greatest preachers since the Reformation. Indeed, he raises some of the very same concerns as RHP advocates like Lee Irons (e.g., the indicative-grounded imperative). The most polemical section of the book is chapter 6, &#8220;The Imperative&#8212;Part 2,&#8221; and even here he praises advocates of the RH approach like Edmund Clowney of Westminster Theological Seminary, who &#8220;to many . . . represents the more moderate wing of RHP&#8221; (116). Carrick seems most concerned about some RHP advocates who have unduly minimized if not altogether eliminated &#8220;the imperative of preaching.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In an article published before the release of his book, Carrick offered a concise assessment: The redemptive-historical school has much to commend it&#8212;namely, its high view of the inspiration and inerrancy of the Scriptures, its commitment to the concept of the unity of the Scriptures, and its profound Christ-centeredness. It does appear, however, to have generated a style of preaching which is, regrettably, neither directly evangelistic nor directly hortatory and which is, therefore, not calculated to have very much impact upon sinner or saint. And yet this lack of application within the redemptive-historical tradition is surely an unfortunate de facto concomitant; it is as surely not a necessary concomitant. There is no reason in principle why the redemptive-historical preacher should not apply the Word of God; and apply the Word he must, if his preaching is not indeed to degenerate into mere &#8220;aesthetic contemplation.&#8221;<sup>7</sup></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So it appears that Carrick himself holds to both ears. As one investigating the controversy, reading Carrick&#8217;s book made me more interested, not less, in the RH approach. He sparked my greater interest in the writings of Clowney and Geerhardus Vos.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Please bear with a personal testimony. The first time I spoke of Carrick&#8217;s book publicly was before a group of mostly OPC pastors in the RHP mold, men whom I anticipated would be less than sympathetic with Carrick&#8217;s thesis, men who actually know some of the men Carrick criticizes. To prepare for meaningful interaction, several of them read Carrick&#8217;s book beforehand. They told me they were mostly appreciative, to their surprise. Now I have realized that we need not take an either-or approach in this controversy. Passionate men of both persuasions have made worthwhile contributions to be seriously considered. Whatever our own views, biblical integrity constrains us to honesty in representing others and charity in relating to all. In that environment, &#8220;iron sharpens iron&#8221; (Prov 27.17), and all stand to benefit from the spirited dialogue. Sadly, one involved in this debate has said a cloud of suspicion hangs over it.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In the remainder of this book review, I would describe its substance and interact modestly with Carrick&#8217;s ideas. Your feedback is welcome since you are my esteemed fellow pastors and I am a student still forming opinions about this topic.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Survey</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Between an introduction and a conclusion, the author presents four parts related to the grammatical form of homiletical statements: the indicative, the exclamative, the interrogative, and the imperative. The section on the imperative seems to have been the author&#8217;s main concern, and here he allows himself two chapters instead of one, the first of which, like the single chapters on the other three grammatical forms, essentially notes the traits of the form, its warrant and theological significance from Scripture, and citations of sermons both canonical and from five exemplary Reformed preachers, viz., Jonathan Edwards, George Whitefield, Samuel Davies, Asahel Nettleton, and Martyn Lloyd-Jones.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The introduction (ch. 1) begins with a plea for the legitimacy of a concept of &#8220;sacred rhetoric,&#8221; despite its negative connotations in the minds of some, since it is only religious speech calculated to persuade. This is not incompatible with a conscious dependence upon the Holy Spirit, so necessary in preaching which glorifies God. We must have Spirit-filled rhetoric. Then the author states his central thesis: &#8220;The essential pattern or structure which God himself has utilized in the proclamation of New Testament Christianity is that of the indicative-imperative. In other words, God himself has, in the gospel of Christ, harnessed these two fundamental grammatical moods and invested them with theological and homiletical significance&#8221; (5). Besides these Carrick notes the existence of the exclamative and the interrogative which he considers aspects of the indicative. He proposes to define, illustrate, and exemplify these four in the remainder of the book, and he succeeds in this.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>&#8220;Christianity begins with a triumphant indicative&#8221; (7). So he begins the chapter (ch. 2) on this grammatical mood with the justly-famous statement of J. Gresham Machen in Christianity and Liberalism. In that titanic struggle, Machen sagely observed that liberalism begins by telling the sinner what he must do; Christianity begins by telling the sinner what God has done. The indicative is a grammatical term &#8220;that points out, states, or declares&#8221; (8). The biblical gospel is in the indicative form, and this heavenly declaration of God&#8217;s redeeming work accomplished in Christ is the foundation of all biblical preaching. One of this book&#8217;s strengths is its frequent appeal to the biblical text cited in full for the reader&#8217;s convenient examination and reflection. Carrick praises Herman Ridderbos&#8217; insight that apostolic preaching had the nature of witnessing (12). This is also seen in the Apostles&#8217; Creed.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The indicative is well-suited to instruction, a major part of the faithful preacher&#8217;s task if not the whole. Nevertheless, we must remember the distinction between redemption accomplished and redemption applied (19-20). This paradigm suggests the indicative-based imperative. The grammatical form of the Scriptural message is rich in theological significance. The New Testament message can be summarized as two pairs of indicative-imperatives, one aimed at sinners and the other at saints:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Christ died for sinners (indicative) &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;- Repent and believe the gospel (imperative)<br>Saints have died to sin (indicative) &#8212;- Reckon yourselves to be dead indeed to sin (imperative)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Hence there is the double indicative of what God has done for sinners and for believers, and the double imperative of what their response must be on the basis of God&#8217;s work. The first is redemption accomplished; the second is redemption applied.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The exclamative (ch. 3) amounts to an emotional indicative (30-31). It possesses an element of excitement and is often signaled by words like how, what, and oh. A section of Scriptural illustration is devoted to each of these, followed by eloquent examples from the great preachers aforementioned. For example, Jonathan Edwards once wrote, &#8220;What multiplied and aggravated sins some men are guilty of!&#8221; (39).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The imperative (part 1, ch. 5) follows the basic content pattern of the previous chapters. The imperative is defined as a grammatical form expressing command, request, or exhortation (83). Clearly the New Testament is filled with apostolic preaching in the imperative form. At this point Carrick elaborates impressively on the twin indicative-imperatives found especially in Acts and the canonical epistles. Indeed, the entire structure of some epistles is obviously indicative-imperative (e.g., Romans, Ephesians). Hebrews uses a repeating pattern of indicative-imperative sections, and James is dominated by imperatives. Not surprisingly, great Reformed preaching has also been characterized by the indicative- based imperative, with powerful exhortations to sinners and saints alike, as the author demonstrates.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The imperative (part 2, ch. 6) boldly presents Carrick&#8217;s concerns about RHP. He traces its history from the Netherlands in the 1930s and 1940s. Klaas Schilder (1890-1952) and B. Holwerda (1909-1952) spearheaded the RH school of thought which gave rise to RHP (108-109). These men were concerned with an &#8220;atomistic&#8221; approach to interpretation and preaching which took texts out of context, failed to grasp the sweeping meta-narrative of Scripture understood synthetically, and then applied them arbitrarily and manipulatively. The biblical text was becoming putty in such a preacher&#8217;s hands, which he could mold at his pleasure, even to the degree it lost its original and legitimate significance. The RH school helped to restore an appreciation for the unity of redemptive history and its Christocentricity (111). It also decried the creeping moralism of preaching in the modern era, in which the grand indicative is conspicuously absent or lacking appropriate emphasis. It is a sad thing when grand gospel indicatives disappear from sermons and the preacher&#8217;s constant concern is that his hearers &#8220;be good and do good,&#8221; without frequent reference to the grace of Christ and our dependence on Him.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>However, some RHP advocates have taken this too far, and according to Carrick their suspicion of exhortation and application recoils upon the Scriptures themselves (113). Traces of this Dutch Reformed influence remain at both Westminster Theological Seminaries (in Pennsylvania and California), where BT and RHP with its reticence in application are not absent. Even WTS Professor Clowney himself, an ardent exponent of both, has warned,</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>We do well to avoid setting up a false antithesis between the RH approach and what might be called the ethical approach to the Scriptures, particularly historical passages. The RH approach necessarily yields ethical application, which is an essential part of preaching the Word. Whenever we are confronted with the saving work of God culminating in Christ, we are faced with ethical demands. A religious response of faith and obedience is required (116).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Carrick presses the point even further in a closely-reasoned, technical argument, composing the remainder of this last chapter, given to essentially two things: 1) the biblical presence and implications of the &#8220;exemplary imperative,&#8221; and 2) an expos&eacute; and indictment of &#8220;the more extreme wing&#8221; of RHP (130). For convenience of reference, we label this EW-RHP. These twin topics are the debate&#8217;s ground zero and deserve more careful consideration.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Notes:</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>1. Also see reviews by Earl Blackburn published in the Reformed Baptist Theological Review, 1.2, pp. 194-196, and Jim Elliff at http://www.ccwonline.org/imperative.html (both attached).<br>2. Assistant Professor of Applied and Doctrinal Theology at Greenville Presbyterian Theological Seminary, Taylors, South Carolina, and one of the principal homiletics instructors at the seminary. He is a graduate of Oxford University and is currently involved in D. Min. studies at Westminster Theological Seminary, California. He was formerly minister of the Cheltenham Evangelical Church, U.K., and of the Matthews Orthodox Presbyterian Church, North Carolina, U.S.A.<br>3. E.g., see John Stott, Between Two Worlds, &#8220;Contemporary Objections to Preaching,&#8221; pp. 50-91; Brian Borgman, My Heart for Thy Cause, pp. 127-141; Gardiner Spring, The Power of the Pulpit (entire volume); Martyn Lloyd- Jones, Preachers and Preaching, &#8220;The Primacy of Preaching&#8221; and &#8220;No Substitute,&#8221; pp. 9-44; John MacArthur et al., Rediscovering Pastoral Ministry, pp. 250-261, etc.<br>4. &#8220;The Idea of Biblical Theology as a Science and as a Theological Discipline,&#8221; inaugural address in 1894 as Professor of Biblical Theology at Princeton Theological Seminary, in Redemptive History and Biblical Interpretation edited by Richard Gaffin, p. 15.<br>5. Ibid, p. 7.<br>6. Lee Irons, Pastor, Redeemer OPC in Encino, CA, available at www.pcea.asn.au/0008_tpb/Red_Hist_Prchg.htm.<br>7. &#8220;Redemptive-Historical Preaching: An Assessment,&#8221; in katek?men: Let Us Hold Fast, 13.1, Summer 2001, published by Greenville Theological Seminary (attached).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/scott-meadows-imp-1/">Review: The Imperative of Preaching Part I | D. Scott Meadows</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/scott-meadows-imp-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 6</title>
		<link>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-6/</link>
					<comments>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-6/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 16:09:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Calvin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositional apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositionalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13455</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>More Contrasts between Calvin and Aquinas! Second, Calvin emphasizes explicitly and repeatedly the effect of the fall on man’s knowledge of God.&#160; Though men have a naturally implanted knowledge of God given to them by and in creation, this knowledge never develops into a “true” knowledge in the sense of a practical and religious principle [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-6/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 6</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong><em>More
Contrasts between Calvin and Aquinas!</em></strong></p>



<p>Second,
Calvin emphasizes explicitly and repeatedly the effect of the fall on man’s
knowledge of God.&nbsp; Though men have a
naturally implanted knowledge of God given to them by and in creation, this knowledge
never develops into a “true” knowledge in the sense of a practical and
religious principle which leads them to worship God aright.&nbsp; Let me put that in my own words, but they are
words which, I think, rightly embody Calvin’s view.&nbsp; He believes that men have a natural
revelation of God, but that this natural revelation never results in a natural
theology which can guide them appropriately in worship or in life in general.
This emphasis is practically absent in Thomas.&nbsp;
Listen to Calvin:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>It must also be remarked, that, though they strive against their own natural understanding, and desire not only to banish him thence, but even to annihilate him in heaven, their insensibility can never prevail so as to prevent God from sometimes recalling them to his tribunal.  But as no dread restrains them from violent opposition to the divine will, it is evident, as long as they are carried away with such a blind impetuosity, that they are governed by a brutish forgetfulness of God. <a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a> </p></blockquote>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>At length they involve themselves in such a vast accumulation of errors, that those sparks which enable them to discover the glory of God are smothered, and at last extinguished by the criminal darkness of iniquity.  That seed, which it is impossible to eradicate, a sense of the existence of a Deity, yet remains; but so corrupted as to produce only the worst of fruits.  Yet this is a further proof of what I now contend for, that the idea of God is naturally engraved on the hearts of men, since necessity extorts a confession of it, even from reprobates themselves.  In a moment of tranquility they facetiously mock the Divine Being, and with loquacious impertinence in many derogate from his power.  But if any despair oppress them, it stimulates them to seek him, and dictates concise prayers, which prove that they are not altogether ignorant of God, but that what ought to have appeared before had been suppressed by obstinacy. <a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a></p></blockquote>



<p>Third,
this very different assessment of the effect of the fall on man’s knowledge of
God comes to concrete expression in the very different use which Thomas and
Calvin make of a classic passage on the subject. I have in mind, of course, Psalm
53:1 which reads in part: “The fool has said in his heart, &#8220;There is no
God,&#8221; They are corrupt, and have committed abominable injustice; There is
no one who does good.”&nbsp; Both Thomas and
Calvin cite this text, but how different is the use they make of it!&nbsp; </p>



<p>Thomas
sees it as proof that the existence of God is not self-evident. He takes at
face value the fool’s assertion that there is no God. Aquinas says: “On the
contrary, no one can mentally admit the opposite of what is self-evident; as
the Philosopher … states concerning the first principles of demonstration. But
the opposite of the proposition “God is” can be mentally admitted: The fool
hath said in his heart, There is no God (Ps. Lii. 1). Therefore that God exists
is not self-evident.” <a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a></p>



<p>Calvin,
on the other hand, takes it as evidence of the deep depravity of the fool.&nbsp; The fool denies a knowledge of God that is ineradicably
implanted in him. Here is Calvin’s comment in the <em>Institutes </em>on Psalm
53:1 with some context:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>While experience testifies that the seeds of religion are sown by God in every heart, we scarcely find one man in a hundred who cherishes what he has received, and not one in whom they grow to maturity, much less bear fruit in due season.  Some perhaps grow vain in their own superstitions, while others revolt from God with intentional wickedness; but all degenerate from the true knowledge of him.  The fact is, that no genuine piety remains in the world.  But, in saying that some fall into superstition through error, I would not insinuate that their ignorance excuses them from guilt; because their blindness is always connected with pride, vanity, and contumacy. <a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a> </p></blockquote>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>David&#8217;s assertion, that &#8220;the fool hath said in his heart, There is no God,&#8221; is primarily, as we shall soon see in another place, to be restricted to those who extinguish the light of nature and willfully stupefy themselves. <a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a> <br></p></blockquote>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a> John Calvin, <em>Institutes of the
Christian Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 4, Section 2)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 4, Section 4)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologica</em>
(Volume 1, Question 2, Article 1)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref4">[4]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 4, Section 1)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref5">[5]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 4, Section 2)</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-6/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 6</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-6/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Owen—A Caveat, part 11</title>
		<link>/john-owen-a-caveat-part-11/</link>
					<comments>/john-owen-a-caveat-part-11/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 16:06:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Owen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[partial-preterism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preterism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10036</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>So far, I have covered six points in my case against John Owen’s preterist view of 2 Peter 3.  Let me add another argument in this post.  Here is my seventh objection to Owen’s exegesis. The Conclusive Case against Owen’s Interpretation Continued Owen assumes that the false teachers of 2 Peter are a reference to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-owen-a-caveat-part-11/">John Owen—A Caveat, part 11</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><span style="font-size: large;">So far, I have covered six points in my case against John Owen’s preterist view of 2 Peter 3.  Let me add another argument in this post.  Here is my seventh objection to Owen’s exegesis.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: xx-large;"><strong>The Conclusive Case against Owen’s Interpretation Continued</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Owen assumes that the false teachers of 2 Peter are a reference to the Jews who clung to the Old Testament institutions and the legalism that had grown up around them.  Here is Owen once more: “He speaks of that wherein both the profane scoffers and those scoffed at were concerned, and that as Jews; —some of them believing, others opposing the faith.  Now, there was no particular concernment of that generation in that sin, nor in that scoffing, as to the day of judgment in general; but there was a peculiar relief for the one and a peculiar dread of the other at hand, in the destruction of the Jewish nation; and, besides, an ample testimony, both to the one and the other, of the power and dominion of the Lord Jesus Christ; —which was the thing in question between them.” (<em>Works, </em>9:134)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">This account of the false teachers with whom Peter was contending is out of sync with the whole presentation of them in 2 Peter.  These men were not legalistic defenders of the Old Judaism.  Peter makes clear that they had been and perhaps still were professing Christians (2 Peter 2:1-2, 20-22) who distorted the teaching of the Apostle Paul (2 Peter 3:16) and (far from being legalists) were antinomians in their views and practice (2 Peter 2:12-18).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">To sum up:  the false teachers of 2 Peter 2 and 3 were not Jews opposing Christ, but antinomians who had professed Christ and followed Paul, but who had distorted Christian truth to their own destruction.  Cf. Matthew 24:48 for the background of Peter’s thought which predicts every feature of these false teachers.</span></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-owen-a-caveat-part-11/">John Owen—A Caveat, part 11</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/john-owen-a-caveat-part-11/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Biblical Philosophy of Theological Education (4 of 7)</title>
		<link>/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-4-of-7/</link>
					<comments>/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-4-of-7/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 21:12:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theology Matters]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9683</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In the previous (third) post on a biblical philosophy of theological education we came to consider the fact that the specific responsibility for theological education resides with a specified class of men in both the Old and New Testaments.&#160; We spent some time reviewing the necessity of this arrangement in New Testament times.&#160; We sought [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-4-of-7/">A Biblical Philosophy of Theological Education (4 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="padding-left: 60px;"><span style="font-size: large;"><em>In the <a href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-3-of-7/">previous (third) post</a> on a biblical philosophy of theological education we came to consider the fact that the specific responsibility for theological education resides with a specified class of men in both the Old and New Testaments.&nbsp; We spent some time reviewing the necessity of this arrangement in New Testament times.&nbsp; We sought to show why such an arrangement is necessary in the New Testament.&nbsp; In this post we now consider the identity and specificity of these arrangements.</em></span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong style="font-size: x-large;">2. The Identity of These Arrangements</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">It is not at all surprising, then, to discover that in the New Testament a permanent class of men occupying an ecclesiastical office described variously as elders, overseers, and pastor-teachers are appointed who have as their distinctive responsibility the teaching of the Word of God (Eph. 4:11-13; 1 Timothy 3:2; Titus 1:9-11).&nbsp; Nor is it surprising that certain men in the office were to be financially supported so that they might give themselves by way of vocation to the study and teaching of this revelation (1 Cor. 9:13-14; Gal. 6:6; 1 Tim. 5:17-18).</span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong style="font-size: x-large;">3. The Specificity of These Arrangements</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">There is a specific passage which addresses with particular relevance the duty of the Christian ministry with regard to theological education.&nbsp; The Christian Ministry as the particular agency for the preservation and communication of Christian Truth to its future teachers is the theme of 2 Timothy 2:1-2.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The Bible reveals that the task of maintaining and promoting Christian truth in the world is not simply or generally the task of the church as a whole.&nbsp; Indisputably, every Christian ought to feel a responsibility in the context of his local church, within the compass of his own gifts, and as suggested by his own complex of duties to promote the truth in the world (Matt. 12:30; 1 Cor. 10:31-11:1).&nbsp; Similarly, each local church as a local manifestation of the universal church must endeavor according to the strength and gifts God has given it to be a pillar and support of the truth (1 Tim. 3:15).&nbsp; Indeed, this work is essential to its very identity.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The New Testament makes clear, however, that it is the Christian ministry in particular that is charged with this responsibility.&nbsp; Key here is the Apostle Paul&#8217;s instruction to Timothy in 2 Timothy 2:1-2: &#8220;You therefore, my son, be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus. 2 The things which you have heard from me in the presence of many witnesses, entrust these to faithful men who will be able to teach others also.&#8221;&nbsp; So key is this passage to a proper understanding of theological education that a brief explanation of its importance must be given here.</span></p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">First, notice the spiritual commodity which this passage specifies.</span></em></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The Apostle calls Timothy to be strong in &#8220;the grace&#8221; that is in Christ Jesus.&nbsp; It has been asserted that the grace mentioned in verse one refers to the doctrines of grace.&nbsp; It is true that one of the clearest and strongest statements of the sovereignty of God&#8217;s grace in Paul&#8217;s writings is found in the previous chapter at 2 Timothy 1:8-10.&nbsp; The doctrines of sovereign grace are definitely involved in this grace of which Paul speaks here.&nbsp; Thus, Paul, when he speaks of the grace that is in Christ Jesus, is thinking of the entire system of grace and truth contained in the Scriptures.&nbsp; Grace here, then, refers partly or wholly to the system of the doctrines of grace which Paul taught.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">This seems to be confirmed by verse two which immediately refers to Christian doctrine in the words, <em>the things which you have heard from me</em>.&nbsp; These words clearly designate Christian doctrine.&nbsp; Paul refers to such doctrine frequently in the surrounding context (2 Tim. 2:8-9; 1:12-14; and 1:8-11).&nbsp; The spiritual commodity which forms the subject and burden of Paul in this passage is the doctrine of grace which he preached.&nbsp; This was the heart of Paul&#8217;s message.&nbsp; It was for this grace and in this grace that Timothy was to be strong.&nbsp; Further, it seems to be clearly implied that the way&#8212;at least one way&#8212;in which he was to be strong in this grace was by communicating it to other faithful men.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">An implication of the duty to communicate &#8220;the things which you have heard from me&#8221; is the careful preservation of the original deposit of truth imparted by Paul to Timothy.&nbsp; It is this Christian truth whole, unimpaired, and unpolluted which must be imparted by Timothy to a new generation of Christian teachers.&nbsp; This means that there must be agreement on the content of those doctrinal &#8220;things&#8221; which Paul mentions.&nbsp; This means in turn that there must be an agreed upon doctrinal basis for such instruction.&nbsp; Where there is no such agreed doctrinal basis, coherent theological education conducted by more than one man is not possible.&nbsp; Reformed Baptists adopt the 1689 Baptist Confession as the best summary of &#8220;the things&#8221; which Timothy heard from the Apostle Paul and the best available creedal summary of Apostolic Christianity.&nbsp; Confessional integrity is especially necessary in the theological education of men in the truths of Apostolic Christianity.&nbsp; For Reformed Baptists such confessional integrity means that such instruction will conform in its teaching to the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith.</span></p>
<p><strong><em><span style="font-size: x-large;">Second, the spiritual genealogy which this passage envisions.</span></em></strong><strong>&nbsp; </strong></p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><span style="font-size: large;">Four generations of truth are specified by Paul here in verse 2.</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: large;"><em>From<strong> Me</strong> in the presence of many witnesses</em></span></li>
<li><em><span style="font-size: large;">The things which <strong>you</strong> have heard</span></em></li>
<li><em><span style="font-size: large;">Entrust these to <strong>faithful men</strong></span></em></li>
<li><em><span style="font-size: large;">Who will be able to teach <strong>others also</strong></span></em></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Thus, the spiritual genealogy found in this passage runs like this:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">Paul</span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">Timothy</span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">Faithful Men</span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: large;">Others Also</span></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">To rightly estimate the importance of this spiritual genealogy for Paul we must remember the poignant circumstances in which these words of 2 Timothy 2:1-2 are written.&nbsp; Paul faces his imminent martyrdom for the sake of Christ (2 Timothy 4:1-8).&nbsp; One of the things most important to the Apostle Paul as he writes Timothy shortly before his death&#8212;one of the things of greatest significance to the Apostle with his death clearly on his mind&#8212;is the preservation and communication of the truths of the gospel of grace.&nbsp; It is not, however, simply or generally the communication of these truths to all the members of the church which burdens his heart.&nbsp; It is most especially and significantly the communication of these truths to faithful church leaders who will continue the genealogy of truth.&nbsp; That is, it is the instruction of men with the ability to hand down the tradition of truth faithfully to the next generation.&nbsp; Myths and false doctrines will arise and assail the truth of the gospel.&nbsp; Timothy is to combat this, not only through his own ministry to the whole church, but through passing the deposit of truth down particularly to faithful men who will maintain unbroken the genealogy of truth.</span></p>
<p><a href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-5-of-7/">Part 5</a></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-4-of-7/">A Biblical Philosophy of Theological Education (4 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-4-of-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Biblical Philosophy of Theological Education (2 of 7)</title>
		<link>/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-2-of-7/</link>
					<comments>/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-2-of-7/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 18:32:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theology Matters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9658</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>While the first post in this series considered &#8220;The Material Substance of Theological Education&#8221; in this post a second subject comes into view. &#160; II. The General Authority for Theological Education A. This Authority Identified The Apostle Paul leaves no doubt as to what agency is responsible for the maintenance and promotion of Christian truth [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-2-of-7/">A Biblical Philosophy of Theological Education (2 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><em><span style="font-size: large;">While the <a href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-1-of-7/">first post</a> in this series considered &#8220;The Material Substance of Theological Education&#8221; in this post a second subject comes into view.</span></em><br />
<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">II. The General Authority for Theological Education</span></strong></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">A. This Authority Identified</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The Apostle Paul leaves no doubt as to what agency is responsible for the maintenance and promotion of Christian truth in the world.&nbsp; It is clearly the church of Jesus Christ that is charged with this responsibility.&nbsp; 1 Timothy 3:15 is plain:&nbsp; &#8220;&#8230; but in case I am delayed, I write so that you will know how one ought to conduct himself in the household of God, which is the church of the living God, the pillar and support of the truth.&#8221;</span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">B. This Authority Specified</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The question may be raised, however, as to what Paul means exactly by the term, church, in 1 Timothy 3:15.&nbsp; To be specific, the question is whether Paul is thinking of what theologians have called the universal church or whether he is instead thinking of the local church.&nbsp; This is not a distinction which ought to be too sharply drawn in 1 Timothy 3:15. This is so because it really appears that Paul (in this passage and some others) understands the local church to be a particular expression of the universal church and speaks of it in terms which assume this relationship.&nbsp; It is clear, for instance, in this passage that Paul is writing to Timothy with regard to his particular responsibilities to guide the church in Ephesus and that this is prominent in his thought in this passage.&nbsp; It also seems clear, however, that he regards this church at Ephesus in light of its connection with the universal church.&nbsp; Paul could hardly mean to describe the local church at Ephesus&#8212;in itself and by itself&#8212;as the house of God, the church of the living God, or the pillar and support of the truth.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Here, then, we must fall back on a broader scriptural understanding of the church and see that each particular church is seen as a local expression of the universal church.&nbsp; Though recognizing their spiritual unity as part of the universal church, Reformed Baptist ecclesiology sees each particular church as governmentally independent and in that sense autonomous.&nbsp; Cf. the <a href="http://www.arbca.com/1689-chapter26" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1689 Baptist Confession, chapter 26, paragraphs 5-7</a>.&nbsp; At the same time, it recognizes that it is vital for these churches to cooperate for the better achievement of their tasks in the world.&nbsp; Such cooperation may take many scriptural forms, and in Reformed Baptist life it has taken many forms.&nbsp; According to the Confession it may involve formal associations of churches where this is providentially possible&#8212;as long as such associations do not infringe on the independence of the local church.&nbsp; Cf. the <a href="http://www.arbca.com/1689-chapter26" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1689 Baptist Confession, chapter 26, paragraphs 14-15</a>.&nbsp; It has often been thought that such tasks as missions (church-planting) and theological education (the training of ministers of the Word or pastor-teachers) especially require, or at least are more easily and better accomplished by means of, such cooperation.&nbsp; It is the assumption of this blog series that this thinking is correct.</span></p>
<p><a href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-3-of-7/"><strong>Part 3</strong></a></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-2-of-7/">A Biblical Philosophy of Theological Education (2 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-2-of-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Pastor&#8217;s Heart</title>
		<link>/the-pastors-heart/</link>
					<comments>/the-pastors-heart/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 20:04:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9510</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>By Pastor Jim Savastio I have pastored in Louisville, KY for nearly 30 years.&#160; Louisville, as many of you will know, has become something of the American Mecca for Reformed Theology.&#160; This is in large measure to the labors of Southern Seminary and Dr. Albert Mohler.&#160; Among the privileges that come from laboring in such [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-pastors-heart/">The Pastor&#8217;s Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Pastor Jim Savastio</p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">I have pastored in Louisville, KY for nearly 30 years.&nbsp; Louisville, as many of you will know, has become something of the American Mecca for Reformed Theology.&nbsp; This is in large measure to the labors of Southern Seminary and Dr. Albert Mohler.&nbsp; Among the privileges that come from laboring in such a town is the opportunity to meet and, in some cases, pastor young men aspiring to the work of the ministry.&nbsp; Inevitably such young men display academic competence and theological acumen.&nbsp; There are, however, several aspects of life and training which are often lacking if a man is to pursue a faithful and beneficial ministry in the long term.&nbsp; In this post I will deal with the matter of a shepherd&#8217;s heart.&nbsp; When I speak of &#8216;heart&#8217; I am addressing the matter of one&#8217;s thinking, affections, and consequent actions.&nbsp; I have often found that theology students love theology and that they tend to delight in one another.&nbsp; What I am most keen to see in them is a love for their own flock in which they are members.&nbsp; As a pastor who is always on the lookout for men who can and will serve the Lord here or in other places, I am concerned that they be skilled in the truth and in the passionate, accurate, clear and practical application of that truth in teaching.&nbsp; I am interested to know that these are godly men who spend time with the Lord in the word and in prayer.&nbsp; I want to see men who are in the battle in regard to their sins.&nbsp; But what I am most interested in is this&#8212;are these men shepherds?&nbsp; How do you tell a shepherd from a non-shepherd?&nbsp; You watch him around sheep.&nbsp; Sheep are drawn to him and he is drawn to them.&nbsp; While I understand that men training for ministry are not yet shepherds, this is the work to which they aspire.&nbsp; Not to be theologians, not to be professors, not even to be preachers&#8212;to be pastors, shepherds who care for the souls of their sheep. To that end allow two exhortations towards those who aspire to ministry as well as those who are in ministry.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>True shepherds know their flocks and are known by their flocks</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">This truth is laid out both implicitly and explicitly in the scriptures.&nbsp; This is an aspect of the shepherd/sheep relationship Jesus himself highlights in John 10:14, &#8220;I am the good shepherd; and I know My<em> sheep, </em>and am known by My own.&#8221;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">To the casual observer it may seem odd that a shepherd can actually know his sheep. Don&#8217;t they all look alike?&nbsp; Aren&#8217;t they all the same? Jesus, as the Good Shepherd, asserts that he knows his sheep individually and intimately.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">While no earthly shepherd can fully know the sheep the way that the Lord does, nonetheless there is something here that any shepherd after the Lord&#8217;s heart will embrace.&nbsp; The pastor must, in the words of Proverbs 27:23, be diligent to know the state of his flock.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The day is coming when every pastor will give an account of his stewardship. Every true hearted pastor lives day by day with the reality of Hebrews 13:17 impressed upon his heart, &#8220;They watch over souls as those who must give an account.&#8221;&nbsp; How can any man do that if he has no knowledge of the people to whom he preaches?&nbsp; Ask any earthly shepherd about his flock and he is ready to answer. How many sheep does he have?&nbsp; Which are the strongest?&nbsp; Which are the weakest?&nbsp; What do they need to survive and thrive?&nbsp; The pastor knows these things because he lives and labors among his people. They matter to him.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">He knows their weaknesses and their vulnerabilities.&nbsp; Pastors, likewise, are to live and labor among a people to whom they are attached with deep bonds of affection. &nbsp;Pastors are exhorted by Peter to shepherd the flock that is among them, exercising (putting into practice) the oversight (1 Peter 5:1ff).&nbsp; The phrase, &#8216;exercising oversight&#8217; means to carefully look after. What is the state of the flock?&nbsp; Are they thriving?&nbsp; Struggling?&nbsp; Weary?&nbsp; Troubled?&nbsp; Worldly?&nbsp; Are they in the Word?&nbsp; Do they have a solid assurance?&nbsp; Are they benefiting from the ministry?&nbsp; Are they at peace with their brethren?&nbsp; How are things in their homes?&nbsp; What are their peculiar burdens?&nbsp; Do the shepherds know these things?&nbsp; Do the shepherds care?&nbsp; Pastors must see these things as being a part of their calling and stewardship for which they will give an account.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">This knowledge goes both ways.&nbsp; Pastors are not to be enigmatic figures to their congregations.&nbsp; Paul commanded the believers in Thessolonica in reference to their elders, &#8220;And we urge you, brethren, to recognize those who labor among you, and are over you in the Lord and admonish you.&#8221; (1 Thess 5:12)&nbsp;&nbsp; The word translated as &#8216;recognize&#8217; in the NKJV is translated by others as respect, honor, or appreciate.&nbsp; The KJV gives the word as &#8216;know&#8217;.&nbsp;&nbsp; These various English words are attempts to translate the Greek word<strong><em>,&nbsp; eido.</em></strong>&nbsp; The word means to know, to perceive, to pay close attention, to inspect or behold.&nbsp; The sheep know whether or not their pastor is qualified, not merely on the basis of his pulpit skills and theological acumen, but because they have some knowledge of his life.&nbsp; He is a man, after all, who is given to hospitality.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>True shepherds love their flocks</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">&#8220;The hireling flees because he is a hireling and does not care about the sheep.&#8221; (John 10:13)&nbsp;&nbsp; The actions of the shepherd differ from the actions of the hireling due, in large measure to his affection for the sheep.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">What makes the earthly shepherd stand his ground when the wolf attacks?&nbsp;&nbsp; Is it simply a sense of duty and stewardship?&nbsp; Is it that he is fearful of his job or the wrath of the owner?&nbsp; Jesus tells what places him squarely in the way of danger&#8212;he cares for the sheep.&nbsp; His heart is towards them.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Love is the most essential element of the Christian faith.&nbsp; All believers are to experience a principled, Spirit wrought affection for one another.&nbsp; There is a special sense in which pastors are to love those entrusted to their care.&nbsp; &nbsp;The opening salvo of 1 Corinthians 13 has much to say to men in the ministry: &#8220;Though I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, but have not love, I have become sounding brass or a clanging cymbal.&nbsp; <sup>2</sup> And though I have <em>the gift of </em>prophecy, and understand all mysteries and all knowledge, and though I have all faith, so that I could remove mountains, but have not love, I am nothing.&#8221;&nbsp; What good is preaching, what profit or power is there in study and counseling if the pastor does not love those to whom he is preaching?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">If a shepherd is to labor for any length of time it is essential to share the heart of Paul expressed in 1 Thessalonians 2:7, 8<strong>&nbsp; &#8220;</strong>But we were gentle among you, just as a nursing <em>mother </em>cherishes her own children.&nbsp; <sup>8</sup> So, affectionately longing for you, we were well pleased to impart to you not only the gospel of God, but also our own lives, because you had become dear to us.&#8221;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">There are men who, out of principle and force of will, strive to give their lives to the flock.&nbsp; They will preach to them and pray for them at the cost to self or health or family, but such an endeavor, if it is not steeped in love, will build resentment in the long haul, towards the brethren, towards ministry and ultimately towards God himself.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-pastors-heart/">The Pastor&#8217;s Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-pastors-heart/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Amillennialism and the Age to Come—A Critical Review # 10</title>
		<link>/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-10/</link>
					<comments>/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-10/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 09:47:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amillenialism and the Age to Come]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matt Waymeyer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[premillenialism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7676</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Part 1, Part 2, Part 3, Part 4, Part 5, Part 6, Part 7, Part 8, Part 9 Does Waymeyer recognize the figurative character of Old Testament prophecy or adopt the typical literalism of Dispensationalism with regard to it? I noted in previous posts that Waymeyer at points seems uncomfortable, or at least speaks as [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-10/">Amillennialism and the Age to Come—A Critical Review # 10</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-1/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1</a>, <a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2</a>, <a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-3/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3</a>, <a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-4/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4</a>, <a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-5/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 5</a>, <a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-6/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 6</a>, <a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-7/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 7</a>, <a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-8/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 8</a>, <a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-9/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 9</a></p>
<p><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Does Waymeyer recognize the figurative character of Old Testament prophecy or adopt the typical literalism of Dispensationalism with regard to it?</span></strong></p>
<p>I noted in previous posts that Waymeyer at points seems uncomfortable, or at least speaks as if he were uncomfortable, with the literalistic approach of other Dispensationalists.  His statements about this occur on pages 61-63 and are worthy of a closer examination.</p>
<p>In these pages Waymeyer is responding to Dean Davis’ comments in <em>The High King of Heaven</em> where Davis notes that a literal interpretation of Zechariah 14 entails the notion that at the end of the present, modern age battles will be fought by men riding on horses, camels, and donkeys.  This direct implication of the literal hermeneutics of Dispensationalism, says Davis, poses one of the “intractable problems” for the premillennial view of this passage.</p>
<p>In response Waymeyer argues that Premillennialists have “long recognized the need to take an “analogical approach” with some Old Testament prophecies.” (61)  In this approach, he says, “statements are taken literally but then translated into their modern-day equivalents.” (61)  Waymeyer then opines: “Because it is unlikely (although certainly not impossible) that horses will be used as the primary means of advancing on Israel … the prophet may be describing the implements of future war with battle imagery familiar in his own day.”  (61)</p>
<p>This is an interesting and even startling admission in several ways.</p>
<p>First, Waymeyer here allows a hermeneutic which he denies to Amillennialists.  James Attebury (in his critique on Amazon) speaks of the Amillennial interpretation of Old Testament prophecy as using “the hermeneutic that the future is being described as an idealized present in Old Testament prophecy.”  Here Waymeyer himself allows the possibility that such a hermeneutic is possible.  An “analogical approach” to the Old Testament prophetic genre is all that Amillennialists require in order to answer Waymeyer’s polemic from Old Testament prophecy.</p>
<p>Second, it is also striking that Waymeyer is not entirely comfortable with his own admission.  Thus, as the above quotation makes clear, he holds out the possibility that Zechariah might still be taken in an entirely literal fashion.  He also makes the—what seems to me—contradictory statement that in this analogical approach statements are still taken literally, but interpreted analogically.  This, as with much else that the Dispensational hermeneutic has to say about the literal interpretation of the figurative language of the Bible, leaves me scratching my head.  It seems clear to me that if a statement is taken literally, then it ought to be interpreted literally.  On the other hand, it seems to me that if a statement is interpreted analogically, then this necessarily assumes that it is—as to its genre—analogical or figurative.</p>
<p>Third, further comments by Waymeyer suggest that he is still quite committed to a highly literal or literalistic interpretation of Old Testament prophecy.  Of course, in this vein we have just seen that he does not quite relinquish the possibility of a literal interpretation of the camels, donkeys, and horses of Zechariah 14.  We must also take account here, however, of his comments about the Feast of Booths and the Passover being celebrated in the Millennium in the following pages. (63)</p>
<p>Here Waymeyer argues that celebration of the Feast of Booths predicted in Zechariah 14 is consistent with the New Covenant’s fulfillment of the Old Testament shadows.  He says: “There is simply no reason why a future, eschatological celebration of this feast would require the re-establishment of anything that has been abolished or rendered obsolete by the first coming of Christ.”  Waymeyer may think so, but when the institution of this Feast is considered in Leviticus 23:33-43 and Deuteronomy 16:13-17, it is clear that the celebrating of this feast involves celebrating a ceremonial sabbath!  It also becomes clear that it is to be celebrated at Jerusalem.  It also becomes clear that it is appointed as one of the three great feasts appointed for the Jews to celebrated as part of their ceremonial calendar.  All of this is contrary to the abolition and obsolescence of the Old Covenant.</p>
<p>Waymeyer also in this context suggests that the Passover will be celebrated in the future!  Citing a personal conversation with Michael Vlach, he affirms this on the basis of the words of Jesus in Luke 22:15-16.  He then adds: “Celebrating the Feast of Booths in the messianic will no more constitute a return to the Mosaic law than eating the Passover will.”  The problem with all this is that it would contradict the New Covenant to eat the Passover after Christ our Passover has been sacrificed (1 Corinthians 5:7).  Furthermore, and emphatically, Jesus does not say that He will eat the Passover in the Age to Come.  He says that He will eat its “fulfillment.” This is something entirely different: “And He said to them, &#8220;I have earnestly desired to eat this Passover with you before I suffer; for I say to you, I shall never again eat it until it is <u>fulfilled</u> in the kingdom of God&#8221;” (Luke 22:15-16).</p>
<p>More to come&#8230;</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-10/">Amillennialism and the Age to Come—A Critical Review # 10</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-10/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Amillennialism and the Age to Come—A Critical Review # 5</title>
		<link>/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-5/</link>
					<comments>/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-5/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2017 11:40:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[amillenialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amillennialism and the Age to Come]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dispensationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology made simple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John the Baptist]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matt Waymeyer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Premillennialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7543</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Part 1, Part 2, Part 3, Part 4 First Criticism:&#160; Prophetic foreshortening must not be applied to New Testament prophecy. (Continued.) In my last post, I promised to give my readers two conclusive arguments against Waymeyer&#8217;s idea that prophetic foreshortening is characteristic of New Testament prophecy.&#160; Here is the first one. First, it directly contradicts [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-5/">Amillennialism and the Age to Come—A Critical Review # 5</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-1/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 1</a>, <a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 2</a>, <a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-3/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 3</a>, <a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-4/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Part 4</a></p>
<h1>First Criticism:&nbsp; Prophetic foreshortening must not be applied to New Testament prophecy. (Continued.)</h1>
<p>In my last post, I promised to give my readers two conclusive arguments against Waymeyer&#8217;s idea that prophetic foreshortening is characteristic of New Testament prophecy.&nbsp; Here is the first one.</p>
<p>First, it directly contradicts the assertion of Jesus that the one who is least in the kingdom is greater than John the Baptist (Matt. 11:11).&nbsp; This is a confusing statement to many and little understood.&nbsp; Its relevance for the present argument is immense.&nbsp; Allow me some space to open up its true meaning.</p>
<p>John the Baptist gladly embraced Jesus as the one who would usher in the glorious and irresistible coming of the kingdom (John 1:29).&nbsp; But when Jesus continued to preach the nearness of the kingdom and even preach the actual presence of the kingdom (Matt. 12:28f.) without the coming of the judgment of the wicked and the onset of the glorious consummation which he had prophesied (Matt 3:10-12), John the Baptist began to have doubts.&nbsp; When John was arrested and imprisoned, the problem became acute.&nbsp; How could the kingdom have come already in Jesus while John was rotting in Herod&#8217;s prison?&nbsp; Prison was the last place John expected to be after the coming of the kingdom! &nbsp;Thus, we read in Matthew 11:2-11,&nbsp; &#8220;Now when John in prison heard of the works of Christ, he sent word by his disciples, <sup>3</sup> and said to Him, &#8220;Are You the Expected One, or shall we look for someone else?&#8221; <sup>4</sup> And Jesus answered and said to them, &#8220;Go and report to John what you hear and see: <sup>5</sup> the BLIND RECEIVE SIGHT and the lame walk, the lepers are cleansed and the deaf hear, and the dead are raised up, and the POOR HAVE THE GOSPEL PREACHED TO THEM. <sup>6</sup> And blessed is he who keeps from stumbling over Me.&#8221; &#8230;. <sup>11</sup> &#8220;Truly, I say to you, among those born of women there has not arisen anyone greater than John the Baptist; yet he who is least in the kingdom of heaven is greater than he.&#8221;&#8221;</p>
<p>How could Jesus say that the one who was least in the kingdom of heaven was greater than John?&nbsp; Verse 11 in speaking of the one &#8220;who is least in the kingdom&#8221; being greater than John the Baptist refers to John in his distinctive capacity as a prophet.&nbsp; That is the capacity in which John is being considered in this context as verses 12-14 make clear: &#8220;And from the days of John the Baptist until now the kingdom of heaven suffers violence, and violent men take it by force. For all the prophets and the Law prophesied until John. And if you care to accept it, he himself is Elijah, who was to come.&#8221;</p>
<p>Prophets were distinguished for their knowledge of the mysteries of the kingdom.&nbsp; It is in this respect that Jesus ranks John as least in the kingdom.&nbsp; It is in his capacity as a prophet&#8212;the last and greatest of the Old Testament prophets&#8212;that Jesus is referring to John.&nbsp; It is, therefore, at the point of insight with regard to the mysteries relating to the coming of the kingdom that the one who is least in the kingdom is greater than John.</p>
<p>Old Testament prophets and prophecy had, as we have noted, what we may call a flattened perspective about the future.&nbsp; To put it in other words, the prophets were given little depth perception about the future.&nbsp; Sometimes, therefore, events that were widely separated in future time can be found predicted and mixed together in their writings.&nbsp; Consider for example the prophecy of Micah about the exile of Israel to and their deliverance from Babylon (Micah 4:9f.) and how this is intimately connected to predictions of the birth and glory of the Messiah (Micah 5:2f.).&nbsp; It is for this reason that the New Testament clearly teaches that prophets themselves did not at times understand clearly the things they were prophesying (1 Peter 1:10-12).</p>
<p>We learn from Matthew 11:2-6 that a godly and believing man like the great prophet John the Baptist struggled with the seeming inconsistency of Jesus&#8217; preaching of the kingdom and with what the Old Testament itself had led the Jews to expect (Dan 2:44). Can we think, therefore, that Jesus&#8217; disciples would be immune to the same doubts?&nbsp; No, they would have to face the same question.&nbsp; How could the all-conquering, glorious eschatological kingdom of God be present in this former carpenter and His Galilean followers?</p>
<p>The parables of the kingdom in Matthew 13 purport to explain the mystery of the kingdom.&nbsp; Thus, the question addressed is how the kingdom could be present in Jesus, His preaching, and His disciples.&nbsp;&nbsp; The common emphasis of these parables is Jesus&#8217; response to this question.&nbsp; This response is the theme of these parables.&nbsp; It is that the kingdom has come and is present in a form unexpected by the Jews, but that this present form anticipates its future, glorious consummation.&nbsp; To put this in other words, the theme of these parables is that the coming of the kingdom has two phases.&nbsp; It unfolds in two stages.&nbsp; It comes in a form unexpected by the Jews (and even John the Baptist), before it comes in its final glorious form.&nbsp; It is in this two stage coming of the kingdom that the mystery of the kingdom is revealed.&nbsp; Matthew 13 is the intended explanation of this mystery of the kingdom.&nbsp; The one who is least in the kingdom now understands that the kingdom comes in two stages&#8212;something that the prophets including John the Baptist&#8212;did not understand.&nbsp; The one who is least in the kingdom understands that Jesus is coming twice.</p>
<p>But in explaining the mystery of the kingdom in this way, Jesus brings an end to prophetic foreshortening.&nbsp; He explains the mystery.&nbsp; Thus, the least in the kingdom&#8212;then and now&#8212;is greater than John the Baptists and all the other Old Testament prophets.&nbsp; To apply prophetic foreshortening to New Testament prophecy is to turn back the clock.&nbsp; It is to put New Testament Christians in the same position as Old Testament prophets.&nbsp; It is to say that Jesus really did not explain the mystery of the kingdom.&nbsp; Virtually, Waymeyer is saying that the kingdom does not come only twice.&nbsp; Mysteriously and in a way not explained in Matthew 13 by Jesus, it actually comes three times:&nbsp; in the present age, in the millennial kingdom, and then in the eternal state.</p>
<p>And all this brings me to a second and consequent criticism.&nbsp; The notion that prophetic foreshortening is to be applied to New Testament prophecy creates havoc with biblical eschatology.&nbsp; Waymeyer substantially and virtually argues that in spite of the way certain passages sound (105), the principle of prophetic foreshortening allows us to see two resurrections, two judgments, and two ages to come where the Bible only speaks of one.</p>
<p>But this application of prophetic foreshortening to New Testament prophecy by Premillennialists is self-defeating.&nbsp; If such gaps still exist, then why may there not be three resurrections, three judgments, and three ages to come, and for that matter three comings of Christ&#8212;something that Dispensationalists like Waymeyer already in a sense actually believe!&nbsp; If it justifies Dispensationalism, why may not it justify a Super-Dispensationalism?&nbsp; If Jesus&#8217; explanation of the mystery is not in some sense its final explanation, then New Testament prophecy may mean or include virtually anything.&nbsp; There is an end to the sufficiency of Scripture for prophetic interpretation if we accept Waymeyer&#8217;s application of prophetic foreshortening to New Testament prophecy.</p>
<p>There is an old hymn with this prayer: &#8220;Be darkness, at Thy coming, light, Confusion, order in Thy path.&#8221;&nbsp; The above discussion is the first of many places in which I find the result of Waymeyer&#8217;s hermeneutic to be the exact opposite.&nbsp; Its result is not light, but darkness; not order, but confusion.&nbsp; It cannot, therefore, be divine.</p>
<p><a href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-6/"><em>Part 6</em></a></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-5/">Amillennialism and the Age to Come—A Critical Review # 5</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/amillennialism-and-the-age-to-come-a-critical-review-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
