<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Are Christians under the third use of the law?	</title>
	<atom:link href="/are-christians-under-the-third-use-of-the-law/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/are-christians-under-the-third-use-of-the-law/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2010 15:18:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Richard W. Daniels		</title>
		<link>/are-christians-under-the-third-use-of-the-law/#comment-107</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard W. Daniels]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2010 15:18:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=529#comment-107</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Luther and Calvin are both often misquoted on these questions.  In the contemporary debate, I guess the question, &quot;Are Christians under the third use of the law&quot; is somewhat incomplete.  &quot;Under&quot; for what?  For justification?  For direction for living?  Also, what law?  Civil regulations delivered by Moses for the nation of Israel?  Principles of justice taught by those civil regulations?  For catechetical starters, however, I know of no better summary of the matter than the hymn by the Lutheran Matthaias Loy, found in the Presbyterian Trinity Hymnal:

The law of God is good and wise
And sets his will before our eyes,
Shows us the way of righteousness,
And dooms to death when we transgress.

Its light of holiness imparts
The knowledge of our sinful hearts
That we may see our lost estate
And seek deliv&#039;rance ere too late.

To those who help in Christ have found
And would in works of love abound
It shows what deeds are his delight
And should be done as good and right.

When men the offered help disdain
And wilfully in sin remain,
Its terror in their ear resounds
And keeps their wickedness in bounds.

The law is good; but since the fall
Its holiness condemns us all;
It dooms us for our sin to die
And has no pow&#039;r to justify.

To Jesus we for refuge flee,
Who from the curse has set us free,
And humbly worship at his throne,
Saved by his grace through faith alone.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Luther and Calvin are both often misquoted on these questions.  In the contemporary debate, I guess the question, &#8220;Are Christians under the third use of the law&#8221; is somewhat incomplete.  &#8220;Under&#8221; for what?  For justification?  For direction for living?  Also, what law?  Civil regulations delivered by Moses for the nation of Israel?  Principles of justice taught by those civil regulations?  For catechetical starters, however, I know of no better summary of the matter than the hymn by the Lutheran Matthaias Loy, found in the Presbyterian Trinity Hymnal:</p>
<p>The law of God is good and wise<br />
And sets his will before our eyes,<br />
Shows us the way of righteousness,<br />
And dooms to death when we transgress.</p>
<p>Its light of holiness imparts<br />
The knowledge of our sinful hearts<br />
That we may see our lost estate<br />
And seek deliv&#8217;rance ere too late.</p>
<p>To those who help in Christ have found<br />
And would in works of love abound<br />
It shows what deeds are his delight<br />
And should be done as good and right.</p>
<p>When men the offered help disdain<br />
And wilfully in sin remain,<br />
Its terror in their ear resounds<br />
And keeps their wickedness in bounds.</p>
<p>The law is good; but since the fall<br />
Its holiness condemns us all;<br />
It dooms us for our sin to die<br />
And has no pow&#8217;r to justify.</p>
<p>To Jesus we for refuge flee,<br />
Who from the curse has set us free,<br />
And humbly worship at his throne,<br />
Saved by his grace through faith alone.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Stephen		</title>
		<link>/are-christians-under-the-third-use-of-the-law/#comment-106</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Stephen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2010 10:27:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=529#comment-106</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My understanding concerning the Moral Law/Ten Words/Commandments is that these and all the right and good precepts that like branhces flow from them are an eternal standard because they express the very heart and will of our Holy GOD and Father. If Adam had kept the commandments of GOD he could of had a genuine rightousness by good works fufilling a works Covenant.He failed thus we fail all in Adam ever will fail.Therefore the Covenant of Grace was before the Covenant of Works.Salvation has always been by Grace through Faith and the Law is good and holy and we are to ever in the inner man seek to keep it with the aide of the Holy Spirit.It Justifies no one,condems no Christian and is a help to us in a good sense in that it ever points us to our need of Grace and the forgivesness we ever have in Christ.&quot;I love Thy law Oh LORD it is the meditation of my heart all day long,&quot; What true Christian does not love His Commandments? I have never met one who was thinking soberly about the matter who does not love all His Commanments. I understand Grace I think by the Holy Spirit well and likewise the Law. In practice the Christian strives to keep it and when he fails,and he will,he flees to the Cross by Faith and remembers the forgivesness gained once for all there.If I am in error in my understaning I desire to be better schooled or taught on this matter,I desire to be teachable in all things.GBU Dear Pastor,Brother &#038; Friend.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My understanding concerning the Moral Law/Ten Words/Commandments is that these and all the right and good precepts that like branhces flow from them are an eternal standard because they express the very heart and will of our Holy GOD and Father. If Adam had kept the commandments of GOD he could of had a genuine rightousness by good works fufilling a works Covenant.He failed thus we fail all in Adam ever will fail.Therefore the Covenant of Grace was before the Covenant of Works.Salvation has always been by Grace through Faith and the Law is good and holy and we are to ever in the inner man seek to keep it with the aide of the Holy Spirit.It Justifies no one,condems no Christian and is a help to us in a good sense in that it ever points us to our need of Grace and the forgivesness we ever have in Christ.&#8221;I love Thy law Oh LORD it is the meditation of my heart all day long,&#8221; What true Christian does not love His Commandments? I have never met one who was thinking soberly about the matter who does not love all His Commanments. I understand Grace I think by the Holy Spirit well and likewise the Law. In practice the Christian strives to keep it and when he fails,and he will,he flees to the Cross by Faith and remembers the forgivesness gained once for all there.If I am in error in my understaning I desire to be better schooled or taught on this matter,I desire to be teachable in all things.GBU Dear Pastor,Brother &amp; Friend.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Richard Barcellos		</title>
		<link>/are-christians-under-the-third-use-of-the-law/#comment-105</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2010 03:25:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=529#comment-105</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Pastor Mike, thanks so much for that great quote of Luther. Luther is sadly misunderstood when it comes to the third use of the law, as is Calvin. I found these words of Dr. Schreiner confusing, &quot;Calvin and Luther had different positions on the third use of the law. Luther is closer to the truth on this matter than Calvin, for he sees more clearly that the Old Testament law is not normative for believers, and that believers are no longer under the Mosaic covenant.&quot; After saying this he adds a qualification that comes close to denying (if not formally denying) what he just said.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pastor Mike, thanks so much for that great quote of Luther. Luther is sadly misunderstood when it comes to the third use of the law, as is Calvin. I found these words of Dr. Schreiner confusing, &#8220;Calvin and Luther had different positions on the third use of the law. Luther is closer to the truth on this matter than Calvin, for he sees more clearly that the Old Testament law is not normative for believers, and that believers are no longer under the Mosaic covenant.&#8221; After saying this he adds a qualification that comes close to denying (if not formally denying) what he just said.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Mike Waters		</title>
		<link>/are-christians-under-the-third-use-of-the-law/#comment-104</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Waters]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2010 02:50:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=529#comment-104</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I assume that you received some time ago a copy of the disputations against the new spirits who have dared to expel the law of God or the Ten Commandments from the church and to assign them to city hall. I never expected that such false spirituality would ever come to anyone&#039;s mind, much less that anyone would support it...

It is most surprising to me that anyone can claim that I reject the law or the Ten Commandments, since there is available, in more than one edition, my exposition of the Ten Commandments, which furthermore are daily preached and practiced in our churches. Furthermore, the commandments are sung in two versions, as well as painted, printed, carved, and recited by the children morning, noon, and night. I know of no manner in which we do not use them, unless it be that we unfortunately do not practice and paint them with our deeds and our life as we should...

Martin Luther (Against the Antinomians, 1539)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I assume that you received some time ago a copy of the disputations against the new spirits who have dared to expel the law of God or the Ten Commandments from the church and to assign them to city hall. I never expected that such false spirituality would ever come to anyone&#8217;s mind, much less that anyone would support it&#8230;</p>
<p>It is most surprising to me that anyone can claim that I reject the law or the Ten Commandments, since there is available, in more than one edition, my exposition of the Ten Commandments, which furthermore are daily preached and practiced in our churches. Furthermore, the commandments are sung in two versions, as well as painted, printed, carved, and recited by the children morning, noon, and night. I know of no manner in which we do not use them, unless it be that we unfortunately do not practice and paint them with our deeds and our life as we should&#8230;</p>
<p>Martin Luther (Against the Antinomians, 1539)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
