<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Theology Matters: Sam Waldron on Pressing Issues	</title>
	<atom:link href="/theology-matters-pressing-issues/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/theology-matters-pressing-issues/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2012 10:45:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Thomas Sullivan		</title>
		<link>/theology-matters-pressing-issues/#comment-337</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Thomas Sullivan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2012 10:45:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1213#comment-337</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Since at this time I have commenced reading the Life of Charles Hodge and will narrate it for my podcast, the statements of Dr. Waldron are so welcome to hear.  The same battles that were fought that led to the disruption of the Presbyterian Church in 1837 face us today, and it is apparent some theologs in our own circles are coming down on the wrong side of the important questions. Thank you for not backing down and clearing the muddy thinking in our day. I can assure you that as I have talked to many Reformed Baptist pastors around the country, what Sam Waldron says here is what these dear brethren want to hear.  May God continue to use your Theological Training Center! - Thomas - Jenison MI]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Since at this time I have commenced reading the Life of Charles Hodge and will narrate it for my podcast, the statements of Dr. Waldron are so welcome to hear.  The same battles that were fought that led to the disruption of the Presbyterian Church in 1837 face us today, and it is apparent some theologs in our own circles are coming down on the wrong side of the important questions. Thank you for not backing down and clearing the muddy thinking in our day. I can assure you that as I have talked to many Reformed Baptist pastors around the country, what Sam Waldron says here is what these dear brethren want to hear.  May God continue to use your Theological Training Center! &#8211; Thomas &#8211; Jenison MI</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
