<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Systematic Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/systematic-theology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 16:24:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Systematic Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 2 of 2]: Analysis and Conclusion</title>
		<link>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/</link>
					<comments>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 15:51:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15601</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ben CarlsonBen has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 2 of 2]: Analysis and Conclusion</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_0 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_0">
								<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_0  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_0  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><em>This is part 2 of a 2 part series on Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology. You can read part 1 <a href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/">here</a></em>.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>II.) Analysis of Calvin’s Teaching on Natural Theology</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>1.) Calvin clearly distinguishes between natural revelation and natural theology.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

For Calvin, there is a substantial difference between the reality of the knowledge of God in the universe and the use of the knowledge of God by sinful man. The reality that God clearly and continually reveals Himself to man as Creator within him and around him is called natural or general revelation. The interpretation and use of that knowledge by men, who in this fallen world are enslaved in sin, is called natural theology. This is their creaturely attempt to interpret and understand general revelation (the knowledge of God in creation) without the help or aid of special revelation (the knowledge of God in Scripture). It is important to highlight the differences if we would correctly understand Calvin’s thought.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>2.) Calvin teaches that since natural revelation is so distorted and corrupted by fallen man, natural theology is a futile endeavor that leads one to a throng of feigned gods but never to the true God.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

God’s revelation of Himself in creation is meant to be a teacher and guide to men to point out the right way (1:5:15). Ideally, all image bearers of God would rightly respond to this knowledge. Yet Calvin is clear that because of sin, man lacks the ability to come to a knowledge of God worthy of the name. With only natural reasoning and common understanding as his guide, sinful man poisons and corrupts natural revelation to such an extent that by itself it only produces the worst possible fruits in him. According to Calvin, no matter if one is chieftain of the whole tribe of philosophers or the worst of the vulgar folk, the best that natural theology can do is lead one to the worship of an unknown god. Therefore, the true knowledge of God cannot be grasped by fallen man on the basis of natural revelation. There must be another way.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>3.) Calvin teaches that special revelation, or the Scriptures, is necessary not only to properly understand the knowledge of God in salvation but also to properly understand the knowledge of God in creation.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

The Bible not only teaches us about God the Redeemer. It also teaches us about God the Creator. In addition to the Book of Nature, the Scriptures are another and better help “which direct us aright to the very Creator of the Universe” and “clearly shows us the true God” (1:6:1). In fact, without their aid and assistance, “the human mind because of its feebleness can in no way attain to God” (1:6:4). In order to do this, we need the spectacles of special revelation (1:6:1). As Calvin says, “We must come, I say, to the Word, where God is truly and vividly described to us from his works, while these very works are appraised not by our depraved judgment but by the rule of eternal truth. If we turn aside from the Word, as I have just now said, though we may strive with strenuous haste, yet, since we have got off the track, we shall never reach the goal. For we should so reason that the splendor of the divine countenance, which even the apostle calls ‘unapproachable’ [I Tim. 6:16], is for us like an inexplicable labyrinth unless we are conducted into it by the thread of the Word; so that it is better to limp along this path than to dash with all speed outside it” (1:6:3). And, “Now, in order that true religion may shine upon us, we ought to hold that it must take its beginning from heavenly doctrine and that no one can get even the slightest taste of right and sound doctrine unless he be a pupil of Scripture” (1:6:2).

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>4.) Calvin teaches that using evidences apart from Scripture as proofs for God’s existence is unnecessary.</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

Since men do not need to be taught about God in the classroom but are masters of divinity from their mothers’ wombs (1:3:3), and since men suppress any knowledge of God they do possess by nature, the attempt to prove the existence of God from natural theology is unnecessary.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

We see that no long or toilsome proof is needed to elicit evidences that serve to illuminate and affirm the divine majesty; since from the few we have sampled at random, whithersoever you turn, it is clear that they are so very manifest and obvious that they can easily be observed with the eyes and pointed out with the finger. (1:5:9)

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

What is necessary, however, is faith.

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

It is therefore in vain that so many burning lamps shine for us in the workmanship of the universe to show forth the glory of its Author. Although they bathe us wholly in their radiance, yet they can of themselves in no way lead us into the right path. Surely they strike some sparks, but before their fuller light shines forth these are smothered. For this reason, the apostle, in that very passage where he calls the worlds the images of things invisible, adds that through faith we understand that they have been fashioned by God’s word [Heb. 11:3]. He means by this that the invisible divinity is made manifest in such spectacles, but that we have not the eyes to see this unless they be illumined by the inner revelation of God through faith. (1:5:14)

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

<strong>III.) Conclusion from Calvin’s Teaching on Natural Theology</strong>

<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->

After surveying the evidence, Calvin is highly critical of any teaching that ascribes to sinful man sound reasoning concerning the knowledge of God. He cannot be any plainer in his assessment: “Human reason, therefore, neither approaches, nor strives toward, nor even takes a straight aim at, this truth: to understand who the true God is or what sort of God he wishes to be toward us” (2:2:18). Yet the natural theology propounded by the medieval scholastics teaches that human reason can do just that. How biblical this teaching is should be addressed exegetically from the relevant passages of Scripture. But from a historical standpoint, it seems clear from Calvin’s own critique of natural theology that it was not consistent with the views of Reformed theology, especially with the teaching on man’s fallen and depraved state.

<!-- /wp:paragraph --></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->			
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->		
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 2 of 2]: Analysis and Conclusion</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 1 of 2]: Summary</title>
		<link>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/</link>
					<comments>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 20:11:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15583</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Ben Carlson Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 1 of 2]: Summary</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_1 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_1">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_1  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_1  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p><em>This is part 1 of a 2 part series on Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology. You can read part 2 <a href="http://calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-pt2/">here</a></em>.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>What was Calvin’s view of natural theology? That is an important question to ask today, especially in light of the discussions and debates taking place concerning the legitimacy of natural theology within Reformed epistemology and apologetics.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>One of the clearest places in the <em>Institutes</em> where Calvin’s evaluation of natural theology can be found is in Book 1, Chapter 5, Section 12. There he states, “Yet hence it appears that if men were taught only by nature, they would hold to nothing certain or solid or clear-cut, but would be so tied to confused principles as to worship an unknown god [cf. Acts 17:23].”</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>John T. McNeill, the editor of Ford Lewis Battles’ translation of the <em>Institutes</em>, makes this noteworthy remark in a footnote after Calvin’s words: “Natural theology (human reasoning about God, under the conditions of sin, unaided by special revelation) has been the subject of this chapter through section 12. All scholars agree that the above words present Calvin’s verdict upon it, held consistently in all his writings.”</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>In this brief essay, I will attempt to lay out Calvin’ critique of natural theology by first summarizing his teaching on the subject from the first six chapters of Book 1, second by analyzing his teaching, and third by offering a concluding thought. As “the theologian” of the Reformation, Calvin gives us a pivotal perspective concerning natural theology that aligns with his teachings on the doctrines of God, man, sin, Scripture, and grace. Therefore, his evaluation needs to be carefully read and understood.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>I.) Summary of Calvin’s Teaching on Natural Theology</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>1.) Calvin states that natural revelation is unmistakably and unfailingly clear to man.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Calvin argues that natural revelation, or the knowledge of God as Creator, Governor, and Judge of the world, is both inscribed on man’s heart and proclaimed throughout the universe.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>First, Calvin says that all men have an awareness of divinity, seed of religion, sense of deity, sort of divinity, and signs of immorality implanted and inscribed by God in their souls. This is the innate, inward, undeniable, and indelible knowledge of God as Creator. All men undoubtedly know Him as such and have no excuse to claim ignorance.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>There is within the human mind, and indeed by natural instinct, an awareness of divinity. This we take to be beyond controversy. To prevent anyone from taking refuge in the pretense of ignorance, God himself has implanted in all men a certain understanding of his divine majesty. (1:3:1)</p>
<p>And they who in other aspects of life seem least to differ from brutes still continue to retain some seed of religion. (1:3:1)</p>
<p>Therefore, since from the beginning of the world there has been no region, no city, in short, no household that could do without religion, there lies in this a tacit confession of a sense of deity inscribed in the hearts of all. (1:3:1)</p>
<p>Men of sound judgment will always be sure that a sense of divinity which can never be effaced is engraved upon men’s minds. (1:3:2)</p>
<p>.  . . that there is some God, is naturally inborn in all, and is fixed deep within, as it were in the very marrow. (1:3:3)</p>
<p>From this we conclude that it is not a doctrine that must first be learned in school, but one which each of us is master from his mother’s womb and which nature itself permits no one to forget, although many strive with every nerve to this end. (1:3:3)</p>
<p>As experience shows, God has sown a seed of religion in all men. (1:4:1)</p>
<p>Yet that seed remains which can in no wise be uprooted: that there is some sort of divinity. (1:4:4)</p>
<p>From this, my present contention is brought out with greater certainty, that a sense of divinity is by nature engraven on human hearts. (1:4:4)</p>
<p>These are unfailing signs of divinity in man. (1:5:5)</p>
<p>What ought we to say here except that the signs of immortality which have been implanted in man cannot be effaced? (1:5:5)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Second, Calvin states that all men are constantly confronted with the knowledge of God as Creator from the dazzling theater of His glory (1:5:8) that He has placed them in as spectators (1:6:2).</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>The final goal of the blessed life, moreover, rests in the knowledge of God [cf. John 17:3]. Lest anyone, then, be excluded from access to happiness, he not only sowed in men’s minds that seed of religion of which we have spoken but revealed himself and daily discloses himself in the whole workmanship of the universe. As a consequence, men cannot open their eyes without being compelled to see him. . . . But upon his individual works he has engraved unmistakable marks of his glory, so clear and so prominent that even unlettered and stupid folk cannot plead the excuse of ignorance. (1:5:1)</p>
<p>Yet, in the first place, wherever you cast your eyes, there is no spot in the universe wherein you cannot discern at least some sparks of his glory. (1:5:1)</p>
<p>There are innumerable evidences both in heaven and on earth that declare his wonderful wisdom; . . . Even the common folk and the most untutored, who have been taught only by the aid of the eyes, cannot be unaware of the excellence of divine art, for it reveals itself in this innumerable and yet distinct and well-ordered variety of the heavenly host. It is, accordingly, clear that there is no one to whom the Lord does not abundantly show his wisdom. (1:5:2)</p>
<p>Therefore, however fitting it may be for man seriously to turn his eyes to contemplate God’s works, since he has been placed in this most glorious theater to be a spectator of them, . . . (1:6:2)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>2.) Calvin states that natural revelation should teach man to fear, love, trust, and hope in God.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Calvin is clear that the knowledge of God in creation has a purpose, and that purpose is to greatly benefit man.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>For this sense of the powers of God is for us a fit teacher of piety, from which religion is born. I call “piety” that reverence joined with love of God which the knowledge of his benefits induces. (1:2:1)</p>
<p>Rather, our knowledge should serve first to teach us fear and reverence; secondly, with it as our guide and teacher, we should learn to seek every good from him, and, having received it, to credit it to his account. . . . Again, you cannot behold him clearly unless you acknowledge him to be the fountainhead and source of every good. From this too would arise the desire to cleave to him and trust in him . . . (1:2:2)</p>
<p>Knowledge of this sort, then, ought not only to arouse us to the worship of God but also to awaken and encourage us to the hope of the future life. (1:5:10)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>3.) Calvin states that natural revelation is unprofitable for sinful man.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Although the knowledge of God as Creator in creation should greatly benefit man, Calvin states that in a fallen world it does no such thing because of man’s sinfulness and blindness to the truth. Instead, with it man falls into superstitions, deserts God, or lives hypocritically. No matter the person, fallen man’s interpretation and response to natural revelation “corrupt by vanity the pure truth of God” (1:5:11) and “seduce[] his mind from rightly seeking him” (1:2:2).</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>But although the Lord represents both himself and his everlasting Kingdom in the mirror of his works with very great clarity, such is our stupidity that we grow increasingly dull toward so manifest testimonies, and they flow away without profiting us. (1:5:11)</p>
<p>Besides while some may evaporate in their own superstitions and others deliberately and wickedly desert God, yet all degenerate from the true knowledge of him. And so it happens that no real piety remains in the world. (1:4:1)</p>
<p>They see such exquisite workmanship in their individual members, from mouth and eyes even to their very toenails. Here also they substitute nature for God. (1:5:4)</p>
<p>Finally, they entangle themselves in such a huge mass of errors that blind wickedness stifles and finally extinguishes those sparks which once flashed forth to show them God’s glory. Yet that seed remains which can in no wise be uprooted: that there is some sort of divinity; but this seed is so corrupted that by itself it produces only the worst fruits. (1:5:4)</p>
<p>Sometimes we are driven by leading and direction of these things to contemplate God; this of necessity happens to all men. Yet after we rashly grasp a conception of some sort of divinity, straightway we fall back into the ravings or evil imaginings of our flesh, and corrupt by our vanity the pure truth of God. In one respect we are indeed unalike, because each one of us privately forges his own particular error; yet we are very much alike in that, one and all, we forsake the one true God for prodigious trifles. Not only the common folk and dull-witted men, but also the most excellent and those otherwise endowed with keen discernment, are infected with this disease. In this regard how volubly has the whole tribe of philosophers shown their stupidity and silliness! (1:5:11)</p>
<p>It is therefore in vain that so many burning lamps shine for us in the workmanship of the universe to show forth the glory of its Author. Although they bathe us wholly in their radiance, yet they can of themselves in no way lead us into the right path. Surely they strike some speaks, but before their fuller light shines forth these are smothered. (1:5:14)</p>
<p>Therefore, although the Lord does not want for testimony while he sweetly attracts men to the knowledge of himself with many and varied kindnesses, they do not cease on this account to follow their own ways, that is, their fatal errors. (1:5:14)</p>
<p>But, however that may be, yet the fact that men soon corrupt the seed of the knowledge of God, sown in their minds out of the wonderful workmanship of nature (thus preventing it from coming to a good and perfect fruit), must be imputed to their own failing; (1:5:15)</p>
<p>For at the same time as we have enjoyed a slight taste of the divine from contemplation of the universe, having neglected the true God, we raise up in his stead dreams and specters of our own brains, and attribute to anything else than the true source the praise of righteousness, wisdom, goodness, and power. Moreover, we so obscure or overturn his daily acts by wickedly judging them that we snatch away from them their glory and from their Author his due praise. (1:5:15)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>4.) Calvin states that natural theology is useless for sinful man.</strong></p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>Calvin argues that sinful man can never attain the true and pure knowledge of God with his depraved understanding. In other words, natural theology, or the ability of man to truly know and positively respond to God’s natural revelation, in a fallen world leads only to confused principles and a diversity of opinions about God, none of which are correct.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- divi:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>But among the philosophers who have tried with reason and learning to penetrate into heaven, how shameful is the diversity! (1:5:12)</p>
<p>. . . but no mortal ever contrived anything that did not basely corrupt religion. (1:5:12)</p>
<p>But since all confess that there is nothing concerning which the learned and the unlearned at the same time disagree so much, hence one may conclude that the minds of men which thus wander in their search after God are more than stupid and blind in the heavenly mysteries. (1:5:12)</p>
<p>Yet hence it appears that if men were taught only by nature, they would hold to nothing certain or solid or clear-cut, but would be so tied to confused principles as to worship an unknown god [cf. Acts 17:23]. (1:5:12)</p>
<p>In short, even if not all suffered under crass vice, or fell into open idolatries, yet there was no pure and approved religion, found upon common understanding alone. For even though few persons did not share in the madness of the common herd, there remains the firm teaching of Paul that the wisdom of God is not understood by the princes of this world [I Cor. 2:8]. But if even the most illustrious wander in darkness, what can we say of the dregs? (1:5:13)</p>
<p>But although we lack the natural ability to mount up unto the pure and clear knowledge of God, all excuse is cut off because the fault of dullness is within us. (1:5:15)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /divi:quote --></p>
<p><!-- divi:paragraph --></p>
<p>In the next post, I will present some analysis of Calvin&#8217;s teaching on Natural Theology.</p>
<p><!-- /divi:paragraph --></p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section --></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/">Calvin&#8217;s Critique of Natural Theology [Pt. 1 of 2]: Summary</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/calvins-critique-of-natural-theology-summary/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Murray and the Covenant of Works (4 of 4)</title>
		<link>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-4-of-4/</link>
					<comments>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-4-of-4/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 20:48:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Adamic Administration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covenant of works]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Murray]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10929</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Part 1  Part 2  Part 3 In this final post I want to say something else in defense of John Murray’s orthodoxy in spite of his hesitation over the terminology “Covenant of Works” and preference for the terminology “Adamic Administration.” So … John Murray was not led into error or heterodox views of justification by his [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-4-of-4/">John Murray and the Covenant of Works (4 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-1-of-4/">Part 1</a>  <a href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-2-of-4/">Part 2</a>  <a href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-3-of-4/">Part 3</a></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">In this final post I want to say something else in defense of John Murray’s orthodoxy in spite of his hesitation over the terminology “Covenant of Works” and preference for the terminology “Adamic Administration.” So …</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">John Murray was not led into error or heterodox views of justification by his hesitations over the terminology, Covenant of Works.  I have already pointed out that John Murray clearly taught in contradistinction to those with whom he is sometimes associated double imputation and the distinction between the active and passive obedience of Christ.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a>  But perhaps no doctrine is more often undermined in the departures from justification <em>sola fide</em> in modern evangelicalism than the doctrine of the traditional meaning of faith alone.  There is the constant tendency to define the exercise of justifying faith as including the faithfulness of obedience to God’s command and including this faithfulness in the quality by which it justifies.  In <em>Redemption: Accomplished and Applied</em> Murray begins by affirming that “In faith we receive and rest upon Christ alone for salvation.”<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a> He goes on to define such faith in a perfectly traditional way as knowledge (<em>notitia)</em>, conviction (<em>assensus</em>), and trust (<em>fiducia</em>).<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a>  He concludes: “It is to be remembered that the efficacy of faith does not reside in itself.  Faith is not something that merits the favour of God.  All the efficacy of faith unto salvation resides in the Saviour.  As one has aptly and truly stated the case, it is not faith that saves but faith in Jesus Christ; strictly speaking, it is not even faith in Christ that saves but Christ that saves through faith.”<a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Let us not be guilty of what the Apostle Paul (1 Timothy 6:4) calls “<em>logomachy</em>” (fighting about words) in our defense of orthodox views of justification and the Covenant of Works.  Let us rather judge by righteous judgment and not make John Murray a sinner, as the saying goes, ‘for a word.’ We run the risk of imbibing a prejudice which will steal from us the treasure which John Murray’s writings are to the church.</span></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> I am thinking of the implications left by Mark Karlberg when he says that Murray’s hand-picked successor At Westminster was Norman Shepherd: Mark Karlberg, <em>Gospel Grace: The Modern-day Controversy</em> (Eugene, OR: Wipf and Stock, 2003), 262.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Murray, <em>Redemption</em>, 106.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Murray, <em>Redemption</em>, 110-112.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> Murray, <em>Redemption</em>, 112.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-4-of-4/">John Murray and the Covenant of Works (4 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-4-of-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Murray and the Covenant of Works (3 of 4)</title>
		<link>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-3-of-4/</link>
					<comments>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-3-of-4/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 16:17:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Adamic Administration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covenant of works]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Murray]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Professor John Murray]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10886</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In my last post I began to defend John Murray’s orthodoxy by saying that Murray’s concerns about the terminology, Covenant of Works, must be properly understood and not exaggerated.  Now let me come to a second point in my defense of Murray. So … Second, John Murray holds everything essential to what was called the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-3-of-4/">John Murray and the Covenant of Works (3 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">In my last post I began to defend John Murray’s orthodoxy by saying that Murray’s concerns about the terminology, <em>Covenant of Works</em>, must be properly understood and not exaggerated.  Now let me come to a second point in my defense of Murray. So …</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Second, John Murray holds everything essential to what was called the Covenant of Works.  Indeed, let me go further.  I think he holds more than some defenders of the Covenant of Works hold of the things that are associated with the Covenant of Works.  Further, I think he holds these things more consistently than such people.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">It is, of course, indisputable that John Murray taught the representative headship of Adam.  This is the master concept which was embodied in the historic Covenant of Works formulation.  This involved a commitment to several crucial conceptions associated with the Covenant of Works.<br />
</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: x-large;">He taught (in contrast to modern heterodoxy exemplified in Daniel Fuller, Norman Shepherd, and the New Perspective on Paul) the imputation of Adam’s sin. No doubt can be entertained about this.  His statements in “The Adamic Administration” make this clear,<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> but the entirety of his treatment of this subject in his masterful <em>The Imputation of Adam’s Sin </em>makes this irrefutable.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: x-large;">He taught (in contrast to modern heterodoxy exemplified in Daniel Fuller, Norman Shepherd, and the New Perspective on Paul) double imputation and the associated distinction between the active and passive obedience of Christ. Not only do his statements in “The Adamic Administration” exemplify this,<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a> but the emphasis he lays on the obedience of Christ as the master category under which the work of Christ is to be understood in <em>Redemption: Accomplished and Applied </em>makes this irrefutably clear.  There he asserts that this master category enables us to see clearly the distinction between the active and passive obedience of Christ.<a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a></span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: x-large;">He taught (in contrast to modern heterodoxy exemplified in Daniel Fuller, Norman Shepherd, and the New Perspective on Paul) the reward of life. Murray makes it indisputably clear in “The Adamic Administration” that the reward of life is more than the continuation of the life with which Adam was created.  Murray says simply: “The tree of life represented everlasting life (Gen. 3:22). But it could not have this application unless there had been some provision connected with Eden which contemplated such life.”<a href="#_ftn5" name="_ftnref5">[5]</a>  In case this is not clear enough, Murray earlier argues that Adam had not partaken of the tree of life.  This conclusion is necessary for Murray because he regard the rewarded of life as more than the life which Adam possessed in the Garden. He argues: “Although from Genesis 3:22 we infer that Adam had not partaken of the tree of life, and although it was not forbidden as the tree of the knowledge of good and evil (cf. Gen. 2:16), yet, apparently, by the arrangements of providence or of revelation, it was recognized as reserved for the issue of probationary obedience.  This would explain Genesis 3:22, 24 (cf. Rev. 2:7; 22:2, 14, especially the expression “the right to the tree of life.”<a href="#_ftn6" name="_ftnref6">[6]</a></span></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Murray, <em>Collected Writings, Volume Two</em>, 50-51, 57-58.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> John Murray, <em>The Imputation of Adam’s Sin</em> (Nutley, NJ: Presbyterian and Reformed Publishing, 1977).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Murray, <em>Collected Writings, Volume Two</em>, 58.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a>John Murray, <em>Redemption: Accomplished and </em>Applied (Edinburgh: Banner of Truth Trust, 1961), 19-21.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref5" name="_ftn5">[5]</a>Murray, <em>Collected Writings, Volume Two</em>, 54.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref6" name="_ftn6">[6]</a> Murray, <em>Collected Writings, Volume Two</em>, 48.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-3-of-4/">John Murray and the Covenant of Works (3 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-3-of-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Murray and the Covenant of Works (2 of 4)</title>
		<link>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-2-of-4/</link>
					<comments>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-2-of-4/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 16:23:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Adamic Administration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covenant of works]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Murray]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Professor John Murray]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10862</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Part 1 In my first post I noted the important connection between orthodox views of the Covenant of Works and the doctrine of justification.&#160; This brings me to John Murray.&#160; John Murray famously questioned the traditional terminology or verbal description of the relation between God and Adam as a Covenant of Works.&#160; Over the years [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-2-of-4/">John Murray and the Covenant of Works (2 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-1-of-4/">Part 1</a></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">In my first post I noted the important connection between orthodox views of the Covenant of Works and the doctrine of justification.&nbsp; This brings me to John Murray.&nbsp; John Murray famously questioned the traditional terminology or verbal description of the relation between God and Adam as a Covenant of Works.&nbsp; Over the years I have come to believe that his caution regarding the traditional description of the relation between God and Adam as a Covenant of Works was unnecessary.&nbsp; I believe that the relation between God and Adam may be described as a &#8220;Covenant.&#8221;&nbsp; I believe that (properly understood and clarified) this relation may even be described as one of &#8220;Works.&#8221;&nbsp; At any rate, I am willing to acknowledge the historical momentum of this terminology, Covenant of Works and use it happily. Clearly, however, Murray&#8217;s hesitations about this terminology have misled some with regard to the true tendencies of his theological trajectory.&nbsp; I think&#8212;and always have thought&#8212;that for substance Murray holds everything essential to what was called the Covenant of Works.&nbsp; I certainly do not believe that his hesitations about the traditional terminology led to any error or heterodoxy regarding the doctrine of justification.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">These two assertions require some defense.&nbsp; Let me now provide that.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">First, Murray&#8217;s concerns about the terminology, <em>Covenant of Works</em>, must be properly understood and not exaggerated. &nbsp;We must not react to his hesitations without appreciating their nature.&nbsp; Murray expresses these hesitations in two major places.&nbsp; They are expressed in an article entitled, &#8220;Covenant Theology.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a>&nbsp; This article may now be found in volume four of his <em>Collected Writings</em>.&nbsp; They are also and more briefly expressed in the introduction to his article entitled, &#8220;The Adamic Administration.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a>&nbsp; This may now be found in volume two of his <em>Collected </em>Writings.&nbsp; Let me say several things about these hesitations.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-size: x-large;">In &#8220;The Adamic Administration&#8221; the first thing that Murray says about the terminology, <em>Covenant of Works</em>, is that it is not &#8220;felicitous.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a> No one perhaps has ever used the English language more carefully than Murray.&nbsp; Thus, his description of this terminology as not &#8220;felicitous&#8221; must be carefully noted.&nbsp; This is not a scathing or wholesale rejection of the terminology or what it represents.&nbsp; The terminology is in his view simply not &#8220;happy.&#8221;</span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: x-large;">The reason for the unhappiness of this terminology is that for Murray &#8220;the elements of grace entering into the administration are not properly provided for by the term &#8216;works&#8217;.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a> For Murray, &#8216;works&#8217; connotes the idea that the reward promised in the Adamic Administration was strictly merited or earned.&nbsp; Murray is of the opinion, and I think that he is right in this opinion, that the reward of life would have been in no way strictly earned by the obedience of Adam.&nbsp; In &#8220;Covenant Theology&#8221; Murray remarks: &#8220;The <em>promise</em> was that of the greatest felicity in heaven.&nbsp; The obligation which God assumed in this promise was wholly gratuitous.&nbsp; God had no debt, strictly speaking, from which a right could belong to man.&nbsp; The only debt was that of his own faithfulness to the promise.&nbsp; And as for man, he could not, strictly and properly, obtain merit from his obedience, and could not seek the reward as a right.&nbsp; The worthiness of works could bear no proportion to the reward of life eternal.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn5" name="_ftnref5">[5]</a>&nbsp; I think that Murray&#8217;s reasoning is irrefutable.&nbsp; Further, it appears to be seconded by the Westminster Confession (and the 1689 in almost the same language) when in chapter 7, paragraph 1 the Westminster says:&nbsp; &#8220;The distance between God and the creature is so great, that although reasonable creatures do owe obedience to him as their Creator, yet they could never have attained the reward of life but by some voluntary condescension on God&#8217;s part, which he hath been pleased to express by way of covenant.&#8221;&nbsp; The only question about this is whether the term &#8216;works&#8217; needs to imply such a strict idea of meriting the reward of life.</span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: x-large;">Murray goes on to say in &#8220;The Adamic Administration&#8221; that this administration is not designated a covenant in Scripture. Murray may perhaps be strictly speaking correct about this (depending on your interpretation of Hosea 6:7).&nbsp; His deeper concern is that the Adamic Administration does not meet what he regards as the proper definition of covenant.&nbsp; For Murray &#8220;Covenant in Scripture denotes the oath-bound confirmation of promise and involves a security which the Adamic economy did not bestow.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn6" name="_ftnref6">[6]</a>&nbsp; I am not carried by Murray&#8217;s argument here.&nbsp; I question his definition of covenant in Scripture.&nbsp; I also think it is possible for there to be a covenant properly defined where the exact terminology of covenant is not used.<a href="#_ftn7" name="_ftnref7">[7]</a></span></li>
<li><span style="font-size: x-large;">Murray is correct, however, to note that the terminology of Covenant of Works is a somewhat later development in Reformed theology. While the major ideas later summarized under this rubric date back with good evidence to Calvin himself, the actual terminology&#8212;Murray thinks&#8212;cannot be found until the last decade of the 16<sup>th</sup>&nbsp; Even then various ways of describing this covenant may be found.&nbsp; It is variously called the covenant of life, favor, and nature.<a href="#_ftn8" name="_ftnref8">[8]</a></span></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">The fundamental lesson to be drawn from all this is that Murray&#8217;s rejection of this terminology must not be turned into something it was not.&nbsp; Even such a stern critic of John Murray as Mark Karlberg in <em>Covenant Theology in Reformed Perspective </em>freely admits and concludes: &#8220;This recognition that the law-principle does characterize the state of nature, man&#8217;s natural relationship with God &#8230; safeguards his formulation of the doctrine of justification by faith and the doctrine of the atonement of Christ. &#8230;. As a result, Murray&#8217;s theological system is essentially compatible with the Westminster Standards &#8230;&#8221;<a href="#_ftn9" name="_ftnref9">[9]</a></span></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> John Murray, <em>Collected Writings, Volume Four: Studies in Theology</em> (Edinburgh: The Banner of Truth Trust, 192), 216-240.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Murray, <em>Collected Writings, Volume Two</em>, 47-59.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Murray, <em>Collected Writings, Volume Two</em>, 49.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> Ibid.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref5" name="_ftn5">[5]</a> Murray, <em>Collected Writings, Volume Four</em>, 222.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref6" name="_ftn6">[6]</a> Murray, <em>Collected Writings, Volume Two</em>, 49.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref7" name="_ftn7">[7]</a> Gonzales, Robert R., Jr. &#8220;The Covenantal Context of the Fall: Did God Make a Primeval Covenant with Adam?&#8221; Reformed Baptist Theological Review IV:2 (2007): 5-32.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref8" name="_ftn8">[8]</a> Murray, <em>Collected Writings, Volume Four</em>, 217-221.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref9" name="_ftn9">[9]</a> Mark W. Karlberg, <em>Covenant Theology in Reformed Perspective</em> (Eugene, OR: Wipf and Stock, 2000), 45.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-2-of-4/">John Murray and the Covenant of Works (2 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-2-of-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Murray and the Covenant of Works (1 of 4)</title>
		<link>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-1-of-4/</link>
					<comments>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-1-of-4/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 20:26:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Adamic Administration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covenant of works]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Professor John Murray]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10804</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>[Recently, I submitted an essay for an upcoming book in memory Dr. Robert Paul Martin entitled:&#160; A Contemporary Treatment of the Covenant of Works in the Tradition of John Murray.&#160; I do not intend to reproduce the entirety of that essay in these blog posts.&#160; I introduced my treatment of the Covenant of Works with [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-1-of-4/">John Murray and the Covenant of Works (1 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><span style="font-size: large;">[Recently, I submitted an essay for an upcoming book in memory Dr. Robert Paul Martin entitled:&nbsp; <em>A Contemporary Treatment of the Covenant of Works in the Tradition of John Murray.</em>&nbsp; I do not intend to reproduce the entirety of that essay in these blog posts.&nbsp; I introduced my treatment of the Covenant of Works with some <em>Preliminary Thoughts on John Murray and the Covenant of Works</em>.&nbsp; I did so because John Murray&#8217;s treatment of this subject (which he entitled, &#8220;The Adamic Administration&#8221;) has caused many rumors and suspicions about his orthodoxy among some Reformed folks.&nbsp; I have always felt that these suspicions were unfair. In these <em>Preliminary Thoughts </em>I explain why.]</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Those in the mainstream of the Reformed tradition have become increasingly sensitive to the importance of holding proper views of the Covenant of Works if one is to hold and defend the traditional Protestant and Reformed doctrine of justification.&nbsp; The modern voices calling for a revision of this article of faith (which has been called the article of the standing or falling of the church) have one after another made clear their opposition to the notion of the Covenant of Works as it has been held and defended in the Reformed tradition.&nbsp; The proponents of the New Perspective on Paul, the advocates of the Federal Vision, and those allied with John Piper&#8217;s mentor Daniel Fuller have generally denied the Covenant of Works and universally revised the Protestant and Reformed doctrine of justification.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">There is, indeed, in my view an important and logical connection between right views of the Covenant of Works and the Protestant doctrine of justification.&nbsp; It is not surprising, then, that inadequate views of the Covenant of Works have increasingly been recognized as dangerous, suspicious, and tantamount to a denial of the traditional doctrine of justification. While such suspicions are understandable and may even be proper, they are not always well-grounded.&nbsp; Innocent people have sometimes been caught in the crossfire over the Covenant of Works and been accused of views which they have not taught.&nbsp; Those whose views of justification are mostly or entirely traditionally Protestant have been accused of heterodoxy and associated with the New Perspective on Paul or the Federal Vision because their views of the Covenant of Works have not come up to the standards of their critics.&nbsp; While we do well to understand that proper views of the Covenant of Works are the final and firm foundations of the traditional Protestant doctrine of justification, we must not accuse those who fail to dot our I&#8217;s or cross our T&#8217;s with heterodoxy.&nbsp; We must allow people to be logically inconsistent with their basically orthodox views of justification in their inadequate views of the Covenant of Works.&nbsp; Of course, we must point out to them the danger in their inconsistent views of the Covenant of Works, but we must not accuse them of actually holding views which we think their errors logically lead to.&nbsp; People are inconsistent.</span></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Sam Waldron, <em>Faith, Obedience, and Justification: Current</em> <em>Evangelical Departures from Sola Fide</em> (Palmdale, CA: Reformed Baptist Academic Press, 2006), 127-223.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-1-of-4/">John Murray and the Covenant of Works (1 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/john-murray-and-the-covenant-of-works-1-of-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Division of Old Testament Law</title>
		<link>/the-division-of-old-testament-law/</link>
					<comments>/the-division-of-old-testament-law/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tom Hicks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2018 18:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Theology Matters]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9894</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Are believers in Christ required to obey any part of Old Testament law? Both Dispensationalists and proponents of New Covenant Theology, or Progressive Covenantalism, as one version of it has come to be called, simply say “no.” In their view, the laws of the Old Testament are fulfilled and abrogated in Christ. Believers are only [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-division-of-old-testament-law/">The Division of Old Testament Law</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: large;">Are believers in Christ required to obey any part of Old Testament law? Both Dispensationalists and proponents of New Covenant Theology, or Progressive Covenantalism, as one version of it has come to be called, simply say “no.” In their view, the laws of the Old Testament are fulfilled and abrogated in Christ. Believers are only required to obey the “law of Christ,” which is taught in the commands of the New Testament alone. That’s a simple hermeneutic that draws a sharp line between the testaments and tells believers they don’t have to obey any Old Testament law. One of the major problems with this perspective is that New Testament authors seem to assume the authority of the Old Testament in matters of certain kinds of law. Another problem is that in spite of objections to the contrary, the Old Testament doesn’t treat all of its laws the same way either. We often hear that “the Law” is a unit, that all of it is moral, and that if any of it is abrogated, then all of it must be. While the issues involved in this dispute among sincere brothers in Christ certainly require more than a simple blog post, I offer the following short critique of those views which teach that Old Testament law is monolithic and without any divisions.</span></p>
<h3>Old Testament</h3>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>1. Old Testament laws are divided into categories</strong>. Deuteronomy 4:13-14 says, “And he declared to you his covenant, which he commanded you to perform, that is, the Ten Commandments, and he wrote them on two tablets of stone. And the LORD commanded me at that time to teach you statutes and rules, that you might do them in the land you are going to possess.” Notice that the “Ten Commandments” (lit. ten words) are distinct from the other designations of Old Testament law: “statutes” and “rules.” Similarly, Moses writes, “Now this is the commandment, the statutes, and the rules that the LORD your God commanded me to teach you” (Deut 6:1). These three kinds of laws: commandments, statutes, and rules, overlap in their semantic range, but they are not identical. Commandments (<em>mitsvah</em>) are “codes of law;” statutes (<em>hoq</em>) are “ordinances;” rules (<em>mishpat</em>) are “case laws.” Therefore, it’s far from correct to say the Old Testament does not divide its laws into various categories.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Furthermore, the order in which God gave the law in the book of Exodus implies the distinctivenesss of the Ten Commandments. God gave the Ten Commandments in Exodus 20. Then in Exodus 21-23, God reveals the civil laws. And then beginning in Exodus 25, God provides the ceremonial laws about the tabernacle. Thus, the Ten Commandments stand alone as distinct and primary, while all other laws in the Old Covenant are subsequent to them.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>2. The Ten Commandments were revealed in a unique way</strong>. God gave the Ten Commandments on Mount Sinai with loud thunder, flashes of lightning, a thick cloud, and a “very loud trumpet blast” (Ex 19:16). No other laws were revealed this way. It was a striking and emotional experience for those who were there. God wanted it to be memorable. He intended the Ten Commandments to stand out in the minds of His people above all other laws. He wanted to impact their senses so that they would never forget the distinctive importance of these ten words. Furthermore, only the Ten Commandments were spoken by God to the whole congregation (Deut 4:12-13). The other commands were spoken through Moses.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>3. God wrote the Ten Commandments with His own finger</strong>. Exodus 31:18 says God gave Moses “tablets of stone, written with the finger of God.” The other laws were written by the pen of Moses. The Ten Commandments were engraved on “stone” to communicate that they are fixed and permanent. God wrote the rest of the old covenant laws through Moses on paper.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>4. The Ten Commandments are uniquely sufficient among all Old Testament laws</strong>. The Old Testament tells us that the Ten Commandments were a sufficient summary of God’s most central laws. We see this taught in Deuteronomy 5:22, which says that after God had spoken the Ten Commandments, “he added no more.” After God gave the Ten Commandments, there was no need to add any more. The Ten Commandments sufficiently summarized the way God’s people were to express their love to Him and to one another. If God’s people obeyed these laws, then they would be keeping the heart of the law, and all other obedience would follow from it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>5. The Ten Commandments alone were placed in the Ark of the Covenant</strong>. God told Moses to put the Ten Commandments inside the ark of the covenant, but to “Take this Book of the Law and put it by the side of the ark of the covenant” (Deut 31:24-26). This shows how the Ten Commandments are at the heart of all the other Old Testament commandments. The civil and ceremonial laws were only to be kept in the land of Canaan (Deut 5:30-33), but the Ten Commandments were written on the hearts of OT believers, and were kept wherever the people went (Ps 37:31; 40:8; Is 51:7).</span></p>
<h3>New Testament</h3>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The New Testament also makes distinctions among Old Testament laws. While it teaches that some Old Testament laws are abrogated, it shows that others are perpetually binding on the hearts and lives of believers.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>1. Jesus teaches that the Ten Commandments are never to be abolished</strong>. He said, “For truly I say to you, until heaven and earth pass away, not a dot will pass from the Law” (Matt 5:17). What law is Christ speaking about? He goes on to list laws from the Ten Commandments: do not murder (Matt 5:21-26); do not commit adultery (Matt 5:27-32); do not lie (Matt 5:33-37).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>2. Adam, the first Gentile, had the Ten Commandments written on his heart</strong>. Romans 2:14-15 says, “For when the Gentiles who do not have the law, <em>by nature</em>, do what the law requires, they are a law to themselves, even though they do not have the law. They show that the work of the law is written on their hearts, while their conscience also bears witness.” What law was Paul writing about? Just a few verses later, Paul goes on to list some of the Ten Commandments: do not steal (Rom 2:21), do not commit adultery (Rom 2:22), do not commit idolatry (Rom 2:22). This same law is written on the consciences of all who bear the image of God. Ephesians 4:24 explicitly links being made in God’s “likeness” to “righteousness,” which means “lawfulness.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">This shows us that there is a natural law within a man, summarized by the Ten Commandments. Other laws are coventantal or positive (posited) laws, which come from outside of a man. For example, Abraham knew by nature, from within, not to murder, but he did not know to be circumcised from within. God had to reveal the command to be circumcised by covenant from without in the Abrahamic covenant. Natural law, written on the human heart, cuts across all covenants. But covenantal positive laws change with the covenant.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>3. Paul says one can “keep the law” without obeying the command to be circumcised</strong>. Many argue that the Old Testament law can’t be divided. But if that were true, then it would be impossible to keep the law without also keeping the command to be circumcised. Paul writes, “So, if a man who is uncircumcised keeps the precepts of the law, will not his uncircumcision be regarded as circumcision?” (Rom 2:26). Paul has a category for Gentiles who “keep the law” without obeying the Old Testament command to be circumcised. What law is Paul thinking about? Again, context shows, it’s the Ten Commandments (Rom 2:21-23).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>4. Paul distinguishes between “the law of commandments” and its “ordinances.”</strong>Ephesians 2:15 says that when Christ died, He abolished “the law of commandments <em>expressed</em> in ordinances.” Notice that Christ didn’t abolish the law of commandments itself, only its expression in ordinances. “Ordinances” are the national “rules” or “decrees” of Israel that were based on moral law, but not identical to it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>5. In the new covenant, certain Old Testament “law” is written on our hearts</strong>. God blesses His new covenant people saying, “I will put my laws into their minds and write them on their hearts” (Heb 8:10).  That’s a quotation from Jeremiah 31, in which the author had Old Testament law in mind. Literally, the words “write them” mean “carve them,” calling to mind how God carved the Ten Commandments into tablets of stone. While the whole Old Covenant has been abrogated in Christ (Heb 8:13), the moral law of the Old Covenant, the Ten Commandments, are written on the hearts of believers (2 Cor 3:3). Old Testament ceremonial laws relating to priesthood are abolished: “When there is a change in the priesthood, there is necessarily a change in the law as well,” but the moral law is written on the hearts of the members of the new covenant: “I will put my laws into their minds and write them on their hearts” (Heb 8:10).</p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Therefore, it seems clear from both testaments that there is a division among Old Testament laws. The Ten Commandments are unique because they are a reflection of God’s own character. Paul teaches us that the Ten Commandments are written on the consciences of Gentiles. They were given by God in a unique way and stand above all other ordinances. In Christ’s death, He abolished the expression of the Ten Commandments in ordinances, but He did not abolish the Ten Commandments themselves. They are written on the hearts of all members of the new covenant, which was established in His blood.</span></span></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/tom-hicks/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2018/03/02211852/TomHicks.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/tom-hicks/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Tom Hicks</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<div class="header">
<div class="description">Tom serves as the Senior Pastor of First Baptist Church of Clinton, LA. He&#8217;s married to Joy, and they have four children: Sophie, Karlie, Rebekah, and David. He received his MDiv and PhD degrees from The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary with a major in Church History, emphasis on Baptists, and with a minor in Systematic Theology. Tom is the author of The Doctrine of Justification in the Theologies of Richard Baxter and Benjamin Keach (PhD diss, SBTS). He serves on the board of directors for Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary and is an adjunct professor of historical theology for the Institute of Reformed Baptist Studies.</div>
</div>
<div id="featured">
<div class="hero"></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-division-of-old-testament-law/">The Division of Old Testament Law</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-division-of-old-testament-law/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Crux of the Free Offer of the Gospel</title>
		<link>/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/</link>
					<comments>/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 18:53:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Course offerings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Offer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Offer of the Gospel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hyper-Calvinism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[well-meant offer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7876</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The following is Dr. Sam Waldron&#8217;s introduction to his lectures for our upcoming module: Hyper-Calvinism &#38; the Free Offer of the Gospel In the historic documents which brought to its climax the confessional development sparked by the Reformation&#8212;the Westminster Confession (1644-46), the Savoy Declaration (1658), and the 1689 Baptist Confession&#8212;the free offer of the gospel [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/">The Crux of the Free Offer of the Gospel</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The following is Dr. Sam Waldron&#8217;s introduction to his lectures for our upcoming module:
</p>
<h2><a href="/hyper-calvinism/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>Hyper-Calvinism &amp; the Free Offer of the Gospel</strong></a></h2>
<p>In the historic documents which brought to its climax the confessional development sparked by the Reformation&#8212;the Westminster Confession (1644-46), the Savoy Declaration (1658), and the 1689 Baptist Confession&#8212;the free offer of the gospel is confessed in each in chapter 7 and in identical language.&nbsp; The Westminster Confession and its daughter and grand-daughter confessions each speak of &#8220;the covenant of grace, wherein he freely offereth unto sinners, life and salvation by Jesus Christ.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></p>
<p>It is both the conviction and assumption of these lectures that the crux of the doctrine of the free offer of the gospel is <em>God&#8217;s Indiscriminate Desire for the Salvation of Sinners</em>.&nbsp; To put this in other words, at the core of the free offer of the gospel is what is called the &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer of the gospel.&nbsp; Though it may be well to speak of the &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer of the gospel for the sake of doctrinal clarity, I am jealous to affirm here that this is both the natural and necessary implication of the &#8220;free&#8221; offer confessed by the climactic Reformation confessions.</p>
<p>My conviction is that the &#8220;free&#8221; offer in the confessional documents is and must be understood as a &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer.&nbsp; Though this affirmation may be defended at length (and will be by Dr. Daniel in his historical treatment in this course, it may be proper here for me to briefly mention the grounds upon which my conviction is based.&nbsp; I maintain that the &#8220;free&#8221; offer in the confessional documents is and must be understood as a &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer for a number of reasons.</p>
<ul>
<li>It is, I think, the logical and necessary implication of speaking of a free offer. In fact, it seems to me that this is the implication of both the word, offer, and the word, free.&nbsp; &#8220;Offer&#8221; contains in it the notion of a proposal presented to someone which the one presenting it desires for him to accept.&nbsp; An offer not presented with such intent or desire would be regarded as insincere.&nbsp; What man proposes marriage to a woman without a desire that she should accept his proposal?&nbsp; What woman would regard such a proposal as authentic or genuine if it was not accompanied by the desire of the man for it to be accepted.&nbsp; The word, free, however, emphasizes the notion of a desire that one should take the offer presented.&nbsp; An offer is presented with the desire that it should be taken by the one to whom it is presented.&nbsp; A &#8220;free&#8221; offer accentuates such desire and the &#8220;well-meant&#8221; character of the offer by providing an extra incentive for the proposal to be accepted.</li>
<li>That this is the meaning and implication of a &#8220;free offer&#8221; was generally recognized by the modern opponents of the free offer in the controversy over common grace in the Christian Reformed denomination in the controversy that came to its denominational culmination in 1924. The Protestant Reformed Churches denied the free offer because they properly understood that a free offer was a well-meant offer&#8212;an offer that contained common grace.&nbsp; So much is this the case that Herman Hanko referencing the first point of common grace adopted by the Christian Reformed Church at the synod of 1924 and writing in the official journal of the Protestant Reformed Churches can write:</li>
</ul>
<p>In the discussions which followed the adoption of this statement of doctrine, the reference to the free offer was often called, &#8220;het puntje van het eerste punt.&#8221;&nbsp; (The main point of the first point.)&nbsp; While it is our intention to deal more specifically with this question at a later date, the point we wish to make now is that a denial of the free offer of the gospel is a part of the doctrinal confession of the Protestant Reformed Churches from their very beginning.&nbsp; This denial of the free offer of the gospel by the Protestant Reformed Churches has set them apart from almost every ecclesiastical fellowship.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></p>
<ul>
<li>That by the confessional free offer was intended a well-meant offer is the necessary conclusion to be reached from the historical backdrop of the climactic Reformed confessions. The high points of this backdrop (Calvin and the Canons of Dort) teach a free and well-meant offer.&nbsp; This is not the place for a detailed presentation of the evidence for this. Dr. Daniel will be providing such a presentation.&nbsp; It may be good, however, to illustrate the truth of this assertion.&nbsp; Perhaps the classic affirmation of the Free Offer by Calvin comes in a letter to Melancthon.&nbsp; There he says:</li>
</ul>
<p>And it cannot be attributed to hallucination, that you, a man acute and wise, and deeply versed in Scripture, confound the election of God with His promises, which are universal.&nbsp; For nothing is more certain than that the gospel is addressed to all promiscuously, but that the Spirit of faith is bestowed on the elect alone, by peculiar privilege.&nbsp; The promises are universal.&nbsp; How does it happen, therefore, that their efficacy is not equally felt by all?&nbsp; For this reason, because God does not reveal His arm to all.&nbsp; Indeed, among men but moderately skilled in Scripture, this subject needs not to be discussed, seeing that the promises of the Gospel make offer of the grace of Christ equally to all; and God, by the external call, invites all who are willing to accept of salvation.<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></p>
<ul>
<li>The classic assertion of the free and well-meant offer of the gospel by the Canons of Dort comes in The Second Head of Doctrine, Article 5 and The Third and Fourth Heads of Doctrine, Articles 6-8. The second reference bears comment.&nbsp; In Articles 6 and 7 gospel preaching and calls given to many who are not elect are described as &#8220;grace&#8221; and &#8220;so great and so gracious a blessing.&#8221;&nbsp; Article 8 then asserts, &#8220;As many as are called by the gospel, are unfeignedly called.&nbsp; For God hath most earnestly and truly declared in His Word, what will be acceptable to him; namely, that all who are called, should comply with the invitation.&#8221; &nbsp;If this language does not assert a free and well-meant offer, one wonders how such an idea could be stated without using the exact or precise words.</li>
</ul>
<p>To all this needs to be added a comment about the more recent history of Reformed truth.&nbsp; The resurgence of Reformed theology beginning in the 50&#8217;s and 60&#8217;s of the 20<sup>th</sup> Century can be traced in large part to Banner of Truth Trust; a Westminster Theological Seminary dominated by Cornelius Van Til and John Murray; and the revival of interest in the writing of Charles H. Spurgeon.&nbsp; In so far as this is true it is right to say that this resurgence of Calvinism was committed to the free and well-meant offer of the gospel.</p>
<p>In spite of all this and with the blossoming of wider interest in Reformed theology, there has come a denial of the well-meant offer of the gospel in recent years.&nbsp; It is this resurgence of a denial of the free and well-meant offer which has given birth in my mind to the necessity of this course and these lectures.</p>
<p>My lectures are not intended strictly speaking as a supplement to those of Dr. Daniel.&nbsp; It seemed better for us both to follow our own track in opening up this subject.&nbsp; I think we are of single mind on the subject, but perhaps such duplication as there may be between us will serve the student.&nbsp; Perhaps as well, whatever differences of emphasis there may be will also be of value to the student.</p>
<h2><strong>Outline of Dr. Waldron&#8217;s Lectures</strong></h2>
<p>Part 1:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Scriptural Exposition (from John 5:34)</p>
<p>Part 2:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Biblical Confirmation</p>
<p>Part 3:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Confessional Position</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Explicit Assertion</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Implicit Affirmation</p>
<p>Part 4:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Doctrinal Implications</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Love of God</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Will of God</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 3:&nbsp; The Mystery of God</p>
<p>Part 5:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Major Objections</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Objection from the Doctrine of Election</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Objection from the Doctrine of Simplicity</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 3:&nbsp; The Objection from the Fact of Anthropopathisms</p>
<p>Part 6:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Practical Applications</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Warning against Rationalism</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Warrant of Faith</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 3:&nbsp; The Way of Preaching</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">It&#8217;s not too late to register! &nbsp;<a href="/hyper-calvinism/"><strong>Register Here</strong></a></span></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a>This language is found in chapter 7, paragraph 2, in the 1689, but in chapter 7 paragraph 3 in the Savoy and Westminster.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a>Herman Hanko, <em>The History of the Free Offer</em>, accessed on the Internet July 21, 2017 <a href="http://www.prca.org/pamphlets/Free%20Offer/Introduction.htm">http://www.prca.org/pamphlets/Free%20Offer/Introduction.htm</a>.&nbsp; Further confirmation of the Protestant Reformed denial of the free offer of the gospel may be seen in David Engelsma, <em>Hyper-Calvinism and the Call of the Gospel: An Examination of the Well-Meant of the Gospel</em> (The Reformed Free Publishing Company: Jenison, MI, 2014).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a>Calvin, John, <em>Selected Works of John Calvin</em>, ed. by Henry Beveridge, trans. by Jules Bonnet (Grand Rapids: Baker Book House, 1983), vol. V, p. 379f.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/">The Crux of the Free Offer of the Gospel</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Final Thoughts on the Revelation Symposium</title>
		<link>/final-thoughts-revelation-symposium/</link>
					<comments>/final-thoughts-revelation-symposium/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2013 15:00:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amillennialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[end times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Futurism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Idealism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Postmillennialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Premillennialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preterism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Revelation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1396</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I thought I would conclude these blog posts with a few stray comments on the Revelation Symposium. First, I wanted to say more, but had no opportunity at the Symposium, about the danger of Partial Preterism. But let me first qualify what I want to say. I admit the difference between partial and full preterism. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/final-thoughts-revelation-symposium/">Final Thoughts on the Revelation Symposium</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I thought I would conclude these blog posts with a few stray comments on the Revelation Symposium.</p>
<p>First, I wanted to say more, but had no opportunity at the Symposium, about the danger of Partial Preterism. But let me first qualify what I want to say.</p>
<p>I admit the difference between partial and full preterism. It is important to acknowledge that partial preterism lies within the bounds of Christian orthodoxy, while full or hyper-preterism does not. It is important to make clear that Gary Demar and many others reject hyper-preterism as heresy. He said so at the Symposium. That is all good. I think he is right about hyper-preterism.</p>
<p>But now let me give my worry. To put my concern in a nutshell, it is this. The same hermeneutic which can ascribe everything in Matthew 24 to the Destruction of Jerusalem in 70 AD and can understand Revelation 1:7 (BEHOLD, HE IS COMING WITH THE CLOUDS, and every eye will see Him, even those who pierced Him; and all the tribes of the earth will mourn over Him. So it is to be. Amen.) of the same event must lead, it seems to me, to full preterism. Yes, I know that Gary and others do not want it to go there, but I think it does. They have probably have attempted it, but they need to explain why it does not. If these passages can apply to AD 70, why not 1 and 2 Thessalonians and every other reference to the <em>parousia</em> of Christ in the New Testament? Partial Preterism is responsible for the logic of its hermeneutic.</p>
<p>And along this line I have another worry. The assumption that the language of shortness and nearness necessarily implies an event within the generation of those living at the time of Christ&#8217;s first advent is the very logic that full preterism uses to teach its views. An examination of the uses of &#8220;near&#8221; and its relatives in the New Testament show that it is used of Christ&#8217;s Second Coming bodily and visibly in glory, I think. Look them up, and if you can take all of the events described as near as a reference to AD 70, you will be on well on your way to hyper-preterism!</p>
<p>I have responded to this assumption about nearness in the essay: &#8220;<a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/A-Reply-to-the-Hyper-Preterist-Argument-from-Imminence.pdf">A Reply to the Hyper-Preterist Argument from Imminence</a>.&#8221; &nbsp;Though the linked essay is addressed against full preterism, its reasoning applies to the partial preterist argument as wells.</p>
<p>Second, wanting to be an equal opportunity offender, let me say that one thing that Jim Hamilton said also worried me. Before I tell you my worry, I do want to say that I do deeply appreciate Jim and his labors. Having said that, however, and before I come to my deepest worry, I have to say that I think it is mislabeling to call Jim&#8217;s position, futurism. He thinks that the seven seals refer to events characteristic of the entire inter-adventual period. He thinks that the 1260 days of Revelation 11 refers to the church age and the two witnesses to the church. He is correct, I think. But this is not futurism. He should have made clear at the symposium that he was defending a highly modified form of futurism.</p>
<p>But here is my worry. Jim said in the&nbsp;roundtable&nbsp;q&amp;a that every ethnic Jew alive at Christ&#8217;s coming would be converted by seeing Christ&#8217;s return. My response at the time was, &#8220;Wow, really?!&#8221; I am really&nbsp;surprised&nbsp;that Jim believes this and hope that I misunderstood him, but I do not think I did. Again, I do not want to make Jim responsible for actually holding what I believe are the logical implications of his position. He is responsible, however, for the good and necessary consequences of what he believes.</p>
<p>What are they? First, being converted by seeing Christ return is not salvation by faith, it is salvation by sight. Sight and faith are two different things (2 Cor. 5:7). Second, the Bible teaches that people must repent before Christ&#8217;s return. Christ delays His return so that people can be repent before He comes (2 Pet. 3:9). No Jew and no Gentile will be saved unless they repent before Christ&#8217;s return. Third, if the privilege of being converted by Christ&#8217;s Second Coming only applies to the Jews, then you have the return in principle of the Dispensational tendency to teach different ways of salvation for their two peoples of God. Fourth, neither Romans 11, nor Revelation 1:7, requires this interpretation. Even if you think Romans 11 teaches a mass conversion of the Jews&#8211;and I doubt it&#8211;, you still do not have to say that they are converted by seeing Christ&#8217;s Second Coming. In fact, in context you have to say that they are justified by&nbsp;believing&nbsp;in Christ before He comes again. Neither Revelation 1:7, nor Zechariah 12:10-14, requires this kind absolute universalism of the conversion of every ethnic Jew. Nor should they be used to contradict the clear NT teaching that men must be saved by faith prior to the Second Coming of Christ.</p>
<p>But let me conclude by once more congratulating both Jim and Gary on their fine presentations and faithfulness to God&#8217;s Word as they understand it!</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/final-thoughts-revelation-symposium/">Final Thoughts on the Revelation Symposium</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/final-thoughts-revelation-symposium/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Meaning of Matthew 24, Part 2</title>
		<link>/meaning-of-matthew-24-2/</link>
					<comments>/meaning-of-matthew-24-2/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 15:00:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amillennialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[end times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Futurism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Idealism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Postmillennialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Premillennialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preterism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Revelation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1388</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In their presentations of preterism and futurism both Gary Demar and Jim Hamilton explained their views of Matthew 24. I used my 20 minute response time in the afternoon to address this. I argued that Gary was right about the meaning of generation in Matthew 24:34 and that Jim was right about the Second Coming [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/meaning-of-matthew-24-2/">The Meaning of Matthew 24, Part 2</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In their presentations of preterism and futurism both Gary Demar and Jim Hamilton explained their views of Matthew 24. I used my 20 minute response time in the afternoon to address this. I argued that Gary was right about the meaning of generation in Matthew 24:34 and that Jim was right about the Second Coming of Christ in glory at the consummation of the age being in view in Matthew 24:36 and that both were wrong to deny the others&#8217; view of these matters. Here in two parts from </em>More of the End Times Made Simple<em> is my understanding of Matthew 24.</em></p>
<p>Following the outline specified [previously], let us now examine the teaching of Matthew 24:1-36.</p>
<p><strong>Introduction:&nbsp; The Disciples&#8217; Questions (vv. 1-3)</strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Matthew 24:</strong><sup>1</sup> And Jesus came out from the temple and was going away when His disciples came up to point out the temple buildings to Him. <sup>2</sup> And He answered and said to them, &#8220;Do you not see all these things? Truly I say to you, not one stone here shall be left upon another, which will not be torn down.&#8221; <sup>3</sup> And as He was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples came to Him privately, saying, &#8220;Tell us, when will these things be, and what <em>will be </em>the sign of Your coming, and of the end of the age?&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>The Olivet Discourse is the answer to the disciples&#8217; questions found in v. 3.&nbsp; As Murray says, &#8220;&#8230;we should most probably regard the disciples as thinking of the destruction of&nbsp; the temple and the coming (<em>parousia</em>) as coincident&#8230;&#8221;&nbsp; In other words, it seems clear from their questions that the disciples assumed that destruction of the temple could mean nothing less than the end of the world.&nbsp; This confusion could not go uncorrected.&nbsp; As we shall see, it does not.</p>
<p><strong>I.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>The Outstanding Features characterizing This Period (vv. 4-14)</strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Matthew 24:</strong><sup>4</sup> And Jesus answered and said to them, &#8220;See to it that no one misleads you. <sup>5</sup> &#8220;For many will come in My name, saying, &#8216;I am the Christ,&#8217; and will mislead many. <sup>6</sup> And you will be hearing of wars and rumors of wars; see that you are not frightened, for <em>those things </em>must take place, but <em>that </em>is not yet the end. <sup>7</sup> For nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom, and in various places there will be famines and earthquakes. <sup>8</sup> But all these things are <em>merely </em>the beginning of birth pangs. <sup>9</sup> Then they will deliver you to tribulation, and will kill you, and you will be hated by all nations on account of My name. <sup>10</sup> And at that time many will fall away and will deliver up one another and hate one another. <sup>11</sup> And many false prophets will arise, and will mislead many. <sup>12</sup> And because lawlessness is increased, most people&#8217;s love will grow cold. <sup>13</sup> But the one who endures to the end, he shall be saved. <sup>14</sup> &#8220;And this gospel of the kingdom shall be preached in the whole world for a witness to all the nations, and then the end shall come.</p></blockquote>
<p>These verses give an overview of the entire interadventual period (the period between Christ&#8217;s first and second advents).&nbsp; The mention of the end in verses 6, 13, and 14 in comparison with verse 3 shows that Christ&#8217;s perspective in these verses reaches out to the very end of the age and His own Second Coming.&nbsp; It is clear from these verses, therefore, that the gospel age will be characterized by tribulation.&nbsp; War, famine, earthquake, tribulation, apostasy, persecution, false religions, increased lawlessness, and the waning of affection for Christ will be the age-long experience of the church of Christ.</p>
<p><strong>II.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>The Great Tribulation during This Period (vv. 15-28)</strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Matthew 24:</strong><sup>15</sup> Therefore when you see the ABOMINATION OF DESOLATION which was spoken of through Daniel the prophet, standing in the holy place (let the reader understand), <sup>16</sup> then let those who are in Judea flee to the mountains; <sup>17</sup> let him who is on the housetop not go down to get the things out that are in his house; <sup>18</sup> and let him who is in the field not turn back to get his cloak. <sup>19</sup> But woe to those who are with child and to those who nurse babes in those days! <sup>20</sup> &#8220;But pray that your flight may not be in the winter, or on a Sabbath; <sup>21</sup> for then there will be a great tribulation, such as has not occurred since the beginning of the world until now, nor ever shall. <sup>22</sup> And unless those days had been cut short, no life would have been saved; but for the sake of the elect those days shall be cut short. <sup>23</sup> Then if anyone says to you, &#8216;Behold, here is the Christ,&#8217; or &#8216;There <em>He is,&#8217; </em>do not believe <em>him. </em><sup>24</sup> For false Christs and false prophets will arise and will show great signs and wonders, so as to mislead, if possible, even the elect. <sup>25</sup> &#8220;Behold, I have told you in advance. <sup>26</sup> &#8220;If therefore they say to you, &#8216;Behold, He is in the wilderness,&#8217; do not go forth, <em>or,</em>&#8216; Behold, He is in the inner rooms, &#8216;do not believe <em>them. </em><sup>27</sup> For just as the lightning comes from the east, and flashes even to the west, so shall the coming of the Son of Man be. <sup>28</sup> &#8220;Wherever the corpse is, there the vultures will gather.</p></blockquote>
<p>Having given the big picture, verses 15-28 focus on the event of most concern to Jesus&#8217; Jewish disciples, the destruction of Jerusalem and the temple.&nbsp;Murray notes,&nbsp; &#8220;In verse 15 it is not as apparent as it is in Luke 21:20 that Jesus is dealing with the destruction of Jerusalem.&nbsp; In the latter the reference is explicit:&nbsp; &#8220;When ye see Jerusalem encompassed by armies, then know ye that its desolation is drawn nigh.&#8221;&nbsp; All the language of the passage clearly describes the events surrounding the destruction of Jerusalem and gives warnings about it pertinent to Jesus&#8217; first century Jewish disciples.</p>
<p>In particular the warning against believing that an imminent or secret appearance of the Messiah is to be associated with these events must be noticed.&nbsp; This makes clear that it is not a period just before the consummation of the age that is in view.</p>
<p>Some have found an objection to the interpretation here defended in the strong language of Matthew 21:21 and 22.&nbsp; Many have felt that such language could only describe the so-called great tribulation at the end of the age.</p>
<ul>
<li>This objection presses the language to ridiculous, literal lengths never intended by the Lord and ignores the possibility of the use of legitimate hyperbole by the Lord.&nbsp; (For examples of hyperbole see Matt. 5:29; 23:24; John 12:19; Luke 14:26; Mark 9:23).</li>
<li>It also is forced to ignore the plain reference of the rest of the passage to the events of AD 70.</li>
<li>Unless one adopts a strictly futurist view, one (say a proponent of the double fulfillment view) is forced to allow that some fulfillment of this horrifying prediction must have occurred in AD 70.</li>
<li>This interpretation also displays ignorance of the massive and horrifying massacre of the Jews at this time.&nbsp; A reading of Josephus account is recommended.<sup>1</sup></li>
<li>This objection also fails to appreciate the covenantal ramifications of this event for the Jews.&nbsp; In this event the wrath of God came upon them to the uttermost (1 Thessalonians 2:16).</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>III.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>The Second Coming ending This Period (vv. 29-33)</strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Matthew 24:</strong><sup>29</sup> But immediately after the tribulation of those days THE SUN WILL BE DARKENED, AND THE MOON WILL NOT GIVE ITS LIGHT, AND THE STARS WILL FALL from the sky, and the powers of the heavens will be shaken, <sup>30</sup> and then the sign of the Son of Man will appear in the sky, and then all the tribes of the earth will mourn, and they will see the SON OF MAN COMING ON THE CLOUDS OF THE SKY with power and great glory. <sup>31</sup> And He will send forth His angels with A GREAT TRUMPET and THEY WILL GATHER TOGETHER His elect from the four winds, from one end of the sky to the other. <sup>32</sup> &#8220;Now learn the parable from the fig tree: when its branch has already become tender, and puts forth its leaves, you know that summer is near; <sup>33</sup> even so you too, when you see all these things, recognize that He is near, <em>right </em>at the door.</p></blockquote>
<p>With this section of Matthew 24 one of the major difficulties with Professor Murray&#8217;s view is confronted.&nbsp;Murray recognizes this and says:</p>
<blockquote><p>When we come to verse 29, we encounter some difficulty.&nbsp; For &#8216;the tribulation of those days&#8217; might appear to refer to the &#8216;great tribulation of verse 21 which is associated particularly with the desolation of Jerusalem.&nbsp; How could it be said that, immediately after 70 A. D., the events specified in verses 29-31 took place?&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>To put the problem in other words, verse 29 seems to say that immediately following the destruction of Jerusalem the coming of Christ in glory occurs.&nbsp; How then can verses 15-28 refer to a destruction of Jerusalem that took place in 70 A. D. and verse 29 refer to the future coming of Christ in glory?</p>
<p>Very properly Murray once again finds the solution in the parallel passage in Luke 21.&nbsp; He shows that Luke inserts words of Jesus not recorded by Matthew that wonderfully help to clarify the meaning.&nbsp; Here are the words that Luke inserts between what is recorded in Matthew 24:28 and what is recorded in Matthew 24:29.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Luke 21:</strong><sup>24</sup> and they will fall by the edge of the sword, and will be led captive into all the nations; and Jerusalem will be trampled under foot by the Gentiles until the times of the Gentiles be fulfilled.</p></blockquote>
<p>These words make very clear that &#8220;<em>the tribulation of those days</em>&#8221; mentioned in Matthew 24:29 includes not only the Jews&#8217; falling by the edge of the sword, but also their being led into captivity, the times of the Gentiles, and thus, the entire interadventual period.&nbsp; The comments of Murray at this point are exceedingly helpful:</p>
<blockquote><p>Luke includes an observation in Jesus&#8217; discourse not included in Matthew&#8217;s account, and it belongs to what precedes Matthew 24:29, and must therefore be inserted.&nbsp; The observation given in Luke 21:24 is that &#8220;Jerusalem will be trodden down by the Gentiles until the times of the Gentiles are fulfilled.&#8221;&nbsp; So, in view of this element, it is apparent that our Lord&#8217;s delineation extended far beyond the destruction of Jerusalem and the events immediately associated with it.&nbsp; Hence the period&nbsp; &#8220;those days&#8221;, in Matthew 24:29, must be regarded as the days that extend to the threshold of what is specified in verses 29-31.&nbsp; But, apart from Luke 21:24, it would be reasonable, even on the basis of Matthew&#8217;s own account, to take the expression &#8220;the tribulation of those days&#8221; inclusively and not restrictively, &#8220;Those days&#8221; could properly be taken to mean the days preceding that of which Jesus now proceeds to speak, the days depicted already in verses 4-14, and &#8220;the tribulation&#8221; not exclusively the &#8220;great tribulation&#8221; of verse 21, but the tribulation which, according to the earlier part of the discourse, is represented as characterizing the interadventual period as a whole.<sup>2</sup></p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Conclusion:&nbsp; The Lord&#8217;s Distinction (vv. 34-36)</strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Matthew 24:</strong><sup>34</sup> Truly I say to you, this generation will not pass away until all these things take place. <sup>35</sup> Heaven and earth will pass away, but My words shall not pass away. <sup>36</sup> But of that day and hour no one knows, not even the angels of heaven, nor the Son, but the Father alone.</p></blockquote>
<p>Murray begins his treatment of these verses by a lengthy treatment of the meaning of <em>generation</em> in verse 34. &nbsp;He argues that it is &#8220;wholly untenable&#8221; to make this word mean race rather than generation.&nbsp; He uses three arguments.&nbsp; First, he argues that in the Septuagint (the Greek version of the Old Testament in use at the time of Christ) this Greek word translates a Hebrew word that means <em>generation</em> and not <em>race.</em>&nbsp; Second, he argues that if Jesus had intended to say <em>race</em>, another and clearer Greek word was available.&nbsp; Third, he argues that the meaning of the word <em>generation</em> in the New Testament is &#8220;clearly that of the living generation, or the generations in succession to one another&#8221;.</p>
<p>In particular Murray notes at this point the clearly parallel use of generation in the near context, Matthew 23:36.&nbsp; Notice this statement in its context.&nbsp; It seems beyond doubt that this parallel use is meant of the then living generation of Jews.</p>
<blockquote><p><sup>34</sup> &#8220;Therefore, behold, I am sending you prophets and wise men and scribes; some of them you will kill and crucify, and some of them you will scourge in your synagogues, and persecute from city to city,&nbsp; <sup>35</sup> so that upon you may fall <em>the guilt of </em>all the righteous blood shed on earth, from the blood of righteous Abel to the blood of Zechariah, the son of Berechiah, whom you murdered between the temple and the altar.&nbsp; <sup>36</sup> <strong><em>&#8220;Truly I say to you, all these things will come upon this generation.</em></strong>&nbsp; <sup>37</sup> &#8220;Jerusalem, Jerusalem, who kills the prophets and stones those who are sent to her! How often I wanted to gather your children together, the way a hen gathers her chicks under her wings, and you were unwilling.&nbsp; <sup>38</sup> &#8220;Behold, your house is being left to you desolate!</p></blockquote>
<p>With this understanding of the word, <em>generation</em>, required in verse 34, Murray then addresses the obvious question raised by the verse.</p>
<blockquote><p>How, then, are we to resolve the question posed by the events specified in the preceding context, especially in verses 29-31, which did not occur in the generation of which our Lord spoke?<sup>3</sup></p></blockquote>
<p>Murray&#8217;s reply to this question is to argue that there is a contrast intended in verses 34-36 between the destruction of Jerusalem and the coming of Christ in glory. Matthew 24:34-36 is often misunderstood because people do not appreciate the contrast that Jesus intends in these verses.&nbsp; Verse 34 must be contrasted with verse 36 or the entire meaning of the passage will be mistaken.</p>
<p>That there is a contrast intended in these verses is plain from three things high-lighted in these verses.&nbsp; First, the fact that verse 36 begins with the word, <em>but</em>, must not be overlooked.&nbsp; This conjunction in Greek commonly is used to introduce a contrasting thought.</p>
<p>Second, the contrast in the two different demonstrative pronouns used in verses 34 and 36 respectively must not be overlooked.&nbsp; <em>&#8220;These&#8221; </em>is the immediate demonstrative pronoun used to designate something relatively near at hand.&nbsp; It is appropriately used to describe the relatively near occurrence of all the things associated with the destruction of the Temple and Jerusalem.&nbsp; It is so used throughout the passage (Matt. 23:36; 24:3, 8, 33).&nbsp; <em>&#8220;That&#8221; </em>is the remote demonstrative pronoun used to designate something that is relatively distant.&nbsp; It is appropriately used to designate the day and hour of Christ&#8217;s coming in glory. <sup>4</sup></p>
<p>Third, the contrast in the matter of time signs also cannot be overlooked.&nbsp; &#8221;This generation&#8221; as Murray shows is clearly a reference to the then living generation of Jews.&nbsp; Thus, a general time sign is given for the destruction of the temple and Jerusalem.&nbsp; When Jesus says that &#8220;no one knows&#8221; including Himself of the day and hour of His return, there is a plain distinction introduced as to time signs between the destruction of Jerusalem and the Second Coming of Christ.&nbsp; No time sign of any kind is given for the Second Coming.&nbsp; (There are signs, but no time signs of the Second Coming.)</p>
<p><sup>1</sup>For a summary of Josephus&#8217; description and an extended response to the objection in question, cf. J. Marcellus Kik, <em>An Eschatology of </em>Victory (Presbyterian and Reformed,1971), 112-120.</p>
<div>
<p><sup>2</sup>John Murray, <em>Collected Writings of John Murray</em>, vol. 2, (Banner of Truth Trust, Edinburgh, 1977), pp. 387ff.</p>
</div>
<div>
<p><sup>3</sup>John Murray, <em>Collected Writings of John Murray</em>, vol. 2, (Banner of Truth Trust, Edinburgh, 1977), pp. 387ff.</p>
</div>
<div>
<p><sup>4</sup>H. E. Dana and Julius R. Mantey, <em>A Manual Grammar of the Greek New Testament,</em> (The Macmillan Company, New York, 1967) pp. 122f.</p>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/meaning-of-matthew-24-2/">The Meaning of Matthew 24, Part 2</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/meaning-of-matthew-24-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
