<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Was the early church user-friendly?	</title>
	<atom:link href="/was-the-early-church-user-friendly/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/was-the-early-church-user-friendly/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2011 02:27:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Jeff Ludwig		</title>
		<link>/was-the-early-church-user-friendly/#comment-261</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff Ludwig]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2011 02:27:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=846#comment-261</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&quot;The church then becomes the primary agent for common grace and not special grace.&quot; Quoted from above comment by Joe Messer.

What a profound insight from Mr. Messer! The Puritan &quot;city on a hill&quot; was special grace right out of Matthew 5:14. How else to account for the miraculous transformation of North America and the great godliness of 17th and 18th century America, despite some slippage prior to the first Great Awakening. The light of His glory shown throughout the land.

Can anyone doubt that Jesus Christ was lifted up in New England and beyond through the working of Almighty God as understood, in a Calvinist sense, by most of the established churches? Truly the land was blessed by the Lord in a temporal sense, in the sense of common grace because there is no question about the Puritan priorities. Christ, our Lord and Savior came first. His name was glorified and missionary outreach to the Indians was based on Biblical truth. The Puritan churches of New England were not &quot;need driven&quot; churches that asked the Indians &quot;what are your concerns&quot; and we&#039;ll pray to the Lord so he&#039;ll help you achieve your goals.&quot; No. They preached Jesus Christ, His life, His death, and His resurrection -- Christ as Lord and Savior. The Puritans were glory driven, not need driven.   Thanks Mr. Messer for inspiring me to this follow-up message.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;The church then becomes the primary agent for common grace and not special grace.&#8221; Quoted from above comment by Joe Messer.</p>
<p>What a profound insight from Mr. Messer! The Puritan &#8220;city on a hill&#8221; was special grace right out of Matthew 5:14. How else to account for the miraculous transformation of North America and the great godliness of 17th and 18th century America, despite some slippage prior to the first Great Awakening. The light of His glory shown throughout the land.</p>
<p>Can anyone doubt that Jesus Christ was lifted up in New England and beyond through the working of Almighty God as understood, in a Calvinist sense, by most of the established churches? Truly the land was blessed by the Lord in a temporal sense, in the sense of common grace because there is no question about the Puritan priorities. Christ, our Lord and Savior came first. His name was glorified and missionary outreach to the Indians was based on Biblical truth. The Puritan churches of New England were not &#8220;need driven&#8221; churches that asked the Indians &#8220;what are your concerns&#8221; and we&#8217;ll pray to the Lord so he&#8217;ll help you achieve your goals.&#8221; No. They preached Jesus Christ, His life, His death, and His resurrection &#8212; Christ as Lord and Savior. The Puritans were glory driven, not need driven.   Thanks Mr. Messer for inspiring me to this follow-up message.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Joe Messer		</title>
		<link>/was-the-early-church-user-friendly/#comment-260</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joe Messer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2011 13:17:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=846#comment-260</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Agreed. I would also add that being &quot;the light of the world&quot; and &quot;a city set on a hill that cannot be hidden&quot; also speaks of the distinctiveness of the church as separate from the world in any user friendly context. Therefore, the local church would remain separated from the natural city in which they were planted in order to provide the best possible disctinctiveness of light from darkness. Thus, the true light of the gospel to our local cities (and all the covenant blessings distinctive to believers), becomes more and more darkened (in my opinion) when the gospel unto eternal salvation becomes the call for the church to engage the culture in order bring about temporal social justices regardless of repentance and faith. The church then becomes the primary agent for common grace and not special grace. Christ did not permit this in John 6.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Agreed. I would also add that being &#8220;the light of the world&#8221; and &#8220;a city set on a hill that cannot be hidden&#8221; also speaks of the distinctiveness of the church as separate from the world in any user friendly context. Therefore, the local church would remain separated from the natural city in which they were planted in order to provide the best possible disctinctiveness of light from darkness. Thus, the true light of the gospel to our local cities (and all the covenant blessings distinctive to believers), becomes more and more darkened (in my opinion) when the gospel unto eternal salvation becomes the call for the church to engage the culture in order bring about temporal social justices regardless of repentance and faith. The church then becomes the primary agent for common grace and not special grace. Christ did not permit this in John 6.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jeff Ludwig		</title>
		<link>/was-the-early-church-user-friendly/#comment-259</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jeff Ludwig]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2011 20:29:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=846#comment-259</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tremendous insight.  In NYC so many churches are carrying the Rick Warren banner of &quot;seeker sensitive&quot; in different forms. Redeemer Presbyterian (PCA) empasizes engaging the city.  Calvary Baptist Church, also a large church in Manhattan is emphasizing engaging the city. Another orthodox evangelical free church here in Brooklyn is also using the language of &quot;engagement&quot; and &quot;relevance&quot;.  Another church saying it is reformed baptist has pentecostal-style worship and a &quot;relevance&quot; outreach. This last church says on its website that it using many of Rick Warren&#039;s ideas, but have had to change some points of his theology here and there (remember, at the same time they are claiming to be Calvinist!).  
 
These churches all have a lot of good preaching and are supporting missionaries and many other fine ministries, but I have been asking myself why I am bothered by all this emphasis on engagement and relevance.  Of course Christ is relevant and it is an understatement to say He is &quot;engaged&quot; with human suffering. This comment definitely points to how the p.r. emphasis of these NYC churches misses the essence of what it is to &quot;do church.&quot;  I certainly do not worship in church to become more relevant or engaged.  I go to glorify the redeemer of my soul and the creator of the universe. &quot;In him all things are made....&quot; I go rejoicing for having been adopted into the family of God.  I go with thanksgiving that an eternity with Jesus Christ in heaven awaits me when I leave this mortal coil and that I will be reunited with my loved ones in Christ forever and ever. This is the line of my heart&#039;s thinking. 
Jeff]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tremendous insight.  In NYC so many churches are carrying the Rick Warren banner of &#8220;seeker sensitive&#8221; in different forms. Redeemer Presbyterian (PCA) empasizes engaging the city.  Calvary Baptist Church, also a large church in Manhattan is emphasizing engaging the city. Another orthodox evangelical free church here in Brooklyn is also using the language of &#8220;engagement&#8221; and &#8220;relevance&#8221;.  Another church saying it is reformed baptist has pentecostal-style worship and a &#8220;relevance&#8221; outreach. This last church says on its website that it using many of Rick Warren&#8217;s ideas, but have had to change some points of his theology here and there (remember, at the same time they are claiming to be Calvinist!).  </p>
<p>These churches all have a lot of good preaching and are supporting missionaries and many other fine ministries, but I have been asking myself why I am bothered by all this emphasis on engagement and relevance.  Of course Christ is relevant and it is an understatement to say He is &#8220;engaged&#8221; with human suffering. This comment definitely points to how the p.r. emphasis of these NYC churches misses the essence of what it is to &#8220;do church.&#8221;  I certainly do not worship in church to become more relevant or engaged.  I go to glorify the redeemer of my soul and the creator of the universe. &#8220;In him all things are made&#8230;.&#8221; I go rejoicing for having been adopted into the family of God.  I go with thanksgiving that an eternity with Jesus Christ in heaven awaits me when I leave this mortal coil and that I will be reunited with my loved ones in Christ forever and ever. This is the line of my heart&#8217;s thinking.<br />
Jeff</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Pastor John Peter Bodner		</title>
		<link>/was-the-early-church-user-friendly/#comment-258</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pastor John Peter Bodner]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2011 19:40:12 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=846#comment-258</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[AMEN and AMEN.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>AMEN and AMEN.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
