<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 1)	</title>
	<atom:link href="/should-we-witness/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/should-we-witness/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2013 14:38:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Should we &#8216;Witness&#8217; for Christ? Sam Waldron says that in a sense we can&#8217;t &#124; The Confessing Baptist		</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness/#comment-373</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Should we &#8216;Witness&#8217; for Christ? Sam Waldron says that in a sense we can&#8217;t &#124; The Confessing Baptist]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2013 14:38:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1303#comment-373</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[...] Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 1) [...]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 1) [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Robert Gonzales		</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness/#comment-372</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Robert Gonzales]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 21:56:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1303#comment-372</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dr Waldron,

Thanks for your helpful clarifying remarks. I agree that many evangelicals fail to appreciate some of the more technical uses of terms like &quot;witness&quot; in the NT. Good point. 

I&#039;m sorry for the confusing paragraph. What I meant to ask was &quot;Would you limit the church&#039;s WITNESS to its &quot;gathered&quot; meetings?&quot; You don&#039;t as you go on to explain. But I can understand why the wording of my question left you baffled. Sorry about that. :-)

B.G.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dr Waldron,</p>
<p>Thanks for your helpful clarifying remarks. I agree that many evangelicals fail to appreciate some of the more technical uses of terms like &#8220;witness&#8221; in the NT. Good point. </p>
<p>I&#8217;m sorry for the confusing paragraph. What I meant to ask was &#8220;Would you limit the church&#8217;s WITNESS to its &#8220;gathered&#8221; meetings?&#8221; You don&#8217;t as you go on to explain. But I can understand why the wording of my question left you baffled. Sorry about that. 🙂</p>
<p>B.G.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Sam Waldron		</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness/#comment-371</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 18:22:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1303#comment-371</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dr. Gonzales,

I also would not want to encourage any position that discourages lay evangelism.  

But I really think most evangelicals when they read the NT don&#039;t realize that witnessing is many times a reference to something only apostles can do.  I think this kind of loose reading of the New Testament was an exegetical set up for the charismatic movement.  

I also grant that we can relate our own experience of the gospel and this would qualify as a kind of witness, but this witness and the apostolic witness are two very different things.

You say, &quot;Also, would you limit the church’s corporate worship to its “gathered” meetings? Doesn’t the church also bear witness to the gospel when it “scatters”? If so, doesn’t the church’s “scattered” evangelism include private or individual Christians proclaiming and bearing witness to the veracity of the gospel?&quot;

I am really confused by this paragraph.  Where did I raise in my post the issue of the church&#039;s corporate worship?  But to answer your question, I do believe that corporate worship only takes place in the church&#039;s gathered meetings. How could &quot;corporate&quot; worship take place any place else?  

Of course, the church does evangelism when it is scattered by confessing Christ before the world.  It ought to so do evangelism.  I do not think, however, that the New Testament word for this is witness.  It is confession.

But if you have any concern about my commitment to lay evangelism, just read the blogs which follow in this series.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Gonzales,</p>
<p>I also would not want to encourage any position that discourages lay evangelism.  </p>
<p>But I really think most evangelicals when they read the NT don&#8217;t realize that witnessing is many times a reference to something only apostles can do.  I think this kind of loose reading of the New Testament was an exegetical set up for the charismatic movement.  </p>
<p>I also grant that we can relate our own experience of the gospel and this would qualify as a kind of witness, but this witness and the apostolic witness are two very different things.</p>
<p>You say, &#8220;Also, would you limit the church’s corporate worship to its “gathered” meetings? Doesn’t the church also bear witness to the gospel when it “scatters”? If so, doesn’t the church’s “scattered” evangelism include private or individual Christians proclaiming and bearing witness to the veracity of the gospel?&#8221;</p>
<p>I am really confused by this paragraph.  Where did I raise in my post the issue of the church&#8217;s corporate worship?  But to answer your question, I do believe that corporate worship only takes place in the church&#8217;s gathered meetings. How could &#8220;corporate&#8221; worship take place any place else?  </p>
<p>Of course, the church does evangelism when it is scattered by confessing Christ before the world.  It ought to so do evangelism.  I do not think, however, that the New Testament word for this is witness.  It is confession.</p>
<p>But if you have any concern about my commitment to lay evangelism, just read the blogs which follow in this series.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Sam Waldron		</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness/#comment-370</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 18:06:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1303#comment-370</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Jess,

Thanks for your question.  It is certainly true that we must confess Jesus Christ as one&#039;s Savior and Lord.  Such a confession is necessary for and essential to baptism and church membership. I think confession is the biblical category and not witness.  Such a confession may involve and sometimes must involve in my view not only what we believe or confess about Jesus Christ, but also how this has impacted us experientially and transformed our lives.  I believe some account of our experience and transformation by the gospel ought to be involved in joining a church.  It seems to me that something like this personal account of Paul&#039;s experience and transformation happened in the case of Barnabas bringing Paul to the Apostles in Acts 9. Confession does involve a personalizing of the gospel and this inevitably involves when given in detail feelings and experiences.  This does not mean, however, that our feelings and experiences are &quot;witness&quot; in the New Testament sense of the word where it refers to the apostolic eyewitness or to the gospel testimony itself.  My experience of the gospel is not the gospel.  The gospel is the gospel.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jess,</p>
<p>Thanks for your question.  It is certainly true that we must confess Jesus Christ as one&#8217;s Savior and Lord.  Such a confession is necessary for and essential to baptism and church membership. I think confession is the biblical category and not witness.  Such a confession may involve and sometimes must involve in my view not only what we believe or confess about Jesus Christ, but also how this has impacted us experientially and transformed our lives.  I believe some account of our experience and transformation by the gospel ought to be involved in joining a church.  It seems to me that something like this personal account of Paul&#8217;s experience and transformation happened in the case of Barnabas bringing Paul to the Apostles in Acts 9. Confession does involve a personalizing of the gospel and this inevitably involves when given in detail feelings and experiences.  This does not mean, however, that our feelings and experiences are &#8220;witness&#8221; in the New Testament sense of the word where it refers to the apostolic eyewitness or to the gospel testimony itself.  My experience of the gospel is not the gospel.  The gospel is the gospel.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Robert Gonzales Jr		</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness/#comment-369</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Robert Gonzales Jr]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 14:58:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1303#comment-369</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dr Waldron,

I agree that the NT uses the noun μαρτυς and verb μαρτυρεω primarily in a more technical sense of being a &quot;legal witness.&quot; Most of the time, that implies being an &quot;eyewitness.&quot; But not always. 

More generally, a &quot;witness&quot; can be &quot;a person who testifies, esp in a court of law, to events or facts within his own knowledge.&quot; And as we know, true human knowledge is not limited to one having personally &quot;seen&quot; or &quot;heard&quot; an event. Witnesses are often called to the stand provide circumstantial evidence of an event or to bear testimony of what someone else said they saw or heard. 

Similarly, I think we today can bear witness in the sense of testifying to others of what Jesus has said through the apostles and prophets. Moreover, we can testify on behalf of Christianity and the gospel by providing circumstantial evidence of his veracity. Indeed, weren&#039;t there believers in the NT who were put to death for bearing testimony to the gospel--whether or not they were eyewitnesses? If the NT can expand the category of &quot;martyr&quot; (i.e., witness) to individuals who die giving testimony to the veracity and claims of the gospel (Acts 22:20; Rev 17:6), can&#039;t we also today use  the term in the broader sense?

Also, would you limit the church&#039;s corporate worship to its &quot;gathered&quot; meetings? Doesn&#039;t the church also bear witness to the gospel when it &quot;scatters&quot;? If so, doesn&#039;t the church&#039;s &quot;scattered&quot; evangelism include private or individual Christians proclaiming and bearing witness to the veracity of the gospel?

I realize that this may be somewhat of a semantic issue and a question of what terminology is preferable. But I wouldn&#039;t want to encourage any position that discourages legitimate lay-evangelism.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dr Waldron,</p>
<p>I agree that the NT uses the noun μαρτυς and verb μαρτυρεω primarily in a more technical sense of being a &#8220;legal witness.&#8221; Most of the time, that implies being an &#8220;eyewitness.&#8221; But not always. </p>
<p>More generally, a &#8220;witness&#8221; can be &#8220;a person who testifies, esp in a court of law, to events or facts within his own knowledge.&#8221; And as we know, true human knowledge is not limited to one having personally &#8220;seen&#8221; or &#8220;heard&#8221; an event. Witnesses are often called to the stand provide circumstantial evidence of an event or to bear testimony of what someone else said they saw or heard. </p>
<p>Similarly, I think we today can bear witness in the sense of testifying to others of what Jesus has said through the apostles and prophets. Moreover, we can testify on behalf of Christianity and the gospel by providing circumstantial evidence of his veracity. Indeed, weren&#8217;t there believers in the NT who were put to death for bearing testimony to the gospel&#8211;whether or not they were eyewitnesses? If the NT can expand the category of &#8220;martyr&#8221; (i.e., witness) to individuals who die giving testimony to the veracity and claims of the gospel (Acts 22:20; Rev 17:6), can&#8217;t we also today use  the term in the broader sense?</p>
<p>Also, would you limit the church&#8217;s corporate worship to its &#8220;gathered&#8221; meetings? Doesn&#8217;t the church also bear witness to the gospel when it &#8220;scatters&#8221;? If so, doesn&#8217;t the church&#8217;s &#8220;scattered&#8221; evangelism include private or individual Christians proclaiming and bearing witness to the veracity of the gospel?</p>
<p>I realize that this may be somewhat of a semantic issue and a question of what terminology is preferable. But I wouldn&#8217;t want to encourage any position that discourages legitimate lay-evangelism.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Jess Keller		</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness/#comment-368</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jess Keller]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 14:23:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1303#comment-368</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Can you speak to how this might relate to how we bear witness to other believers, as well--in particular, as a personal testimony may be required in order to become an accepted member of a church?  Should we rather be in association with a church on the basis that we confess Him Lord and Savior and not on the thread of personal experiences and feelings?]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Can you speak to how this might relate to how we bear witness to other believers, as well&#8211;in particular, as a personal testimony may be required in order to become an accepted member of a church?  Should we rather be in association with a church on the basis that we confess Him Lord and Savior and not on the thread of personal experiences and feelings?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
