<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Course offerings | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/course-offerings/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 18:53:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Course offerings | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The Crux of the Free Offer of the Gospel</title>
		<link>/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/</link>
					<comments>/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 18:53:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Course offerings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Offer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Offer of the Gospel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hyper-Calvinism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[well-meant offer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7876</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The following is Dr. Sam Waldron&#8217;s introduction to his lectures for our upcoming module: Hyper-Calvinism &#38; the Free Offer of the Gospel In the historic documents which brought to its climax the confessional development sparked by the Reformation&#8212;the Westminster Confession (1644-46), the Savoy Declaration (1658), and the 1689 Baptist Confession&#8212;the free offer of the gospel [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/">The Crux of the Free Offer of the Gospel</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The following is Dr. Sam Waldron&#8217;s introduction to his lectures for our upcoming module:
</p>
<h2><a href="/hyper-calvinism/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>Hyper-Calvinism &amp; the Free Offer of the Gospel</strong></a></h2>
<p>In the historic documents which brought to its climax the confessional development sparked by the Reformation&#8212;the Westminster Confession (1644-46), the Savoy Declaration (1658), and the 1689 Baptist Confession&#8212;the free offer of the gospel is confessed in each in chapter 7 and in identical language.&nbsp; The Westminster Confession and its daughter and grand-daughter confessions each speak of &#8220;the covenant of grace, wherein he freely offereth unto sinners, life and salvation by Jesus Christ.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></p>
<p>It is both the conviction and assumption of these lectures that the crux of the doctrine of the free offer of the gospel is <em>God&#8217;s Indiscriminate Desire for the Salvation of Sinners</em>.&nbsp; To put this in other words, at the core of the free offer of the gospel is what is called the &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer of the gospel.&nbsp; Though it may be well to speak of the &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer of the gospel for the sake of doctrinal clarity, I am jealous to affirm here that this is both the natural and necessary implication of the &#8220;free&#8221; offer confessed by the climactic Reformation confessions.</p>
<p>My conviction is that the &#8220;free&#8221; offer in the confessional documents is and must be understood as a &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer.&nbsp; Though this affirmation may be defended at length (and will be by Dr. Daniel in his historical treatment in this course, it may be proper here for me to briefly mention the grounds upon which my conviction is based.&nbsp; I maintain that the &#8220;free&#8221; offer in the confessional documents is and must be understood as a &#8220;well-meant&#8221; offer for a number of reasons.</p>
<ul>
<li>It is, I think, the logical and necessary implication of speaking of a free offer. In fact, it seems to me that this is the implication of both the word, offer, and the word, free.&nbsp; &#8220;Offer&#8221; contains in it the notion of a proposal presented to someone which the one presenting it desires for him to accept.&nbsp; An offer not presented with such intent or desire would be regarded as insincere.&nbsp; What man proposes marriage to a woman without a desire that she should accept his proposal?&nbsp; What woman would regard such a proposal as authentic or genuine if it was not accompanied by the desire of the man for it to be accepted.&nbsp; The word, free, however, emphasizes the notion of a desire that one should take the offer presented.&nbsp; An offer is presented with the desire that it should be taken by the one to whom it is presented.&nbsp; A &#8220;free&#8221; offer accentuates such desire and the &#8220;well-meant&#8221; character of the offer by providing an extra incentive for the proposal to be accepted.</li>
<li>That this is the meaning and implication of a &#8220;free offer&#8221; was generally recognized by the modern opponents of the free offer in the controversy over common grace in the Christian Reformed denomination in the controversy that came to its denominational culmination in 1924. The Protestant Reformed Churches denied the free offer because they properly understood that a free offer was a well-meant offer&#8212;an offer that contained common grace.&nbsp; So much is this the case that Herman Hanko referencing the first point of common grace adopted by the Christian Reformed Church at the synod of 1924 and writing in the official journal of the Protestant Reformed Churches can write:</li>
</ul>
<p>In the discussions which followed the adoption of this statement of doctrine, the reference to the free offer was often called, &#8220;het puntje van het eerste punt.&#8221;&nbsp; (The main point of the first point.)&nbsp; While it is our intention to deal more specifically with this question at a later date, the point we wish to make now is that a denial of the free offer of the gospel is a part of the doctrinal confession of the Protestant Reformed Churches from their very beginning.&nbsp; This denial of the free offer of the gospel by the Protestant Reformed Churches has set them apart from almost every ecclesiastical fellowship.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></p>
<ul>
<li>That by the confessional free offer was intended a well-meant offer is the necessary conclusion to be reached from the historical backdrop of the climactic Reformed confessions. The high points of this backdrop (Calvin and the Canons of Dort) teach a free and well-meant offer.&nbsp; This is not the place for a detailed presentation of the evidence for this. Dr. Daniel will be providing such a presentation.&nbsp; It may be good, however, to illustrate the truth of this assertion.&nbsp; Perhaps the classic affirmation of the Free Offer by Calvin comes in a letter to Melancthon.&nbsp; There he says:</li>
</ul>
<p>And it cannot be attributed to hallucination, that you, a man acute and wise, and deeply versed in Scripture, confound the election of God with His promises, which are universal.&nbsp; For nothing is more certain than that the gospel is addressed to all promiscuously, but that the Spirit of faith is bestowed on the elect alone, by peculiar privilege.&nbsp; The promises are universal.&nbsp; How does it happen, therefore, that their efficacy is not equally felt by all?&nbsp; For this reason, because God does not reveal His arm to all.&nbsp; Indeed, among men but moderately skilled in Scripture, this subject needs not to be discussed, seeing that the promises of the Gospel make offer of the grace of Christ equally to all; and God, by the external call, invites all who are willing to accept of salvation.<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></p>
<ul>
<li>The classic assertion of the free and well-meant offer of the gospel by the Canons of Dort comes in The Second Head of Doctrine, Article 5 and The Third and Fourth Heads of Doctrine, Articles 6-8. The second reference bears comment.&nbsp; In Articles 6 and 7 gospel preaching and calls given to many who are not elect are described as &#8220;grace&#8221; and &#8220;so great and so gracious a blessing.&#8221;&nbsp; Article 8 then asserts, &#8220;As many as are called by the gospel, are unfeignedly called.&nbsp; For God hath most earnestly and truly declared in His Word, what will be acceptable to him; namely, that all who are called, should comply with the invitation.&#8221; &nbsp;If this language does not assert a free and well-meant offer, one wonders how such an idea could be stated without using the exact or precise words.</li>
</ul>
<p>To all this needs to be added a comment about the more recent history of Reformed truth.&nbsp; The resurgence of Reformed theology beginning in the 50&#8217;s and 60&#8217;s of the 20<sup>th</sup> Century can be traced in large part to Banner of Truth Trust; a Westminster Theological Seminary dominated by Cornelius Van Til and John Murray; and the revival of interest in the writing of Charles H. Spurgeon.&nbsp; In so far as this is true it is right to say that this resurgence of Calvinism was committed to the free and well-meant offer of the gospel.</p>
<p>In spite of all this and with the blossoming of wider interest in Reformed theology, there has come a denial of the well-meant offer of the gospel in recent years.&nbsp; It is this resurgence of a denial of the free and well-meant offer which has given birth in my mind to the necessity of this course and these lectures.</p>
<p>My lectures are not intended strictly speaking as a supplement to those of Dr. Daniel.&nbsp; It seemed better for us both to follow our own track in opening up this subject.&nbsp; I think we are of single mind on the subject, but perhaps such duplication as there may be between us will serve the student.&nbsp; Perhaps as well, whatever differences of emphasis there may be will also be of value to the student.</p>
<h2><strong>Outline of Dr. Waldron&#8217;s Lectures</strong></h2>
<p>Part 1:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Scriptural Exposition (from John 5:34)</p>
<p>Part 2:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Biblical Confirmation</p>
<p>Part 3:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Confessional Position</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Explicit Assertion</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Implicit Affirmation</p>
<p>Part 4:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Doctrinal Implications</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Love of God</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Will of God</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 3:&nbsp; The Mystery of God</p>
<p>Part 5:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Major Objections</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Objection from the Doctrine of Election</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Objection from the Doctrine of Simplicity</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 3:&nbsp; The Objection from the Fact of Anthropopathisms</p>
<p>Part 6:&nbsp; The Well-Meant Offer&#8212;Its Practical Applications</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 1:&nbsp; The Warning against Rationalism</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 2:&nbsp; The Warrant of Faith</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Section 3:&nbsp; The Way of Preaching</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">It&#8217;s not too late to register! &nbsp;<a href="/hyper-calvinism/"><strong>Register Here</strong></a></span></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a>This language is found in chapter 7, paragraph 2, in the 1689, but in chapter 7 paragraph 3 in the Savoy and Westminster.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a>Herman Hanko, <em>The History of the Free Offer</em>, accessed on the Internet July 21, 2017 <a href="http://www.prca.org/pamphlets/Free%20Offer/Introduction.htm">http://www.prca.org/pamphlets/Free%20Offer/Introduction.htm</a>.&nbsp; Further confirmation of the Protestant Reformed denial of the free offer of the gospel may be seen in David Engelsma, <em>Hyper-Calvinism and the Call of the Gospel: An Examination of the Well-Meant of the Gospel</em> (The Reformed Free Publishing Company: Jenison, MI, 2014).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a>Calvin, John, <em>Selected Works of John Calvin</em>, ed. by Henry Beveridge, trans. by Jules Bonnet (Grand Rapids: Baker Book House, 1983), vol. V, p. 379f.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/">The Crux of the Free Offer of the Gospel</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-crux-of-the-free-offer-of-the-gospel/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Update from Dr. Sam Waldron</title>
		<link>/update-from-sam-waldron/</link>
					<comments>/update-from-sam-waldron/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2013 17:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Course offerings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1431</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Below is an e-mail update sent out from Dr. Sam Waldron. If you would like to be added to the Midwest Center for Theological Studies e-mail list, please sign up here! Friends of MCTS, In April I wrote an email to report to you our friends to keep you abreast of several, encouraging changes in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/update-from-sam-waldron/">Update from Dr. Sam Waldron</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Below is an e-mail update sent out from Dr. Sam Waldron. If you would like to be added to the Midwest Center for Theological Studies e-mail list, <a title="MCTS E-Mail Sign Up" href="http://eepurl.com/DqxTr" target="_blank" rel="noopener">please sign up here</a>!</em></p>
<p>Friends of MCTS,</p>
<p>In April I wrote an email to report to you our friends to keep you abreast of several, encouraging changes in the ministry of MCTS.</p>
<p>First, while MCTS is governed by a board of directors, it is hosted by a local church.&nbsp; MCTS is now hosted by Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro where I was set apart as a pastor in June and joined Pastors Joe Wilson and Ron Miller in the eldership of that church.&nbsp; We are very thankful for the very positive and supportive atmosphere at Grace toward the ministry of MCTS.</p>
<p>Second, I want to report on what I believe to be a very successful MCTS Board Meeting.&nbsp; My hope was that we could encourage our board by honoring in specific ways their authority over MCTS to take a much more active role in the leadership of MCTS.&nbsp; I am very encouraged that this was accomplished.&nbsp; I want to thank the board members for their diligent work and the help I am sure they will be to us in the future.&nbsp; The chartering and formation of several active committees promise to lead us forward in very helpful ways.</p>
<p>Third, the coming school year is almost upon us.&nbsp; We have six live classes scheduled to be taught including the last two in our Basic Training curriculum.&nbsp; I begin the year with the second of my three courses taking the student through the historical theology.&nbsp; It deals with what I call the Augustinian Church and covers what are often thought of as the Medieval and Reformation periods of church history.&nbsp;&nbsp; Michael Emadi will then be teaching the two semesters of Elementary Hebrew for us later in the fall and then beginning the second semester in January.&nbsp; Richard Barcellos will be teaching an overview of Biblical Theology in a modular course in January and Tom Ascol will be leading our modular course on Preaching in June.&nbsp; I will be teaching Modern Church History in the spring. If you would like to livestream any of these classes online or take them for credit as a student, please let our registrar know:&nbsp;<a href="mailto:registrar@mctsowensboro.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">registrar@mctsowensboro.org</a></p>
<p>Fourth, American Vision has just released an over hour long video of the Revelation Symposium moderated&nbsp; by Brian Borgman in February in which I participated along with Jim Hamilton and Gary Demar.&nbsp; A two minute promotional video is available here:&nbsp;<a href="http://mctsowensboro.us7.list-manage.com/track/click?u=11118de60955d83b1e4e6bea8&amp;id=01d6a46c10&amp;e=b2a6109dc6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/<wbr>2013/08/waldron-on-revelation/</wbr></a></p>
<p>Fifth, we exist to serve Christ&#8217;s churches by training men for the ministry.&nbsp; If you would like to help us in that work, feel free to&nbsp;contact&nbsp;our registrar. Again, his e-mail address is:&nbsp;<a href="mailto:registrar@mctsowensboro.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">registrar@mctsowensboro.<wbr>org</wbr></a></p>
<p>The Lord Reigns,<br />
Dr. Sam Waldron</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/update-from-sam-waldron/">Update from Dr. Sam Waldron</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/update-from-sam-waldron/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>James White Gives a Message for Muslims</title>
		<link>/james-white-gives-message-for-muslims/</link>
					<comments>/james-white-gives-message-for-muslims/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2010 16:11:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Course offerings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gospel Muslims]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[James White]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=490</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Recently on the Aramaic Broadcasting Network, James White gave a message for Muslims on a live episode of Answering Islam.&#160; Please take six minutes and watch what he has to say.&#160; What a powerful gospel presentation! And please don&#8217;t forget that Dr. White will be teaching on Islam (along with Roman Catholicism, Mormonism, and the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/james-white-gives-message-for-muslims/">James White Gives a Message for Muslims</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Recently on the <a title="Aramaic Broadcasting Network" href="http://www.abnsat.com/" target="_self" rel="noopener">Aramaic Broadcasting Network</a>, James White gave a message for Muslims on a live episode of Answering Islam.&nbsp; Please take six minutes and watch what he has to say.&nbsp; What a powerful gospel presentation!</p>
<p>And please don&#8217;t forget that <a title="White Polemics Course" href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/event/2011-01-03-polemics-j-term-with-james-white/" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dr. White will be teaching on Islam (along with Roman Catholicism, Mormonism, and the new atheism) next month here at MCTS</a>.&nbsp; We&#8217;d love for you to join us in person or through the internet for this important course!</p>
<p><object classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" width="480" height="385" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"><param name="src" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/UUOIhX3VOvU?fs=1&amp;hl=en_US"><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true"></object></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/james-white-gives-message-for-muslims/">James White Gives a Message for Muslims</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/james-white-gives-message-for-muslims/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MCTS Continued Education for Pastors</title>
		<link>/mcts-continued-education-for-pastors/</link>
					<comments>/mcts-continued-education-for-pastors/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2010 21:37:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Course offerings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[continued education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=475</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>For the past two semesters MCTS has invited pastors to join us via the internet for continued education. Several from various parts of the U.S. and elsewhere (Canada, Philippines) have done so. MCTS offers two week-night courses every semester (Tuesday and Thursday from 6-9pm CT, approx.). For $50, pastors are given access to the live [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-continued-education-for-pastors/">MCTS Continued Education for Pastors</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For the past two semesters MCTS has invited pastors to join us via the internet for continued education. Several from various parts of the U.S. and elsewhere (Canada, Philippines) have done so. MCTS offers two week-night courses every semester (Tuesday and Thursday from 6-9pm CT, approx.). For $50, pastors are given access to the live lectures, links to the same recorded lectures (which can be accessed anytime), and all class handouts – syllabus, lecture notes, etc. Continued education students are also welcome to interact via ADOBE Connect on their computer screen.</p>
<p>Here are some testimonies of men who have utilized this form of continued education.</p>
<p><em>A pastor’s interpretive tools must remain sharp so that he may rightly divide the word of truth. I’m thankful for the honing I’ve received recently from the Hermeneutics course offered by MCTS.</em></p>
<p><em> Steve Nutter, Pastor</em><br />
Providence Reformed Baptist Church<br />
Minneapolis, MN</p>
<p><em>Having sat in on Intermediate Greek at MCTS, I would give MCTS Continuing Ed a strong endorsement. I sought to refresh and enhance my Greek competency beyond the usual seminary basics. Though self study is always ongoing, the CE framework provided the structure and motivation to move forward quickly and with appropriate guidance. An excellent, solidly delivered curriculum and an inclusive online delivery format provided a result that could not have been otherwise attained. This has had a positive impact in my teaching and lay preaching, as well as my personal study. I am most thankful.</em></p>
<p>Ken B. Wilson<br />
Professor, Computer Studies<br />
School of Advanced Technology<br />
Algonquin College</p>
<p>Next semester Dr. Waldron will be teaching a three-hour course on the Doctrine of Man and Ethics. This course covers the origin, identity, constitution, and free agency of man; man’s original relationship with God and integrity before God; the creation ordinances; the Fall; actual, original, and imputed sin; the consequences of sin; common grace, and ethics in light of man’s creation.</p>
<p>Dr. Barcellos will be teaching a two-hour course on NT Greek Exegesis. This course applies the exegetical methodology learned in a previous course (i.e., diagrammatical analysis and syntactical outlining) to various passages in Paul’s epistles.</p>
<p>If you are interested in taking one or both of the courses or would like to know more about Continuing Education at MCTS, please email Dr. Barcellos at rb@rbap.net. Courses for the spring 2011 semester begin in mid-January.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-continued-education-for-pastors/">MCTS Continued Education for Pastors</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mcts-continued-education-for-pastors/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dr. James White coming to MCTS</title>
		<link>/dr-james-white-coming-to-mcts/</link>
					<comments>/dr-james-white-coming-to-mcts/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2010 21:33:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Course offerings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/?p=327</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dr. James White will be lecturing at MCTS on New Atheism, Islam, Roman Catholicism, and Mormonism, if he can get all of that in during a one-week course, from January 3-8. Drs. White, Waldron, and Barcellos will also be conducting a round-table discussion concerning important theological issues of our day. Students who attend the course will [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/dr-james-white-coming-to-mcts/">Dr. James White coming to MCTS</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/event/2011-01-03-polemics-j-term-with-james-white/">Dr. James White will be lecturing at MCTS on New Atheism, Islam, Roman Catholicism, and Mormonism</a>, if he can get all of that in during a one-week course, from January 3-8. Drs. White, Waldron, and Barcellos will also be conducting a round-table discussion concerning important theological issues of our day. Students who attend the course will be able to have dinner with Dr. White Monday-Friday. For more info., go <a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/event/2011-01-03-polemics-j-term-with-james-white/">here</a>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/dr-james-white-coming-to-mcts/">Dr. James White coming to MCTS</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/dr-james-white-coming-to-mcts/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dr. James White at MCTS: Registration now open!</title>
		<link>/dr-james-white-at-mcts-registration-now-open/</link>
					<comments>/dr-james-white-at-mcts-registration-now-open/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2010 15:01:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Course offerings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/?p=265</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>From January 3-8, 2011, Dr. James White will be lecturing at MCTS on various subjects &#8211; New Atheism, Islam, Roman Catholicism, and Mormonism. We have room for 25-30 visiting students. We will house you and feed you one meal (dinner) per day. Dr. White will lecture from 5-10pm. During the day, there will be opportunity [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/dr-james-white-at-mcts-registration-now-open/">Dr. James White at MCTS: Registration now open!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From January 3-8, 2011, <a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/event/2011-01-03-polemics-j-term-with-james-white/">Dr. James White will be lecturing at MCTS</a> on various subjects &#8211; New Atheism, Islam, Roman Catholicism, and Mormonism. We have room for 25-30 visiting students. We will house you and feed you one meal (dinner) per day. Dr. White will lecture from 5-10pm. During the day, there will be opportunity to read, study, exercise, and maybe even to hang out with Dr. White. You can get information about registration <a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/event/2011-01-03-polemics-j-term-with-james-white/">here</a>. If you have any questions, let us know.</p>
<p>PS: If you can&#8217;t make it and want to watch the lectures live, there is an option in the registration process to pay $10 to access the live lectures.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/dr-james-white-at-mcts-registration-now-open/">Dr. James White at MCTS: Registration now open!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/dr-james-white-at-mcts-registration-now-open/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>News: White ad up at Challies&#8217; site</title>
		<link>/news-white-ad-up-at-challies-site/</link>
					<comments>/news-white-ad-up-at-challies-site/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2010 13:24:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Course offerings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/?p=254</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A nice ad for the Dr. James White module on Polemics &#8211; new Atheism, Roman Catholicism, Islam, and Mormonism &#8211; is up at Time Challies site. Nice work, JB! Richard BarcellosDr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/news-white-ad-up-at-challies-site/">News: White ad up at Challies&#8217; site</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.challies.com/">A nice ad</a> for the Dr. James White module on <a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/event/2011-01-03-polemics-j-term-with-james-white/">Polemics &#8211; new Atheism, Roman Catholicism, Islam, and Mormonism</a> &#8211; <a href="http://www.challies.com/">is up at Time Challies site</a>. Nice work, JB!</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/news-white-ad-up-at-challies-site/">News: White ad up at Challies&#8217; site</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/news-white-ad-up-at-challies-site/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>James White at MCTS &#8211; registration opens next week!</title>
		<link>/james-white-at-mcts-registration-opens-next-week/</link>
					<comments>/james-white-at-mcts-registration-opens-next-week/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2010 18:52:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Course offerings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/?p=237</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dr. James White will be teaching a one-week course in early January at MCTS. This course will introduce the student to the major apologetic themes relating to evangelizing and responding to Islam, Roman Catholicism, Mormonism, and the “New Atheism.” This should be a great and very timely course! You can read more about it here. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/james-white-at-mcts-registration-opens-next-week/">James White at MCTS &#8211; registration opens next week!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dr. James White will be teaching a one-week course in early January at MCTS. This course will introduce the student to the major apologetic themes relating to evangelizing and responding to Islam, Roman Catholicism, Mormonism, and the “New Atheism.”</p>
<p>This should be a great and very timely course! You can read more about it <a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/event/2011-01-03-polemics-j-term-with-james-white/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/james-white-at-mcts-registration-opens-next-week/">James White at MCTS &#8211; registration opens next week!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/james-white-at-mcts-registration-opens-next-week/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
