<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Ecclesiology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/ecclesiology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 18:31:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Ecclesiology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The Separation of Church and State? &#124; (Part 4 of 4) A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the  Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State</title>
		<link>/the-separation-of-church-and-state/</link>
					<comments>/the-separation-of-church-and-state/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 18:31:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Civil Government]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15474</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Separation of Church and State? These blogs have been a polemic against the original Reformed and Westminster view of church and state. Before I conclude these blogs, I want to give a brief and simple description of a scriptural and proper view of religious liberty. I will be speaking, therefore, of the separation of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-separation-of-church-and-state/">The Separation of Church and State? | (Part 4 of 4) A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the  Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2><strong>The Separation of Church and State?</strong></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>These blogs have been a polemic against the original Reformed and Westminster view of church and state. Before I conclude these blogs, I want to give a brief and simple description of a scriptural and proper view of religious liberty. I will be speaking, therefore, of the separation of church and state. There is a proper and biblical separation of church and state. Let me be clear that I am not speaking of separating the state from God. The separation of church and state does not entail &#8220;the separation of God and state.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong><em>The Presumption of Such a Separation:</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>We must begin by reminding ourselves of the redemptive history of the Theocratic Kingdom.&nbsp; With the expiration of the partially restored Theocratic order in A. D. 70, all civil authority in the world ceased to be Theocratic in the proper sense.&nbsp; God is no longer the unique king of any civil entity.&nbsp; No nation is now mandated to adhere to a specially revealed civil order.&nbsp; While the moral principles enshrined in the civil &nbsp;laws of the Old Covenant remain authoritative, no nation is bound to the detailed, civil order of Old Testament Israel.&nbsp; This is the explicit teaching of the 1689 Baptist Confession: &#8220;To them also he gave sundry judicial laws, which expired together with the state of that people, not obliging any now by virtue of that institution; their general equity only being of moral use.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Add to all of this the destruction of the Temple as the earthly throne of Yahweh, and one must also conclude that no longer are church and state a united entity.&nbsp; The redeemed community no longer has a civil structure.&nbsp; Thus, the divine establishment of the Gentile civil authorities means that the separation of the civil and ecclesiastical institutions in human society is now God&#8217;s preceptive will. &nbsp;The alteration of this order will be signaled only by the return of Christ.&nbsp; Thus, the separation of church and state is assumed and commanded by the Lord Jesus Christ when he directed that we should &#8220;render to Caesar the things that are Caesar&#8217;s and to God the things that are God&#8217;s&#8221; (Matt. 22:21).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong><em>The Arguments for Such a Separation:</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Many arguments could be brought forward in defense of religious freedom or soul liberty.&nbsp; I will only mention two:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>(1) &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Dictating religious belief and worship is not the task or function of the state.&nbsp; It is outside the sphere of the civil authorities. The state is to preserve civil justice and peace and protect men from violence to their bodies or property.&nbsp; This is the teaching of the Bible (Rom. 13:3, 4; Mt. 22:21; I Tim. 2:2; 1 Pet. 2:14; Ps. 82:1-4, 58:2, Deut. 4:27; Gen 6:11, 12, 9:5, 6; Ps. 72:14, Ezek. 7:23, 45:9; Prov. 21:15, 24:11, 12, 29:14, 26, 31:5). Men may and do differ as to religious belief without disrupting the peace or offering violence to others.&nbsp; The weapon of the civil authority is the sword (Rom. 13:1-7).&nbsp; Swords are not good weapons&#8212;they are not even the right weapons&#8212;with which to mold or rule men&#8217;s consciences.&nbsp; Civil authority rules men&#8217;s bodies, not their souls (Neh. 9:37).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>(2) &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; If a state is to dictate religious belief or worship, this inevitably requires the State to rule the church or the church to rule the state.&nbsp; Both church and state, however, are now independent under God. Since the Bible teaches the sphere-sovereignty of both the state and the church under God, to require the state to restrain violations of the first table of the law necessarily violates the teaching of Scripture.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong><em>The Limits of Such Separation:</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Are there limits to religious freedom?&nbsp; The obvious answer is certainly! When anyone&#8217;s professed religion disrupts civil justice or peace and threatens violence to the body or property of someone else, then it exposes itself to the legitimate action of the state. Such &#8220;religious liberty&#8221; must be restrained.&nbsp; It is no one&#8217;s religious right to beat their children to death. It is no one&#8217;s religious right to have an abortion on demand. Many other examples might be provided of religiously held &#8220;rights&#8221; which should not be permitted.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>We can uphold the great truth that Christ is King over all things. We can affirm that civil government must rule in light of the whole Word of God. We can assert that the 1<sup>st</sup> Table of the Law should be enforced by the father on his family, by the church on its members, and by the individual on himself. We can uphold and affirm all of this, but we to do so we need not revert to the dangerous viewpoint of the union of church and state. That view enshrined in the original Westminster Confession destroys religious liberty and a proper separation of church and state.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-separation-of-church-and-state/">The Separation of Church and State? | (Part 4 of 4) A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the  Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-separation-of-church-and-state/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Christ Is King! &#124; (Part 3 of 4) A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State</title>
		<link>/christ-is-king/</link>
					<comments>/christ-is-king/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 22:18:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Civil Government]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15410</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Christ Is King! In my first two blogs, I have attempted to point out the dangers which lurk in the waters of the original Westminster and older Presbyterianism. Someone might ask at this point about the fact that Christ is King over all things including the realm of civil authority. Is it necessary to jettison [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/christ-is-king/">Christ Is King! | (Part 3 of 4) A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2><strong>Christ Is King!</strong></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In my first two blogs, I have attempted to point out the dangers which lurk in the waters of the original Westminster and older Presbyterianism. Someone might ask at this point about the fact that Christ is King over all things including the realm of civil authority. Is it necessary to jettison religious freedom in order to uphold the universal reign of Christ? I think that is a good question. It deserves a good answer. Thankfully, one is available.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Let me restate the question. Isn&#8217;t the civil authority to rule according to the Word of God?&nbsp; If so, how can it allow religious freedom?&nbsp; Must it not, therefore, enforce the first table of the law?&nbsp; If God forbids idolatry, for instance, must not the state also forbid and penalize idolatry and, therefore, proscribe Mormonism, Islam, Hinduism, and, indeed, any religion which does not profess to worship the Christian Trinity?&nbsp;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Here a crucial distinction must be enunciated.&nbsp; It is certainly true that civil authority is subject to the Word of God, but this does not mean that it is the duty of the civil authority to enforce every part of God&#8217;s Word with its own authority.&nbsp; Several illustrations will make this clear.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Ephesians 6:4, for instance, requires, &#8220;And you fathers bring up your children in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.&#8221;&nbsp; Is the civil magistrate required to enforce this?&nbsp; No!&nbsp; Why?&nbsp; Because the Word is not his authority?&nbsp; No!&nbsp; But because He is not a Father.&nbsp; in 1 Peter 5:2 pastors are exhorted to shepherd the flock of God. Should the civil magistrate enforce this?&nbsp; No, because he is not a pastor.&nbsp;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Lest anyone think that this is just a Baptist or American way of thinking. Let me quote that great Scotsman and Presbyterian John Murray. He well says, &#8220;Since the civil magistrate is invested with this authority by God and is obliged by divine ordinance to discharge these functions, he is responsible to God, the one living and true God who alone has ordained him.&nbsp; The magistrate is, therefore, under obligation to discharge the office devolving upon him in accordance with the revealed will of God.&nbsp; The Bible is the supreme and infallible revelation of God&#8217;s will and it is, therefore, the supreme and infallible rule in all departments of life.&nbsp; The civil magistrate is under obligation to recognize it as the infallible rule for the exercise of civil magistracy.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Murray continues: &#8220;It must be recognized, however, that it is only within his own restricted sphere of authority that the civil magistrate, in his capacity as civil magistrate, is to apply the revelation of God&#8217;s will as provided in Scripture.&nbsp; It is only to the extent to which the revelation of Scripture bears upon the functions discharged by the state and upon the performance of the office of the civil magistrate, that he, in the discharge of these functions, is bound to fulfil the demands of Scripture.&nbsp; If the civil magistrate should attempt, in his capacity as magistrate, to carry into effect the demands of Scripture which bear upon him in other capacities, or the demands of Scripture upon other institutions, he would immediately be guilty of violating his prerogatives and of contravening the requirements of Scripture.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Murray goes on: &#8220;The sphere of the church is distinct from that of the civil magistrate &#8230; What needs to be appreciated now is that its sphere is co-ordinate with that of the state.&nbsp; The church is not subordinate to the state, nor is the state subordinate to the church.&nbsp; They are both subordinate to God, and to Christ in his mediatorial dominion as head over all things to his body the church.&nbsp; Both church and state are under obligation to recognize this subordination, and the corresponding co-ordination of their respective spheres of operation in the divine institution.&nbsp; Each must maintain and assert its autonomy in reference to the other and preserve its freedom from intrusion on the part of the other.&#8221; [John Murray, <em>Collected Writings</em>, 1:253-54.]</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Let me, then, ask the key question again. Why is the civil magistrate not to enforce the &#8220;first Table of the Law&#8221;?&nbsp; Is it because he is somehow not subject to the Word of God?&nbsp; No! He is not to enforce it because it is not within his jurisdiction to do so.&nbsp; Simply put, it is not his job! He must protect the religious liberty of all those subject to him by guarding their liberty, but it is not his duty to enforce religious uniformity on his subordinates. Though He rules in light of the Word of God, it is not his right to enforce religious uniformity on those under him. To put this in other words, it is not within the sphere of his sovereignty to do this. The body and not the soul is the concern and the sphere of the civil magistrate. Cf. Nehemiah 9:37.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/christ-is-king/">Christ Is King! | (Part 3 of 4) A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/christ-is-king/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What Lies Beneath! &#124; (Part 2 of 4) A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the  Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State</title>
		<link>/what-lies-beneath/</link>
					<comments>/what-lies-beneath/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 15:38:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Civil Government]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15405</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>What Lies Beneath! Most people are not experts on the history of Presbyterianism. This means that they might not realize that the mild and mannerly Presbyterianism with which we are familiar in the USA is not necessarily representative of the views of the original Reformed and Presbyterian views of church and state. The dear man [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/what-lies-beneath/">What Lies Beneath! | (Part 2 of 4) A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the  Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2><strong>What Lies Beneath!</strong></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Most people are not experts on the history of Presbyterianism. This means that they might not realize that the mild and mannerly Presbyterianism with which we are familiar in the USA is not necessarily representative of the views of the original Reformed and Presbyterian views of church and state. The dear man of God which voiced those views in the webinar may not want all the practical implications of his confession. His confession&#8212;the original Westminster&#8212;still says what it says and practically implies what it implies.&nbsp; If he confesses it, then he must live with it and promote it. The fact is that the original Westminster is no friend to the religious liberty that Reformed Baptists and other Baptists hold dear.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Let us look then at what the original Westminster actually says. Take special note of the parts I have placed in bold italics.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In chapter 23 and paragraph 3 the privilege of interfering in the affairs of the church is plainly asserted.&nbsp; There it states: &#8220;The civil magistrate may not assume to himself the administration of the word and sacraments, or the power of the keys of the kingdom of heaven: <strong><em>yet he hath authority, and it is his duty, to take order, that unity and peace be preserved in the church, that the truth of God be kept pure and entire, that all blasphemies and heresies be suppressed, all corruptions and abuses in worship and discipline prevented or reformed, and all the ordinances of God duly settled, administered, and observed.&nbsp; For the better effecting whereof, he hath power to call synods, to be present at them, and to provide that whatsoever is transacted in them be according to the mind of God.</em></strong>&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In Chapter 20 and paragraph 4 of the original Westminster a similar provision is made for the persecution of those contradicting the state religions.&nbsp; Of them it says: &#8220;for their publishing such opinions, or maintaining of such practices, as are contrary to the light of nature, or to the known principles of Christianity (whether concerning faith, worship, or conversation), or to the power of godliness; or, such erroneous opinions or practices, as either in their own nature, or in the manner of publishing or maintaining them are destructive to the external peace and order which Christ hath established in the Church, they may lawfully be called to account, and proceeded against, by the censures of the Church, <strong><em>and by the power of the civil magistrate</em></strong>.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>How can the state do such things without seriously compromising the church&#8217;s sovereignty under God&#8211;without making the church a slave of men?&nbsp; It cannot! If a state is to dictate religious belief or worship, this inevitably requires the State to rule the church or the church to rule the state.&nbsp; Since the Bible teaches the sphere-sovereignty of both the state and the church under God, to require the state to restrain violations of the first table of the law necessarily violates the teaching of Scripture. Furthermore, and of course, such a union of church and state inevitably destroys freedom of religion and the religious and soul liberty of Christians.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>American Presbyterians, to their credit, saw these problems. Therefore, they became committed to a more biblical view of the separation of church and state. For this reason, they revised these statements of the original Westminster. Here is that revision. It is held by most Presbyterians in the USA.&nbsp; It may be found at <a href="http://www.opc.org/documents/WCF_text.html">http://www.opc.org/documents/WCF_text.html</a>. There it is described as the WESTMINSTER CONFESSION OF FAITH incorporating the American Revisions as adopted by the Orthodox Presbyterian Church.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>First, let us notice the significant change which takes place in Chapter 20, paragraph 4. Here is the revision of 20:4: &#8220;for their publishing of such opinions, or maintaining of such practices, as are contrary to the light of nature, or to the known principles of Christianity (whether concerning faith, worship, or conversation), or to the power of godliness; or, such erroneous opinions or practices, as either in their own nature, or in the manner of publishing or maintaining them, are destructive to the external peace and order which Christ hath established in the church, they may lawfully be called to account, and proceeded against, by the censures of the church.&#8221; Notice the deletion of any reference to their being proceeded against by the power of the magistrate.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Here is the parallel section of 23:3. Take special note of the sections I have placed in bold italics: &#8220;Civil magistrates may not assume to themselves the administration of the Word and sacraments; or the power of the keys of the kingdom of heaven; or, in the least, interfere in matters of faith. Yet, as nursing fathers, <strong><em>it is the duty of civil magistrates to protect the church of our common Lord, without giving the preference to any denomination of Christians above the rest, in such a manner that all ecclesiastical persons whatever shall enjoy the full, free, and unquestioned liberty of discharging every part of their sacred functions, without violence or danger. And, as Jesus Christ hath appointed a regular government and discipline in his church, no law of any commonwealth should interfere with, let, or hinder, the due exercise thereof, among the voluntary members of any denomination of Christians, according to their own profession and belief. It is the duty of civil magistrates to protect the person and good name of all their people, in such an effectual manner as that no person be suffered, either upon pretense of religion or of infidelity, to offer any indignity, violence, abuse, or injury to any other person whatsoever: and to take order, that all religious and ecclesiastical assemblies be held without molestation or disturbance.</em></strong>&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Clearly, American Presbyterians recognized and revised the dangerous statements of the original Westminster. What lies beneath the fine-sounding phrases of the original Westminster and the original Presbyterian view of church and state is a view and practice hostile to religious liberty. And it is not just Baptists who think so. So also did American Presbyterians themselves.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/what-lies-beneath/">What Lies Beneath! | (Part 2 of 4) A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the  Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/what-lies-beneath/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What Dangers Lurk! &#8211; A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the  Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State Part 1 of 4</title>
		<link>/what-dangers-lurk/</link>
					<comments>/what-dangers-lurk/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 16:56:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Civil Government]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1689]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Church]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[civil government]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[westminster confession]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15327</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>What Dangers Lurk! I found myself last week in a Webinar on the church&#8217;s response to the Covid 19 Crisis. In particular, the theme revolved around the idea of civil disobedience with respect to civil orders for churches to cease assembling for the time being as a medical quarantine.&#160; I was on a panel hosted [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/what-dangers-lurk/">What Dangers Lurk! &#8211; A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the  Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State Part 1 of 4</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>What Dangers Lurk!</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>I found myself last week in a Webinar on the church&#8217;s response to the Covid 19 Crisis. In particular, the theme revolved around the idea of civil disobedience with respect to civil orders for churches to cease assembling for the time being as a medical quarantine.&nbsp; I was on a panel hosted by Scott Brown with five other pastors. These pastors represented various views of this matter and different approaches to the theological foundations which should guide the church and its pastors in making decisions on this matter.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Let me say that I found much to respect, appreciate, and agree with in the statements of these men. Surprisingly, though we came at this matter from somewhat different theological directions, it seemed to me that in our actual decisions and responses there was a high degree of practical agreement and unity. I suppose this was the case because all of us were foundationally committed to a Reformed approach to the Scriptures.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This respect and appreciation included the careful statements of one brother whose church (as he made clear) holds the original 1647 version of the Westminster Confession. (This is made explicit by the website of his church.) I deeply respect his affirmation that Christ is King over all things including not only the church but also the state. This is biblical and timely truth. I also respect his insistence on the civil magistrate governing not only in terms of the 2<sup>nd</sup>, but also the 1<sup>st</sup> Table of the Law. Such sentiments have a fine and Christian sounding ring to them! As a Reformed Baptist I am all for the observance of both tables of the law. I mourn the widespread violation of the first four commandments by many modern, professing Christians.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But Reformed Baptists did not receive religious freedom until 1688, the year of the glorious revolution in Great Britain. The reason for this was that the kind of view of church and state enshrined in the original version of the Westminster Confession was until then accepted and enforced by civil law. I think we must beware of what is deeply implied in the notion that the civil government is to enforce the 1<sup>st</sup> Table of the law. Historically, Baptists have been opposed to such a notion. The reason for this was because they understood that this notion is directly opposed to a right understanding of the separation of church and state and religious freedom&#8212;and specifically their religious freedom! There are reasons that Baptists took the lead in pushing for the Bill of Rights in our country and insisted that it include the free exercise of religion. There are lurking dangers in the original Westminster view of this. In my next few blogs, I want to open up the problem with the original Westminster and suggest a biblical alternative.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/what-dangers-lurk/">What Dangers Lurk! &#8211; A Few Observations on Civil Government Enforcing the 1st Table of the Law and the  Dangers in the Original Westminster Confession and Its View of Church and State Part 1 of 4</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/what-dangers-lurk/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</title>
		<link>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/</link>
					<comments>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 20:10:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Church Discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[church discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[practical theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13854</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Bible teaches us that holiness is one of the major marks of a true church. The church&#8217;s holiness is based off the great command found in Leviticus 19:2, &#8220;You shall be holy, for I the LORD your God am holy.&#8221; And the church&#8217;s holiness is the result of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Jesus [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/">Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-drop-cap">The Bible teaches us that holiness is one of the major marks
of a true church. The church&#8217;s holiness is based off the great command found in
Leviticus 19:2, &#8220;You shall be holy, for I the LORD your God am holy.&#8221; And the
church&#8217;s holiness is the result of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Jesus has saved
the church by giving Himself up for her. He saved her by spilling His own
precious blood on the cross. And as a result, the church has become the body
and bride of Jesus Christ. It belongs to Him. He is her Head and her Husband.
And Jesus didn&#8217;t die to purchase a sick body and an ugly bride. He died for the
church to be holy and without blemish. He died so she would reflect His holy
character. He died so that she would be holy as He is holy! Holy in her
profession of the truth and holy in her practice of living out the truth. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But in saying this, a problem should arise in our minds. A
big problem. And it&#8217;s this: the church is not perfect. At least not yet. If you
have but a faint understanding of your own heart, hopefully that&#8217;s not a
surprise. The church is full of saints but saints who are still sinners. Sadly,
saints who still break God&#8217;s commandments. And saints who still hurt one
another with their words and their actions.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Therefore, it must be the priority of every true church to
carry out what is called church discipline. This simply means the church must
have in place a way of dealing with and correcting sin when it rears its ugly
head. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If we are thinking of the church as the body of Christ,
church discipline is like undergoing surgery in order to cut out cancerous
tumors from the body so that the body would be healthy again. Or if we are
thinking of the church as the bride of Christ, church discipline is like
getting a top-of-the-line spa treatment in order for the dirt and filth and
warts and lumps to all be removed so that the bride would be beautiful again.&nbsp;&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Church discipline may not feel good, but it is absolutely
necessary. Church discipline must be enforced if any church wants to remain
pure, and holy, and undefiled before her Lord. If we let the tumors grow and do
nothing about them, the body will eventually die. And if we let the filth build
up without ever cleaning ourselves, the husband may become so disgusted with
his bride that he eventually leaves her! </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The classic passage on church discipline is found in Matthew
18:15-20. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>[15] &#8220;If your brother sins against you, go and tell him his fault, between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained your brother. [16] But if he does not listen, take one or two others along with you, that every charge may be established by the evidence of two or three witnesses. [17] If he refuses to listen to them, tell it to the church. And if he refuses to listen even to the church, let him be to you as a Gentile and a tax collector. [18] Truly, I say to you, whatever you bind on earth shall be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven. [19] Again I say to you, if two of you agree on earth about anything they ask, it will be done for them by my Father in heaven. [20] For where two or three are gathered in my name, there am I among them.&#8221; (ESV)</em></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In future posts, we will consider these verses in greater
detail. But for the present, consider six introductory remarks concerning
Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"large"} -->
<p class="has-large-font-size"><strong>Introductory Remarks</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>1.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline in Matthew 18:15-20 must never be severed from its context. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The context of this passage is very important. Sometimes
Jesus&#8217; overall teaching in this section is not emphasized enough when we think
about and talk about church discipline. This teaching on church discipline
comes in the midst of Jesus&#8217; teaching on how His disciples should love each
other, especially how they should love the least of His disciples. Remember, in
Matthew 18, Jesus teaches His disciples what it means to live as a citizen in
His kingdom. More than that, He teaches them what it means to be great in His
kingdom &#8211; and it has nothing to do with how the world defines greatness.
Greatness for Christ is not about popularity or power or riches or fame or
attractiveness or anything else the world is impressed with. Instead, greatness
in Christ&#8217;s kingdom is shown through humble service &amp; brotherly love. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus teaches this in Matthew 18 in four different ways: First,
His disciples are to show humility to one another (vv. 1-4). Second, His
disciples are to protect each other specifically from sin (vv. 5-9). Third, His
disciples are to highly esteem each other (vv. 10-14). And finally, His
disciples are to continually forgive each other (vv. 15-35). This teaching on
church discipline, then, makes up the first part in the fourth and final
section in this chapter, which deals with forgiveness.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>What does this mean then? It means that church discipline
and forgiveness and true Christian love are all vitally connected. We may be
tempted to think that church discipline and forgiveness have little or nothing
to do with each other. We may be tempted to think that church discipline is all
law while forgiveness is all grace, that church discipline is enslaving while
forgiveness is freeing, that church discipline makes me feel bad while
forgiveness makes me feel good!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Well, this dichotomy, this separation of church discipline
and forgiveness, is nowhere in Jesus&#8217; teaching. In fact, the exact opposite
occurs. Jesus&#8217; teaching on love and forgiveness includes church discipline!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus teaches us here that church discipline is the means of
forgiveness. It is the way of bringing about forgiveness and reconciliation and
restoration! And the goal of church discipline is forgiveness. Why are members
disciplined? So that forgiveness would occur. When forgiveness is not reached
between two people, discipline must be administered so that forgiveness might
become a reality!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Hopefully you see that church discipline and forgiveness
should not be pitted against each other but should work hand-in-hand to glorify
God, to keep the church pure and holy, and to bring about much peace and
happiness in the lives of God&#8217;s people. When we think about church discipline, we
should think about seeking forgiveness. The first is the means of obtaining the
second.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>2.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline concerns professing Christians. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>What Jesus says here concerns those who are brothers and
sisters in Christ. They are those who have made credible professions of faith,
have been baptized, and are members of a local church of Jesus Christ. In other
words, this teaching is for church members, for those who have been publicly
recognized as brothers and sisters in Christ. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>It is not, however, for unbelievers. How would it make any
sense to take your grievances to the church if the person who has sinned
against you is not even in the church to begin with? What can the church do
about it? If your unbelieving coworker sins against you, the only things we can
do is preach the gospel to him and pray for his salvation, but we can&#8217;t
discipline him. He has never been a part of this holy society we call the
church. He is an unbeliever outside of the kingdom of God. So we can&#8217;t put him
out of an organization he has never joined in the first place!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This doesn&#8217;t mean you shouldn&#8217;t seek forgiveness with people
in other areas of life; it simply means this step-by-step process that Jesus
teaches us is given specifically to the church and for the church to use with
its own members. It was not given to families or to schools or to society as a
whole.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are good principles there for anyone to follow, but it
is given specifically for the body and bride of Christ.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>3.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline deals with private sins committed against another brother or sister in Christ.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is important to note. The character of the kind of sin
Jesus is describing is private, not public. And it is against an individual,
not a group. Since it is private, certain measures are put in place by our Lord
to try to keep things as private as possible.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>John Calvin spends much time distinguishing between private
sins and public sins in his section on church discipline in the <em>Institutes</em>.
For sins that have been committed more openly, sins that affect more than just
one or two people but sins done in public where everyone knows about them and
where the whole church is immediately scandalized by them, Calvin argues that
these types of sin don&#8217;t fall within the instructions of Christ here in Matthew
18. People who sin in a public, grievous way are to be swiftly, solemnly, and
immediately rebuked in public, meaning something needs to be said to the church
when they gather together to worship God. We have examples of this happening in
the New Testament. Just think about Peter&#8217;s scandalous sin of distorting the
gospel of grace when he refused to eat with Gentile believers and how Paul
openly rebuked him to his face before the believers in Antioch (Galatians
2:11-14). This was no private meeting between the two apostles. The sin was so
grievous and so public that Paul was forced to rebuke Peter before the church.
And then he writes about it for all to read!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But for sins that have been committed more privately where
very few people know about it and very few people have been offended by it, the
steps laid down by Christ here in Matthew 18 must be followed. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are always exceptions to the rule. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are certain private sins that are so grievous that
immediate public church discipline must be enforced. Some of these sins might
include things that would put a person behind bars for a long time. Even if the
crime was committed in private, sometimes it must be exposed by the light for
all to see and abhor, including the civil authorities. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are also certain people who commit private sins that
must be made public. Here I am thinking about church officers. If a church
officer commits a particular sin that disqualifies him from the office of
either elder or deacon, something needs to be said to the church to give them
the reason why he has stepped down.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But the private sins I am talking about might include the
following: theft of some small amount, deliberately lying to another brother&#8217;s
face for your own personal advantage, unrighteous anger directed at another
believer, a complete lack of respect and honor for an older member of the
church, gossiping and slandering the good name of a Christian, a divisive
spirit that tries to stir up trouble in the church, and being a stumbling block
to one of Christ&#8217;s little ones. These may be small offenses in the eyes of our
society but let me tell you this: they are grave offenses in the sight of our
holy God who commands us to love one another as Christ loves us.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, all public sin should at all times be publicly rebuked;
some private sins should also at all times be publicly rebuked; but most
private sins should at first be privately rebuked. (but of course, it should
lead to a public rebuke in the presence of all if the person persists in sin).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>4.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline gives us a methodical, step-by-step process to deal with unrepentant sin. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Seeking forgiveness and reconciliation may be a process. I
wish it wasn&#8217;t the case. I wish that when someone sinned against another he or
she would immediately seek forgiveness. But sadly, while we live in this fallen
world, that is not always the case. And if forgiveness does not immediately
occur, there are distinct steps that must be taken in order to secure it. In
fact, there are four steps listed here in Matthew 18 that must be taken in
order to bring about forgiveness from an unrepentant Christian.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, we should not be trigger happy to discipline, and even
more than that, to excommunicate unrepentant members who have sinned in a
private way. As William Hendriksen says, &#8220;Church discipline, when viewed
negatively, is a matter of last resort&#8221; (699, Gospel of Matthew). None of this
should be rushed. Each step takes time to complete. Careful attention must be
taken and certain measures must be exhausted before moving on to the next step.
</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Maybe an illustration might be helpful. Instead of thinking
of these steps as little stair steps like the ones before me which only take a
second to climb (and easy to skip if you have some jumping abilities), think of
these steps to secure forgiveness like riding escalators from floor to floor at
the Mall of America. The Mall of America has four floors. And it has escalators
that will take you up to each floor. But it takes some time to go from one
floor to the next. And it takes a lot of time to go from the bottom floor to
the very top. You have to slowly but surely move from one to the next. Well, in
a similar way, each escalator of church discipline must be ascended before one
moves on to the next. Getting from step one to step four should not be
instantaneous.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>5.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline has, as its goal, the gaining or winning back of a professing Christian who has gone astray.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This step-by-step process of church discipline is
redemptive. The unrepentant professing Christian is like a sheep that has gone
astray. He or she has left the fold of Christ. He or she has sinned and turned
from the Highway of Holiness. And if that person keeps living in unrepentant
sin, if that person keeps walking down crooked, dark paths, he or she will not
reach the Celestial City. He or she will be attacked by deadly predators and will
be completely destroyed.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So seeking forgiveness in the way prescribed by Christ gets them back on the right track. It brings them back to the fold of God. It displays the very heart of Jesus Christ, the Good Shepherd, who leaves the 99 sheep on the mountains in order to search and find the one that went astray. As James says in James 5:19-20:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>&#8220;[19] My brothers, if anyone among you wanders from the truth and someone brings him back, [20] let him know that whoever brings back a sinner from his wandering will save his soul from death and will cover a multitude of sins.&#8221; (ESV)</em></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, in this area of church discipline, we need to check our
hearts. We need to make sure that if we want to walk up these steps, we are
doing so for the glory of God and for the ultimate good of the straying
Christian. It must not be our desire to seek vengeance or to get even with
someone who has wronged us. We also must not revel in another person&#8217;s
downfall. Instead, we must show brotherly love and tender affection to those
who have wronged us. We must remember how wicked our own hearts are, how much
we daily offend our Lord, and how much He has mercy on us. We have to keep ever
before us the goal of church discipline, which is repentance and forgiveness
and restoration, not condemnation and damnation. We want to win our brother and
sister back; not destroy them.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>6.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline is steeped in OT laws and principles.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus was not one who wanted to unhitch the Old Testament
from the New Testament. There have been teachers throughout church history who
have taught that New Testament believers should move on from the Old Testament
and leave that baggage behind as they follow Christ.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Well, certainly there are some things in the Old Testament
that shouldn&#8217;t be practiced any more in light of the coming of Christ, animal
sacrifices being one of them, but we should never dishonor or take lightly the
teaching of the Old Testament. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Why? Because Jesus didn&#8217;t. Jesus had a high view of the
Scriptures. And He saw a lot of use for the Old Testament in the New Testament
church. In fact, His step-by-step procedure for dealing with sin is based on
teaching from the Mosaic law! Yes, parts of the OT law were to inform and
structure the way the church of Jesus Christ governs itself and functions in
this world. Every step finds its roots in laws given to the nation of Israel.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This makes us think that Jesus may have considered the
church as the New Israel. And it also makes us think that there were more than
just temporary, ceremonial laws in the OT. Some of the laws in the Old
Testament transcend OT Israel and have direct application to the church of
Jesus Christ today. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, the Old Testament wasn&#8217;t to be thrown out or seen as
irrelevant for Christians. Instead, it was to be studied and examined and
applied to various situations which crop up in the church today. We will see
this as we go through the steps of church discipline.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is how I believe we should look at these steps: Two of them occur privately, and two of them occur publicly, in that order. So in future posts, we will look at the two private steps of seeking forgiveness, and then we will look at the two public steps of seeking forgiveness. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/">Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 5 of 5)</title>
		<link>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-5-of-5/</link>
					<comments>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-5-of-5/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 17:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[balance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eddlesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eldership]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Parity]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10284</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Part 1    Part 2    Part 3  Part 4 In this last post I want simply to collect a number of practical thoughts which flow out of a biblical view of the plurality, parity, and diversity of the eldership. 1.) See in the diversity, parity, and plurality of the eldership the glory of the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-5-of-5/">Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 5 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-1-of-5/">Part 1 </a>   <a href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-2-of-5/">Part 2 </a>   <a href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-3-of-5/">Part 3</a>  <a href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-4-of-5/">Part 4</a></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">In this last post I want simply to collect a number of practical thoughts which flow out of a biblical view of the plurality, parity, and diversity of the eldership.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">1.) See in the diversity, parity, and plurality of the eldership the glory of the one, supreme, and almighty Shepherd of the church!  I argue here in the same way that the Epistle to the Hebrews argues.  Cf. Hebrews 7:19-28.  Just as the limited duration and plurality of levitical priests pointed forward to the one, everlasting priest after the order of Melchizedek, so also the plurality of human pastors, the parity of human elders, and the diversity of human elders points up to the glory of the Chief Shepherd of the church.  He alone can make us perfect in every good work to do His will working in us that which is well-pleasing in God’s sight.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">2.) Look not to any human pastor for everything you need.  Do not limit yourself to one pastor’s gifts or teaching.  Do not virtually say I am of Apollos! or I am of Peter! or I am of Paul!  Such a posture is both limiting to your growth and potentially divisive.  Do not look finally to any limited, human pastor, but to the unlimited Christ and His unlimited grace.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">3.) Observe the constant need for humility and the perpetual danger of pride in connection with the vocation to which pastors are called.  Thankfully, I have not spent a lot of time in the typical pastors’ fraternals, but I have heard enough about such fraternals to know that they are often characterized by boasting and one-up-manship on the part of those named as Christ’s under-shepherds.  I will also confess to you that I often feel the green monster of envy rising in my own heart and need to thrust the sword of the Spirit through that monster. But equally debilitating to the minister is another monster.  The twin of the green monster of envy is the black monster of discouragement about my lack of usefulness which rises in my heart.  That monster sucks the zeal and desire to labor earnestly for Christ out of my soul.  It says to the pastors’ soul, “<em>It will not do any good to preach.  They will not listen.  You will do no good.  You have never done any good</em>.”  I think this black monster is also born of pride like the green monster.  What will slay both these monsters is deep humility before Christ, the seeking of grace from Christ, and the determination to simply do what Christ has called us to do to the best of our ability.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">4.) Be careful not to impose on the eldership your limited, human ideas and structures.  The study of the church and the various views of the eldership that have developed in it is cluttered with views of the eldership which are simply too limiting.  What views am I talking about?  There is the notion that you can have only one pastor in a church.  There is the notion that you can have only one bishop in a church.  There is the notion that you must have a senior pastor who hires and fires the other so-called pastors.  There is the notion that you can have only one supported pastor.  There is the notion that you can impose on the eldership the cookie-cutter view which says that there are only two kinds of elders:  teaching elders and ruling elders. There are other sorts of defective views as well.  Some who get a hold of the biblical vision for the parity and equality of elders go to extremes as well.  Since all elders are equal, then all must have equal profile in the church.  They must all preach or teach or lead equally.  They must be supported equally.  Others who hold the parity of the eldership actually conclude that no elders at all should be financially supported.  Perhaps this was the extreme which Paul was combatting in 1 Timothy 5:17. Others conclude that only missionaries or traveling evangelists should be supported, but not ordinary elders.  All of these views are based on a one-sided and imbalanced view of the eldership which takes one part of the biblical teaching to an extreme and ends up denying other aspects of the biblical teaching.  We must hold together the plurality, the parity, and the diversity of the eldership!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">5.) Make sure your church is a good steward of the gifts of its elders. One of the saddest things about the limiting views which I just listed in the previous observation is that often it means that some elders’ gifts are not fully utilized in the church.  Or it means that some men who should be elders are not even recognized by the church.  Or it means that to exercise their God-given gifts men are forced to leave their church to find a place of ministry.  If only there had been in the church a biblical vision for the eldership, if only there had not been the humanly limited views of the eldership that prevail in so many places, the church might have been blessed and God’s kingdom advanced.  But no!  The limited views of the eldership dictated by human wisdom had to be honored; and God’s blessing on the church through gifted men was lost.</span></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-5-of-5/">Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 5 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-5-of-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 4 of 5)</title>
		<link>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-4-of-5/</link>
					<comments>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-4-of-5/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 19:37:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[parity and diversity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[parity of eldership]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10205</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Part 1&#160; &#160; Part 2&#160; &#160; Part 3 We have looked at the reality that there is diversity of spiritual giftedness in true elders and that there is also diversity of financial support.&#160; In this post a third area of diversity among the elders will be our focus.&#160; With regard to biblical eldership, there is [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-4-of-5/">Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 4 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-1-of-5/">Part 1&nbsp;</a> &nbsp; <a href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-2-of-5/">Part 2&nbsp;</a> &nbsp; <a href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-3-of-5/">Part 3</a></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">We have looked at the reality that there is diversity of spiritual giftedness in true elders and that there is also diversity of financial support.&nbsp; In this post a third area of diversity among the elders will be our focus.&nbsp; With regard to biblical eldership, there is also the diversity of actual influence.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">It is also clear that there may be great diversity in a man&#8217;s actual influence as a Christian minister.&nbsp; This was certainly true even of the highest office in Christ&#8217;s church&#8212;the office of Apostle.&nbsp; Paul labored more than all the Apostles.&nbsp; He had, thus, a proportionately greater influence (1 Cor. 15:10).&nbsp; It also seems clear that Peter exercised a greater influence than many of the other Apostles (Matt. 16:18; Acts 1:15; 2:14, 38; 3:1).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">What is true of the extraordinary office of Apostle certainly must be true of the ordinary office of the pastor or elder.&nbsp; The sovereignty of God in the work of salvation and the differing gifts the Spirit gives lead to differing degrees of influence for good in Christ&#8217;s church.&nbsp; Of course, once more church history and Christian experience demonstrate that this is true.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">The New Testament, then, teaches the plurality, the parity, and the diversity of elders in the eldership of the local church.&nbsp; It is in light of these three principles that the eldership of every local church ought to be organized.&nbsp; The distribution of responsibilities and ministries must be guided by each of these three principles.&nbsp; The diversity of gift, influence and support must not disguise the parity of official authority belonging to each elder.&nbsp; The parity and plurality of the elders should not suppress the implications of the diversity of elders in the distribution of the responsibilities and ministries in the church.&nbsp; Parity of office does not require an artificial equality in the distribution of ministry or financial support.&nbsp; Rather, the sovereignty of Christ in giving a diversity of gifts should be acknowledged in such matters.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">One great implication of the diversity of the eldership as we have seen it in this blog series is that <em>part of the calling of a pastor is giving the man who is to be called a clear job description</em>.&nbsp; This is especially true where the man is not to be the first or sole supported pastor of a church.&nbsp; Of course, the Bible provides every elder such a job description in its explanation of the duties of the office.&nbsp; These duties, however, will vary in their proportion and their weight depending on his particular gifts and specific responsibilities.&nbsp; His ability to fulfill such duties will also be dependent on the time he can devote to such responsibilities.&nbsp; In turn this will be dependent on whether and to what extent he is financially supported.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">To re-emphasize my main point:&nbsp; all of this requires that the elder-to-be must be provided a clear idea or specific, job description of the particular duties he is called to fulfill as an elder.&nbsp; This is necessary in order to help a conscientious man make a responsible decision to accept the position being offered to him.&nbsp; This is also necessary in order to assure that hopes are not raised by the call to the eldership which are false or unrealistic.</span></p>
<p><a href="/?p=10284&amp;preview=true">Part 5</a></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-4-of-5/">Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 4 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-4-of-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 3 of 5)</title>
		<link>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-3-of-5/</link>
					<comments>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-3-of-5/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2018 17:20:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Parity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[parity of eldership]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Baptist]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10121</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In our last post we looked at the reality that there is a diversity of spiritual gifts in true elders.&#160; I commented that this has important practical implications for the church and its elders.&#160; But there is also diversity in other respects, specifically there is diversity of financial support. The New Testament teaches that there [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-3-of-5/">Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 3 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">In our last post we looked at the reality that there is a diversity of spiritual gifts in true elders.&nbsp; I commented that this has important practical implications for the church and its elders.&nbsp; But there is also diversity in other respects, specifically there is diversity of financial support.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">The New Testament teaches that there is diversity in the matter of financial support.&nbsp; Some elders may be fully supported by the church.&nbsp; Other elders may work at another vocation to support themselves.&nbsp; Let it be emphasized that this diversity is not the product of human sinfulness. &nbsp;It is ecclesiastically lawful for it to be so.&nbsp; The key text here is, of course, 1 Timothy 5:17-18.</span></p>
<blockquote><p><span style="font-size: x-large;">The elders who rule well are to be considered worthy of double honor, especially those who work hard at preaching and teaching. <sup>18</sup> For the Scripture says, &#8220;YOU SHALL NOT MUZZLE THE OX WHILE HE IS THRESHING,&#8221; and &#8220;The laborer is worthy of his wages.&#8221;</span></p></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Two questions must be answered with regard to this passage.&nbsp; First, what is double honor? Second, to whom is such double honor to be given?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>(1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; What is double honor?</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Double honor in 1 Timothy 5:17 means generous financial support.&nbsp; How do we know this?&nbsp; Double honor in the context of 1 Timothy 5:17 is contrasted with the honor to be given to widows.&nbsp; Without any doubt this honor for widows consists in financial support (1 Tim. 5:3, 4, 8, 16).&nbsp; Widows are, then, to be honored, while well-ruling elders are to be given double honor&#8212;the generous financial support necessary to comfortably support a man in a leadership position who may also have a wife and children.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">The financial character of this honor is confirmed by verse 18.&nbsp; Here Paul cites the same Old Testament text that he used in 1 Corinthians 9:9 to teach that ministers of the gospel should live of the gospel or be generously, financially supported.&nbsp; He also cites a saying of the Lord that in both Matt. 10:10 and Luke 10:7 had to do with the financial support of those who preach the gospel.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">The term, double, used here is not intended literally.&nbsp; It is used figuratively in the New Testament to refer to a large or generous portion of something (Matthew 23:15; Rev. 18:6).&nbsp; <strong>Matthew 23:15</strong> &#8220;Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, because you travel around on sea and land to make one proselyte; and when he becomes one, you make him twice as much a son of hell as yourselves.&#8221; <strong>Revelation 18:6</strong> &#8220;Pay her back even as she has paid, and give back to her double according to her deeds; in the cup which she has mixed, mix twice as much for her.&#8221;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">In accord with its usage in the New Testament, then, double here simply means or denotes that this financial support is to be ample or generous.&nbsp; The generosity with which elders should be financially supported is confirmed by the parallel passages (Galatians 6:6; 1 Corinthians 9:14).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>(2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To whom is such double honor to be given?</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">This financial support of the elders&#8212;according to the Apostle Paul&#8212;is not to be indiscriminately divided among or necessarily given to all elders.&nbsp; Notice how the passage speaks of this matter.&nbsp; Timothy and the church at Ephesus under his leadership are to focus that financial support on the elders who rule well. Among those who rule well financial support is especially to be given to those who work hard at preaching and teaching.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">I think of this passage as viewing the eldership in terms of three concentric circles.&nbsp; Financial support is focused on the innermost circle, may extend to the next circle outward, but does not extend to all elders in general.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">The measure of a man&#8217;s spiritual gifts in ruling and especially teaching and preaching (as well as his experience, maturity, diligence, and godliness) is related to the matter of financial support.&nbsp; Of course, the church&#8217;s ability may in some cases prevent the church from doing all it should do with regard to the financial support of elders.&nbsp; In such cases the priorities set by 1 Timothy 5:17 should govern the distribution of financial support to elders.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">We may draw from all this a clear conclusion.&nbsp; The Scriptures could not be more clear that there is diversity with regard to the financial support of elders.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Let me state plainly that voting a man in as a pastor or elder does not mean that the church has any necessary commitment to support that man financially.&nbsp; Nor does it mean that they are committed to financially supporting that man at the level that they may be supporting pastors already.&nbsp; Practically, all this means that a separate act of the church from the election of a pastor may be appropriate or even necessary to grant a pastor financial support.&nbsp; 1 Timothy 5:17 makes very clear that some elders or pastors may not be financially supported at all.&nbsp; This is, then, a different issue than recognizing that a man is a qualified elder.</span></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-3-of-5/">Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 3 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-3-of-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 2 of 5)</title>
		<link>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-2-of-5/</link>
					<comments>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-2-of-5/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2018 16:37:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eldership]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Parity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Baptist]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10112</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A few years ago a friend of mine mistakenly affirmed that I believed in the absolute parity of the eldership.&#160; I informed him, and let me now inform all of my readers, that I emphatically do not believe in such a view of parity.&#160; I believe, in fact, in three different kinds of diversity within [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-2-of-5/">Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 2 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">A few years ago a friend of mine mistakenly affirmed that I believed in the absolute parity of the eldership.&nbsp; I informed him, and let me now inform all of my readers, that I emphatically do not believe in such a view of parity.&nbsp; I believe, in fact, in three different kinds of diversity within the elders of the church.&nbsp; I will argue that there is diversity of spiritual gift, financial support, and actual influence.&nbsp; I believe that these three areas of diversity are much more than theoretical in their significance.&nbsp; They have important practical applications with regard to how the eldership and the church does its holy business.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">The diversity of elders is clearly taught in the Scriptures.&nbsp; It is not, as we have seen, a diversity with regard to office, authority, or title.&nbsp; But in what, then, does this diversity in the eldership consist? It consists, as I said, in a diversity of spiritual gift, financial support, and actual influence.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Consider, first, the diversity of spiritual gift.</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Both the Bible and experience show that elders may have greatly varying gifts.&nbsp; To think through this matter systematically, let me ask you to consider several things. <strong>First</strong>, the New Testament emphasizes the sovereignty of God in imparting those gifts.&nbsp; 1 Corinthians 12:11 affirms: &#8220;But one and the same Spirit works all these things, distributing to each one individually just as He wills.&#8221;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Second</strong>, the New Testament also emphasizes (and in the same passage) the variety of spiritual gifts which the Spirit in His sovereignty imparts, and the variation given to different members of the body of Christ.&nbsp; 1 Corinthians 12:4-7 says: &#8220;Now there are varieties of gifts, but the same Spirit. And there are varieties of ministries, and the same Lord. There are varieties of effects, but the same God who works all things in all persons.&nbsp; But to each one is given the manifestation of the Spirit for the common good.&#8221;&nbsp; This same emphasis is found in Romans 12:3-7 and 1 Pet. 4:10-11.&nbsp; What is true of the gifts of the Spirit to the church in general is, of course, true for the elders of the church as well.&nbsp; Here too there is variety of gift according to the sovereignty of the Spirit.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Third</strong>, there are several different gifts that are important specifically for the eldership.&nbsp; Romans 12:7-8 names the gifts of teaching, exhorting, and leading.&nbsp; 1 Corinthians 12:28 mentions the gifts of teaching and administration.&nbsp; 1 Peter 4:11 mentions the gift of speaking.&nbsp; But once more we must remember that God gives these spiritual gifts in varying degrees.&nbsp; The parable of Jesus emphasizes this in Matthew 25:14-15.&nbsp; The varying degrees of gift given to Christians and especially to ministers is also taught in Ephesians 4:7-11.&nbsp; What these passages clearly teach, church history and our own experience confirm. Great diversity exists in the mix and measure of spiritual gifts given to pastor-teachers.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Now this reality has very important practical implications.&nbsp; For one thing, this means that the qualifications for the eldership should not be measured in terms of the gifts of the outstanding preacher-pastor that we admire so much.&nbsp; There may be lesser degrees of gift which still qualify a man for the eldership.&nbsp; Similarly, we must also not limit the exercise of the highly gifted pastor by insisting on an artificial equality in the public ministry of the Word in the church.&nbsp; Equality of office does not mean equality in opportunities for public ministry in the church.&nbsp; This should make us accept men of more slender gifts as true elders, but also makes us feel that no artificial equality needs to be implemented in the public ministry of the church.</span></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-2-of-5/">Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 2 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-2-of-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 1 of 5)</title>
		<link>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-1-of-5/</link>
					<comments>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-1-of-5/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2018 23:29:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Parity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pastors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Baptist]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10097</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We distribute a book as a Seminary that I helped to write and edit many years ago.  It is entitled, In Defense of Parity. In that short volume, I with a few other men defend the notion (which many of us hold as Reformed Baptists) that there is no official distinction to be made between [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-1-of-5/">Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 1 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">We distribute a book as a Seminary that I helped to write and edit many years ago.  It is entitled, <em>In Defense of Parity</em>. In that short volume, I with a few other men defend the notion (which many of us hold as Reformed Baptists) that there is no official distinction to be made between the different elders of the church.  In other words, such a view of parity says that biblically all elders are pastors and all pastors are elders.  This view is based on what seems to me to be an indisputable exegetical reality.  That reality is that in the Bible the three words <strong><em>presbuteros</em></strong><em>, <strong>episkopos</strong>, </em>and<em> <strong>poimein</strong></em> refer to the same office in the church.  This is a little confusing because each of these three Greek words has both an <em>older</em> and a <em>newer</em>.  <strong><em>Presbuteros</em></strong> is translated presbyter in older English and elder in newer English.  <strong><em>Episkopos</em></strong> is translated in older English as bishop and as overseer in newer English.  <strong><em>Poimein</em></strong> is translated pastor in older English but shepherd in newer English.  Parity simply asserts that all these words refer to the identical office in the church.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">But to repeat myself, I am not going to spend a lot of time defending that conclusion or implication of the parity of the eldership and the equivalence of the terms shepherd, elder, and overseer with regard to referencing the same office in the church. The reason is that this conclusion is the assumption or presupposition of these blog posts rather than their thrust or focus.  Here I want to speak of my growing conviction over the years that the parity of the eldership needs to be balanced by the biblical teaching regarding the diversity of the eldership.</span></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-1-of-5/">Parity in the Eldership and the Need for Balance (part 1 of 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/parity-in-the-eldership-and-the-need-for-balance-part-1-of-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
