<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Books | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/books/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 20:39:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Books | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith (part 1)</title>
		<link>/modern-exposition-of-the-1689-baptist-confession-of-faith-part-1/</link>
					<comments>/modern-exposition-of-the-1689-baptist-confession-of-faith-part-1/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 20:39:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1689]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Modern Exposition]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1794</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>One of the major improvements, I hope, is in the expanded appendices at the end of the exposition.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/modern-exposition-of-the-1689-baptist-confession-of-faith-part-1/">Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith (part 1)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: justify;">The Manuscript for the 5th edition of <em>A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith</em> has been sent to the publisher! &nbsp;Over the next few weeks we plan to share some insights, additions and improvements that you can expect to see in the new edition.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">
<p style="text-align: justify;">I want to enlarge on the improvements in the 5th edition of <em>A Modern Exposition</em>.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">One of the major improvements, I hope, is in the expanded appendices at the end of the exposition.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><strong>Appendix A</strong>: The Historical Origin of the 1689 &#8230; corrects some historical inaccuracies owing to the primitive state of the sources I used to construct it in the original version of the Exposition.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><strong>Appendix B:</strong> The Analytical Outline of the 1689 &#8230; is a development of an outline I originally borrowed from Greg Nichols. It is now refined by the insights I have gleaned from Jim Renihan&#8217;s teaching on the structure of the Confession.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><strong>Appendix C</strong>: The Doctrinal Overview of the 1689 Baptist Confession is entirely new. It provides an argument that the Confession embodies a tradition which combines historic (catholic) orthodoxy with Reformed theology and Baptist principles.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;"><strong>Appendix D</strong>: The Proper Holding of the 1689 Baptist Confession is my response to the notion that the membership in a confessional church requires full subscription and that, therefore, the 1689 is too detailed to be a good, local church confession. I argue that elders must teach the Confession and thus fully subscribe, but members need only sweetly submit to the Confession and need not fully subscribe. This article has been posted on <a href="http://founders.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Founders.org</a> &nbsp;for some years now. <a href="http://founders.org/fj61/how-and-why-your-church-should-hold-to-the-1689-confession/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">How (and Why) Your Church Should Hold to the 1689 Confession</a></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Sam Waldron</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/modern-exposition-of-the-1689-baptist-confession-of-faith-part-1/">Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith (part 1)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/modern-exposition-of-the-1689-baptist-confession-of-faith-part-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (III)</title>
		<link>/wells-on-the-sabbath-chap-three-iii/</link>
					<comments>/wells-on-the-sabbath-chap-three-iii/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2011 02:51:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Wells]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=953</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Wells references Matt. 12:1-14 several times in chapter 3 but offers no exposition of the passage.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-on-the-sabbath-chap-three-iii/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (III)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/05/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/">Tom Wells&#8217; book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (II)</a></p>
<p><strong>Matthew 12:1-14&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Wells references Matt. 12:1-14 several times in chapter 3[1] but offers no exposition of the passage.[2] I will offer a brief exposition.</p>
<p>In Matt. 12, we are told that &#8220;Jesus went through the grainfields on the Sabbath. And His disciples were hungry, and began to pluck heads of grain and to eat&#8221; (Matt. 12:1). The Pharisees replied, &#8220;Look, Your disciples are doing what is not lawful to do on the Sabbath!&#8221; (Matt. 12:2). Jesus then offers two examples from the OT; &#8220;&#8230;David&#8230; and those who were with him&#8221; (Matt. 12:3) and &#8220;the priests in the temple&#8221; (Matt. 12:5).[3] Concerning the priests, he says, &#8220;Or have you not read in the law that on the Sabbath the priests in the temple profane the Sabbath, and are blameless?&#8221; (Matt. 12:5). Whatever the priests were doing, the Pharisees&#8217; logic implied it was a violation of the Sabbath. Their logic taught that the priests, David, and Christ&#8217;s disciples were profaning the Sabbath. But Jesus says the priests &#8220;&#8230;are blameless&#8221; (Matt. 12:5). Then he quotes Hos. 6:6. He says, &#8220;But if you had known what this means, &#8216;<em>I desire mercy and not sacrifice</em>,&#8217; you would not have condemned the guiltless&#8221; (Matt. 12:7).[4] He pronounces his disciples &#8220;guiltless&#8221; by referencing two OT examples. In the next section of Matt. 12, the Pharisees ask, &#8220;Is it lawful to heal on the Sabbath?&#8221; (Matt. 12:10). Jesus concludes in v. 12, &#8220;Therefore it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath.&#8221; This clearly teaches that healing on the Sabbath was lawful as was preserving the life of a sheep (vv. 10-12). His disciples ate because eating is necessary to sustain human life. All of these actions, according to Christ, were lawful on the Sabbath according to OT law. Jesus was correcting faulty thinking about the Sabbath by consulting prior revelation.</p>
<p>Someone might want to offer Matt. 12 as an example of Jesus abrogating the Sabbath (cf. Mk. 2:23-28 and Lk. 6:1-11).[5] They might claim that Jesus advocates Sabbath-breaking thereby proving that he was abolishing it. But does this text bear this out? Did Jesus, in fact, advocate Sabbath-breaking during his earthly ministry? We have just examined Matt. 12:1-14 and seen Christ justifying works of necessity and mercy and concluding in v. 12, &#8220;Therefore it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath.&#8221; The &#8220;good&#8221; in the context of Matt. 12 involved not only what his disciples did and what he did, but what David and those with him and the old covenant priests did. The supposed violation of the Sabbath in this passage (and others) is actually an upholding of the Sabbath and in accordance with OT revelation. Jesus never advocated Sabbath-breaking during his earthly ministry. Jesus&#8217; teaching upholds existing Sabbath law.</p>
<p>Those who offer this objection may claim that when Jesus says, &#8220;But I say to you that in this place there is One greater than the temple&#8221; (v. 6) and &#8220;For the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath&#8221; (v. 8), Jesus is claiming authority to abolish the Sabbath as he abolished the temple. In once sense, Christ did abolish the Sabbath. He abolished it in its various functions under the old covenant. And, in one sense, Christ abolished the temple. He did not, however, abolish the temple in all senses. His church is now God&#8217;s temple, where spiritual sacrifices are offered (Eph. 2:19-22; 1 Pt. 2:4-5). What does Jesus mean, when he says, &#8220;But I say to you that in this place there is One greater than the temple&#8221; (Mt. 12:6) and &#8220;For the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath&#8221; (Matt. 12:8; cf. Mk. 2:28)? Fairbairn offers this explanation:</p>
<p>The Temple, He had said, has claims of service, which it was no proper desecration of the Sabbath, but the reverse, to satisfy; and &#8216;a greater than the Temple was there.&#8217; &#8216;The Temple yields to Christ, the Sabbath yields to the Temple, therefore the Sabbath yields to Christ&#8217;&#8211;so the sentiment is syllogistically expressed by Bengel; but yields, it must be observed, in both cases alike, only for the performance of works not antagonistic, but homogeneous, to its nature. &#8230; He is Lord of the Sabbath, and, as such, has a right to order everything concerning it, so as to make it, in the fullest sense, a day of blessing for man&#8211;a right, therefore, if He should see fit, to transfer its observance from the last day of the week to the first, that it might be associated with the consummation of His redemptive work, and to make it, in accordance with the impulsive life and energy thereby brought in, more than in the past, a day of active and hallowed employment for the good of men.[6]</p>
<p>Just as the temple yields to Christ and is transformed to fit the redemptive-historical circumstances brought in by his death and resurrection/exaltation, so the Sabbath yields to Christ and is transformed to fit the redemptive-historical circumstances brought in by his death and resurrection/exaltation. The new covenant has both a temple and a Sabbath. This connects Christ&#8217;s teaching on the temple and the Sabbath with subsequent revelation.</p>
<p>Instead of Matt. 12 proving that Christ abolished the Sabbath, it actually argues that he upheld it and sought to correct the Pharisees&#8217; faulty interpretation of Sabbath law. Fairbairn says, &#8220;Jesus grasped, as usual, the real spirit of the institution; for we are to remember, He is explaining the law of the Sabbath as it then stood, not superseding it by another.&#8221;[7] Christ upheld the Sabbath, cleared it of Pharisaic encumbrances, and set the stage for further revelation about it.</p>
<p>This objection assumes that the Sabbath in all senses was temporary, ceremonial law. Ceremonial laws are temporary laws for old covenant Israel and were a shadow of things to come (Col. 2:16-17). They were all abrogated by the coming of Christ and the inauguration of the new covenant (2 Cor. 3:7-18; Gal. 3-4; Eph. 2:14-16; Col. 2:16; and Heb. 8-10 [cf. esp. 8:6-7, 13; 9:9-10, 15; 10:1, 9, 15-18]). If the Sabbath is ceremonial law in all senses, then it has been abrogated. But the Sabbath is not ceremonial law in all senses, as we have seen (cf. Gen. 2:2-3; Ex. 20:8-11; Is. 56:2, 4, 6; and Mk. 2:27). And if Jesus considered it as ceremonial only, one would think he would treat it like he did other ceremonial laws. Beckwith and Stott comment:</p>
<p>But if Jesus regarded the sabbath as purely ceremonial and purely temporary, it is remarkable that he gives so much attention to it in his teaching, and also that in all he teaches about it he never mentions its temporary character. This is even more remarkable when one remembers that he emphasizes the temporary character of other parts of the Old Testament ceremonial&#8211;the laws of purity in Mark 7:14-23 and Luke 11:39-41, and the temple (with its sacrifices) in Mark 13:2 and John 4:21. By contrast, &#8230;he seems&#8230;to speak of the sabbath as one of the unchanging ordinances for all mankind.[8]</p>
<p>Jesus neither abrogated the Sabbath in all senses in his earthly ministry nor did he predict its soon demise. He upheld it and gave evidence that it would continue under his lordship as the Son of Man (Mk. 2:27-28).</p>
<p>We will look at Mk. 2:27-28 in our next post.</p>
<hr size="1">[1] I counted 10.</p>
<p>[2] In fact, the book contains little exegesis. Wells cites many texts and makes many observations; but he does little exegesis or exposition of passages. There was much proof-texting surrounded by observations that put the reader in an interpretive strait-jacket. I found his theological-interpretive method not very sound.</p>
<p>[3] Notice that Jesus is referring to previous revelation.</p>
<p>[4] Here is another reference to previous revelation.</p>
<p>[5] I am not assuming Wells does this.</p>
<p>[6] Patrick Fairbairn, <em>The Revelation of Law in Scripture</em> (Phillipsburg, NJ: P&amp;R Publishing Company, 1996), 238.</p>
<p>[7] Fairbairn,<em> Revelation of Law</em>, 237.</p>
<p>[8] Roger T. Beckwith and Wilfrid Stott, <em>This is the Day: The Biblical Doctrine of the Christian Sunday in its Jewish and Early Christian Setting</em> (London: Marshall, Morgan &amp; Scott, 1978), 26.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-on-the-sabbath-chap-three-iii/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (III)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/wells-on-the-sabbath-chap-three-iii/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Covenant of Creation</title>
		<link>/the-covenant-of-creation/</link>
					<comments>/the-covenant-of-creation/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2011 17:35:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covenant of creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[covenant of works]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roland S. Ward]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=943</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The guys at Reformed Forum discuss the Creation Covenant with Dr. Roland S. Ward.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-covenant-of-creation/">The Covenant of Creation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The guys at Reformed Forum discuss the Creation Covenant with Dr. Roland S. Ward. I highly recommend Ward&#8217;s book  <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Reformed-Theology-Creation-Covenant-Covenants/dp/095862416X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1305567192&amp;sr=1-1"><em>God &amp; Adam: Reformed Theology and the Creation Covenant</em>.</a> It is a wealth of information on this important issue.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-covenant-of-creation/">The Covenant of Creation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-covenant-of-creation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (II)</title>
		<link>/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/</link>
					<comments>/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 05:16:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Wells]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=911</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Gospels are full of allusions to and echoes of previous revelation. And the Gospels set the stage for further revelation which will explain both the redemptive acts and words of Jesus Christ (Jn. 14:26; 16:13-15).</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (II)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/05/tom-wells-sabbath-chapter-three-i/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (I)</a></p>
<p>Let me make a few necessary comments on the genre and interpretation of the Gospels. The Gospels contain narrative accounts of various aspects of Christ’s earthly ministry. He taught in a very distinct redemptive-historical context and the Gospel authors each had theological purposes for choosing what they narrated and what they commented upon. We must remind ourselves that OT and NT narratives do just that – they narrate, they tell us what happened, though with theological purpose.[1] We must grant that some of the teachings of Christ in the Gospels are perpetually binding and not to be left on the shelf of narrated history. I say some because Christ commanded things to individuals that are not meant to be perpetually binding on others (cf. Matt. 26:36, “Sit here while I go over there and pray.”). But to demand a distinct type of teaching in order to justify ethics (<a href="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/2011/05/tom-wells-sabbath-chapter-three-i/">what Wells did in the previous post</a>) and then claim that the Gospel passages don’t contain that type of teaching is simply a wrong-headed, constricting hermeneutical procedure. What if there are other grounds for considering Christ’s teachings on the Sabbath as applicable to Christians? A much better approach would be to read the Gospels looking for teaching related to prior and subsequent revelation and then to determine ethical perpetuity based on how Christ’s teaching is related to its broader, canonical-ethical/redemptive-historical context. The Gospels are full of allusions to and echoes of previous revelation. And the Gospels set the stage for further revelation which will explain both the redemptive acts and words of Jesus Christ (Jn. 14:26; 16:13-15). We must never interpret the Gospels as an end in themselves. Two passages in the Gospels are especially instructive in light of this – Matt. 12:1-14 and Mk. 2:27-28. These texts both reach back in redemptive history, alluding to and echoing previous revelation, and set the stage for further revelation. We will look at each passage briefly in the next post.</p>
<hr size="1" />[1] This is not to suggest that OT narratives and the Gospels are one and the same genre on every level. Whether the Gospels are seen as theological biographies, covenantal treaty documents, or a complex of different genres the presence of narrative is still true.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (II)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/wells-sabbath-chapter-three-ii/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (I)</title>
		<link>/tom-wells-sabbath-chapter-three-i/</link>
					<comments>/tom-wells-sabbath-chapter-three-i/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2011 13:04:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lord's Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Wells]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=897</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>“There is not one syllable of positive teaching by the Lord Jesus peculiar to the Sabbath in any Gospel passage.” - Tom Wells</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/tom-wells-sabbath-chapter-three-i/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (I)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Chapter 3: Gospel Texts on Sabbath-Keeping</strong></p>
<p>In chapter 3, Wells combs the Gospels for teaching related to the Sabbath. He makes this assertion: “<em>There is not one syllable of positive teaching by the Lord Jesus peculiar to the Sabbath in any Gospel passage</em>” (42).[1] What he means by “<em>positive teaching</em>” is “teaching that tells Christians or Jews what they must do, or not do on any Sabbath” (42). What he means by “<em>peculiar to the Sabbath</em>” is “teaching that is true for the Sabbath that is not also true for every other day of the year” (42). In Wells’ thinking, this would mean that if the Gospels do not contain teaching that either commands or forbids specific activities on the Sabbath or commands or forbids things that apply on any other day, then it was never Jesus’ intention “to command anyone to keep a Sabbath” (47). Do you feel the pressure of these twin pillars? If there is no “<em>positive teaching…peculiar to the Sabbath</em>,” Jesus was not commanding Sabbath observance. I find these constricting hermeneutical hedges both interesting and wrong-headed. It is as if Wells sets up for us in advance what kind of teaching on the Sabbath must be present in order to justify any kind of Sabbath observance for Christians or Jews from the lips of our Lord. Wells knows, as does any casual reader of the Gospels, that the Sabbath command was something already in place at the time of Christ’s earthly ministry. Jesus simply assumes its validity. Wells also knows, as does any casual reader of the Gospels, that Christ sought to correct the faulty understanding and practice of some first century Jews concerning the Sabbath. The Sabbath was already an ancient institution, predating Jesus and his contemporaries but had been abused. Requiring Jesus to present us with “<em>positive teaching…peculiar to the Sabbath</em>” seems to exclude any other type of teaching that might lead us to the conclusion that the Sabbath transcends the old covenant and has ethical tentacles that reach into the new covenant.</p>
<p>Let’s assume Wells’ position for a minute. Jesus’ teaching was not for the purpose of identifying what Christians or Jews can or can’t do on the Sabbath or Lord’s Day (45). Jesus’ teaching on the Sabbath did not command or forbid anything either commanded or forbidden on any other day. Does that prove that there is no Sabbath or Lord’s Day for the Christian to obey? Assuming the validity of Wells’ equation, all it would prove is what it asserts – nothing more and nothing less. Again, Jesus was correcting the faulty teaching of his day on the Sabbath that added to and took from the word of God – commanding and forbidding things God did not. Jesus advocated a return to Sabbath-keeping as it had been revealed by God. Also, Jesus did say, “So then, it is lawful to do good on the Sabbath” (Matt. 12:12). This sure seems like “<em>positive teaching</em>” to me.</p>
<hr size="1" />[1] Italics are Wells’.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/tom-wells-sabbath-chapter-three-i/">Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (I)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/tom-wells-sabbath-chapter-three-i/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reformed Baptist Theological Review update</title>
		<link>/reformed-baptist-theological-review-update/</link>
					<comments>/reformed-baptist-theological-review-update/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2011 21:34:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christian Sabbath]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RBTR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[W. Gary Crampton]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=822</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>RBTR VII:1 is almost ready to ship to the printer. It should be available in a few weeks.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/reformed-baptist-theological-review-update/">Reformed Baptist Theological Review update</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Coming&nbsp;soon:<strong>&nbsp; </strong><strong>RBTR VII:1, Spring 2010</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p><strong>ARTICLES</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;EPHESIANS 1:8-10 IN LIGHT OF ITS IMMEDIATE CONTEXTUAL MEANING AND REDEMPTIVE-HISTORICAL/CANONICAL CONTEXT: God Getting Glory for Himself through the Work of the Redeemer and Reconciler of All Things,&#8221; Richard C. Barcellos, 7-35.</p>
<p>&#8220;ADAM&#8217;S QUEST FOR A BETTER LIFE: A Study in Calvin&#8217;s Doctrine of Pre-Redemptive Eschatology,&#8221; James E. Dolezal, 37-50.</p>
<p>&#8220;THE SUM OF ALL BLESSINGS: Jonathan Edwards on the Holy Spirit,&#8221; W. Gary Crampton, Th.D., 51-77.</p>
<p><em>&#8220;THE CHRISTIAN AND THE SABBATH</em>, TOM WELLS: A Review Article (Part I),&#8221; Richard C. Barcellos, 79-91.</p>
<p><strong>BOOK REVIEWS</strong></p>
<p><em>Christless Christianity: The Alternative Gospel of the American Church</em>, Michael Horton (Grand Rapids: Baker Books, 2008), and <em>The Gospel-Driven Life: Being Good News People in a Bad News World</em>, Michael Horton (Grand Rapids: Baker Books, 2009), reviewed by John Divito, 93-97.</p>
<p><em>Heaven and Earth in the Gospel of Matthew, </em>Jonathan T. Pennignton<em> </em>(Grand Rapids: Baker Academic, 2009), 399pp,<em> </em>reviewed by Samuel C. Emadi, 97-101.</p>
<p><em>Imputation and Impartation: Union with Christ in American Reformed Theology, </em>William B. Evans (Wipf &amp; Stock, 2009, 296 pp.),<em> </em>reviewed by Matthew Barrett, 102-106.</p>
<p><em>That Scripture Might Be Fulfilled: Typology and the Death of Christ, </em>Paul M. Hoskins<em> </em>(Xulon Press: 2009, 200pp.),<em> </em>reviewed by Richard C. Barcellos, 106-108.</p>
<p><em>The Ten Commandments: Ethics for the Twenty-First Century </em>Mark F. Rooker<em> </em>(Nashville: B&amp;H Publishing Group, 2010, 234pp.),<em> </em>reviewed by Richard C. Barcellos, 108-114.<em></em></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/reformed-baptist-theological-review-update/">Reformed Baptist Theological Review update</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/reformed-baptist-theological-review-update/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MSNBC’s Martin Bashir on The Paul Edwards Program</title>
		<link>/bashir-on-edwards/</link>
					<comments>/bashir-on-edwards/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2011 13:39:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Martin Bashir]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS< Rob Bell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Edwards]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=773</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Bashir says he does attend Keller’s church, married to a Christian woman, and is a committed Christian.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/bashir-on-edwards/">MSNBC’s Martin Bashir on The Paul Edwards Program</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Listen to Paul Edwards interview Martin Bashir <a href="http://www.godandculture.com/blog/msnbcs-martin-bashir-on-the-paul-edwards-program?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+TheGodAndCultureBlog+%28The+God+and+Culture+Blog%29">here</a>. I highly recommend <a href="http://www.godandculture.com/blog/msnbcs-martin-bashir-on-the-paul-edwards-program?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+TheGodAndCultureBlog+%28The+God+and+Culture+Blog%29">it</a>! Bashir is the one who bashed a Bell recently. <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/1f642.png" alt="🙂" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>
<p>Here are my thoughts. The quotes utilize the dynamic equivalence theory. <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/1f642.png" alt="🙂" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>
<p>Bashir says the book is evasive, disingenuous, and historically inaccurate. Bell selectively quotes Luther and uses him out of context. He does that repeatedly with historical and biblical texts. Bashir slams Bell’s method.</p>
<p>“Bashir knows more about historic Christianity than Rob Bell,” Paul Edwards. I agree with Paul. <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/1f642.png" alt="🙂" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>
<p>Bashir is really sharp. He was born into a Muslim family. He says that Christianity will offend any culture it goes to at some point.</p>
<p>The book is “…the psychological out-workings of a young man… and I am sympathetic with that.” “He is a victim of his own experience, as we all are to a point.”</p>
<p>“Any theological position that can’t be questioned is not worth following.” This includes Islam.</p>
<p>He nails the emergent movement as a youth movement away from historic Christian theology and practice. “If the church has been so backwards and out of touch with culture, how has it survived?” Amen!</p>
<p>“If I start rapping and dressing and talking like a 15 year-old as a parent, it won’t work.” Amen!</p>
<p>Bashir says he does attend Keller’s church, married to a Christian woman, and is a committed Christian. Amen!</p>
<p>“My personal faith was entirely irrelevant in that interview.” Well, I&#8217;m not so sure of that.</p>
<p>He is very sharp and easy to listen to.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/bashir-on-edwards/">MSNBC’s Martin Bashir on The Paul Edwards Program</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/bashir-on-edwards/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Him We Proclaim-Preaching Christ From all the Scriptures</title>
		<link>/him-we-proclaim-preaching-christ-from-all-the-scriptures/</link>
					<comments>/him-we-proclaim-preaching-christ-from-all-the-scriptures/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 17:26:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dennis Johnson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[R. Scott Clark]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=721</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>R. Scott Clark interviews Dennis Johnson concerning his book Him We Proclaim. I recommend the book highly, especially chapters 4. The Complication, Chastening, Rejection, and Recovery of Apostolic Preaching in the History of the Church, 5. Challenges to Apostolic Preaching, and 7. Theological Foundations of Apostolic Preaching. The interview can be listened to here. Richard [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/him-we-proclaim-preaching-christ-from-all-the-scriptures/">Him We Proclaim-Preaching Christ From all the Scriptures</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>R. Scott Clark <a href="http://wscal.edu/resource-center/resource/him-we-proclaim">interviews </a>Dennis Johnson concerning his book <a href="http://bookstore.wscal.edu/products/1224">Him We Proclaim</a>. I recommend the book highly, especially chapters 4. The Complication, Chastening, Rejection, and Recovery of Apostolic Preaching in the History of the Church, 5. Challenges to Apostolic Preaching, and 7. Theological Foundations of Apostolic Preaching. The interview can be listened to <a href="http://wscal.edu/resource-center/resource/him-we-proclaim">here</a>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/him-we-proclaim-preaching-christ-from-all-the-scriptures/">Him We Proclaim-Preaching Christ From all the Scriptures</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/him-we-proclaim-preaching-christ-from-all-the-scriptures/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MCTS Podcast 14: Dr. James White &#8211; his 2011 plans</title>
		<link>/mcts-podcast-14/</link>
					<comments>/mcts-podcast-14/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 18:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[books on islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. James White]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=710</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dr. White shares his 2011 travel plans and writing projects.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-podcast-14/">MCTS Podcast 14: Dr. James White &#8211; his 2011 plans</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dr. White shares his 2011 travel plans and writing projects.</p>
<p><object classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" width="400" height="300" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true"><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"><param name="src" value="http://vimeo.com/moogaloop.swf?clip_id=20444062&amp;server=vimeo.com&amp;show_title=0&amp;show_byline=0&amp;show_portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff&amp;fullscreen=1&amp;autoplay=0&amp;loop=0"></object></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-podcast-14/">MCTS Podcast 14: Dr. James White &#8211; his 2011 plans</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mcts-podcast-14/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ReformedCast: The Family Tree of Reformed Biblical Theology</title>
		<link>/reformedcast-the-family-tree-of-reformed-biblical-theology/</link>
					<comments>/reformedcast-the-family-tree-of-reformed-biblical-theology/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 17:10:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Historical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geerhardus Vos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Owen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=616</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Scott Oakland interviewed me last night about my dissertation. You can listen here or here (mp3). The book is available at www.rbap.net. Richard BarcellosDr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/reformedcast-the-family-tree-of-reformed-biblical-theology/">ReformedCast: The Family Tree of Reformed Biblical Theology</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Scott Oakland interviewed me last night about my dissertation. You can listen <a href="http://reformedcast.com/2011/01/24/episode-20-the-family-tree-of-reformed-biblical-theology-13110/">here </a>or <a href="http://traffic.libsyn.com/reformedcast/Episode__20_-_The_Family_Tree_of_Reformed_Biblical_Theology.mp3">here (mp3)</a>. The book is available at <a href="http://www.rbap.net/">www.rbap.net</a>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/reformedcast-the-family-tree-of-reformed-biblical-theology/">ReformedCast: The Family Tree of Reformed Biblical Theology</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/reformedcast-the-family-tree-of-reformed-biblical-theology/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		<enclosure url="http://traffic.libsyn.com/reformedcast/Episode__20_-_The_Family_Tree_of_Reformed_Biblical_Theology.mp3" length="0" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="http://traffic.libsyn.com/reformedcast/Episode__20_-_The_Family_Tree_of_Reformed_Biblical_Theology.mp3" length="0" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
