<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Reformed Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/reformed-theology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2017 17:40:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Reformed Theology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Does the Bible Teach Common Grace?</title>
		<link>/does-the-bible-teach-common-grace/</link>
					<comments>/does-the-bible-teach-common-grace/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2017 17:40:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9143</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Reformed Contentions It is a popular assertion of those who oppose the doctrine of common grace to claim that in the Bible, the word grace only refers to God&#8217;s saving grace given to the elect and never to God&#8217;s common grace displayed to the reprobate. This is in fact what Ron Hanko, son of Herman [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/does-the-bible-teach-common-grace/">Does the Bible Teach Common Grace?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Reformed Contentions</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">It is a popular assertion of those who oppose the doctrine of common grace to claim that in the Bible, the word <em>grace</em> only refers to God&#8217;s saving grace given to the elect and never to God&#8217;s common grace displayed to the reprobate. This is in fact what Ron Hanko, son of Herman Hanko and a minister in the Protestant Reformed Church, asserts. He says, &#8220;The word <em>grace</em> is used over 300 times in the Bible. . . . Never once in the Bible is it used in reference to the reprobate wicked. Never once. Go home and check it.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> If this wasn&#8217;t clear enough, he later emphatically declares that the term <em>grace</em> (as well as <em>love</em>) is &#8220;never, never used in reference to the reprobate wicked. Never.&#8221; Instead, Hanko unashamedly proclaims that &#8220;in all of His common providence [God&#8217;s] disposition toward them is unremitting and unchangeable hatred.&#8221; He likens the providential operations of God to the care of a meat farmer for his livestock: the farmer does not attend to the needs of his animals because he loves them but only because he is raising them for the slaughter. But the doctrine of common grace includes more terms than simply <em>grace</em>. Hanko admits that many more words are included under the general umbrella of grace when he says, &#8220;When we are speaking about common grace we are also speaking of common love, common mercy, common goodness, common longsuffering. They all go together. They can&#8217;t be separated. . . . They all stand or fall together.&#8221; If this is so, showing from the Bible that God displays any of these affections towards the non-elect will substantiate the doctrine of common grace. Unfortunately, the scope of this paper is limited to only the term <em>grace</em>. The question I set out to answer is simply this: &#8220;Does the Bible ever say that God shows grace to the reprobate?&#8221; If it does, common grace is a biblical doctrine, and its avowed enemies who condemn it should rightly be silenced.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a> If, however, the Bible does not use the term <em>grace</em> in this way, common grace can still be substantiated in other ways,<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a> but its advocates should be willing to reassess their assertions in light of the biblical evidence. In what follows, I will endeavor to examine the word <em>grace</em> in both its Old and New Testament contexts in order to answer this question. I will only list and comment upon the verses that are relevant to this issue, i.e. God showing grace to those who will never be saved.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Precise Classification</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Before we begin, the question must be asked, &#8220;What does common grace mean?&#8221; Richard Muller, in his <em>Dictionary of Latin and Greek Theological Terms</em>, gives this historic, Reformed definition:</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">i.e., a nonsaving, universal grace according to which God in his goodness bestows his favor upon all creation in the general blessings of physical sustenance and moral influence for the good. &nbsp;Thus, rain falls on the just and the unjust, and all men have the law engraved on their hearts. &nbsp;<em>Gratia communis</em> is therefore contrasted by the Reformed with particular or special grace (<em>gratia particularis sive specialis</em>, q.v.).<a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Though this explanation is adequate, I also believe that the doctrine of common grace includes what Muller calls <em>gratia universalis</em>,<a href="#_ftn5" name="_ftnref5">[5]</a> or what Abraham Kuyper calls general grace,<a href="#_ftn6" name="_ftnref6">[6]</a> i.e. God&#8217;s universal desire for all men to be saved. Nevertheless, the issue is whether or not God has a favorable disposition (or as Muller puts it, &#8220;God in his goodness bestows his favor&#8221;) to the wicked in this present life. Whether that disposition includes a desire to bless the reprobate with physical and/or spiritual good is an altogether different matter and should only be discussed by those who affirm the doctrine of common grace, since those who reject it deny that God desires to bestow any kind of favor on the reprobate.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">I must also assert that the doctrine of common grace relates directly to God&#8217;s preceptive will and not to His decretive will. This dimension of God&#8217;s will truly tells us something about God&#8217;s heart towards His creation, although mystery abounds in attempting to harmonize His universal beneficence with His decree of predestination, election, and reprobation in eternity passed.<a href="#_ftn7" name="_ftnref7">[7]</a> The fact is, if the Bible says that God pours out grace upon those that will never be saved, He is not pretending to do so; He really has a gracious disposition towards all who are created in His own image, sinner and saint alike. In giving providential gifts to the ungodly, God is not just displaying His &#8220;divine power&#8221; but in &#8220;back of the bestowal there is an attitude on the part of God, called love, which constrains him to bestow these tokens of his lovingkindness.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn8" name="_ftnref8">[8]</a> Let us now examine the Scriptures to see if these things are so.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Biblical Concentration</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Does the Bible ever use the term <em>grace</em> in a common or universal way? Even among those who affirm the doctrine of common grace, there is disagreement. For instance, the great Dutch theologian, Herman Bavinck, does not think so. He says, &#8220;Used with reference to God, however, its object is never creatures in general, nor the Gentiles, but only his people.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn9" name="_ftnref9">[9]</a> Is he correct?</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Old Testament Usage of Grace (???/ ?????)</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The noun ??? is used 69 times in the Old Testament, and its verbal form ????? is used 78 times. It is the most common word for grace, favor, acceptance, and good-will. Virtually every example of God showing grace to people in the OT has to do with the elect.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">God bestows grace on Noah (Gen. 6:8), Jacob (Gen. 33:5,11), Benjamin (Gen. 43:29), those whom God decides to be gracious to (Exod. 33:11), Moses (Exod. 33:12,17), the people of Israel (Num. 6:25; Ps. 67:1; 2 Kings 13:23), Gideon (Judges 6:17-18), David (2 Sam. 15:25; Ps. 4:1; 6:2; 9:13; 25:16; 26:11; 27:7; 30:10; 31:9; 41:4,10; 51:1, 56:1, 57:1, 86:3,16; 119:29,58,132), those who walk uprightly (Ps. 84:11), Zion (Ps. 102:13,14), God&#8217;s servants (Ps. 123:2-3), those who never let steadfast love and faithfulness leave them (Prov. 3:4), the humble (Prov. 3:34), a people who shall dwell in Zion (Is. 30:18-19), Isaiah and those who wait for the LORD (Is. 33:2), those who survived the sword (Jer. 31:2), the remnant of Joseph (Amos 5:15), the finished temple/Christ (Zech. 4:7), and the house of David and the inhabitants of Jerusalem (Zech. 12:10).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">God&#8217;s grace is so bound up in His relationship with His people that in two places, David explicitly prays that the Lord would not be gracious to his wicked enemies. He says, &#8220;You, O LORD God of hosts, the God of Israel, Awake to punish all the nations; Do not be gracious to any who are treacherous in iniquity&#8221; (Ps. 59:5). Again, he says, &#8220;Let there be none to extend lovingkindness to him, Nor any to be gracious to his fatherless children&#8221; (Ps. 109:12). More than this, God actually commands the Israelites to show no grace to &#8220;the Hittites, the Girgashites, the Amorites, the Canaanites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites, seven nations more numerous and mightier than you&#8221; (Deut. 7:1-2). Instead, these nations were to be devoted to complete destruction. Additionally, Isaiah prophesies that God will not be gracious to Babylon when He destroys her in the eschaton. He proclaims, &#8220;When its limbs are dry, they are broken off; Women come and make a fire with them, For they are not a people of discernment, Therefore their Maker will not have compassion on them. And their Creator will not be gracious to them&#8221; (Is. 27:11). Even though God is their Maker and Creator, He is under no obligation to show grace to rebellious sinners. It is all freely given to those whom He desires to be gracious to.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">However, there is one place in the OT where God is said to show grace to the wicked. Isaiah 26:10 reads, &#8220;Though the wicked is shown favor, He does not learn righteousness; He deals unjustly in the land of uprightness, And does not perceive the majesty of the LORD.&#8221; The ESV, HCSB, ISV, and the NET Bible all use the word if: &#8220;If favor is shown to the wicked . . .&#8221; This would seem to imply that Isaiah is giving a hypothetical scenario whereby grace is really not shown to the wicked.<a href="#_ftn10" name="_ftnref10">[10]</a> The meaning would be, &#8220;If grace were somehow shown to the wicked, they would still not learn righteousness.&#8221; But I do not believe this verse should be understood as a hypothetical scenario divorced from reality. What Isaiah is saying is a statement of fact: God shows grace to the wicked, though it does not make them any better off. Why do I think this? First, the word <em>if</em> is not found in the original Hebrew. The text literally reads, &#8220;Show favor to the wicked.&#8221; <em>If</em> is supplied by these versions primarily as a matter of interpretation, not translation. Other versions such as the NIV, NASB, and KJV omit this word. Secondly, the context suggests the reality of God being gracious to the wicked. In this passage, Isaiah is stressing the importance of God sending His judgments on the earth. &#8220;All the inhabitants of the earth&#8221; learn righteousness when God&#8217;s judgments are displayed (v. 9). Isaiah says this as a matter of fact. God&#8217;s uplifted hand against sin causes both the righteous and the wicked to fear Him and turn away from evil, even if for the wicked it is only an outward reformation of their lives. Matthew Henry comments,</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">It is God&#8217;s gracious design, in sending abroad his judgments, thereby to bring men to seek him and serve him: When thy judgments are upon the earth, laying all waste, then we have reason to expect that not only God&#8217;s professing people, but even the inhabitants of the world, will learn righteousness, will have their mistakes rectified and their lives reformed, will be brought to acknowledge God&#8217;s righteousness in punishing them, will repent of their own unrighteousness in offending God, and so be brought to walk in right paths.<a href="#_ftn11" name="_ftnref11">[11]</a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">But Isaiah correctly observes in verse 10 that when only grace is shown to the wicked, they will not learn righteousness but go on in their evil and corrupt ways. As Calvin points out, &#8220;. . . the wicked cannot be brought in any way to love God, though he endeavor, by every sort of kindness, to draw and gain them over . . . whatever may be the acts of kindness by which God draws the wicked, they will never learn to act uprightly.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn12" name="_ftnref12">[12]</a> Although God&#8217;s grace is meant to lead them to repentance, they abuse it and distort it by going on in their sin. Therefore, they store up for themselves justly-deserved wrath (Rom. 2:4-5). And that fiery wrath will fall upon their own heads if they continue on in their rebellion (v. 11). Verses 9 and 10 then demonstrate realities which produce separate and polarizing results for the enemies of God. Though God shows grace to the wicked, the wicked show disrespect to God, and their hearts are given fully to do evil (Ecc. 8:11). Therefore, as God pours out grace upon evildoers, God must also unsheathe His iron rod of judgment in order to restrain their sins and teach them righteousness.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">New Testament Usage of Grace (?????/?????????)</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The noun ????? is used 157 times in the New Testament, and its verbal form ????????? is used 23 times. HELPS Word-studies says that grace is &#8220;preeminently used of the Lord&#8217;s <em>favor</em>, freely <em>extended to give Himself</em> away to people (because He &#8216;ever leans toward them&#8217;).&#8221;<a href="#_ftn13" name="_ftnref13">[13]</a> Bavinck adds, &#8220;. . . subjectively, it means favor, a positive disposition on the part of the giver, and gratitude and devotion on the part of the recipient. Ascribed to God, grace is the voluntary, unrestrained, and unmerited favor that he shows to sinners and that, instead of the verdict of death, brings them righteousness and life.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn14" name="_ftnref14">[14]</a> By his definition, Bavinck seems to assert that all grace in the New Testament is <em>saving</em> grace. Is he correct? Here are my findings:</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">God bestows grace on Mary (Lk. 1:30), the young Jesus (Lk. 2:40,52), the children of God (Jn. 1:16), the apostles and the whole church (Acts 4:33), Stephen (Acts 6:8), Joseph (Acts 7:10), David (Acts 7:46), the new converts in the church at Antioch (Acts 11:23), newly converted Jews and God-fearing proselytes (Acts 13:43), Paul and Barnabus (Acts 14:26), Silas (Acts 15:40), believers in Achaia (Acts 18:27), the Ephesian elders (Acts 20:32), Paul (Acts 27:24, Rom. 1:5; 12:3; 15:15; 1 Cor. 3:10; 15:10; 2 Cor. 12:9; Eph. 3:2,7,8; 1 Tim. 1:14), saints in Rome (Rom. 1:7; 16:20), all believers (Rom. 3:24, 5:2; 5:15,17; 6:14; 8:32; 12:6; 1 Cor. 2:12; 2 Cor. 8:9; Eph. 1:6,7; 2:5,7,8; 4:7,32; Col. 2:13; 3:13), 2 Thess. 1:12; 2:16; 3:18; 2 Tm. 1:9; Tit. 2:11; 3:7; Heb. 2:9; 1 Pet. 1:10,13; 1 Pet. 4:10; 1 Pet. 5:12; 2 Pet. 3:18; Rev. 22:21), a believing remnant of Jews (Rom. 11:5), saints in Corinth (1 Cor. 1:3,4; 16:23; 2 Cor. 1:2; 2 Cor. 9:8,14; 13:14; Gal. 1:15; 2:9), Paul and Timothy (2 Cor. 1:12), new converts (2 Cor. 4:15), the churches of Macedonia (2 Cor. 8:1), the churches of Galatia (Gal. 1:3,6; 6:18), Abraham (Gal. 3:18), the saints in Ephesus (Eph. 1:2; 6:4), the saints at Philippi (Phil. 1:2,29; 4:23), Paul and the Philippian church (Phil. 1:7), the exalted Jesus (Phil. 2:9), the saints at Colossae (Col. 1:2,6; 4:18), the church of the Thessalonians (1 Thess. 1:1; 5:28; 2 Thess. 1:2), Timothy (1 Tm. 1:2; 6:21, 2 Tm. 1:2; 2:1; 4:22), Titus (Tit. 1:4), Titus and the Cretan believers (Tit. 3:15), Philemon (Phlm. 1:3,25), the Hebrew churches (Heb. 13:25), the humble (Jam. 4:6), the elect exiles of the Dispersion (1 Pet. 1:2; 2 Pet. 1:2, those who suffer for righteousness&#8217; sake (1 Pet. 2:20). Christian husbands and wives (1 Pet. 3:7), the elect lady and her children (2 Jn. 1:3), and the seven church in Asia (Rev. 1:4).<a href="#_ftn15" name="_ftnref15">[15]</a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">As it was in the OT, so it is in the New: virtually all NT references to God&#8217;s grace concern God&#8217;s favor towards His people. But there are a few places that seem to say otherwise.</span></p>
<p><strong> <span style="font-size: x-large;">1.) The Blind</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Luke 7:21 reads, &#8220;In that hour He healed many people of diseases and plagues and evil spirits, and on many who were blind He bestowed sight.&#8221; Jesus did this to demonstrate to John the Baptist and his disciples that He was the promised Messiah who would bring about cosmic restoration to a world shattered by sin (vv. 22-23). In verse 21, the verb &#8220;bestowed&#8221; is the Greek verb &#8220;to show grace.&#8221; It was Jesus who &#8220;graced&#8221; sight on many of the blind. His gracious disposition toward them moved Him to heal them of their physical infirmities. Now I think most would agree that during His earthly ministry, Jesus performed physical miracles upon some who never experienced the spiritual miracle of regeneration.<a href="#_ftn16" name="_ftnref16">[16]</a> If this was the case, we have good reason to believe that from this passage Jesus showed grace to some who were never saved. Unless one will argue that all those who received their sight were the elect, here is an instance where the God-man gave gracious blessings to some who would never have the eyes of their hearts opened to behold His glory.</span></p>
<p><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">2.) Unloving Debtors</span></strong><a href="#_ftn17" name="_ftnref17"><strong>[17]</strong></a></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">In Luke 7:41-42, Jesus tells this parable: &#8220;A moneylender had two debtors: one owed five hundred denarii, and the other fifty. When they were unable to repay, he graciously forgave them both. So which of them will love him more?&#8221; The phrase &#8220;graciously forgave&#8221; is the Greek verb &#8220;to be gracious.&#8221; Both of these debtors were &#8220;graced&#8221; of their debts by the moneylender. The one who had a lesser debt was Simon the Pharisee, and the one who had the greater debt was the woman crying at Jesus&#8217; feet. Jesus refers to Himself as the moneylender. Both Simon and the woman had their sins &#8220;graced&#8221; by Jesus, yet only the woman went home that day forgiven and justified.<a href="#_ftn18" name="_ftnref18">[18]</a> Granting that we must be careful in our interpretation of parables, this parable still teaches us something about the disposition of Christ to sinners. We learn that Jesus can be gracious and merciful to some who are never truly forgiven. He can show grace to Pharisees, although not all Pharisees thank and love Him for it.</span></p>
<p><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">3.) All Professing Believers</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">There are several interesting passages that speak about God&#8217;s grace to those who are in danger of falling away or who have already apostatized. They are 2 Corinthians 6:1, Galatians 5:4, Hebrews 10:29, and Hebrews 12:15. In 2 Corinthians 6:1, Paul says, &#8220;Working together with Him, then, we appeal to you not to receive the grace of God in vain.&#8221; Similarly, Paul says in Galatians 5:4, &#8220;You are severed from Christ, you who would be justified by the law; you have fallen away from grace.&#8221; In Hebrews 10:29 he says, &#8220;How much worse punishment, do you think, will be deserved by the one who has trampled underfoot the Son of God, and has profaned the blood of the covenant by which he was sanctified, and has outraged the Spirit of grace?&#8221; And again, in Hebrews 12:15 he says, &#8220;See to it that no one fails to obtain the grace of God; that no &#8216;root of bitterness&#8217; springs up and causes trouble, and by it many become defiled.&#8221; How do we understand these passages? Does God give His grace (and even the Spirit of grace) to those who eventually fail to obtain salvation? Is Paul saying that someone can receive the grace of God in vain and so be eternally lost? Paul seems to think that this was a real possibility! Calvin did too. He said that sinners could &#8220;willfully render useless [God&#8217;s] grace, by which they had been favored.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn19" name="_ftnref19">[19]</a> Of course, I am not referring to the efficacious grace of God. If a professing believer would perish in his sin, it would only prove that these passages were talking about the offer of grace or the common gracious operations of the Holy Spirit upon the reprobate, i.e. resistible grace, not effectual saving grace to the elect. But the fact remains, Paul taught that there is some sort of grace in the outward call of the gospel that professing believers could receive in vain, profane, fall away from, or fail to obtain through their own slothfulness and hardheartedness. He can only give these exhortations because God is really offering and holding out grace to everyone who hears the gospel. But, as John Gill points out, even this &#8220;declaration of the love and grace of God to sinners&#8221; can be resisted and received in vain &#8220;when it is but notionally received, or received in word only: when it is abused and perverted to vile purposes, and when men drop, deny it, and fall off from it.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn20" name="_ftnref20">[20]</a> God, then, shows grace to those who finally prove themselves to be goats amidst the sheepfold.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Concluding Comments</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Are the PRC and other Hyper-Calvinists correct in saying that the term <em>grace</em> is only reserved for the elect and their salvation? Not entirely. Hanko&#8217;s assertion that in the Bible the word <em>grace</em> is never used in reference to the reprobate wicked is not biblical. There may be only one reference to God showing grace to the non-elect in the Old Testament (Is. 26:10), but it is an important one. In the New Testament, however, there may be several places where God shows grace to those who finally perish in their sins. I admit that if this word study teaches us anything, it is this: God has a special, saving grace reserved only for His people. Nearly every reference to the term <em>grace</em> refers to God&#8217;s special favor and love for the elect. Both Old and New Testaments seem adamant about jealously reserving the grace of God for the people of God and no others. But there are exceptions to the rule. Isaiah 26:10 affirms that God shows grace to the wicked, Luke 7:21 and Luke 7:41-42 imply that Jesus showed grace to some who were never saved, and passages such as 1 Corinthians 6:1 and Hebrews 10:29 teach us that God offers grace through the gospel to all professing believers, even those who eventually fall away. These usages are by far rare, but from examining how the Bible uses this word, we stand on sure and steady ground to declare that common grace is a biblical doctrine. The Bible proves God shows grace to the wicked. And if space were permitted, the same could be said for God&#8217;s common love,<a href="#_ftn21" name="_ftnref21">[21]</a> steadfast love,<a href="#_ftn22" name="_ftnref22">[22]</a> mercy,<a href="#_ftn23" name="_ftnref23">[23]</a> goodness,<a href="#_ftn24" name="_ftnref24">[24]</a> compassion,<a href="#_ftn25" name="_ftnref25">[25]</a> longsuffering,<a href="#_ftn26" name="_ftnref26">[26]</a> and blessing.<a href="#_ftn27" name="_ftnref27">[27]</a></span></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Ron Hanko, &#8220;Common Grace: Is it Biblical?&#8221; (audio of sermon, Loughbrickland, Northern Ireland, February 3, 1995), tinysa.com/sermon/22706142927.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> For instance, David Engelsma, in his book <em>Christianizing the World</em>, says, &#8220;The theory of common grace is not only condemned by scripture, but also is refuted by history and experience.&#8221; See David J. Engelsma, <em>Christianizing the World</em> (Jenison, MI: Reformed Free Publishing Association, 2016), 133.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Even if the Bible never used the precise terminology of common or universal grace, the concept could still be encoded in the pages of Scripture. We must not commit the word/concept fallacy. We recognize that the words Trinity, the hypostatic union, the Covenant of Works, the Covenant of Grace, and amillenialism are not found in the Bible, but the concepts are present. Matthew 5:43-48 and Luke 6:27-36 do not explicitly say that God is loving and merciful to the reprobate, but sound exegesis of these texts proves that these concepts are certainly implied.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> Richard Muller, <em>Dictionary of Latin and Greek Theological Terms</em> (Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Academic, 1995), 130.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref5" name="_ftn5">[5]</a> Ibid, 133. Muller defines universal grace as &#8220;that grace of God in the universal call of the gospel according to which salvation is offered to all.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref6" name="_ftn6">[6]</a> Discussed by Engelsma in <em>Christianizing the World</em>, 164.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref7" name="_ftn7">[7]</a> One way of reconciling this blessed paradox while upholding God&#8217;s simplicity and impassibility is differentiating between God&#8217;s will of propension and God&#8217;s will of volition/purpose. R.L. Dabney states, &#8220;. . . God does have compassion for the reprobate, but not express volition to save them, because his infinite wisdom regulates his whole will and guides and harmonizes (not suppresses) all its active principles.&#8221; In other words, God can possess &#8220;natural propensions of pity towards persons whom his wisdom restrains him from ever purposing to save.&#8221; See R.L. Dabney, &#8220;God&#8217;s Indiscriminate Proposals of Mercy, As Related to His Power, Wisdom, and Sincerity,&#8221; <em>The Princeton Review</em> (1878), accessed September 21, 2017, <a href="http://www.romans45.org/dabney/mercy.htm">http://www.romans45.org/dabney/mercy.htm</a>.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref8" name="_ftn8">[8]</a> John Murray, &#8220;The Free Offer of the Gospel&#8221; (report presented to the Fifteenth (1948) General Assembly of the Orthodox Presbyterian Church, Wildwood, NJ, May 1948), accessed September 13, 2017, <a href="http://opc.org/GA/free_offer.html">http://opc.org/GA/free_offer.html</a>. Engelsma argues in <em>Christianizing the World </em>that providence is not grace but divine power. He goes on to say that &#8220;God&#8217;s providence is his power upholding and governing the creation he made in the beginning. In his providence, God maintains even the ungodly in their humanity, so that they can develop the creation, uncovering and using its bounties; order their society, especially by government; and in general direct their life together in such a way as to benefit themselves and avoid many evils. But providence is not inherently grace and blessing, not even in the instances in which providence provides the ungodly with many good gifts, for example order in society, or health, or nourishing food. The things themselves are good, but if God gives them to a man or woman in his wrath and if the man or woman uses and enjoys them without acknowledgement of God the giver, without gratitude to God, and without a use of them that serves God, the things are a curse to the one who so misuses them. . . . To the reprobate unbeliever, all the good things of providence are a curse in divine wrath, exposing his inexcusable wickedness and increasing his guilt (135-6). I agree that the wicked twist and distort the good gifts of God to their own destruction. But their intentions and motives are not the issue. Our concern has to do with the disposition of God in giving these things. If the Bible specifically says that God shows grace to the wicked, His providential gifts of &#8220;health, earthly riches, a good job, and the order kept by civil government&#8221; flow not from divine power or wrath but are &#8220;inherently, necessarily, and always grace and grace&#8217;s blessings&#8221; (70). It would be a contradiction in terms if God &#8220;graced&#8221; the reprobate out of His wrath and hatred for him!</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref9" name="_ftn9">[9]</a> Herman Bavinck, <em>Reformed Dogmatics: God and Creation</em>, ed. John Bolt, trans. John Vriend (1895; repr., Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Academic, 2004), 2:214.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref10" name="_ftn10">[10]</a> This is in fact how Franz Delitzsch interprets Isaiah&#8217;s words: &#8220;???? ??? is a hypothetical clause, which is left to be indicated by the emphasis, like Nehemiah 1:8 (Ewald, 357, b): granting that favour (che?n equals &#8220;goodness,&#8221; Romans 2:4) is constantly shown to the wicked man.&#8221; See Franz Delitzsch, <em>Commentary on the Old Testament: Isaiah</em>, trans. James Martin (repr., Grand Rapids, MI: William B. Eerdmans, 1991), 7:446.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref11" name="_ftn11">[11]</a> Matthew Henry, <em>Matthew Henry&#8217;s Commentary on the Whole Bible</em>, vol. 4, <em>Isaiah to Malachi</em> (repr., Peabody, MA: Hendrickson Publishers, 2011), 109.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref12" name="_ftn12">[12]</a> John Calvin, <em>Commentary on Isaiah &#8211; Volume 2</em>, trans. William Pringle (Grand Rapids, MI: Christian Classics Ethereal Library, 2005), 178-79, accessed September 14, 2017, <a href="http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom14.pdf">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom14.pdf</a>.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref13" name="_ftn13">[13]</a> <em>HELPS Lexicon</em>, s.v. &#8220;Charis,&#8221; accessed September 14, 2017, <a href="http://thediscoverybible.com/">http://thediscoverybible.com/</a>.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref14" name="_ftn14">[14]</a> Bavinck, <em>Reformed Dogmatics, </em>2:214.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref15" name="_ftn15">[15]</a> God bestowing grace on Christians is a rather broad category. To be more specific, BDAG states, &#8220;The context will show whether the emphasis is upon the <em>possession of divine grace</em> as a source of blessings for the believer, or upon a <em>store of grace </em>that is dispensed, or a <em>state of grace </em>(i.e. standing in God&#8217;s favor) that is brought about, or a <em>deed of grace </em>wrought by God in Christ, or a <em>work of grace </em>that grows fr. more to more.&#8221; See Walter Bauer et al., <em>A Greek-English Lexicon of the New Testament and Other Early Christian Literature</em>, 2nd ed. (Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1979), 878.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref16" name="_ftn16">[16]</a> A prime example of this would be what happened to the large crowd of 5,000. Jesus had compassion on them, healed them, and fed them (Matt. 14:13-21; Jn. 6:1-15). They both witnessed and experienced physical miracles. But later on Jesus told them, &#8220;Truly, truly, I say to you, you are seeking Me, not because you saw signs, but because you ate your fill of the loaves. Do not work for the food that perishes, but for the food that endures to eternal life, which the Son of Man will give to you. For on Him God the Father has set his seal&#8221; (Jn. 6:26-27). What was the result of this conversation? &#8220;After this many of His disciples turned back and no longer walked with Him&#8221; (Jn. 6:66). &nbsp;Many of the same disciples who partook of Jesus&#8217; physical miracles (restored physical health) did not partake of Jesus&#8217; spiritual miracles (eternal life). They were blessed materially, not spiritually.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref17" name="_ftn17">[17]</a> It is interesting to note that in another parable about debtors (The Parable of the Unforgiving Debtor in Matt. 18:23-35), the king/master, who represents Jesus&#8217; heavenly Father (v. 35), shows patience (??????????) (v.26), compassion (?????????????) (v.27), and mercy (?????) (v. 33) to one who eventually ends up in jail for the rest of his life due to his unforgiving heart. This parable teaches us that God shows patience, compassion, and mercy to sinners who are eventually thrown into the dungeon of hell for all eternity.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref18" name="_ftn18">[18]</a> Calvin comments that Simon was probably not forgiven: &#8220;From the words of Christ, therefore, we are not at liberty to infer, that Simon had been a debtor to a small amount, or that he was absolved from guilt. It is more probable that, as he was a blind hypocrite, he was still plunged in the filth of his sins.&#8221; See John Calvin, <em>Commentary on a Harmony of the Evangelists, Matthew, Mark, and Luke &#8211; Volume 2</em>, ed. William Pringle (Grand Rapids, MI: Christian Classics Ethereal Library, 2005), 115, accessed September 14, 2017, http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom32.pdf.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref19" name="_ftn19">[19]</a> John Calvin, <em>Commentary on Hebrews</em>, ed. John Owen (Grand Rapids, MI: Christian Classics Ethereal Library, 2005), 218, accessed September 13, 2017, <a href="http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom44.pdf">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom44.pdf</a>. Here is the full quote: &#8220;Hence learn that all who willfully render useless his grace, by which they had been favored, act disdainfully towards the Spirit of God.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref20" name="_ftn20">[20]</a> John Gill, &#8220;The Second Epistle of Paul the Apostle to the Corinthians,&#8221; in <em>The Baptist Commentary Series Volume I: John Gill&#8217;s Exposition of the Old and New Testaments</em>, vol. 8, <em>John to Galatians</em> (1809; repr., Paris, AR: The Baptist Standard Bearer, 2006), 793-94.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref21" name="_ftn21">[21]</a> In the OT, God sets His love on Cyrus (Is. 48:14) and the idolatrous children of Israel (Hos. 3:1). In the NT, Jesus as the God-man loves sinners and tax collectors (Matt. 11:19; Lk. 7:34) and the unconverted rich young man (Mk. 10:21), and God the Father loves sinful mankind in general (Jn. 3:16; Tit. 3:4).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref22" name="_ftn22">[22]</a> In the OT, God&#8217;s steadfast love fills the earth (Ps. 33:5; 119:64). If steadfast love only refers to God&#8217;s covenant love, how can God show <em>hesed</em> to sinners and saints alike? It may be that this love is displayed in the general blessings that come to the whole world due to the Noahic Covenant (Gen. 9:8-17). If this is the case, even the chief of wicked reprobates is a recipient of God&#8217;s <em>hesed</em>.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref23" name="_ftn23">[23]</a> In the OT, God shows mercy to the stiff-necked and hard-hearted people of Judah (2 Chron. 36:15-17). In the NT, God in Jesus shows mercy to a demon possessed boy (Matt. 17:14-18), the unforgiving servant (Matt. 18:33), and the ten lepers (Mk. 10:11-19).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref24" name="_ftn24">[24]</a> In a partial study of the OT, God&#8217;s goodness extends to Jacob&#8217;s family and the surrounding nations (Gen. 50:20), the nation of Israel in general (Exod. 3:8/Deut. 1:25; Exod. 18:9; Num. 10:29,32; Deut. 6:24/10:13; 8:10; 26:11; Josh. 21:45; 1 Kings 8:56; Neh. 9:20), and wicked men (Job 22:18). In the NT, God is good to those who labor and are heavy laden (Matt. 11:28-30), the hungry (Lk. 1:53), the ungrateful and the evil (Lk. 6:35), the rich man in hell (Lk. 16:25), those at the wedding feast in Cana (Jn. 2:1-11), pagans at Lystra (Acts 14:17), hypocrites (Rom. 2:4), those who do good and submit to civil authorities (Rom. 13:4), those who committed the unpardonable sin (Heb. 6:4-6), and everyone who receives something good from the hands of God (Jam. 1:17).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref25" name="_ftn25">[25]</a> In the OT, God shows compassion on the idolatrous and blasphemous Israelites (Neh. 9:19) and on all that He has made (Ps. 145:9). In the NT, God through Christ feels compassion on the crowds (Matt. 9:36; 14:14; 15:32; Mk. 6:34; 8:2), the unforgiving debtor (Matt. 18:27), and the prodigal son (Lk. 15:20).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref26" name="_ftn26">[26]</a> In the OT, God exercises longsuffering toward the rebellious and stiff-necked Israelites (Neh. 9:17). In the NT, God is patient with a faithless and twisted generation (Matt. 17:17; Mk. 9:19; Lk. 9:41), the unforgiving debtor (Matt. 18:26), hypocrites (Rom. 2:4), vessels of wrath prepared for destruction (Rom. 9:22), and the wicked who were destroyed by the Flood (1 Pt. 3:20).</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref27" name="_ftn27">[27]</a> In the OT, God blesses Noah and his sons (Gen. 9:1), Ishmael (Gen. 17:20), and Laban (Gen. 30:27,30). In the NT, God in Christ blesses children (Mk. 10:16) and the Old Covenant Jews (Acts 3:26).</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/does-the-bible-teach-common-grace/">Does the Bible Teach Common Grace?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/does-the-bible-teach-common-grace/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>(part 7 of 7)A Critical Review of “He Died for Me”</title>
		<link>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-7-of-7/</link>
					<comments>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-7-of-7/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rexford Semrad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2017 10:47:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Offer of the Gospel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[He Died for Me]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeffrey Johnson]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7957</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>part 1, part 2, part 3, part 4, part 5, part 6 Johnson, Jeffrey. He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#38; the Universal Gospel. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp. Critical Evaluation (Continued) An alternate solution While I commend Johnson for defending the free and well-meant offer of the gospel, I am convinced [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-7-of-7/">(part 7 of 7)A Critical Review of “He Died for Me”</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/">part 1</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/">part 2</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/">part 3</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-4-of-7/">part 4</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-5-of-7/">part 5</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-6-of-7/">part 6</a></p>
<p>Johnson, Jeffrey. <a href="http://amzn.to/2vxSX9C" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><em>He Died for Me: Limite</em></strong><strong><em>d Atonement &amp; the Universal Gospel</em></strong></a>. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Critical Evaluation (Continued)</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>An alternate solution</strong></span></p>
<p>While I commend Johnson for defending the free and well-meant offer of the gospel, I am convinced that he is going about it the wrong way.  The key to understanding the well-meant offer is not found by delving into the secret, decretive will of God and asking, “for whom did Christ die?”  Rather, it is found in rightly upholding and believing the preceptive will of God.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></p>
<p>Quite simply, what God commands, He actually desires.  When God commands all men everywhere to repent and believe the gospel, He actually wants all men everywhere to repent and believe the gospel.  When Jesus Christ invites sinners to come to Him, He really desires that they come to Him.  The rationalism of the Hyper-Calvinist declares that this cannot be so, because we cannot say that God wants what He has not decreed.  But to defend God’s decretive will by denying His preceptive will is not biblical.</p>
<p>Allow me to illustrate.  God commands all men to be faithful to their wives.  So if a man came to us and asked, “Does God want me to cheat on my wife?” we would emphatically reply, “Of course not!  He has commanded you not to commit adultery.”  We would not say, “Let’s wait and see.  If God has decreed that you will cheat on your wife, you will, and then we will know that He wanted you to.”  The fact that God’s decree is His will cannot be allowed to negate the fact that God’s command is His will.  The implications of the idea that God does not really desire what He commands can be devastating and we must never allow ourselves to be guilty of doing this.</p>
<p>So, in the very same way that I can tell every pregnant woman that God <em>earnestly desires</em> that she refrain from murdering her baby at Planned Parenthood, I can tell anyone and everyone that God <em>sincerely desires</em> that they repent of their sins and trust in the Lord Jesus Christ for the eternal welfare of their souls.  We should not shrink back for a moment from the statement that God desires all men to be saved and come to the knowledge of the truth. But neither should we shrink back from the truth that God has by His decree determined that most will not do so.  Perhaps in eternity God will give us some insight as to how these two truths coincide, but for now, it is our place to hold them both in tension, for both truths are revealed in the Word of God.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></p>
<p>I am not proposing two opposing wills in God.  We must be careful not to speak of God as if He were schizophrenic. William Perkins explains:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #333333;">There is but one will in God. Yet God does not equally will all things, but wills all things in divers respects. He does not will and nil the same thing. He wills the conversion of Jerusalem, in that he approves it as a good thing in itself. In that he commands it, and exhorts men to repent and believe and be converted. It is also good in that he gives them the outward means of their conversion. But, He does not will it in that he did not decree effectually to work their conversion. For God approves he may require many things which nevertheless for just causes known to himself, he will not do. <a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Conclusion</strong></span></p>
<p>Clearly, there are a number of points with which I am in disagreement with Johnson, and I cannot accept many of his arguments or his primary thesis.  A more revealing title for the book would be <em>He Died for the Reprobate</em>.  Yet I would not hesitate to recommend this book (with obvious qualifications) to anyone who already has a solid understanding of the doctrines of grace.  While I do not think Johnson’s arguments against John Owen’s <a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a> view of particular redemption actually hold water, I still think it is good for them to be heard.  Too many Calvinists today have never been exposed to anything but Owen’s view, and Johnson does a fantastic job of introducing his readers to viewpoints of other Reformed theologians.</p>
<p>I think many Calvinists who read this book will have a gut reaction to declare that Johnson is not really Reformed, that he is an Amyraldian or four-point Calvinist, and simply dismiss him out of hand.  I strongly exhort anyone with this temptation to refrain from such conclusions!  Just because Johnson rejects John Owen’s method of defending the doctrine of limited atonement does not mean he rejects the doctrine itself.  He is not outside the Reformed tradition.  A perusal of the original sources the he quotes for support will make this clear.  Though they may not all support his thesis as much as he would like, he is not abusing them.  Anyone still not convinced need only to read p. 402 in vol. 3 of Bavinck’s <em>Reformed Dogmatics</em>.</p>
<p>Johnson is a talented writer as well as a faithful minister of the Word of God.  <em>He Died for Me</em> has been the catalyst that caused me to give more thought than ever before to the atonement we have in Christ Jesus, and for that I am forever in his debt.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Deut. 29:29.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> For an excellent discussion of this point, see John Calvin, <em>Institutes of the Christian Religion</em>, Book 1, Chapter 8, Section 3.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> William Perkins, <em>A Treatise of God’s Free Grace and Man’s Free Will</em>, (2012, Puritan Publications) Kindle Edition.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> Johnson brings up Owen sixty times in this book.  It is clear that one of his primary goals is to reject Owen’s view of the atonement.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/rex/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/03/23164330/rex-semrad.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/rex/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Rexford Semrad</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Rexford Semrad has served as an administrator at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary since 2015. He is married to his wife of 32 years, Marion, and has 8 children. He is a member of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, KY where he serves as a Deacon and a Gifted Brother. Among other things, Rex particularly enjoys theology, hot sauce and Church history.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-7-of-7/">(part 7 of 7)A Critical Review of “He Died for Me”</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-7-of-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>(part 6 of 7) A Critical Review of “He Died for Me&#8221;</title>
		<link>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-6-of-7/</link>
					<comments>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-6-of-7/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rexford Semrad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2017 10:47:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1 John 2:2]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[He Died for Me]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeffrey Johnson]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7954</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>part 1, part 2, part 3, part 4, part 5 Johnson, Jeffrey. He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#38; the Universal Gospel. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp. Critical Evaluation (Continued) A test case It will be helpful, I think, to take a moment to apply Johnson’s ideas directly to one of the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-6-of-7/">(part 6 of 7) A Critical Review of “He Died for Me&#8221;</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/">part 1</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/">part 2</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/">part 3</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-4-of-7/">part 4</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-5-of-7/">part 5</a></p>
<p>Johnson, Jeffrey. <a href="http://amzn.to/2vxSX9C" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><em>He Died for Me: Limite</em></strong><strong><em>d Atonement &amp; the Universal Gospel</em></strong></a>. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Critical Evaluation (Continued)</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>A test case</strong></span></p>
<p>It will be helpful, I think, to take a moment to apply Johnson’s ideas directly to one of the texts he believes supports his thesis, and see how it fits.  1 John 2:2 is the text we will examine, but we will include verse 1 for added context.  “My little children, I am writing these things to you so that you may not sin. And if anyone sins, we have an Advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous; <sup>2</sup> and He Himself is the propitiation for our sins; and not for ours only, but also for those of the whole world.”</p>
<p>Notice first, John is offering comfort and encouragement to his little children, that if (and when) they sin, they have an Advocate (intercessor, mediator) with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous.  In order to strengthen this consolation further, John reminds them of one of the primary aspects of Christ’s advocacy on their behalf:  He is the propitiation for their sins.  What is more comforting when we have sinned than bringing to remembrance the truth that Jesus Christ Himself is the propitiation for our sins?  The wrath of God for our sins has been turned away from us by the atoning sacrifice of His Son on our behalf.</p>
<p>John adds that Christ is not the propitiation for our sins only, but for the sins of the whole world.  Now, if Johnson is correct, what John is saying is that Christ has not only propitiated the wrath of God against the sins of His people, but has also turned the wrath of God away from everyone in the world.  The manner in which He has turned away the wrath of God against the whole world is that He is an effectual propitiation only for the elect, but He is also a sufficient but ineffectual propitiation for the reprobate.</p>
<p>My question is this: how does the additional information that Christ has also sufficiently though ineffectually turned the wrath of God away from the reprobate bring any consolation to John’s dear little children?  Johnson says, “The fact that it can be said to all that Christ ‘died for our sins’ gives the elect the inward assurance that the promise of forgiveness includes them” (114). But I beg to differ.  I cannot fathom how believing that Christ died not only for the elect, but also ineffectually for the reprobate can bring inward assurance to the elect that forgiveness of sins includes them.  How does the idea that Christ also died for those who still suffer eternally for their sins provide any comfort?  No, the comfort of Christians is the sure and certain knowledge that they have come to Christ who has appeased the wrath of God in their behalf and in behalf of all who will ever come to Him, and He will never cast them away. <a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></p>
<p><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-7-of-7/"><strong><em>Part 7</em></strong></a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> For an interpretation that does bring comfort, see Calvin’s comments on this passage in <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/">part 3</a>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/rex/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/03/23164330/rex-semrad.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/rex/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Rexford Semrad</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Rexford Semrad has served as an administrator at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary since 2015. He is married to his wife of 32 years, Marion, and has 8 children. He is a member of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, KY where he serves as a Deacon and a Gifted Brother. Among other things, Rex particularly enjoys theology, hot sauce and Church history.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-6-of-7/">(part 6 of 7) A Critical Review of “He Died for Me&#8221;</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-6-of-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 5 of 7)</title>
		<link>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-5-of-7/</link>
					<comments>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-5-of-7/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rexford Semrad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2017 10:47:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Free Offer of the Gospel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[He Died for Me]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeffrey Johnson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[well-meant offer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7950</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>part 1, part 2, part 3, part 4 Johnson, Jeffrey. He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#38; the Universal Gospel. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp. Critical Evaluation (Continued) The well-meant offer of the gospel Johnson spends eleven pages on what he calls The Theological Argument for Universal Sufficiency (133-143). While statements like, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-5-of-7/">A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 5 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: small;"><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/">part 1</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/">part 2</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/">part 3</a></span>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-4-of-7/">part 4</a></p>
<p>Johnson, Jeffrey. <a href="http://amzn.to/2vxSX9C" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><em>He Died for Me: Limite</em></strong><strong><em>d Atonement &amp; the Universal Gospel</em></strong></a>. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Critical Evaluation (Continued)</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>The well-meant offer of the gospel</strong></span></p>
<p>Johnson spends eleven pages on what he calls The Theological Argument for Universal Sufficiency (133-143). While statements like, “And if we are commissioned to call all to repentance and faith in the gospel, then there must have been a sufficient provision made for all, or otherwise God is commanding reprobates to place their faith in an empty promise” (141) are not troubling if understood in the sense that Owen does (<a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-4-of-7/">part 4</a>), it becomes a problem when we realize that for Johnson, sufficient provision demands that Christ died for all.  He asks, “…how can we truthfully call all people to [the] gospel of Christ if Christ did not die for all people?” (135).</p>
<p>First of all, I would argue that the idea that coextensive provision is necessary for a genuine, sincere offer is false.  Roger Nicole illustrates this point: “For instance, advertisers who offer some objects on the pages of a newspaper do not feel that honesty in any way demands of them to have a stock coextensive with the circulation figures of the newspaper.  Really, the only requisite for a sincere invitation is this—that if the conditions be fulfilled, that which is offered will actually be granted.”<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> In gospel proclamation we do not tell all men Christ died for them, but we urge all men to come to Christ with the sure and certain promise that every sinner who comes to Him in faith will find a perfect, sufficient and effectual Savior who will never cast him out.</p>
<p>Perhaps a more important point is that <strong>I do not believe Johnson’s solution actually solves his own problem</strong>.  <span style="font-size: large;"><strong><em>If</em></strong></span> we cannot truthfully call all people to the gospel of Christ if Christ did not die for all people,<strong> <em><span style="font-size: large;">then</span> how</em> can we truthfully call all people to the gospel of Christ if Christ only died for all people in an organic manner, but His death is only ever made effectual in those who were already joined to him in federal union at the time of His death?</strong></p>
<p>Johnson’s perceived need to tell all men that Christ died for them is not shared by many of his fellow Moderate Calvinists.  In his notes on Edward Fisher’s <em>The Marrow of Modern Divinity</em>, Thomas Boston is careful to explain that when Fisher says “Christ is dead for you” he does not mean “Christ died for you.”  “Christ is dead for you” means that Christ is available to you, that if you turn to Him in faith you will most assuredly find a sufficient and effectual Savior.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a> He also makes this explicit statement, “Our Lord Jesus Christ died not for, nor took upon him the sins of, all and every individual man, but he died for, and took upon him the sins of, all the elect, (John 10:15, 15:13, Acts 20:28, Eph 5:25, Titus 2:14), and no other doctrine is here taught by our author touching the extent of the death of Christ.”<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></p>
<p>Andrew Fuller urged preachers to take no regard to the secret things of God, such as particular redemption, when freely offering the gospel:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #333333;">There is no contradiction between this peculiarity of design in the death of Christ, and a universal obligation on those who hear the gospel to believe in him, or a universal invitation being addressed to them. If God, through the death of his Son, have promised salvation to all who comply with the gospel; and if there be no natural impossibility as to a compliance, nor any obstruction but that which arises from aversion of heart; exhortations and invitations to believe and be saved are consistent; and our duty, as preachers of the gospel, is to administer them, without any more regard to particular redemption than to election; both being secret things, which belong to the Lord our God, and which, however they be a rule to him, are none to us. If that which sinners are called upon to believe respected the particular design of Christ to save them, it would then be inconsistent; but they are neither exhorted nor invited to believe any thing but what is revealed, and what will prove true, whether they believe it or not. He that believeth in Jesus Christ must believe in him as he is revealed in the gospel, and that is as the Saviour of sinners. It is only as a sinner, exposed to the righteous displeasure of God, that he must approach him.<a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>When Johnson asks, “[I]f Christ’s death is not sufficient for the salvation of all people, then on what basis does God promise to forgive all people?” (136), he is making a mistake.  God nowhere promises to forgive all people!  God promises to forgive all who come to Christ and trust in Him alone for their eternal salvation.  Even if we take our cue from John 3:16, this is plain to see.  For God loved the mass of wicked fallen sinners so much that He sent His only begotten Son, so that every single one of those wicked sinners who trusts in Him will not perish, but have everlasting life.  What makes this a genuine, bona fide offer that does not “push the dishonesty onto God” (137), is not that Christ died for all men in some manner that is only effectual for some of them, but that it is a promise that has never and shall never fail!  Every sinner who comes to Christ will be saved, and we have no need to delve into the secret will of God to make that declaration, or to call men to Christ in honesty and sincerity.</p>
<p><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-6-of-7/"><strong><em>Part 6</em></strong></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> Roger Nicole, “The Case for Definite Atonement,” <em>Evangelical Theological Society Bulletin</em> (Fall 1967), 207. Cited in Joel Beeke, <em>Living for God’s Glory: An introduction to Calvinism</em> (Lake Mary, FL: Reformation Trust, 2008), 96.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Edward Fisher, <em>The Marrow of Modern Divinity</em> (Ross-shire, Scotland: Christian Focus Publications, 2009), 153.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Ibid., 122.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> Andrew Fuller, <em>The Gospel Worthy of All Acceptation</em>, in <em>The Works of Andrew Fuller</em> (East Peoria, IL: Versa Press, 1841; reprint, Carlisle: Banner of Truth Trust, 2007), 171.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/rex/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/03/23164330/rex-semrad.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/rex/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Rexford Semrad</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Rexford Semrad has served as an administrator at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary since 2015. He is married to his wife of 32 years, Marion, and has 8 children. He is a member of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, KY where he serves as a Deacon and a Gifted Brother. Among other things, Rex particularly enjoys theology, hot sauce and Church history.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-5-of-7/">A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 5 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-5-of-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 4 of 7)</title>
		<link>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-4-of-7/</link>
					<comments>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-4-of-7/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rexford Semrad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2017 10:47:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[He Died for Me]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeffrey Johnson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Owen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Limited Atonement]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7945</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>part 1, part 2, part 3 Johnson, Jeffrey. He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#38; the Universal Gospel. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.&#160; 201 pp. Critical Evaluation (Continued) Owen forgot about election? Two of Johnson&#8217;s statements are particularly well suited to make the jaws of his readers drop to the floor: &#8220;However, there is [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-4-of-7/">A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 4 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: small;"><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/">part 1</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/">part 2</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/">part 3</a></span></p>
<p>Johnson, Jeffrey. <a href="http://amzn.to/2vxSX9C" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><em>He Died for Me: Limite</em></strong><strong><em>d Atonement &amp; the Universal Gospel</em></strong></a>. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.&nbsp; 201 pp.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Critical Evaluation (Continued)</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>Owen forgot about election?</strong></span></p>
<p>Two of Johnson&#8217;s statements are particularly well suited to make the jaws of his readers drop to the floor: &#8220;However, there is something Owen did not consider. In fact, it is a crucial element that changes everything. Owen failed to factor in the one gift that God has given His people that was not procured by the death of Christ&#8212;election&#8221; (172), and then, &#8220;Though Owen was right when he said faith was procured by the death of Christ, he did not consider that the cross did not procure election, which is the reason that the saving benefits of the cross, including faith, are only efficaciously applied to the elect in time&#8221; (176).&nbsp; But once I got past the shock of someone accusing John Owen of failing to consider <em>election</em> in his arguments for why the atonement of Christ is only effectual <em>for the elect</em>, I gave the idea a great deal of thought.&nbsp; But I came to the opposite conclusion.</p>
<p>Rather than failing to consider the role of election that Johnson sees in making the atonement effectual to the elect, Owen could not fathom any sense in which there could be an atonement apart from election.&nbsp; Johnson may be comfortable with the idea that &#8220;In its relationship to Christ as Mediator the atonement is universal, but with reference to his work as his people&#8217;s Surety, his redemption is particular&#8221; (179, 180), but Owen never could be.&nbsp; Owen recognized first and foremost, that Christ&#8217;s sacrifice was the Mediator of the Covenant of Grace offering Himself up for those whom the Father had given Him.&nbsp; While His mediatorial sacrifice certainly had repercussions on the reprobate, there is no sense in which that sacrifice could be considered to be made &#8220;for them.&#8221;</p>
<p>For Johnson, <em>(actual) universal sufficiency</em> means that Christ died for all men.&nbsp; So in that sense he is correct when he states, &#8220;Owen could not embrace (actual) universal sufficiency because that which brings about the application of the atonement&#8212;saving faith&#8212;was effectually procured by the death of Christ&#8221; (117).&nbsp;&nbsp; But that was not Owen&#8217;s only argument against the idea of Christ dying for all men. It was not even his primary argument, as is evident: &#8220;it is denied that the blood of Christ was a sufficient price and ransom for all and every one, not because it was not sufficient, but because it was not a ransom.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> For Owen, all things associated with the death of Christ&#8212;ransom, satisfaction, reconciliation, redemption&#8212;could only be understood biblically if they were comprehended with direct reference to the elect.&nbsp; The Bible everywhere speaks of Christ&#8217;s death as substitution, satisfaction, reconciliation and redemption with regard to His chosen people, the church.&nbsp; But the Bible nowhere speaks of Christ as a sufficient but ineffectual Surety, Mediator or Savior for the non-elect.&nbsp; Scripture is equally silent regarding a sacrifice that is a sufficient but ineffectual ransom, a sufficient but ineffectual propitiation or a sufficient but ineffectual redemption.&nbsp; Johnson is correct when he asserts, &#8220;according to Owen, there cannot be two intentions for the death of Christ&#8212;one intention designed to save the elect and another intention designed to provide a way of salvation for the non-elect&#8221; (63, 64).&nbsp; Owen could not fathom a second intention designed to provide a way of salvation for the non-elect, because Scripture nowhere reveals such an idea.</p>
<p>Before moving on from the subject of John Owen, we must recognize that he did not altogether deny the sufficiency of Christ&#8217;s sacrifice to pay for the sins of all men.&nbsp; Johnson admits as much on page 119.&nbsp; But what is not found in Johnson&#8217;s book is the fact that Owen was actually in agreement that Christ&#8217;s sacrifice is sufficient and it does have implications for the indiscriminate publication of the gospel.</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #333333;">Now, this fulness and sufficiency of the merit of the death of Christ is a foundation unto two things:&#8211; First, The general publishing of the gospel unto &#8220;all nations,&#8221; with the right that it hath to be preached to &#8220;every creature,&#8221; Matt. xxviii. 19; Mark xvi. 15; because the way of salvation which it declares is wide enough for all to walk in. There is enough in the remedy it brings to light to heal all their diseases, to deliver them from all their evils. If there were a thousand worlds, the gospel of Christ might, upon this ground, be preached to them all, there being enough in Christ for the salvation of them all, if so be they will derive virtue from him by touching him in faith; the only way to draw refreshment from this fountain of salvation.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>And again,</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #333333;">Secondly, That the Scripture sets forth the death of Christ, to all whom the gospel is preached [unto], as an all-sufficient means for the bringing of sinners unto God, so as that whosoever believe it and come in unto him shall certainly be saved. Thirdly, What can be concluded hence, but that the death of Christ is of such infinite value as that it is able to save to the utmost every one to whom it is made known, if by true faith they obtain an interest therein and a right thereunto, we cannot perceive. This truth we have formerly confirmed by many testimonies of Scripture, and do conceive that this innate sufficiency of the death of Christ is the foundation of its promiscuous proposal to elect and reprobate</span>.<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></p></blockquote>
<p>So, we find disagreement with Johnson, not in his insistence that Christ&#8217;s sacrifice must be sufficient for all if we are indiscriminately to preach the gospel to all men, but rather in his insistence that in order for Christ&#8217;s sacrifice to be sufficient for all men, it must have in some manner been offered for all men.</p>
<p><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-5-of-7/"><em>Part 5</em></a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> John Owen, <em>The Death of Death in the Death of Christ</em>, in <em>The Works of John Owen</em>, ed. William H. Goold, vol. 10 (1850-1853, reprint, Carlisle: Banner of Truth Trust, 1967), 296.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Owen, <em>Works</em>, vol. 10, 297.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Ibid., 376.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/rex/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/03/23164330/rex-semrad.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/rex/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Rexford Semrad</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Rexford Semrad has served as an administrator at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary since 2015. He is married to his wife of 32 years, Marion, and has 8 children. He is a member of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, KY where he serves as a Deacon and a Gifted Brother. Among other things, Rex particularly enjoys theology, hot sauce and Church history.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-4-of-7/">A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 4 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-4-of-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 3 of 7)</title>
		<link>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/</link>
					<comments>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rexford Semrad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 11:54:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[He Died for Me]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeffrey Johnson]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7928</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>part 1, part 2 Johnson, Jeffrey. He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#38; the Universal Gospel. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp. Critical Evaluation (Continued) Exegesis An extremely disappointing aspect of He Died for Me was Johnson’s exegesis, or rather, the lack thereof.  For instance, under the heading The Exegetical Argument for Universal [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/">A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 3 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: small;"><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/">part 1</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/">part 2</a></span></p>
<p>Johnson, Jeffrey. <a href="http://amzn.to/2uStkPA" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><em>He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &amp; the Universal Gospel</em></strong></a>. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Critical Evaluation (Continued)</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>Exegesis</strong></span></p>
<p>An extremely disappointing aspect of <em>He Died for Me</em> was Johnson’s exegesis, or rather, the lack thereof.  For instance, under the heading <em>The Exegetical Argument for Universal Sufficiency</em>, he states: “Though every proof text will be highly contested, such as 1 Timothy 2:4–6, Hebrews 2:9–10, and 1 John 2:2, I’m not sure how much closer the apostle Paul could have been in making a distinction between sufficiency and efficacy when he claimed that Christ “is the Savior of all people, especially of those who believe” (1 Tim. 4:10)” (130). But he does not provide any exegesis for any of these passages.</p>
<p>Instead, Johnson makes the claim that the purpose for the illustration of the brass serpent was to explain how Christ can be the Savior of all people (129, 130), claims that high Calvinists must explain why such terms as <em>all</em> and <em>world</em> do not mean all people (130), and then states that they typically do so by building a case that restricts <em>all</em> and <em>world</em> to the elect (131).  Then he moves on to John 3:15-21.  After a short discussion of why he believes that <em>world</em> in John 3:16 cannot mean the elect alone, he comes to this conclusion: “Both those who hear and believe and those who hear and do not believe have one thing in common—they both heard the universal offer of the gospel. And if they both (believers and unbelievers) heard the offer, it strongly suggests that they both are included in the ‘world’ of the ‘whosoever.’”</p>
<p>Much stands against Johnson’s seemingly assumed interpretations of the four passages he listed.  The limitation of the universal language in these passages is not something artificially imposed by high Calvinists.  Louis Berkhof, whom Johnson repeatedly claims as a moderate Calvinist,<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> provides solid exegetical arguments for the limited nature of the universal language in each of them in his <em>Systematic Theology</em>. <a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a>  And he does not do so by merely equating the world with the elect.  And John Calvin, Johnson’s most quoted moderate Calvinist, would take issue with him on both 1 Timothy 4:10 and 1 John 2:2.</p>
<p>Calvin was far from regarding 1 Timothy 4:10 as proof of sufficiency for all men but efficacy only for the elect.  He did not think the term <em>Savior</em> should be taken in the sense of eternal salvation:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">To make this more clear, it ought to be understood that this is an argument drawn from the less to the greater; for the word <em>soter</em> is here a general term, and denotes one Who defends and preserves. He means that the kindness of God extends to all men. And if there is no man who does not feel the goodness of God towards him, and who is not a partaker of it, how much more shall it be experienced by the godly, who hope in him? <a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>And in reference to 1 John 2:2, Calvin explicitly denies that the Lombardian Formula is suitable to the passage, but declares, “under the word all or whole, he does not include the reprobate, but designates those who should believe as well as those who were then scattered through various parts of the world. For then is really made evident, as it is meet, the grace of Christ, when it is declared to be the only true salvation of the world.” <a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a></p>
<p>I do not know which surprised me more: that he included Hebrews 2:9-10 when the context so clearly indicates that the everyone for whom Christ tasted death was every one of His brethren, or the fact that he seemed to equate the <em>whosoever</em> of John 3:16 with the <em>world </em>of John 3:16.  The phrase translated “whoever believes” is more literally rendered “every believing one” or “every believer” and therefore cannot be a reference to the reprobate as well as the elect or a reference to the world in general.  The final exegetical issue that I will mention comes from another section of the book.  First Corinthians 15:3, according to Johnson, “implies that Paul had no problem telling everyone that ‘Christ died for our sins” (113).  Paul is not speaking to unbelievers in this passage, but rather to the church for whom Christ died.  There is no reason to assume that Paul was here giving a direct quote of the words he used in preaching the gospel to unbelievers.  The fact that there is not one example in any of the Gospels or the book of Acts of anyone telling unbelievers that Christ died for them strongly suggests that this is not the proper interpretation.</p>
<p><i>Continue to </i><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-4-of-7/"><strong>part 4</strong></a><i>.</i></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> While I do not fully reject Johnson’s division of Calvinists into Hyper, High, Moderate, &amp; Low, I’m not sure how helpful it really is, and it definitely seems as if his reasoning for declaring some to be Moderate is a bit arbitrary.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Louis Berkhof, <em>Systematic Theology </em>(1939; reprint, Grand Rapids: Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., 1988), 395-98.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> John Calvin, <em>Calvin’s Commentaries</em>, vol. 21, <em>Commentaries on The Epistles to Timothy, Titus, and Philemon</em> (Edinburgh, Scotland: Calvin Translation Society; reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker Book House, 2009), 112.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> John Calvin, <em>Calvin’s Commentaries</em>, vol. 22, <em>Commentaries on The Catholic Epistles</em> (Edinburgh, Scotland: Calvin Translation Society; reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker, 2009), 173.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/rex/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/03/23164330/rex-semrad.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/rex/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Rexford Semrad</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Rexford Semrad has served as an administrator at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary since 2015. He is married to his wife of 32 years, Marion, and has 8 children. He is a member of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, KY where he serves as a Deacon and a Gifted Brother. Among other things, Rex particularly enjoys theology, hot sauce and Church history.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/">A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 3 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 2 of 7)</title>
		<link>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/</link>
					<comments>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rexford Semrad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 10:02:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[He Died for Me]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Idem]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeffrey Johnson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Owen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tantundem]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7904</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>part 1 Johnson, Jeffrey. He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#38; the Universal Gospel. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp. Critical Evaluation There are several helpful aspects to He Died for Me.  Readers will be exposed to many statements from respected Reformed theologians of the past that may surprise them.  I don’t think [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/">A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 2 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: small;"><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/">part 1</a></span></p>
<p>Johnson, Jeffrey. <a href="http://amzn.to/2uStkPA" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><em>He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &amp; the Universal Gospel</em></strong></a>. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: xx-large;"><strong>Critical Evaluation</strong></span></p>
<p>There are several helpful aspects to <em>He Died for Me</em>.  Readers will be exposed to many statements from respected Reformed theologians of the past that may surprise them.  I don’t think most Calvinists in our day realize how frequently universal language has been used in the past, even by trusted Reformed men who strongly adhere to the doctrine of particular redemption.  Even the reader who is not persuaded by Johnson’s arguments will be better off for taking the time to think through them.  Thinking deeply upon the doctrine of the redemption we have in Jesus Christ will be a blessed consequence of reading this book.  The portions of the book in which Johnson deals directly with the issue of the atonement with regard to the elect are particularly edifying.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong><em>Idem</em> vs. <em>Tantundem</em></strong></span></p>
<p>That being said, I was not persuaded by Johnson’s arguments, and I find that I must take issue with him on a number of points. The first of these is the way he treats <em>idem</em> as quantitative punishment and <em>tantundem</em> as qualitative punishment with regard to the atonement.  His use of these two Latin terms seems to me to be quite out of step with their historical meaning, especially with regard to the later of the two.  In fact, I cannot understand how the term <em>tantundem</em> can properly mean <em>qualitative</em> at all.</p>
<p>These terms began to be used with reference to the atonement when, in the appendix of one of his books, Richard Baxter took issue with Owen’s <em>Death of Death in the Death of Christ</em>.  Owen responded to Baxter with <em>The Death of Christ, the Price He Paid, &amp; the Purchase He made</em>.  Earlier, Owen had contended with Hugo Grotius, because Grotius had argued that Christ’s sufferings were <em>tantundem,</em> meaning that the Father had to agree graciously to accept a lesser payment than was actually owed.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a>  In the discussion with Baxter, Owen used the terms in this way: “I affirm that he paid <em>idem</em>, that is, the same thing that was in the obligation, and not <em>tantundem</em>, something equivalent thereunto, in another kind.” <a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a></p>
<p>The usage of these terms to refer to “the same thing” over against “something equivalent” is present in others as well.  Johnson quotes Thomas Manton as saying, “He was to suffer what we were to suffer; if not the idem (quantitative), every way the same, yet the tantundem (qualitative), that which was sufficient to Christ’s ends, that which was to carry a full resemblance with our punishment” (124). The terms in parentheses are added by Johnson, and seem very misleading to me.  In the context, Manton is speaking of the desertion of Christ by the Father, and his point is that though Christ cannot be forsaken by God in the same manner as the damned will be, yet he did “suffer so much of it as his holy person was capable of.” <a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></p>
<p>This is actually quite interesting, because whether or not Christ’s suffering is <em>idem</em> or <em>tantundem</em> really depends on how one looks at it.  Thomas Brooks also uses the terms to mean <em>the thing itself</em> or <em>something equivalent</em> when he argues that in different respects both <em>idem</em> and <em>tantundem</em> may be affirmed.  In respect to the substance, kind or nature of the suffering, it was <em>idem</em> or the same as the sinner should have undergone, for the punishment due to the sinner is death.  However, in terms of the duration of it or the desperation going along with it, Christ’s suffering was <em>tantundem</em>, not the same, but equivalent. <a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a></p>
<p>While Johnson’s use of <em>tantundem</em> to mean <em>qualitative</em> is troubling, I must also take issue with his understanding of what Owen meant by <em>idem</em>.  He states: “By framing the argument in such a way, Owen presumed that the degree of pain and suffering inflicted on Christ was quantitatively measured out by the number of sins of those imputed to His account” (117). He then provides a quote from Owen, that in isolation appears to back up this claim.  He seems to be equating Owen’s view with what is sometimes referred to as the commercial view of the atonement, that Christ had to suffer a certain amount for each sin of each of the people for whom He died, so much so that had God elected another man or if one of the elect had committed another sin, He would have had to suffer more.</p>
<p>Johnson should know better than to ascribe such an idea to Owen.   He quotes Charles Hodge: “This is not the doctrine of any Church on earth, and never has been” (123).  Now Hodge may have been ignorant of some Calvinistic Baptist views, but he was certainly well aware of the views of Owen, Turretin, and Perkins.</p>
<p>By <em>idem</em>, Owen did not mean that Christ suffered “so much for so many” as Hodge put it, but that the wages paid were the very wages owed, for the wages of sin is death.  “The idem and very thing threatened in the constitution of the law is death. The terminating of that penalty to the person offending was in the commination, and had it not been relaxed, must have been in the execution; but in the constitution of the obligation, which respects purely the kind of penalty, primarily it was not. ‘Death is the reward of sin,’ is all that is there.”<a href="#_ftn5" name="_ftnref5">[5]</a>  As Carl Trueman explains:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">[W]hen responding to Baxter in <em>Of the Death of Christ</em>, Owen makes the point that the penalty required for sin was death. This is an important point: there is a danger when thinking of Christ’s atonement in terms of satisfaction for debt that one can be led astray into thinking in crudely quantitative terms: sin has accumulated x amount of debt; so the penalty is to be paid in terms of x, where x is analogous to money or property. That is not the model with which Owen is operating: the penalty is not quantitative in such a way; rather, it is perhaps better described as qualitative. It is not that Christ has to pile up a heap of suffering to match the offense human beings have given to God; it is that he has to die. Death is the penalty. <a href="#_ftn6" name="_ftnref6">[6]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>So, if what Johnson means when he repeatedly (17, 20, 23, 39, 117, 118, 148, 165, 167, 170) accuses Owen and other high Calvinists of holding a quantitative view of punishment is that they hold some equivalent to the commercial view, he is quite wrong.  If that is not what he means by the quantitative view, then I am completely at a loss for what he really means by either a quantitative or qualitative view.</p>
<p>Continued <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/">Part 3</a>&#8230;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> John Owen, <em>The Death of Christ, the Price He Paid, and the Purchase He Made</em>, in <em>The Works of John Owen</em>, ed. William H. Goold, vol. 10 (1850-1853, reprint, Carlisle: Banner of Truth Trust, 1967), 437.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Ibid., 438</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> Thomas Manton, <em>The Works of Thomas Manton</em>, vol. 2 (Edinburgh: Banner of Truth Trust, 1993), 272.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> Thomas Brooks, <em>A Golden Key to Open Hidden Treasures</em> (1675), p. 96. Kindle.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref5" name="_ftn5">[5]</a> Owen, <em>Death of Christ</em>, 433.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref6" name="_ftn6">[6]</a> Carl R. Trueman “Atonement and the Covenant of Redemption, John Owen on the Nature of Christ’s Satisfaction,” <em>From Heaven He Came and Sought Her: Definite Atonement in Historical, Biblical, Theological, and Pastoral Perspective</em>, eds. David Gibson and Jonathan Gibson (Wheaton, IL: Crossway, 2013), 224.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/rex/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/03/23164330/rex-semrad.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/rex/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Rexford Semrad</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Rexford Semrad has served as an administrator at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary since 2015. He is married to his wife of 32 years, Marion, and has 8 children. He is a member of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, KY where he serves as a Deacon and a Gifted Brother. Among other things, Rex particularly enjoys theology, hot sauce and Church history.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/">A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 2 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Critical Review of &#8220;He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel&#8221; (part 1 of 7)</title>
		<link>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/</link>
					<comments>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rexford Semrad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2017 10:32:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[He Died for Me]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[High Calvinism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeffrey Johnson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Owen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lombardian Formula]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moderate Calvinism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7890</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Johnson, Jeffrey. He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#38; the Universal Gospel. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp. Introduction Much to my dismay and disappointment, an old error seems to have taken a new hold of the minds of many Calvinists in recent years: the denial of the free and well-meant offer of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/">A Critical Review of &#8220;He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel&#8221; (part 1 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Johnson, Jeffrey. <a href="http://amzn.to/2uStkPA" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><em>He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &amp; the Universal Gospel</em></strong></a>. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Introduction</strong></span></p>
<p>Much to my dismay and disappointment, an old error seems to have taken a new hold of the minds of many Calvinists in recent years: the denial of the free and well-meant offer of the gospel.  It is no longer uncommon to hear that God does not desire that every person who hears the proclamation of the gospel should embrace Christ and be saved, or that God’s only purpose in proclaiming the gospel to the reprobate is to harden them and increase their guilt.  Such conclusions are required by the doctrine of limited atonement or particular redemption, are they not?</p>
<p>The answer of the Reformed tradition as a whole and of the Canons of Dort in particular to that question is a resounding “No.” But how can we hold firmly to the two seemingly contradictory doctrines of limited atonement and the free and well-meant offer of the gospel?  Jeffrey Johnson, a Reformed Baptist pastor in Conway, AR, and author of numerous books, has taken up the noble task of helping his readers understand why these doctrines are not actually contrary to one another and can both be embraced simultaneously.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Summary</strong></span></p>
<p>Johnson is convinced that the key to understanding these things rightly is found in a proper view of the Lombardian Formula, which states that the death of Christ is both limited in its efficacy and universal in its sufficiency (15).  He believes that “High Calvinists” such as Theodore Beza, William Perkins, Francis Turretin and John Owen changed or rejected this formula, and rather than holding to “actual” sufficiency, believed only in “hypothetical” sufficiency.  He is convinced that it is critical to reject the “High Calvinist” view for various reasons, and embrace the “Moderate Calvinist” understanding of the sufficiency of the atonement.  He also does a very good job discussing “Low Calvinist” or four-point Calvinist views and recognizes some strengths in their arguments, before explaining why they must ultimately be rejected.</p>
<p>According to Johnson, high Calvinists like John Owen hold to an <em>idem</em> or quantitative view of the atonement, along with Hyper-Calvinists, and this must be rejected for a <em>tantundem</em> or qualitative view.  This is absolutely essential in order to have an atonement that is actually sufficient for the whole world, and in his opinion, such sufficiency is necessary in order for the offer of the gospel to be well-meant.  He asks, “If Christ did not die for the non-elect, are we lying when we command them to believe in the death of Christ for the salvation of their souls? That is, when we preach the gospel to the non-elect, are we offering them a provision that is not there for them to receive?” (135). Johnson’s strongly implied answer to these questions is “yes.”</p>
<p>So how can it be proper to tell all men that Christ died for them if we still hold to the doctrine of limited atonement, as Johnson does?  He finds the answer to this question in a unique, three-fold understanding of union with Christ: federal union, organic union, and personal union.  Since Christ took true humanity upon Himself, He is therefore in organic union with all humankind.  Because this union is with all mankind, and not merely the elect, and because it is a qualitative atonement rather than a quantitative one, “…the price Christ paid to redeem His chosen people” is “a sufficient price to redeem the whole world” (177).  He concludes, “Thus, universal sufficiency is secured by Christ’s organic unity with humanity” (177).</p>
<p>While organic unity is his basis for the sufficiency of Christ’s death for all men, federal union is the basis for Christ’s death being effectual only to the elect.  The elect were in union with Christ in His death on the cross, their sins were imputed to Him in a qualitative sense, and His death effectually purchased faith for them, and them alone.  “This means that what causes the atonement to be efficaciously applied to the elect and not to the non-elect is not anything inherently in the atonement itself. Rather, its efficacy is determined and restricted to those who were already, due to election, in federal union with Christ as He suffered under the wrath of God” (174).</p>
<p>Personal union occurs when the Holy Spirit regenerates the elect and they exercise the faith Christ purchased for them.  It is this personal union with Christ in which all the benefits of His death are effectually applied.</p>
<p>I would summarize his argument this way.  In order to preach the gospel to all men in sincerity, we must be able to tell all men that Christ died for them.  Christ took true human nature upon Himself, therein uniting Himself with all men, and died a qualitative death in that nature.  For that reason we can tell all men that Christ died for them.  But Christ was uniquely in union with His chosen people in His death, and because of that union, He purchased faith for them.  That faith is then exercised in time as the elect are joined to Christ when the Holy Spirit regenerates them and they experience personal union with Him.  This is how the Lombardian Formula, that Christ’s death was sufficient for all men but efficient only for the elect, solves our dilemma and enables us to proclaim the gospel in sincerity without denying particular redemption.</p>
<p>A Critical Evaluation begins with <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/"><strong>part 2.</strong></a></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/rex/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/03/23164330/rex-semrad.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/rex/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Rexford Semrad</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Rexford Semrad has served as an administrator at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary since 2015. He is married to his wife of 32 years, Marion, and has 8 children. He is a member of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, KY where he serves as a Deacon and a Gifted Brother. Among other things, Rex particularly enjoys theology, hot sauce and Church history.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/">A Critical Review of &#8220;He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel&#8221; (part 1 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Critical Review of Donald Macleod&#8217;s &#8220;The Person of Christ&#8221;</title>
		<link>/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/</link>
					<comments>/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 13:48:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donald Macleod]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Person of Christ]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7656</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Introduction Do the ancient creeds of Nicea and Chalcedon accurately describe the person of Christ? Is He truly, very God and very man as these documents teach? Donald Macleod, principal and professor of systematic theology at the Free Church of Scotland College in Edinburgh, Scotland, defends the reliability of these creeds against the onslaught of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/">A Critical Review of Donald Macleod&#8217;s &#8220;The Person of Christ&#8221;</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Introduction</span></strong></p>
<p>Do the ancient creeds of Nicea and Chalcedon accurately describe the person of Christ? Is He truly, very God and very man as these documents teach? Donald Macleod, principal and professor of systematic theology at the Free Church of Scotland College in Edinburgh, Scotland, defends the reliability of these creeds against the onslaught of higher criticism in his book <em>The Person of Christ</em>. Macleod states, “This book…reflects my belief that the great creeds, far from betraying the gospels, faithfully encapsulate their central concern to portray Jesus as the incarnate Son of God” (15). Concerning his approach, Macleod begins his treatment of Christology with one that is &#8220;from above&#8221; and not &#8220;from below.&#8221; As he states himself, &#8220;The New Testament, almost unanimously, presents us with a Christology from above. It starts from the side of his deity, not from that of his humanity&#8221; (22). Part one, then, covers the deity of Christ while part two covers His humanity.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Summary</span></strong></p>
<p>Chapter one deals with the meaning and defense of the virgin birth. Macleod shows how the virgin birth is a miraculous sign that points to the supernatural nature of Christ and the gospel message, the judgment on sinful man, and a new humanity. It also serves to teach us about the divine sonship of Christ, His sinlessness, and the positive roles of the Holy Spirit and Mary. In chapter two, Macleod moves backward one logical step from the virgin birth to the pre-existence of Christ. The Gospel of John, the Epistle to the Hebrews, the Pauline corpus of writings, and parts of the synoptic Gospels provide enough evidence for even the skeptic to conclude that Jesus possessed a self-consciousness prior to His being sent into the world by the Father. But can Christ’s pre-existence be affirmed apart from His deity? Macleod says no: “no formal distinction can be drawn between deity and pre-existence” (57)…A person who was divine could not but be pre-existent. His godhead proved that he could not have come into being in 4 BC” (70). Chapter three presents the reader with a necessary implication of Christ’s pre-existence: His divine sonship. Macleod begins by explaining the term <em>monogenes hyios </em>as it relates to Christ: it refers to the uniqueness, and not the begottenness, of Jesus. He then goes on to deny any ontological subordinationism in the Son and affirms the co-equalness of the Son with the Father. He does, however, affirm economical subordination as it came to be in the covenant of redemption. Chapter four deals with the reliability of the church&#8217;s witness to the deity of Christ. Macleod argues that the Jesus of history is the Christ of faith. The written testimonies of the early church concerning Jesus are both genuine and reliable, but only the testimony of the Holy Spirit will persuade men of their divine authenticity. Macleod comments, &#8220;Scholarship can give a substantial vindication of the facts, but it cannot enable us to see compelling beauty in the face of Jesus. That is possible only when God the Father, through the Holy Spirit, shares with us his own view of his Son&#8221; (118). Chapter five is concerned with explaining the theology of and circumstances surrounding the Nicean Creed&#8217;s famous declaration that &#8220;Christ, as the Son of God, was <em>homoousios</em> (consubstantial) with the Father&#8221; (121). The Arian heresy, which denied Jesus&#8217; self-existence, eternity, and co-equality with God the Father, was the reason for such a statement to be drawn at the Council of Nicea in 325 AD. If Christ was not God, Christianity was a failed and doomed religion. Macleod then goes on to define the contours of the Son&#8217;s consubstantiality with the Father: He is a distinct person, He was eternally begotten of the very essence of the Father (what he terms &#8216;eternal sonship&#8217;), and He was eternally generated, not originated or made. Macleod next explains that <em>homoousios</em> means that the Father and Son are &#8220;one being and one God&#8221; or &#8220;identically one and the same substance&#8221; (139), defines <em>perichoresis</em> in this manner: &#8220;within the one godhead the three persons co-inhere in each other and interpenetrate each other&#8221; (140), argues that <em>filioque</em> should be understood as the procession of the Spirit from the Father and Son relationally, not causally, and affirms that the essence of the Son and the Spirit is <em>autotheos</em> and not subordinate to the Father&#8217;s in any way.</p>
<p>Chapter six begins part two of the book, which is entitled “Very God, Very Man”—Chalcedon &amp; Beyond. In this chapter he covers the incarnation. The heresies of Docetism and Apollinarianism drove the early church to formulate its doctrine of the incarnation around two premises: “Christ took a true human body and he took a reasonable human soul” (161). In other words, Christ partook of all human attributes, including ignorance and emotions, save sin alone in order to save us “from alongside us” (180). Chapter seven addresses the relationship of Christ’s two natures in the Council of Chalcedon. The heresies of Nestorianism and Eutychianism were combatted with the formulation of the hypostatic union of Christ’s two natures. This formula encapsulates three truths: “that Christ is one person; that the union between his two natures arises from the fact that they both belong to one and the same person; and that this one person, the Son of God, is the Agent behind all of the Lord’s actions, the Speaker of all his utterances and the Subject of all his experiences” (189). Macleod ends with an extended discussion of the <em>communication idiomatum </em>in the person of Christ and the <em>enhypostasia </em>of His human nature. Chapter eight deals with the concept of <em>kenosis</em>. In this act of making Himself nothing, Christ did not abandon, retract, or transpose certain attributes of His deity to assume humanity but instead the pre-incarnate Christ, who “occupied a position of the highest imaginable eminence” (212), did not insist on His rights to be served, worshipped, and glorified but voluntarily veiled His glory and made Himself nothing (or vanity) by taking upon Himself a human nature and dying under the curse and wrath of God. Chapter nine touches on the inherent and actual sinlessness of Christ. It is to be remembered that He assumed a perfect human nature, not a fallen one, when He entered into a state of humiliation. Finally, chapter ten presents several modern approaches to the doctrine of Christ divorced from the Chalcedonian Creed. Denials of the incarnation, resurrection, and uniqueness of Christ from different nineteenth and twentieth-century theologians are discussed and dismantled by Macleod.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Critique</span></strong></p>
<p>            Macleod certainly interacts with the entire spectrum of Christological issues and their differing viewpoints in this book. The sheer breadth of the theologians he quotes from and is conversant with is quite impressive. In other words, Macleod has done his homework! But if his goal was to uphold the creeds of the past, I think he was close but missed the bullseye of his target. As stated in the introduction of this paper, Macleod declares his belief that the Nicaean and Chalcedonian creeds “faithfully encapsulate [the gospels’] central concern to portray Jesus as the incarnate Son of God” (15). It is true that throughout this book Macleod constantly battles against those who reject these ancient confessions of faith in order to vindicate them as true summaries of what the Bible teaches concerning the person of Christ. I heartily commend him for entering into the arena of higher criticism and coming out the victor. But in the process, he does seem to modify or even reinterpret certain concepts and terms in these creeds to fit his own theological system. Nowhere is this illustrated more clearly than with Macleod&#8217;s understanding of the Son&#8217;s begottenness.</p>
<p>Macleod is quite clear about rejecting the historical and traditional meaning of the begottenness of Christ. Though he affirms His eternal sonship and begottenness, Macleod takes a modern approach to understanding the term <em>monogenes</em>. He states, “But what is that concept? There is little doubt that <em>monogenes</em> expresses the uniqueness of Jesus. He is the only one of his kind” (72). He goes on to ask,</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">But is there a uniqueness more fundamental than that the Son is uniquely loved? Is he uniquely loved because there is something either in the origin of his existence or in the mode of his existence that is unique? It is extremely doubtful where <em>monogenes</em> by itself refers to uniqueness of origin (73).</span></p></blockquote>
<p>He also states that <em>monogenes </em>carries with it little conceptual content: “It is doubtful that <em>begotten</em> adds anything to <em>Son</em>, apart from laying down that he is Son in a unique way” (73). In another place he states,</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The problem, as we have seen, is that although we know that the Son is distinguished by the fact that he is begotten, we know little or nothing of what divine begottenness is. It carries us little beyond, &#8216;Is the Son of&#8217;&#8230;The truth is, we are lost. We know that the Son is distinguished by the fact that he is begotten, but we do not know what <em>begotten</em> is&#8221; (137).</span></p></blockquote>
<p>He then concludes,</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The following conclusions, then, seem safe. First, <em>monogenes</em> says nothing about origins because the Son is unoriginated. Secondly, it emphasizes the uniqueness of Jesus’ sonship. Thirdly, this uniqueness consists in four things: he is an object of special love, he is the Father’s equal, he is the Father’s likeness and he is an eternal, not an adopted, Son (74).</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Here are my issues with such an approach:</p>
<p>(1) This sort of agnosticism to the term <em>mongenes </em>is absolutely unnecessary. Certainly, if begotten only means “unique” I can understand the mountainous problems Macleod faces. All one would know is that the Son is unique from the Father, but the content of that uniqueness remains shrouded in mystery and only slightly revealed in God&#8217;s plan of redemption. If begottenness is stripped of derivation, causation, or origination, this term really has no meaning at all! In fact, &#8220;Son&#8221; loses all its practical meaning as well! We do, however, know what this term means if we don&#8217;t limit its definition to merely &#8220;unique&#8221; but include the necessary ideas of generation and subordination. Etymologically, there is a good case to be made that <em>monogenes </em>is related to <em>gennao </em>and not <em>ginomai</em>. Although he asserts the opposite, he is mistaken. The King James Version does not “probably rest on a misapprehension” (73) but on the correct interpretation of the word. Sadly, he even goes so far as to quote Raymond Brown, avowed critic of the orthodox faith, to back up his claim! If Macleod would simply allow begottenness to retain its etymological and historical meaning, the derivation and subordination of the Son to the Father would serve as a key distinction between the two divine persons. Begottenness then would supply us with rich content that helps explain the personal distinctions inherent in the immanent Trinity.</p>
<p>(2) Macleod seems to think that the Patristic Fathers believed in an ontological subordination of the Son to the Father which tainted not only their writings but also their creeds. He says that “Christian orthodoxy has been only too willing to allow a subordinationist strain to remain in its own confession, just beside the insistence on Jesus’ deity” (76). He quotes Chrysostom as saying, “If anyone say that the Father is greater, inasmuch as he is the cause of the Son, we will not contradict this.” But Chrysostom was not saying this about the Son’s essence but His person! There is a whole world of difference between saying that the Father is greater than the Son according to His subsistence rather than according to His being!</p>
<p>(3) Though Macleod believes the Greek fathers were wrong to translate <em>monogenes </em>as “only-begotten,” he later criticizes the modern-day theologian Hugh Montefiore for not opting to translate <em>apaugasma </em>as “effulgence” like the Greek fathers did by stating, “The Greek fathers (who, after all, spoke the language) were surely in a better position to evaluate such grammatical niceties” (79). But didn’t virtually all the Greek fathers translate <em>monogenes </em>as only-begotten? If so, Macleod may benefit from a taste of his own medicine!</p>
<p>(4) At times Macleod seems to oppose the very thesis he sets out to defend. His stance is this: “If the Son and the Spirit are God then they are unoriginate (<em>agenetos</em>), that neither generation nor procession can mean origination and hence that all talk of derivation and causation are inappropriate (145).” But he admits that the general position of Patristic theology (and by implication the express teaching of the ancient creeds of Nicaea and Chalcedon) was that the eternal generation of the Son implied derivation, and therefore some sort of subordination (76). Isn’t Macleod contradicting and even arguing against his own claim that these documents “faithfully encapsulate [the gospels’] central concern to portray Jesus as the incarnate Son of God” (15) when he unwittingly charges them with incorrect views on the Son’s generation? The fact is, talk of derivation and causation are in these creeds, and if Macleod is consistent, he would have to call them (or at least parts of them) “inappropriate” instead of “faithful” to the teaching of the New Testament, thereby undermining his entire thesis and siding with the Enlightenment instead of the early church.</p>
<p>(5) It seems to me that Macleod functions as if the categories of subordination are only economical and ontological. It appears that he entirely bypasses the category of subordination of hypostases/modes of subsistences. This is seen when he fails to distinguish between the persons of the Trinity and the being of the Trinity as he denies generation and subordinationism. He claims that since Christ is the eternal Son He has no origin. That of course is true concerning the Son of God’s essence. He is <em>homousias </em>with the Father and <em>autotheos</em>. But what about the Son’s <em>hypostasis</em>? Is his personal subsistence without origin as well? Macleod says nothing. He has no issue with affirming an economical subordination of the Son to the Father brought about in the <em>pactum salutis </em>but goes no further than that. He explicitly states this when he says, “New Testament subordinationism is federal, not ontological” (78). But what about hypostatical? Again, this category seems to be missing from Macleod’s understanding.</p>
<p>(6) Macleod believes the language of derivation and origination &#8220;is fatal to the co-equal deity of the Son&#8221; (144). He thinks it creates &#8220;a totally asymmetrical Trinity in which the Father held the essence underived, while the Son and Spirit held it as derived from him&#8221; (144). He accuses John of Damascus and Augustine of enmeshing themselves &#8220;hopelessly in the language of causality&#8221; (144). For him, this language was influenced more by &#8220;Origen&#8217;s subordinationism&#8221; (145) than by biblical exegesis. Any hint of causality within the godhead reeks of &#8220;tritheism&#8221; (144). Since generation and procession have nothing to do with causality, Macleod believes &#8220;there is nothing inherently shocking about&#8221; speaking of the Son proceeding from the Father and Spirit (147). In fact, the Father Himself &#8220;owes it to the Son and Spirit that he is what he is (Father) as much as they owe to him and to each other that they are what they are (respectively Spirit and Son)&#8221; (149). Although Macleod attempts to avoid the pitfall of essential subordinationism, he falls into another by erasing any distinctions within the Godhead. If causality implies tritheism, Macleod’s view implies modalism!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Conclusion</span></strong></p>
<p>            In conclusion, Macleod’s treatment of the person of Christ is generally balanced and in line with the creedal statements of Nicea and Chalcedon. Though I disagree with him on his view of the Son’s begottenness and believe he strays from the ancient creeds at this point, his overall defense of historic Christian beliefs against the theologians of the Enlightenment assists the modern-day church in its proclamation that God descended from heaven and assumed flesh “<em>for us men and for our salvation</em>” (250).</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/">A Critical Review of Donald Macleod&#8217;s &#8220;The Person of Christ&#8221;</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview with Dr. Curt Daniel (part 4 of 4)</title>
		<link>/interview-with-dr-curt-daniel-part-4-of-4/</link>
					<comments>/interview-with-dr-curt-daniel-part-4-of-4/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 20:35:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1689]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amyraldianism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Curt Daniel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Duty-Faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hyper-Calvinism]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7011</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Questions 9-10: (SW – Sam Waldron, CD – Curt Daniel SW: “In your view does the Confession teach the view of the free offer (7:2) and common grace (14:3) which you hold and defend?” CD: “I agree with the 1689 in upholding the free offer of the Gospel (7:2) and common grace (14:3).” 1689:7:2 Moreover, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/interview-with-dr-curt-daniel-part-4-of-4/">Interview with Dr. Curt Daniel (part 4 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Questions 9-10: (SW – Sam Waldron, CD – Curt Daniel</p>
<p><strong>SW</strong>: “In your view does the Confession teach the view of the free offer (7:2) and common grace (14:3) which you hold and defend?”</p>
<p><strong>CD</strong>: “I agree with the 1689 in upholding the free offer of the Gospel (7:2) and common grace (14:3).”</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>1689:7:2</strong> Moreover, man having brought himself under the curse of the law by his fall, it pleased the Lord to make a covenant of grace, wherein he freely offereth unto sinners life and salvation by Jesus Christ, requiring of them faith in him, that they may be saved; and promising to give unto all those that are ordained unto eternal life, his Holy Spirit, to make them willing and able to believe</p>
<p><strong>1689:14:3</strong> This faith, although it be different in degrees, and may be weak or strong, yet it is in the least degree of it different in the kind or nature of it, as is all other saving grace, from the faith and common grace of temporary believers; and therefore, though it may be many times assailed and weakened, yet it gets the victory, growing up in many to the attainment of a full assurance through Christ, who is both the author and finisher of our faith.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>SW</strong>: “What is at stake in Reformed Baptists today continuing to hold clear views of the free offer of the gospel?”</p>
<p><strong>CD</strong>: “Reformed Baptists must uphold the doctrines of grace as Biblical and not succumb to the temptation to misuse them in order to deny the free offer, Duty Faith or common grace. Once those truths are rejected, our evangelism suffers enormously. There is a tendency to lose zeal for lost souls, decrease in obedience to the Great Commission, and to lessen prayer for the lost. I have found that Hyper-Calvinism also breeds a dry, proud and moribund attitude, sometimes also legalism and an unhealthy introspection. We need to maintain the biblical balance of divine sovereignty and human responsibility. I agree with great Calvinists in the past on these issues, such as Spurgeon and Edwards.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/interview-with-dr-curt-daniel-part-4-of-4/">Interview with Dr. Curt Daniel (part 4 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/interview-with-dr-curt-daniel-part-4-of-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
