<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 5)	</title>
	<atom:link href="/should-we-witness-5/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/should-we-witness-5/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2013 00:06:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Matt Foreman		</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness-5/#comment-381</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Matt Foreman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2013 00:06:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1331#comment-381</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dr. Sam (I hope I can call you that, since I once nearly burned my house down around you!), 
Thanks for these posts so far.  While I might still reserve the right to use &#039;testifying&#039; or &#039;witness&#039; in the broader sense, I think these posts have been very helpful, clear, and well-argued.  I greatly appreciate them!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Sam (I hope I can call you that, since I once nearly burned my house down around you!),<br />
Thanks for these posts so far.  While I might still reserve the right to use &#8216;testifying&#8217; or &#8216;witness&#8217; in the broader sense, I think these posts have been very helpful, clear, and well-argued.  I greatly appreciate them!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Should we witness for Christ? Sam Waldron says that in a sense we can&#8217;t &#124; The Confessing Baptist		</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness-5/#comment-380</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Should we witness for Christ? Sam Waldron says that in a sense we can&#8217;t &#124; The Confessing Baptist]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2013 14:44:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1331#comment-380</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[...] Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 5) [...]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 5) [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Sam Waldron		</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness-5/#comment-379</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 17:27:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1331#comment-379</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Bob,

Thank you for your question.  Generally, I agree with this assertion.  But I believe it must be interpreted in terms of community of the church and not individualistically.  We are not charged to make disciples all by ourselves.  Indeed, many Christians might be overwhelmed by such an idea and pressing it upon them this way--individualistically--would not help them, but only make them give up in despair.  They should be encouraged to nurture a heart for the lost, take every opportunity to speak to the lost, understand that the limitations of their life situation are taken into account by the Lord, to do this in terms of their unique gifts in the body of Christ, and to do it as part of the body of Christ.  I think this approach is more helpful and more true to the nature of the Great Commission as given first to the Apostles and through them to the church corporately.  The commission is for a community to gather a community.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Bob,</p>
<p>Thank you for your question.  Generally, I agree with this assertion.  But I believe it must be interpreted in terms of community of the church and not individualistically.  We are not charged to make disciples all by ourselves.  Indeed, many Christians might be overwhelmed by such an idea and pressing it upon them this way&#8211;individualistically&#8211;would not help them, but only make them give up in despair.  They should be encouraged to nurture a heart for the lost, take every opportunity to speak to the lost, understand that the limitations of their life situation are taken into account by the Lord, to do this in terms of their unique gifts in the body of Christ, and to do it as part of the body of Christ.  I think this approach is more helpful and more true to the nature of the Great Commission as given first to the Apostles and through them to the church corporately.  The commission is for a community to gather a community.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Bob		</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness-5/#comment-378</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Bob]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2012 23:21:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1331#comment-378</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dr. Waldron,

I would like to know your opinion regarding a phrase that you may have heard: &quot;every disciple [should be] a disciple-maker.&quot; 

As you see the Great Commission being given corporately to the church and not at an individual level, I would like to know if you see any problems with this assertion. 

In Christ,

-Bob]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Waldron,</p>
<p>I would like to know your opinion regarding a phrase that you may have heard: &#8220;every disciple [should be] a disciple-maker.&#8221; </p>
<p>As you see the Great Commission being given corporately to the church and not at an individual level, I would like to know if you see any problems with this assertion. </p>
<p>In Christ,</p>
<p>-Bob</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
