<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Ben Habegger | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/author/bkhabegger/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2019 17:47:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Ben Habegger | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 8 of 8 )</title>
		<link>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-8-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-8-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Habegger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2019 17:47:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amillennialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Zechariah 14]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11231</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Post #1 Post #2 Post #3 Post #4 Post #5 Post #6 Post#7 Post #8 &#8220;Zechariah 14:20&#8211;21: Jerusalem&#8217;s Perfect Consecration to the Lord&#8221; &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; Last in our series on Zechariah 14, we encounter a description of Jerusalem&#8217;s final holiness. 20&#160;In that day there will&#160;be inscribed&#160;on the bells of the horses, &#8220;HOLY TO THE LORD.&#8221; And [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-8-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 8 of 8 )</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-small-font-size">    <br> <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/">Post #1</a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-2-of-8/">Post #2</a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-3-of-8/">Post #3 </a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-4-of-8/">Post #4 </a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-5-of-8/">Post #5  </a>   <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-6-of-8/">Post #6 </a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-7-of-8/">Post#7</a>          </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Post #8 &#8220;Zechariah 14:20&#8211;21: Jerusalem&#8217;s
Perfect Consecration to the Lord&#8221;</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Last
in our series on Zechariah 14, we encounter a description of Jerusalem&#8217;s final
holiness. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong><sup>20&nbsp;</sup></strong>In that day there will&nbsp;<em>be inscribed</em>&nbsp;on the bells of the horses, &#8220;HOLY TO THE LORD.&#8221; And the&nbsp;cooking pots in the&nbsp;Lord&#8217;s&nbsp;house will be like the bowls before the altar.&nbsp;<strong><sup>21&nbsp;</sup></strong>Every cooking pot in Jerusalem and in Judah will be&nbsp;holy to the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;of hosts; and all who sacrifice will come and take of them and boil in them. And there will no longer be a&nbsp;Canaanite in the house of the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;of hosts in that day. </p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Why mention the bells on horses?
They are mentioned in order to shock Zechariah&#8217;s audience. &#8220;Shocking here is
the reference to an item associated with the horse, a ritually unclean animal
according to Lev. 11:1&#8211;8. In this new Jerusalem, that which was once treated as
unclean is now not merely clean, but holy.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a> The
inscription on the bells of the horses is the same as that on the high priest&#8217;s
turban! Notice the original context of this inscription:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong><sup>36</sup></strong> You shall also make a plate of pure gold and shall engrave on it, like the engravings of a seal, &#8216;Holy to the Lord.&#8217; <strong><sup>37</sup></strong> You shall fasten it on a blue cord, and it shall be on the turban; it shall be at the front of the turban. <strong><sup>38</sup></strong> It shall be on Aaron&#8217;s forehead, and Aaron shall take away the iniquity of the holy things which the sons of Israel consecrate, with regard to all their holy gifts; and it shall always be on his forehead, that they may be accepted before the Lord. (Exod. 28:36&#8211;38)</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Under the Levitical priesthood, the
high priest bore a seal of holiness which took away the lingering iniquity of
the people&#8217;s consecrated gifts; but Zechariah envisions a time when the most
ordinary items used in everyday life would be as pure and consecrated as the
garments which the high priest would wear in the holiest place of the temple
(Exod. 29:29&#8211;30)! This should signify even more to New Testament saints. The
high priest&#8217;s holy crown (Exod. 29:6) which he would bear before God&#8217;s own
presence prefigured the perfect holiness of Jesus our high priest. Christ&#8217;s
undefiled holiness renders his people&#8217;s spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God;
but one day, every aspect of the saints&#8217; lives will overflow with innate
holiness. Not only will our high priest&#8217;s holiness be imputed to us, but it
will have thoroughly transformed us to be holy as he is holy. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Zechariah reinforces his point by also speaking of pots and
pans. &#8220;Similarly, the cooking pots in the temple would be as holy as the basins
in front of the altar. Even the most common pot would become holy, so holy that
anyone wishing to sacrifice could readily use them.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a> Even
a premillennial interpreter like Kenneth Barker fails to adequately harmonize
these verses in Zechariah with a literal millennial temple. A literal temple
would demand a strict distinction between the holy and the common, the sacred
and the profane, as premillennialists should acknowledge if they identify
Ezekiel&#8217;s visionary temple with such a millennial temple (cf. Ezek. 42:13&#8211;14,
20; 43:12, 26; 44:13, 19, 23, 25&#8211;27; 45:1&#8211;7; 46:19&#8211;20; 48:10&#8211;14). Nevertheless,
Barker favorably quotes Perowne in his summary of Zechariah 14:20&#8211;21: &#8220;All
distinction between sacred and secular shall be at an end, because all shall
now be alike holy.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a>
These words flatly contradict the entire notion of a literal millennial temple,
but they accurately reflect the thrust of Zechariah&#8217;s words. As MacKay puts it,
&#8220;Even the smallest and seemingly most trivial details of life are consecrated
to the Lord. This, of course,
would involve the cessation of the Levitical distinction between sacred and
common.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a> E. B.
Pusey concludes, &#8220;In this priestly-levitical drapery the thought is expressed,
that in the perfected kingdom of God not only will everything without exception
be holy, but all will be equally holy.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>&nbsp;Zechariah ends by
saying that &#8220;there will no longer be a&nbsp;Canaanite in the house of the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;of hosts in that day.&#8221; The
background to this statement may be similar to the situation in Nehemiah&#8217;s day
when Tobiah the Ammonite was given storage rooms within the temple courts and
Canaanite merchants from Tyre sold merchandise in Jerusalem on the Sabbath
(Neh. 13:4&#8211;9, 16, 20&#8211;21). The word for a Canaanite also came to denote a merchant
(cf. the term&#8217;s translation in Prov. 31:24 and Isa. 23:8).<a href="#_ftn6">[6]</a> Given
these considerations, Zechariah may be thinking of the pollution of merchants
(such as those whom Jesus drove out of the temple) more than the pollution of a
pagan intruder. In any case MacKay is right to say, &#8220;The mention of the
Canaanite is not to debar any on racial grounds, but on ethical and spiritual.
&#8216;Nothing impure will ever enter it, nor will anyone who does what is shameful
or deceitful, but only those whose names are written in the Lamb&#8217;s book of
life&#8217; (Rev. 21:27).&#8221;<a href="#_ftn7">[7]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The glory described in this chapter answers to the prophecy
of Zechariah&#8217;s contemporary, Haggai. In a text which Hebrews 12:26&#8211;29
interprets as describing the removal of the present creation and the resultant
establishment of God&#8217;s eternal kingdom, Haggai 2:6&#8211;9 mirrors the thoughts of
Zechariah&#8217;s final chapter:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong><sup>6&nbsp;</sup></strong>For thus says the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;of hosts, &#8216;Once more&nbsp;in a&nbsp;little while, I am going to&nbsp;shake the heavens and the earth, the sea also and the dry land.<strong><sup>7&nbsp;</sup></strong>I will shake&nbsp;all the nations; and&nbsp;they will come with the&nbsp;wealth of all nations, and I will&nbsp;fill this house with glory,&#8217; says the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;of hosts.<strong><sup>8&nbsp;</sup></strong>&#8216;The&nbsp;silver is Mine and the gold is Mine,&#8217; declares the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;of hosts.<strong><sup>9&nbsp;</sup></strong>&#8216;The latter&nbsp;glory of this house will be greater than the&nbsp;former,&#8217; says the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;of hosts, &#8216;and in this place I will give&nbsp;peace,&#8217; declares the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;of hosts. </p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Even so, come Lord Jesus.<br></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a> Boda,
<em>Zechariah</em>, 779.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a>
Gregory, <em>Longing for God</em>, 211.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a> Kenneth L. Barker, <em>Zechariah</em>, Expositor&#8217;s Bible
Commentary, rev. ed., ed. Tremper Longman III and David E. Garland, vol. 8 (Grand
Rapids: Zondervan, 2008), 832.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref4">[4]</a>
MacKay, <em>Haggai,
Zechariah and Malachi</em>, 318.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref5">[5]</a> E. B. Pusey, <em>The Minor Prophets: A Commentary</em>, vol. 2 (Grand Rapids: Baker, 1950), 414.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref6">[6]</a> Boda,
<em>Zechariah</em>, 782.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref7">[7]</a>
MacKay, <em>Haggai,
Zechariah and Malachi</em>, 319.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-8-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 8 of 8 )</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-8-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 7 of 8 )</title>
		<link>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-7-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-7-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Habegger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 18:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[amillenialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amillennialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Zechariah 14]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11205</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Post #1 Post #2 Post #3 Post #4 Post #5 Post #6 Post #7 “Zechariah 14:16–19: The Lord Summons the Nations to His Feast” Verses 16–19 of Zechariah 14 continue the thought of the section addressed in the last post. What becomes of the Gentile nations? 16&#160;Then it will come about that any who are [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-7-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 7 of 8 )</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>     <br>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/">Post #1</a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-2-of-8/">Post #2</a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-3-of-8/">Post #3 </a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-4-of-8/">Post #4 </a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-5-of-8/">Post #5  </a>   <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-6-of-8/">Post #6 </a>               </p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Post #7 “Zechariah 14:16–19: The Lord
Summons the Nations to His Feast”</strong></p>



<p>Verses 16–19 of Zechariah 14 continue the thought of the
section addressed in the last post. What becomes of the Gentile nations?</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong><sup>16&nbsp;</sup></strong>Then it will come about that any who are left of all the nations that went against Jerusalem will&nbsp;go up from year to year to worship the King, the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;of hosts, and to celebrate the&nbsp;Feast of Booths.&nbsp;<strong><sup>17&nbsp;</sup></strong>And it will be that whichever of the families of the earth does not go up to Jerusalem to worship the&nbsp;King, the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;of hosts, there will be&nbsp;no rain on them.<strong><sup>18&nbsp;</sup></strong>If the family of Egypt does not go up or enter, then no&nbsp;<em>rain will fall</em>&nbsp;on them; it will be the&nbsp;plague with which the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;smites the nations who do not go up to celebrate the Feast of Booths.&nbsp;<strong><sup>19&nbsp;</sup></strong>This will be the&nbsp;punishment of Egypt, and the&nbsp;punishment of all the nations who do not go up to celebrate the Feast of Booths.</p></blockquote>



<p>The last post dealt with the horrible fate of the nations
who attacked Jerusalem. There are those Gentiles, however, who survive the Day
of the Lord. Though once strangers and enemies to Israel and her God, this
remnant of Gentiles are now fellow worshipers with the Israelites. This picture
of a remnant from the Gentile nations which engages in perpetual observance of
the Feast of Booths (or “Tabernacles”) beautifully reveals the deep meaning and
eventual fulfillment of this Old Testament feast.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>The conversion of the nations is not pictured in terms of their being circumcised, or obeying the Law of Moses, but of worshipping the Lord. It must be noted that ‘go up’ still thinks in terms of pilgrimage to Jerusalem. The language of the Old Covenant is being used to express the reality of the New (Isa. 66:23), and especially in its culmination when John sees ‘a great multitude that no-one could count, from every nation, tribe, people and language, standing before the throne and in front of the Lamb’ (Rev. 7:9). John’s great multitude also ‘were holding palm branches in their hands’ (Rev. 7:9), and while this may reflect on Christ’s triumphal entry into Jerusalem (John 12:13), it also fits in with what is said here <strong>to celebrate the Feast of Tabernacles.</strong> On the first of the seven days of this feast the Israelites were instructed to ‘take choice fruit from the trees, and palm fronds, leafy branches and poplars, and rejoice before the Lord your God for seven days’ (Lev. 23:40). But why is this festival singled out for mention? It came at the end of the religious calendar and so in measure summed up all the worship of Israel (note its position in Lev. 23 and Deut. 16.) It was also a festival in which the resident alien was permitted a role (Deut. 16:14). During this time the people lived in booths constructed out of branches to remind them of how they lived during the period in the Wilderness and how the Lord had guided them at that time (Lev. 23:42–43). It was also a time when they remembered the Lord’s on-going bounty to them in the harvest (Lev. 23:39; Deut. 16:13–15). The nations in coming to this feast were therefore making a double acknowledgment: that it was the Lord who had guided them to where they were, and that it was his bounty that they enjoyed in the harvest. In the light of the Lord’s providential and saving goodness, the feast was one characterised by joy. ‘Be joyful at your Feast. … your joy will be complete’ (Deut. 16:14, 15). This is why the redeemed of the nations celebrate it with joy.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a></p></blockquote>



<p>What harvest is celebrated by this
eschatological Feast of Booths? Barry Webb answers well. “It is <em>people</em> – formerly enemies, but now
worshippers – gathered in from <em>all the
nations</em>, to <em>worship</em>, at last,
their rightful Lord and King.”<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a></p>



<p>How fitting that the text now contrasts a harvest
celebration with the withholding of rain. “‘Rain’ here stands for all the
blessings that the Lord bestows, particularly in the harvest (10:1). These will
be withheld from those who persist in their rebellion.”<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a>
Andrew Hill adds, “The lack of rainfall was one of the curses God pronounced
against Israel for covenant disobedience (cf. Deut. 28:22–24). Here that curse
is extended to the nations by virtue of God’s rule over all peoples.”<a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a> T. V.
Moore remarks, “In this future condition, the present mingled state of reward
and punishment shall end. Now God sends rain on the just and the unjust, then
he will separate the good and the evil, and render unto every man according to
his works.”<a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a></p>



<p>Why does Egypt receive special mention? Again, Andrew Hill
is helpful. “Egypt is singled out for mention, perhaps because it was the
origin of the Hebrew exodus (of which the Feast of Tabernacles was to be a
reminder, Lev. 23:43), and in the past it was a nation that ‘had suffered the
most from the plagues at God’s hands. If it did not participate in the future,
it would suffer again.’”<a href="#_ftn6">[6]</a> Elsewhere
Egypt is envisioned as sharing in future worship with God’s people, signifying
the conversion of former pagans (see Is. 19:19–25).<a href="#_ftn7">[7]</a> Here,
Egypt stands for those who refuse to so worship. It is also noteworthy that the
Book of the Revelation uses Egypt as a type of the Satanic world system which
persecutes God’s church. The trumpet judgments and the bowls of God’s final
wrath all point back to the plagues which God sent against Egypt when their
king refused to let Israel go. The city where the two prophetic witnesses are
slain is symbolically named Egypt (Rev. 11:8). Why does Egypt slay the
witnesses? It does so because of the divine plagues with which these prophets
strike Egypt, including the plague of drought (Rev. 11:6, 10). Even now, the
prophetic witness of the church painfully reminds the unrepentant world that already
“the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and
unrighteousness of men who&nbsp;suppress the truth&nbsp;in unrighteousness”
(Rom. 1:18). In the future day of which Zechariah speaks, Egypt as well as all
the unrepentant nations will forever suffer the unmitigated plagues of God’s
wrath (cf. Rev. 14:10–11; 15:1; 18:8; 21:8; 22:14–15, 18–19).<br></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a>
MacKay, <em>Haggai,
Zechariah and Malachi</em>, 316.</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a> Webb,
<em>Zechariah</em>, 181.</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a>
MacKay, <em>Haggai, Zechariah
and Malachi</em>, 317.</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref4">[4]</a> Hill,
<em>Haggai,</em> <em>Zechariah and
Malachi</em>, 270.</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref5">[5]</a> Thomas V. Moore, <em>A Commentary on Haggai, Zechariah and Malachi</em>, Geneva Series of Commentaries (Carlisle, PA: Banner
of Truth, 1993), 313.</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref6">[6]</a> Hill,
<em>Haggai,</em> <em>Zechariah and
Malachi</em>, 270.</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref7">[7]</a> Carl Friedrich Keil, <em>The Twelve Minor Prophets</em>, Keil and
Delitzsch’s Biblical Commentary on the Old Testament (Grand Rapids: Eerdmans,
1971), 457.</p>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-7-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 7 of 8 )</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-7-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 6 of 8 )</title>
		<link>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-6-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-6-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Habegger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 21:02:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[amillenialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Zechariah 14]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11135</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Post #6 &#8220;Zechariah 14:12&#8211;15: The Lord Does Battle Against the Nations&#8221; Post #1 Post #2 Post #3 Post #4 Post #5 &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; Next in this last chapter of Zechariah comes a description of the Lord&#8217;s final dominion over the nations. The nations will either willingly submit to the Lord or else be subject to punishment. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-6-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 6 of 8 )</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Post #6 &#8220;Zechariah 14:12&#8211;15: The Lord Does
Battle Against the Nations&#8221;</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"small"} -->
<p class="has-small-font-size">   <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/">Post #1</a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-2-of-8/">Post #2</a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-3-of-8/">Post #3 </a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-4-of-8/">Post #4 </a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-5-of-8/">Post #5  </a>                   </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Next in
this last chapter of Zechariah comes a description of the Lord&#8217;s final dominion
over the nations. The nations will either willingly submit to the Lord or else
be subject to punishment. We will break down this larger section (verses 12&#8211;19)
and address it in two separate posts. For now, let&#8217;s look at verses 12&#8211;15.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong><sup>12&nbsp;</sup></strong>Now this will be the plague with which the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;will strike all the peoples who have gone to war against Jerusalem; their flesh will&nbsp;rot while they stand on their feet, and their eyes will rot in their sockets, and their tongue will rot in their mouth.&nbsp;<strong><sup>13&nbsp;</sup></strong>It will come about in that day that a great panic from the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;will&nbsp;fall on them; and they will&nbsp;seize one another&#8217;s hand, and the hand of one will&nbsp;be lifted against the hand of another.&nbsp;<strong><sup>14&nbsp;</sup></strong>Judah also will fight at Jerusalem; and the&nbsp;wealth of all the surrounding nations will be gathered, gold and silver and garments in great abundance.&nbsp;<strong><sup>15&nbsp;</sup></strong>So also like this&nbsp;plague will be the plague on the horse, the mule, the camel, the donkey and all the cattle that will be in those camps.</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>These verses return to the earlier scene when the Lord comes
down to fight Jerusalem&#8217;s foes. He will destroy their bodies and the bodies of
their beasts so rapidly that they are consumed while still standing.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>
Although swift, the destruction is also gruesome. The plague consumes portions
of the armies while the remaining combatants are so terrified that they turn
their weapons on each other in the confusion; this hearkens back to various Old
Testament battles in which God fought for his people by turning their attackers
against each other. The rotting disease and the victory of little Judah over
her mighty enemies may also allude to the covenant curses which God promised
disobedient Israel (Lev. 26:16&#8211;17, 25, 39; Deut. 28:21&#8211;22, 25, 27&#8211;28, 59&#8211;61);
in this context, however, those same curses turn to consume Israel&#8217;s enemies.<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a> </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Given the military imagery of this and other apocalyptic
texts, many people expect a very literal gathering of the world&#8217;s militaries in
the Middle East just before the Second Advent. Such an interpretation would
tend to overlook the deeper significance of the relevant prophecies. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>As has been stated earlier in this blog series, Jerusalem
here stands for the church at the end of this age of tribulation. It is the
church on earth, surrounded by her enemies. Therefore the armies sent against
her need not be the sorts of forces deployed in earthly warfare, though
physical force will doubtless be involved. Far less need they be gathered in
one geographical location. Everywhere the church is, there the nations will
assault her. John saw these nations as they &#8220;came up on the&nbsp;broad plain of
the earth and surrounded the&nbsp;camp of the&nbsp;saints and the&nbsp;beloved
city.&#8221; (Rev. 20:9) The camp of the saints, God&#8217;s people preserved in the
wilderness of this world (Rev. 12:6, 14), are identified as the beloved city. In
order to oppose her, the Satanically-deceived nations will tread &#8220;the breadth
of the earth&#8221; (nkjv, csb). Furthermore, this warfare should
be compared to that of the beast against the two witnesses in Revelation 11:7,
that of the beast against the saints in Revelation 13:7, and that of the beast
and his ten kings against the Lamb and his people in Revelation 17:14.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The picture here in Zechariah 14 is that of total
disintegration and terror among the attacking nations. They and their wartime
resources are struck by the sword of Christ&#8217;s mouth (Rev. 19:15, 21), and the
confusion is such that they begin to destroy one another. Verse 14 adds, &#8220;Judah
also will fight at Jerusalem; and the&nbsp;wealth of all the surrounding
nations will be gathered, gold and silver and garments in great abundance.&#8221; In
that last hour, we know that the church militant will face her last battle (see
the near context in Zech. 12&#8211;13); but whereas they were momentarily overrun in
verse 2, now the glorified church&#8212;the church triumphant&#8212;joins her Lord in this
battle as his victorious heavenly army (Rev. 19:8, 14). And as was promised
them, they will share in the spoils. They will plunder the Egyptians. They will
inherit the earth.<br></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a> Boda,
<em>Zechariah</em>, 772.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a> The
description of rotting flesh also seems similar to that of leprosy (cf. Num.
12:12). It is interesting that King Uzziah is referenced earlier in the text,
since God struck him with leprosy when he attempted sacrilege.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-6-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 6 of 8 )</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-6-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 5 of 8 )</title>
		<link>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-5-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-5-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Habegger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 14:47:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amillennialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Zechariah 14]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11106</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Post #5 “Zechariah 14:6–11: The Lord’s Reign from Jerusalem,” Part 2 Post #1 Post #2 Post #3 Post #4 Continuing our discussion of verses 6–11, we pick up with the prophecy of the holy city being raised above the now leveled land surrounding it. The exaltation of Jerusalem in verse 10 reflects a common prophetic [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-5-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 5 of 8 )</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Post #5 “Zechariah 14:6–11: The Lord’s
Reign from Jerusalem,” Part 2</strong></p>



<p> <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/">Post #1</a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-2-of-8/">Post #2</a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-3-of-8/">Post #3 </a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-4-of-8/">Post #4 </a>                   </p>



<p>Continuing our discussion of verses 6–11, we pick up with
the prophecy of the holy city being raised above the now leveled land
surrounding it. The exaltation of Jerusalem in verse 10 reflects a common
prophetic theme. Perhaps the clearest parallel appears in Isaiah 2:2–3:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong><sup>2</sup></strong> Now it will come about that in the last days the mountain of the house of the Lord will be established as the chief of the mountains, and will be raised above the hills; and all the nations will stream to it. <strong><sup>3</sup></strong> And many peoples will come and say, “Come, let us go up to the mountain of the Lord, to the house of the God of Jacob; that He may teach us concerning His ways and that we may walk in His paths.” For the law will go forth from Zion and the word of the Lord from Jerusalem. </p></blockquote>



<p>The words of this same prophecy are
also found in Micah 4:1–2, where they follow and contrast the Babylonian
desolation of an impure Jerusalem (Micah 3:11–12). God removed his presence
from the temple because of Jerusalem’s iniquity; but one day, God’s presence
will eternally dwell in a purified Jerusalem, and the city will nevermore be
put to shame. Zion will tower over all the earth, and all nations will be under
its dominion. The kingdom of the heavenly Zion will become a great mountain and
fill the whole earth (Dan. 2:35).</p>



<p>The geographical markers here mentioned by Zechariah had
symbolic meaning which we might easily miss. Bryan Gregory explains:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Before the exile, Geba and Rimmon denoted the northern and southern boundaries of Judah during the days of Josiah’s reform. In other words, the land will be restored to her preexilic, pre-disaster state, and being ‘leveled out,’ will provide a geological setting for the crown jewel of the new creation, the city of Jerusalem…. The city itself will then be defined by distinct boundaries, stretching from the Gate of Benjamin (on the city’s northern side) to the place of the First Gate (the location of which is now lost but possibly denotes an old gate on the east side of the city), down to the Corner Gate (on the western side), and from the Tower of Hananel (probably near the northwest corner) down to the king’s winepresses in the south. The boundaries are not only a way of tracing the city’s limits but are more importantly an allusion to Jeremiah 31 where the Lord had promised that the city would be rebuilt from the Tower of Hananel to the Corner Gate (Jer. 31:38). Part of the promise to Jeremiah was that the whole city would once again become holy, never again to be uprooted or demolished (Jer. 31:39–40; cf. Zech. 14:20–21). In other words, the boundaries paint a picture of Jerusalem as a city entirely safe from the threat of violence.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a></p></blockquote>



<p>In terms the contemporary
inhabitants of Jerusalem understood, Zechariah echoed Jeremiah, promising that
the holy city would remain intact from one end (or wall) to the other, and that
it would be exalted above the whole land.</p>



<p>Verse 11 pointedly states that “people will live in it.” “In
the period after the return from the Exile,” says MacKay, “there seems to have
been an ongoing problem with population in Jerusalem. Many of those who
returned preferred to live in the countryside and had to be forced to come to
the capital (Neh. 7:4; 11:1–2). But there will be no problem about getting
people to live in the capital when the king has returned to it.”<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a> The
absence of a curse, as MacKay goes on to explain, </p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>refers to the ‘ban’ which the Lord imposed on the cities of Canaan because of their great wickedness (Josh. 6:17–18; see also Mal. 4:6). The fate of God’s people for their rebellion had been understood in similar terms (Isa. 43:28). But when the Lord returns to the city, ‘no longer will there be any curse’ (Rev. 22:3). His people will have been purified and will be ready to enter into his presence.<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a> </p></blockquote>



<p>Given the factors we’ve discussed in the last post as well
as this one, Zechariah’s prophecy fits better within the context of the new
Jerusalem which “will dwell in security” in the new creation than it fits with
a millennial Jerusalem which continues to experience day and night and the
(lightened) effects of the Adamic curse and is eventually surrounded by a
Satanic coalition of nations bent on her destruction (Rev. 20:9). <br></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a>
Gregory, <em>Longing for God</em>, 208–209.</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a>
MacKay, <em>Haggai,
Zechariah and Malachi</em>, 311.</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a> Ibid.</p>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-5-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 5 of 8 )</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-5-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 4 of 8 )</title>
		<link>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-4-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-4-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Habegger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 16:17:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[amillenialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Zechariah 14]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11083</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Post #4 &#8220;Zechariah 14:6&#8211;11: The Lord&#8217;s Reign from Jerusalem,&#8221; Part 1 Post #1 Post #2 Post #3 We now come to verses 6&#8211;11, a section which will require two separate posts. Once the Lord arrives to rescue Jerusalem, the Lord remains to forever reign from Jerusalem; and as the apostle John would later note, &#8220;there [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-4-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 4 of 8 )</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Post #4 &#8220;Zechariah 14:6&#8211;11: The Lord&#8217;s Reign from Jerusalem,&#8221; Part 1</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>   <br><a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/">Post #1</a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-2-of-8/">Post #2</a>  <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-3-of-8/">Post #3 </a>                     </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>We now come to verses 6&#8211;11, a
section which will require two separate posts. Once the Lord arrives to rescue
Jerusalem, the Lord remains to forever reign from Jerusalem; and as the apostle
John would later note, &#8220;there will be no night there&#8221; (Rev. 21:25).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote {"className":"is-style-default"} -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-style-default"><p><strong><sup>6&nbsp;</sup></strong>In that day there will be&nbsp;no light; the&nbsp;luminaries will dwindle.&nbsp;<strong><sup>7&nbsp;</sup></strong>For it will be&nbsp;a unique day which is&nbsp;known to the&nbsp;Lord, neither day nor night, but it will come about that at&nbsp;evening time there will be light. <strong><sup>8&nbsp;</sup></strong>And in that day&nbsp;living waters will flow out of Jerusalem, half of them toward the eastern sea and the other half toward the western sea; it will be in summer as well as in winter. <strong><sup>9&nbsp;</sup></strong>And the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;will be&nbsp;king over all the earth; in that day the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;will be&nbsp;<em>the only</em>&nbsp;one, and His name&nbsp;<em>the only</em>&nbsp;one. <strong><sup>10&nbsp;</sup></strong>All the land will be changed into a plain from&nbsp;Geba to&nbsp;Rimmon south of Jerusalem; but&nbsp;Jerusalem will&nbsp;rise and&nbsp;remain on its site from&nbsp;Benjamin&#8217;s Gate as far as the place of the First Gate to the&nbsp;Corner Gate, and from the&nbsp;Tower of Hananel to the king&#8217;s wine presses.&nbsp;<strong><sup>11&nbsp;</sup></strong>People will live in it, and there will&nbsp;no longer be a curse, for Jerusalem will&nbsp;dwell in security.</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Several items here require
attention, including the light without luminaries, the living waters, the
universal worship of Yahweh, the exaltation of Jerusalem above the surrounding
land, Jerusalem&#8217;s secure population, and the absence of a curse. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The
text and translation of verse 6 are difficult, but when taken along with verse
7, the larger point seems clear.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a> The
&#8220;luminaries&#8221; are probably the heavenly bodies. The failing of these heavenly
bodies has both literal and figurative significance throughout the prophets,
especially in connection with &#8220;the&nbsp;great and awesome day of the&nbsp;Lord&#8221; (Joel 2:31; cf. also Isa. 13:9&#8211;13; Joel
3:15; Matt. 24:29; Mark 13:24&#8211;25; Luke 21:25; Rev. 6:12&#8211;13). Bryan Gregory also
observes, &#8220;The disruption to the normal cycles of day and night is significant.
In God&#8217;s promise to Noah, he had promised that the normal rhythms of seasons
and days would not cease for as long as the earth endures (Gen. 8:22).&#8221;<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a> Thus
Zechariah indicates that, although he speaks in terms of the old city of
Jerusalem and land of Judah, this holy city and promised land will be part of
the new creation. The earth as his readers know it will have passed away.<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>MacKay helps to illumine the significance of the &#8220;living
waters&#8221;:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote {"className":"is-style-default"} -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-style-default"><p>Jerusalem was always poorly provided with water, but the renewed city is the source of a divinely provided supply. Zechariah here resumes the picture presented by Joel and Ezekiel of the Temple as a source of water (Joel 3:18; Ezek. 47:1&#8211;12). This is not just typical of physical change, but of the spiritual blessings that water represents. It is &#8216;living&#8217; water flowing freshly from a spring or fountain, and symbolic of true spiritual life given in salvation (Jer. 2:13; John 4:10; 7:38). This looks back to the river of Paradise, when &#8216;a river watering the garden flowed from Eden&#8217; (Gen. 2:10), and it looks forward to Paradise restored&#8230;. Truly &#8216;there is a river whose streams make glad the city of God, the holy place where the Most High dwells&#8217; (Ps. 46:4).</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote {"className":"is-style-default"} -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-style-default"><p>Unlike Ezekiel&#8217;s river which flowed only to the east (Ezek. 47:1, an embarrassment for those who take both prophecies to refer to the same <em>literal</em> future event), the water splits <strong>half to the eastern sea</strong>, that is the Dead Sea, <strong>and half to the western sea</strong>, that is, the Mediterranean. In this way it is available for all the land. And it is available all the time, <strong>in summer and in winter</strong>. Many streams in Palestine were only winter torrents which dried up in the heat of summer, when the need for water was at its greatest. Not so this source of supply. It is available all the year round. There is no disruption of the bliss of the new creation &#8216;for the old order of things has passed away&#8217; (Rev. 21:4).<a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a> <br></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>

Verse 9 expresses the consummated, universal submission and worship given to the one true God in the age to come. &#8220;And the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;will be&nbsp;king over all the earth; in that day the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;will be&nbsp;<em>the only</em>&nbsp;one, and His name&nbsp;<em>the only</em>&nbsp;one.&#8221; Night forever gone. The river of living water. All the earth serving and worshipping the Lord. If these things do not point us to John&#8217;s vision of the eternal state in Revelation 21 and 22, I doubt much will.  

</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a> Boda,
<em>Zechariah</em>, 760&#8211;61, fn.b., 762. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a> Bryan R. Gregory, <em>Longing for God in an Age of Discouragement: the
Gospel According to Zechariah</em>, The Gospel
According to the Old Testament, ed. Iain M. Duguid (Phillipsburg, NJ: P&amp;R
Publishing, 2010), 207.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a> Boda
also suggests an allusion in the Hebrew text to Genesis 1:3&#8211;5, implying a
recreation. &#8220;This suggests that 14:7 refers to a day of recreation, with 14:6
returning the earth to a state prior to the creative activity in Genesis 1, and
14:7 initiating the process of creation in Genesis 1. This recreation day, just
as the original creation day, is known only to Yahweh, in whose hands are the
times and seasons (see Ecclesiastes 3). However, the fact that the light
appears now in the evening suggests a clear shift in the cosmos, so that there
is perpetual light and no night. This is a feature of texts envisioning a
future idyllic age (cf. Isa. 60:19, 20; Rev. 21:25; 22:5).&#8221; See Boda, <em>Zechariah</em>, 762&#8211;63.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref4">[4]</a>
MacKay, <em>Haggai,
Zechariah and Malachi</em>,
308&#8211;309.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-4-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 ( 4 of 8 )</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-4-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 (3 of 8)</title>
		<link>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-3-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-3-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Habegger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2019 15:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amillennialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Zechariah 14]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11068</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Post #3 &#8220;Zechariah 14:1&#8211;5: The Lord&#8217;s Coming to Jerusalem,&#8221; Part 2 Post #1 Post #2 The last post addressed verses 1&#8211;5 of the text but did not deal with some questions about the prophetic details. If the prophecy uses the land of Judah and the city of Jerusalem as veiled references to the New Testament [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-3-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 (3 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Post #3 &#8220;Zechariah 14:1&#8211;5: The Lord&#8217;s Coming
to Jerusalem,&#8221; Part 2</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"small"} -->
<p class="has-small-font-size"><a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/">Post #1</a> <a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-2-of-8/">Post #2</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">The
last post addressed verses 1&#8211;5 of the text but did not deal with some questions
about the prophetic details. If the prophecy uses the land of Judah and the
city of Jerusalem as veiled references to the New Testament church, why are
certain geographical markers emphasized? </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">For
instance, why does Zechariah stress that the valley of escape created by the
divided Mount of Olives will reach all the way to Azel? Davis sees in these
details a great deal of symbolism involving the escape of God&#8217;s people to a
city of refuge.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>
More likely, much of the description of the earthquake, including the mention
of Azel, simply refers to details of the historical earthquake during the reign
of Uzziah.<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a> It is as if the prophet rehearses
the details of that past event to say, &#8220;It will be like that again when the
Lord comes to defend his city. His people will have a way of escape.&#8221; That is
certainly the comparison in verse 5: &#8220;Yes, you will flee just as you fled
before the&nbsp;earthquake in the days of Uzziah king of Judah.&#8221; There is also
conflicting manuscript evidence here which should be factored into the
interpretation. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote {"className":"is-style-large"} -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-style-large"><p>Either this valley will become an escape route for the Hebrews fleeing Jerusalem in the face of the assault against the city by the nations (so NIV, NLT, NRSV; following the mt), or the valley will be filled and blocked like it was during the earthquake at the time of King Uzziah (so NAB, NEB, NJB; following the LXX; Targ.). A different vowel pointing of the same Hebrew root word renders the two separate meanings, and &#8216;either is equally possible&#8217;. Baldwin&#8217;s (1972: 218) mediation of the difficulty is helpful, noting: &#8216;It is impossible to be sure how the text read originally, but the general meaning is clear. The earth movements which open a valley eastwards will also block up the Kidron valley, so providing a level escape route from Jerusalem.&#8217;<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">The
earthquake of Uzziah&#8217;s time is barely mentioned in scripture. Amos prophesied
two years before what was apparently the same earthquake (Amos 1:1). Such an
earthquake must have been severe if it was still remembered over two centuries
later in post-exilic Judah. It was an unforgettable national disaster which
doubtless gripped the imaginations of Zechariah&#8217;s original audience.<a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a> That historical event is
likened to the Lord&#8217;s coming, which will shake the entire earth (cf. Hag.
2:6&#8211;7; Heb. 12:26&#8211;27) and bring terror to those caught desecrating his holy
dwelling.<a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">While
appreciating the complex imagery of the text, we should perhaps not forget that
the literal Mount of Olives may have a prominent role at the Second Advent of
Christ. Matthew and Mark pointedly state that Jesus sat on the Mount of Olives
as he taught his disciples about his Second Advent (Matt. 24:3; Mark 13:3).
Luke also says that Jesus ascended to heaven from the Mount of Olives (Acts
1:12). At the time of Christ&#8217;s ascension, two men in white announced to his
disciples that he would come back in just the same way which they had seen him
leave (Acts 1:10&#8211;11). Jesus ascended to heaven bodily, and he will return
bodily; he may also return to the same place, the Mount of Olives.<a href="#_ftn6">[6]</a> This would be in keeping with
how the prophecies of his First Advent were fulfilled. The Christ came out of
Bethlehem in Judah symbolically, since he was David&#8217;s seed and Bethlehem was
David&#8217;s ancestral town; but Jesus was also born in the literal city of
Bethlehem (Mic. 5:2; Matt. 2:1; Luke 2:4&#8211;7, 11). <br></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a>
Davis, <em>High King of
Heaven</em>,
397&#8211;98.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a> For a
discussion of the word <em>Azel</em>, see Mark J. Boda, <em>The Book of Zechariah</em>, New International Commentary on the Old Testament (Grand
Rapids: Eerdmans, 2016), 758.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a> Hill,
<em>Haggai,</em> <em>Zechariah and
Malachi</em>, 262. See also Hill&#8217;s discussion of the name <em>Azel</em> on the same page.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref4">[4]</a> These
online articles give summaries of fascinating archeological evidence for this
major earthquake: <a href="https://patternsofevidence.com/2019/01/20/biblical-quake-confirmed/">https://patternsofevidence.com/2019/01/20/biblical-quake-confirmed/</a>
.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref5">[5]</a>
Josephus makes an intriguing connection between Uzziah&#8217;s attempted desecration
of the Holy Place (2 Chron. 26:16&#8211;20) and the earthquake. Azariah the king
(called this in 2 Kings 15 but Uzziah in 2 Chron. 26) attempted to usurp the
role of Azariah the high priest; but the Lord struck the king with leprosy and
drove him out of the temple. Josephus says that the earthquake also happened at
the same time. He even records certain effects of the earthquake which seem to
mirror Zechariah&#8217;s words: &#8220;And before the city, at a place called Eroge, half
the mountain broke off from the rest on the west, and rolled itself four
furlongs, and stood still at the east mountain, till the roads, as well as the
king&#8217;s gardens, were spoiled by the obstruction.&#8221; See Flavius Josephus, <em>Antiquities of the Jews</em>, book 9, chapter
10, paragraph 4, verse 225, William Whiston. In any case, the parallels between
King Uzziah and the &#8220;man of sin&#8221; who will attempt to usurp Christ&#8217;s
prerogatives are worthy of note (see 2 Thess. 2:3&#8211;8).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref6">[6]</a> Hill,
<em>Haggai,</em> <em>Zechariah and
Malachi</em>, 261. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-3-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 (3 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-3-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 (2 of 8)</title>
		<link>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-2-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-2-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Habegger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 18:53:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[premillenialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Zechariah 14]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11023</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Post #2 &#8220;Zechariah 14:1&#8211;5: The Lord&#8217;s Coming to Jerusalem,&#8221; Part 1 Post 1 &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; The opening verses of chapter 14 portray the final conflict between the nations and the holy city. This conflict culminates in the sudden arrival of the Lord God and his heavenly hosts. 1 Behold, a&#160;day is coming for the&#160;Lord&#160;when&#160;the spoil taken [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-2-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 (2 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Post #2 &#8220;Zechariah 14:1&#8211;5: The Lord&#8217;s Coming to Jerusalem,&#8221; Part 1</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"align":"left","fontSize":"small"} -->
<p style="text-align:left" class="has-small-font-size"><a href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/">Post 1</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The
opening verses of chapter 14 portray the final conflict between the nations and
the holy city. This conflict culminates in the sudden arrival of the Lord God
and his heavenly hosts.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong><sup>1</sup></strong> Behold, a&nbsp;day is coming for the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;when&nbsp;the spoil taken from you will be divided among you.&nbsp;<strong><sup>2&nbsp;</sup></strong>For I will&nbsp;gather all the nations against Jerusalem to battle, and the city will be captured, the&nbsp;houses plundered, the women ravished and half of the city exiled, but the rest of the people will not be cut off from the city.&nbsp;<strong><sup>3&nbsp;</sup></strong>Then the&nbsp;Lord&nbsp;will go forth and&nbsp;fight against those nations, as&nbsp;when He fights on a day of battle.&nbsp;<strong><sup>4&nbsp;</sup></strong>In that day His feet will&nbsp;stand on the Mount of Olives, which is in front of Jerusalem on the east; and the Mount of Olives will be&nbsp;split in its middle from east to west by a very large valley, so that half of the mountain will move toward the north and the other half toward the south.&nbsp;<strong><sup>5&nbsp;</sup></strong>You will flee by the valley of My mountains, for the valley of the mountains will reach to Azel; yes, you will flee just as you fled before the&nbsp;earthquake in the days of Uzziah king of Judah.&nbsp;Then the&nbsp;Lord, my God, will come,&nbsp;<em>and </em>all the holy ones with&nbsp;Him!<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Verse 2 puts this final conflict into proper perspective:
the Lord himself &#8220;will gather all the nations against Jerusalem to battle.&#8221;
This time when God gathers his enemies against his people &#8220;for the war of
the&nbsp;great day of God, the Almighty&#8221; (Rev. 16:14) is prophesied in several
places throughout scripture (cf. Ezek. 38:1&#8211;23; 39:1&#8211;6; Joel 3:2; Rev.
16:12&#8211;16; 19:19; 20:8&#8211;9). Here we must focus on the unique picture which
Zechariah paints of this event.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The
nations gather and battle against Jerusalem, and they are initially successful.
They capture the city, loot the houses, rape the women, and even succeed in
carrying away captive half the inhabitants. Still, the other half of the city&#8217;s
people will not be killed or exiled. Why? The Lord himself will appear on the
scene and catch the nations in their heinous act of desecration; and when God
arrives, he will descend in full battle array. When he touches down on the
earth right outside the walls of Jerusalem, the Mount of Olives will split to
form a valley, a way of escape for the beleaguered inhabitants of the city.
John MacKay explains verse 2 this way: &#8220;The message is that the future of the
church will involve a time when it will be surrounded by its enemies and
seemingly overwhelmed by them&#8230;. Under the metaphor of the pillaging of an ancient
city, the church is presented as suffering grievously at the hands of her
enemies, and yet there has been a remnant left.&#8221;<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The
reference to the Mount of Olives should remind us of Ezekiel&#8217;s words, written a
generation before Zechariah&#8217;s time. MacKay makes the connection when discussing
verse 4:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>&#8216;His feet&#8217; indicates
a theophany, perhaps one where the presence of God causes the earth to shake
(Ps. 68:8; 97:4; Micah 1:3&#8211;4; Nahum 1:3, 5). The addition &#8216;east of Jerusalem&#8217; &#8211;
which was scarcely needed to locate this well-known hill &#8211; links this vision
with that granted to Ezekiel when the Lord&#8217;s
glory left Jerusalem and &#8216;stopped above the mountain east of it&#8217; (Ezek. 11:23).
The Lord whose visible presence
with his people had then ceased now returns in power, as was similarly forecast
in Ezekiel 43:2. It is not of course to some reconstructed city that he comes,
but to the New Jerusalem which is the reality symbolised in these visions. It
is the city that bears the name &#8216;the Lord
is there&#8217; (Ezek. 48:35).<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Dean Davis further opines, &#8220;Verse 4 pictures the LORD
creating an unexpected way of escape for his people; verse 5 pictures them
using it&#8230;. Quite intentionally, the imagery used here reminds us of Israel&#8217;s
miraculous deliverance at the Red Sea (Exodus 14:1ff).&#8221;<a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a> </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; But what
about the details of the earthquake and Azel, and should we expect the Lord
Jesus to descend upon the literal hill called the Mount of Olives? These
questions will be answered in the next post.<br></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a>
All scripture quotations are taken from the nasb
Updated Edition of 1995.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a> Ibid., 303&#8211;304.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a>
Ibid., 305. Cf. also Andrew E. Hill, <em>Haggai,</em> <em>Zechariah and Malachi: An Introduction and
Commentary</em>, Tyndale Old Testament Commentaries, ed. David G. Firth, vol. 28
(Downers Grove, IL: InterVarsity Press, 2012), 261.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref4">[4]</a> Dean
Davis, <em>The High King
of Heaven: Discovering the Master Keys to the Great End Time Debate</em> (Enumclaw, WA: Redemption Press, 2014), 397.
Cf. also Barry G. Webb, <em>The Message of Zechariah</em>, The Bible
Speaks Today, ed. J. A. Motyer (Downers Grove, IL: InterVarsity Press, 2003),
179.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-2-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 (2 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-2-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 (1 of 8)</title>
		<link>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Habegger]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 20:26:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[amillenialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dispensationalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[premillenialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Zechariah 14]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11006</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Post #1 “The Need for an Amillennial Approach” The last chapter of Zechariah tends to be neglected by amillennialists, especially in comparison to the emphasis given it by premillennialists. While amillennialists anticipate a single consummation and glorification of God’s kingdom in connection with the single Second Coming of the Lord Jesus, premillennialists use texts like [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 (1 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: xx-large;"><strong>Post #1 “The Need for an Amillennial Approach”</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">The last chapter of Zechariah tends to be neglected by amillennialists, especially in comparison to the emphasis given it by premillennialists. While amillennialists anticipate a single consummation and glorification of God’s kingdom in connection with the single Second Coming of the Lord Jesus, premillennialists use texts like Zechariah 14 to argue for an intermediate reign of Jesus upon the present earth. Such a reign would separate the Second Coming from the eternal perfection of God’s kingdom by at least a thousand years (a time period taken from Revelation 20). The dispensational variety of premillennialism particularly insists upon a strictly literal reading of Zechariah and other Old Testament apocalyptic literature. The result is a Second Coming which radically subjugates sinners and improves their fallen world without banishing sin and death entirely.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Such a “millennial” reign is a problem for the amillennialist because it contradicts the straightforward eschatology of the New Testament. The apostles and prophets and Jesus himself all declare that the very event of Christ’s return will be the end of sin and death. The Second Coming immediately brings the final separation of the righteous from the wicked, the end of the opportunity for repentance, and the eternal glory of a new creation freed from sin’s curse. Further problems also arise when a dispensational hermeneutic is applied to Zechariah 14. Because the role of apocalyptic symbolism is minimized, the result is a renewed Judaism, complete with temple worship and required annual feasts. Although some details may differ from earlier historical iterations, this is essentially the Mosaic system of worship resurrected. It would be a titanic reversal of Christ’s blood-bought accomplishments and a return to those types and shadows which his priestly work has rendered obsolete (Heb. 7:18–22; 8:13; 9:8–10; 10:1, 8–9, 18). A premillennial interpretation of Zechariah’s last chapter, especially that demanded by dispensational literalism, is clearly untenable when seen through the lens of the New Testament.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">For these reasons, an interpretation is needed which does not posit an intermediate messianic reign including renewed Judaism and the lingering effects of Adam’s fall. The interpreter must understand that the Old Testament prophets often foretold New Testament realities through the symbolic use of Old Covenant language. A woodenly literal hermeneutic cannot consistently explain such prophecies as that of Malachi 1:11: “For from the rising of the sun even to its setting, My name <em>will be</em> great among the nations, and in every place incense is going to be offered to My name, and a grain offering <em>that is</em> pure; for My name <em>will be</em> great among the nations,” says the Lord of hosts.” On the one hand, literal aspects of the Old Covenant such as incense and grain offerings could only be legitimately performed at the authorized location of the Jerusalem temple. On the other hand, the New Covenant era renders such a sacrificial system obsolete. However, once the interpreter acknowledges that the Spirit speaking through Malachi used Old Covenant institutions as pictures of future, New Covenant realities, Malachi’s words harmonize well with those of Jesus recorded in John 4:21 and 23: “Woman, believe Me, an hour is coming when neither in this mountain nor in Jerusalem will you worship the Father…. But an hour is coming, and now is, when the true worshipers will worship the Father in spirit and truth; for such people the Father seeks to be His worshipers.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Similarly, the apocalyptic mention of Jerusalem in Zechariah 14 must be allowed to point beyond the earthly city of David. “For here we do not have a lasting city, but we are seeking <em>the city</em> which is to come” (Heb. 13:14). Indeed, those in the New Testament church already “have come to Mount Zion and to the city of the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem” (Heb. 12:22). We are not of the old Sinai covenant “which corresponds to the present Jerusalem”; we are of the new covenant corresponding to “the Jerusalem above” who “is our mother” (Gal. 4:24–26). James the Lord’s brother points to the prophecy of Amos and thus confirms that God has rebuilt and restored the ruined tabernacle of David so that the Gentiles may seek the Lord and be called by his name (Acts 15:13–18). The nations are now joining themselves to Zion, the redeemed city of God, the New Testament church of Jesus Christ. If James and the other apostles could confidently use such a hermeneutic, so can we. This hermeneutic will provide us with an amillennial interpretation of Zechariah 14. Concerning Old Testament promises fulfilled after Christ’s First Advent, John MacKay rightly says, “The realisation is in terms of the heirs and successors of the Old Testament Zion, Jerusalem and Israel. This is not to rewrite the promise, but to satisfy it in its fullest and proper extent.”<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">Beginning with the next post, this blog series will present such an amillennial approach to the last chapter of the Book of Zechariah.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> John L. MacKay, <em>Haggai, Zechariah and Malachi: God’s Restored People</em>, Focus on the Bible Commentary Series (Fearn, Ross-shire, Scotland, Great Britain: Christian Focus, 2010), 417.</p>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/">An Amillennial Interpretation of Zechariah 14 (1 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/an-amillennial-interpretation-of-zechariah-14-1-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
