<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Current Events | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/current-events/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2013 21:00:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Current Events | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Reformed Rap Ruckus: Comments from the Empty Chair</title>
		<link>/reformed-rap-ruckus/</link>
					<comments>/reformed-rap-ruckus/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2013 21:00:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Rap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship of God]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1485</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Due to the kindness and large-heartedness of my friend Scott Brown, I was one of the speakers at the NCFIC conference on the Worship of God. Sadly, despite the many good and helpful emphases of that conference, it is now famous for the controversial and negative statements made about Reformed Rap by a panel of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/reformed-rap-ruckus/">Reformed Rap Ruckus: Comments from the Empty Chair</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Due to the kindness and large-heartedness of my friend <a title="Scott Brown" href="http://scottbrownonline.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Scott Brown</a>, I was one of the speakers at the <a title="Worship of God Conference" href="https://ncfic.org/events/view/the-worship-of-god" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NCFIC conference on the Worship of God</a>. Sadly, despite the many good and helpful emphases of that conference, it is now famous for the controversial and negative statements made about Reformed Rap by a panel of speakers in a Q &amp; A session towards the end of the conference. If you have viewed the video, you will notice an empty chair at the table of panelists. Though I do not actually know why that chair is empty, it holds a special significance for me since I could have been in it. I do not know whether to be sad or really happy that due to another conference obligation I had to leave the Worship of God conference early and could not participate in the panel. If I had been there, I hope I woould have had the boldness and wisdom to say something like what I will say here. This is why I entitle this blog: &#8220;Comments from the Empty Chair.&#8221;</p>
<p>Being old (Well 62!) and not particularly &#8220;Facebook and blog aware,&#8221; I was alerted to this controversy first by a much younger member of my church. After <a title="NCFIC Panel Discussion" href="https://vimeo.com/80291749" target="_blank" rel="noopener">viewing the video</a> and reading <a title="Ligon Duncan on Reformed Rap" href="http://www.raanetwork.org/the-holy-hip-hop-hullabaloo/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ligon Duncan&#8217;s related comments</a>, I wrote the following email to the to my younger, but like-minded, brother in the Lord. It is slightly edited for this blog.</p>
<blockquote><p>Thanks for pointing out the article from Ligon Duncan addressing the Reformed rap furor caused by the panel at the Worship of God conference. It is pretty well known&#8211;at least I have made no secret of it&#8211;that I enjoy Shai Linne&#8217;s doctrinally solid raps. I have played them for college students in college classes with a good conscience and with gladness that they present the Christian religion in a different and contemporary cultural form. I think that as an art form and performance this may give them a helpfulness that other art forms and performance styles may not possess for today&#8217;s generation.</p>
<p>I certainly do not agree with many of the things the panelists said. . . . I am glad that <a title="Botkin Apology" href="http://scottbrownonline.com/an-apology/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Botkin apologized for the unfortunate things he said</a>. I certainly do not agree with the very negative tone of the video as a whole about Reformed rap. Yes, Reformed rap does draw attention to the perfomer (or rapper), but all musical performance art does. I do not think that rap can be singled out for this reason as bad.</p>
<p>Having said all of this, my reservation about rap in a meeting of the church is the same as my reservation about a lot of contemporary and traditional music in church. I doubt if it has much or any utility in meetings of the church, because it is performance. If rap has any justification in the liturgy of the church it would be as music I suppose. Meetings of the church are not about performance, but about worship. By the way, the moment preaching takes on the indirectness and artificiality of performance I think it ceases to be true preaching with the authenticity and directness necessary. The part of worship involved here is singing the praise of God and particularly the congregational singing of the praise of God.</p>
<p>You mentioned as a speculative possibility a whole church rapping together. I have actually never seen congregational rapping and know of no instance of it. It would have to be a whole other world before any churches I know could do this. Indeed, rap seems to me to be essentially a performance style.</p>
<p>In sum, I have no problem with Reformed rap as performance or art form. I can see how it might be used in concerts or other gatherings with an evangelistic intent. I cannot see how it could have any utility or edification and thus place in a meeting of the church of the living God.</p></blockquote>
<p>Since I wrote the above email both <a title="Scott Brown Apology" href="http://scottbrownonline.com/please-forgive-me/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Scott Brown</a> and <a title="Joel Beeke Apology" href="http://www.challies.com/articles/joel-beeke-christian-rap-and-public-apologies" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Joel Beeke</a> have issued apologies for aspects of their comments.  I think their apologies show wisdom and humility.  Both emphasize the distinction I am insisting on in this blog.  Let me only add that my ministry at the NCFIC conference emphasized the crucial distinction I was making at the Worship of God conference between the corporate worship of the church and other situations.  The question of whether Reformed rap may be a good and useful kind of performance art and thus evangelistic tool is very different from the question of whether any such performance art has any place in the formal worship of Christ&#8217;s church. These questions should be separated for a more fruitful discussion.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/reformed-rap-ruckus/">Reformed Rap Ruckus: Comments from the Empty Chair</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/reformed-rap-ruckus/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Update from Dr. Sam Waldron</title>
		<link>/update-from-sam-waldron/</link>
					<comments>/update-from-sam-waldron/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2013 17:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Course offerings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1431</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Below is an e-mail update sent out from Dr. Sam Waldron. If you would like to be added to the Midwest Center for Theological Studies e-mail list, please sign up here! Friends of MCTS, In April I wrote an email to report to you our friends to keep you abreast of several, encouraging changes in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/update-from-sam-waldron/">Update from Dr. Sam Waldron</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Below is an e-mail update sent out from Dr. Sam Waldron. If you would like to be added to the Midwest Center for Theological Studies e-mail list, <a title="MCTS E-Mail Sign Up" href="http://eepurl.com/DqxTr" target="_blank" rel="noopener">please sign up here</a>!</em></p>
<p>Friends of MCTS,</p>
<p>In April I wrote an email to report to you our friends to keep you abreast of several, encouraging changes in the ministry of MCTS.</p>
<p>First, while MCTS is governed by a board of directors, it is hosted by a local church.&nbsp; MCTS is now hosted by Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro where I was set apart as a pastor in June and joined Pastors Joe Wilson and Ron Miller in the eldership of that church.&nbsp; We are very thankful for the very positive and supportive atmosphere at Grace toward the ministry of MCTS.</p>
<p>Second, I want to report on what I believe to be a very successful MCTS Board Meeting.&nbsp; My hope was that we could encourage our board by honoring in specific ways their authority over MCTS to take a much more active role in the leadership of MCTS.&nbsp; I am very encouraged that this was accomplished.&nbsp; I want to thank the board members for their diligent work and the help I am sure they will be to us in the future.&nbsp; The chartering and formation of several active committees promise to lead us forward in very helpful ways.</p>
<p>Third, the coming school year is almost upon us.&nbsp; We have six live classes scheduled to be taught including the last two in our Basic Training curriculum.&nbsp; I begin the year with the second of my three courses taking the student through the historical theology.&nbsp; It deals with what I call the Augustinian Church and covers what are often thought of as the Medieval and Reformation periods of church history.&nbsp;&nbsp; Michael Emadi will then be teaching the two semesters of Elementary Hebrew for us later in the fall and then beginning the second semester in January.&nbsp; Richard Barcellos will be teaching an overview of Biblical Theology in a modular course in January and Tom Ascol will be leading our modular course on Preaching in June.&nbsp; I will be teaching Modern Church History in the spring. If you would like to livestream any of these classes online or take them for credit as a student, please let our registrar know:&nbsp;<a href="mailto:registrar@mctsowensboro.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">registrar@mctsowensboro.org</a></p>
<p>Fourth, American Vision has just released an over hour long video of the Revelation Symposium moderated&nbsp; by Brian Borgman in February in which I participated along with Jim Hamilton and Gary Demar.&nbsp; A two minute promotional video is available here:&nbsp;<a href="http://mctsowensboro.us7.list-manage.com/track/click?u=11118de60955d83b1e4e6bea8&amp;id=01d6a46c10&amp;e=b2a6109dc6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/<wbr>2013/08/waldron-on-revelation/</wbr></a></p>
<p>Fifth, we exist to serve Christ&#8217;s churches by training men for the ministry.&nbsp; If you would like to help us in that work, feel free to&nbsp;contact&nbsp;our registrar. Again, his e-mail address is:&nbsp;<a href="mailto:registrar@mctsowensboro.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">registrar@mctsowensboro.<wbr>org</wbr></a></p>
<p>The Lord Reigns,<br />
Dr. Sam Waldron</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/update-from-sam-waldron/">Update from Dr. Sam Waldron</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/update-from-sam-waldron/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Serving Christ in Namibia, Africa</title>
		<link>/serving-christ-in-namibia-africa/</link>
					<comments>/serving-christ-in-namibia-africa/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2011 15:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Divito]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Namibia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1128</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dear Brothers and Sisters in Christ, Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ! Dr. Richard Barcellos and I were privileged to serve our Savior in Namibia, Africa earlier this month. At the request of several Reformed Baptist pastors and missionaries, we were asked to equip pastors and church [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/serving-christ-in-namibia-africa/">Serving Christ in Namibia, Africa</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dear Brothers and Sisters in Christ,</p>
<p>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ!</p>
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos and I were privileged to serve our Savior in Namibia, Africa earlier this month. At the request of several Reformed Baptist pastors and missionaries, we were asked to equip pastors and church leaders in theological training at the newly formed Grace Ministerial Academy in Windhoek. Through the week of August 8th through the 12th, Rich taught a course on Hermeneutics in the morning while I followed up in the afternoon with a course on Worldviews. We had several pastors and church leaders as students as well as a few others auditing our courses.  They were hungry to grow in their knowledge of God&#8217;s Word and our prayer is that we helped each of them to &#8220;hold firm to the trustworthy word as taught, so that he may be able to give instruction in sound doctrine and also to rebuke those who contradict it&#8221; (Titus 1:9).  One of the students made my week when he commented after one of my classes something like, &#8220;I took a class on Worldviews at [a seminary in Africa]. They taught it philisophically. You are teaching it biblically. Thank you.&#8221; I know Rich also received encouraging feedback.</p>
<p>Additionally, we both had opportunities to preach in local churches while in Namibia. Between the two of us, we preached several times at three different churches. Furthermore, Eastside Baptist Church in Windhoek asked me to teach twice during evening meetings at their church. Because I am a former Mormon, their pastors asked me to teach on Mormonism and witnessing to cultists during their midweek service. They also requested that I cover Decision Making and the Will of God at a special Thursday meeting, a topic that I care deeply about. After finishing my message on biblical decision making, the church where Rich and I preached on our second Lord&#8217;s Day in Swakopmund requested that I repeat my message at their church. By God&#8217;s grace, our preaching and teaching was warmly received. As you can see, these pastors and churches were clearly hungry to spiritually feast on God&#8217;s truth taught from His Word. Praise God!</p>
<p>We thank all of you who prayed for us while we were in Africa. The Lord definitely heard your prayers! Our travels went smoothly, we remained in good health, and our families did well while we were away. But most importantly, we were able to serve Christ and His churches in Namibia. Now we look forward to seeing the fruit of our labors. May Christ richly bless His kingdom in Namibia and beyond for His glory!</p>
<p>&#8220;Now to him who is able to do far more abundantly than all that we ask or think, according to the power at work within us, to him be glory in the church and in Christ Jesus throughout all generations, forever and ever. Amen&#8221; (Ephesians 3:20-21).</p>
<p>Because of His grace,<br />
John Divito<br />
Member, Heritage Baptist Church, Owensboro, KY<br />
Administrator, Midwest Center for Theological Studies</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/serving-christ-in-namibia-africa/">Serving Christ in Namibia, Africa</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/serving-christ-in-namibia-africa/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MCTS Podcast 23: Dr. Waldron&#8217;s Upcoming Writing Projects</title>
		<link>/mcts-podcast-23-dr-waldrons-upcoming-writing-projects/</link>
					<comments>/mcts-podcast-23-dr-waldrons-upcoming-writing-projects/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2011 14:00:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Divito]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Regulative Principle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1101</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In our latest video podcast, Dr. Waldron discusses his upcoming writing projects, including some thoughts on the regulative principle of worship. adminCBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-podcast-23-dr-waldrons-upcoming-writing-projects/">MCTS Podcast 23: Dr. Waldron&#8217;s Upcoming Writing Projects</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In our latest video podcast, Dr. Waldron discusses his upcoming writing projects, including some thoughts on the regulative principle of worship.<br />
<object classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" width="398" height="299" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true"><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"><param name="src" value="http://vimeo.com/moogaloop.swf?clip_id=26844131&amp;server=vimeo.com&amp;show_title=0&amp;show_byline=0&amp;show_portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff&amp;fullscreen=1&amp;autoplay=1&amp;loop=0"></object></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-podcast-23-dr-waldrons-upcoming-writing-projects/">MCTS Podcast 23: Dr. Waldron&#8217;s Upcoming Writing Projects</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mcts-podcast-23-dr-waldrons-upcoming-writing-projects/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Please Pray for Our Training in Namibia</title>
		<link>/please-pray-for-our-training-in-namibia/</link>
					<comments>/please-pray-for-our-training-in-namibia/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2011 16:00:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Divito]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Namibia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1111</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Next week, Dr. Richard Barcellos and I will be flying to Namibia, Africa to teach two modular courses to indigenous pastors and church leaders at Grace Ministerial Academy. He will be covering hermeneutics while I will handle worldviews. Please pray for us! In training these pastors, we have a wonderful opportunity but also a humbling [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/please-pray-for-our-training-in-namibia/">Please Pray for Our Training in Namibia</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-1114" title="GraceMinisterialAcademy" src="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/GraceMinisterialAcademy-300x225.jpg" alt="Grace Ministerial Academy" width="300" height="225" align="right">Next week, Dr. Richard Barcellos and I will be flying to Namibia, Africa to teach two modular courses to indigenous pastors and church leaders at <a href="http://buddyandjulianamibia.blogspot.com/2011/04/grace-ministerial-academy.html">Grace Ministerial Academy</a>. He will be covering hermeneutics while I will handle worldviews.</p>
<p>Please pray for us! In training these pastors, we have a wonderful opportunity but also a humbling responsibility entrusted to us. To help you in your prayers, I have included below my course syllabus. May we glorify Christ through the equipping of His people for the growth of His kingdom!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Christianity and Its Competitors:</strong><br />
<em>Contending for the Christian Worldview</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Course Purpose</strong><br />
The purpose of this course is to equip each pastor and church leader to &#8220;hold firm to the trustworthy word as taught, so that he may be able to give instruction in sound doctrine and also to rebuke those who contradict it&#8221; (Titus 1:9).  This will be accomplished through establishing a Biblical foundation of contending for the faith, explaining the Christian worldview, and evaluating other competing worldviews.</p>
<p><strong>Course Reading</strong><br />
James W. Sire, <em>Scripture Twisting: 20 Ways the Cults Misread the Bible</em> (Downers Grove IL, USA: Intervarsity Press, 1980).<br />
Richard Gehman, <em>Who are the Living Dead? A Theology of Death, Life After Death and the Living-Dead</em> (Nairobi, Kenya: Evangel Publishing House, 1999).</p>
<p><strong>Course Requirements</strong><br />
<em> Four Quizzes</em>: each quiz is worth 25 points, 100 points total<br />
A quiz will be given each day on Tuesday through Friday covering the previous day&#8217;s lectures.  The quizzes will have multiple choice, true or false, matching, fill-in-the-blank, short answer, and listing questions included.  Together, they will cover all of the lecture material for the course.</p>
<p><em>Final Exam</em>: each essay is worth 50 points, 100 points total<br />
A final exam will assess overall competence in the topics covered in the course. Two essay questions will be completed which integrate the course reading with critical reflection on the lecture content and supplemental material.</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Final Essay Questions</span><br />
1)	Using Sire&#8217;s <em>Scripture Twisting</em>, select ten Scripture reading errors. For each misreading, identify and define it, give an example of it from the lectures or supplemental materials (<em>not</em> included in Sire&#8217;s book), and provide a biblical response. 5 pages minimum.<br />
2)	Summarize and compare the theology of death, life after death, and the living-dead between three worldviews: 1) African Traditional Religion (using Gehman&#8217;s <em>Who are the Living Dead?</em>), 2) a Christian competitor (chosen from the course lectures or the supplemental materials), and 3) the biblical worldview. 5 pages minimum.</p>
<p><strong>Course Evaluation</strong><br />
The student&#8217;s final grade will be determined by dividing his total points earned in half. A student will have successfully completed this course by achieving a cumulative grade of 75 percent or above for his course work. The letter equivalents for the percentile grades assigned are as follows:</p>
<table border="0">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>A	&#8212;	96-100</td>
<td>B-	&#8212;	81-84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>A-	&#8212;	91-95</td>
<td>C+	&#8212;	78-80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>B+	&#8212;	88-90</td>
<td>C	&#8212;	75-77</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>B	&#8212;	85-87</td>
<td>C-	&#8212;	71-74</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>Course Outline</strong><br />
<em>First Unit: Christianity</em><br />
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 1: Biblical Foundations</span><br />
I. 	Jude 1-4<br />
II.	1 Peter 3:14-16<br />
III.	Romans 1:18-32<br />
IV.	Acts 17:16-34<br />
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 2: The Christian Worldview</span><br />
I.	What is a Worldview?<br />
II.	What is the Christian Worldview?</p>
<p><em>Second Unit: Its Competitors</em><br />
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 1: Recognizing False Worldviews</span><br />
I. 	The Five Keys of Biblical Discernment<br />
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 2: Evaluating False Worldviews</span><br />
I.	Roman Catholicism<br />
II.	Prosperity Gospel<br />
III.	Seventh-Day Adventism<br />
IV.	Jehovah&#8217;s Witnesses<br />
V.	Mormonism</p>
<p><em>Appendix</em></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/please-pray-for-our-training-in-namibia/">Please Pray for Our Training in Namibia</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/please-pray-for-our-training-in-namibia/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MCTS Podcast 20: Dr. Waldron&#8217;s International Ministry Opportunities</title>
		<link>/mcts-podcast-20/</link>
					<comments>/mcts-podcast-20/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2011 14:00:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Divito]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1091</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>On this week&#8217;s video podcast, Dr. Sam Waldron discusses some of his recent and upcoming international ministry opportunities. adminCBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-podcast-20/">MCTS Podcast 20: Dr. Waldron&#8217;s International Ministry Opportunities</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On this week&#8217;s video podcast, Dr. Sam Waldron discusses some of his recent and upcoming international ministry opportunities.<br />
<object classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" width="398" height="299" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true"><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"><param name="src" value="http://vimeo.com/moogaloop.swf?clip_id=26551529&amp;server=vimeo.com&amp;show_title=0&amp;show_byline=0&amp;show_portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff&amp;fullscreen=1&amp;autoplay=1&amp;loop=0"></object></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-podcast-20/">MCTS Podcast 20: Dr. Waldron&#8217;s International Ministry Opportunities</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mcts-podcast-20/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 8 of 8)</title>
		<link>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-part-8-of-8/</link>
					<comments>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-part-8-of-8/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2011 14:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[end times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[harold camping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[may 21]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rapture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1017</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I have one final observation to make on this whole debacle. When those who profess to be Bible-believing Christians with bold face claim to be able to decipher the time of Christ&#8217;s coming, we are apt to assume that the Bible must not be clear about this issue. If so many professing Christians over so [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-part-8-of-8/">Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 8 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have one final observation to make on this whole debacle.</p>
<p>When those who profess to be Bible-believing Christians with bold face claim to be able to decipher the time of Christ&#8217;s coming, we are apt to assume that the Bible must not be clear about this issue.  If so many professing Christians over so many centuries have predicted the time of Christ&#8217;s return, and if so many well-meaning Christians have listened to them, then the Bible must not be clear on this.  The Bible must open the door to it.</p>
<p>But let me ask you a question, Is the Bible clear that no one can and no one ought to attempt to predict of the time of Christ&#8217;s return?  Yes. Then what is the problem?  Is the problem with the Bible?  Is the problem with the clarity of Scripture?  Is the problem with the sufficiency of Scripture?  May we conclude that the Bible is an inadequate guide on this matter?  That is the way men are apt to argue.  That is what men are apt to conclude.  But all such suspicions are wrong.  The problem is not with the Bible.  The Bible is clear, and it is sufficient!</p>
<p>The problem is with us.  The problem is that we human beings are not very good listeners.  The problem is that we are like that rude person who incessantly presumes to finish our sentences for us.  Let me end this message with a simple plea.  I will address it to myself, but you make the application to yourself.  <em>Sam, would just shut up and let God finish what He is saying?  Sam, would you just be quiet and listen.  Sam, would you stop trying to finish God&#8217;s sentences for Him and listen&#8212;really listen&#8212;to what He has to say!</em></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-part-8-of-8/">Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 8 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-part-8-of-8/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 7 of 8)</title>
		<link>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-7/</link>
					<comments>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-7/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2011 14:00:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[end times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[harold camping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[may 21]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rapture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1014</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>III. Its Concluding Application The “date-setters” make predictions that time after time prove to be false. Thus, they are akin to false prophets, and we may apply to such false teachers the warnings of Deuteronomy 18:20f. Deuteronomy 18:20-22 20 &#8220;&#8216;But the prophet who speaks a word presumptuously in My name which I have not commanded [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-7/">Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 7 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>III.	Its Concluding Application</strong></p>
<p>The “date-setters” make predictions that time after time prove to be false.  Thus, they are akin to false prophets, and we may apply to such false teachers the warnings of Deuteronomy 18:20f.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Deuteronomy 18:20-22   20</strong> &#8220;&#8216;But the prophet who speaks a word presumptuously in My name which I have not commanded him to speak, or which he speaks in the name of other gods, that prophet shall die.&#8217; You may say in your heart, &#8216;How will we know the word which the LORD has not spoken?&#8217; When a prophet speaks in the name of the LORD, if the thing does not come about or come true, that is the thing which the LORD has not spoken. The prophet has spoken it presumptuously; you shall not be afraid of him.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>This passage says three things that we may apply to ourselves with regard to the modern date-setters.</p>
<p><em><strong>Deuteronomy 18:22 addresses the people of God regarding the false prophet with the command, &#8220;You shall not be afraid of him.&#8221;</strong></em> The last words of Deuteronomy 18 are perfectly applicable to the modern date-setters.  There is something in us that tends to respond fearfully to the Campings of the world.  Could it be true?  What if they are right?  But even before Camping’s prediction disproved itself, the Bible gave us sober reason not to believe it.  Christ has said that such predicting of His return is impossible.  So heed the warning of the Word of God against such false prophets.  Don&#8217;t be afraid of them!  Don&#8217;t be worried by them!  Don&#8217;t be rattled by them!  Don&#8217;t be moved by them!  Don&#8217;t be made cautious by them!  Don&#8217;t give respect to their forecasts in any way!  They may speak with a show of great learning.  They may speak with amazing dogmatism.  They may speak calm solemnity.  Still, don&#8217;t be afraid of them.</p>
<p><em><strong>Deuteronomy 18:20 commands of the false prophet:  &#8220;That prophet shall die.&#8221;</strong></em> False prophets in the Old Testament were to be put to death.  We live no longer in the Old Testament economy, and I am not teaching that we should not literally kill false prophets like Camping.  But there is an application of this command to us in the NT church.  We should do everything we can to kill their influence and standing in the church.  We should rebuke them, denounce them, warn people against them, and, if they happen to be members of our churches, exercise church discipline against them.</p>
<p>Why is this an important duty for us to take to heart?  Such false teachers give occasion to the wicked to mock Christianity.  They give Bible-believing Christianity a bad name.  They deceive and lead into sin immature believers.  They bring scorn on the very doctrine they pretend to uphold, the second coming of Christ.  People hear of such date-setting for the second coming of Christ and say to themselves, “Those crazy Christians are at it again!”  We must get the Word out that people who write and believe predictions like Camping’s do not represent biblical Christianity or our Savior.  We must let people know that Christ Himself condemns such predictions.</p>
<p><em><strong>Deuteronomy 18 also contains a command about the true prophet in verse 19:  &#8220;Whoever will not listen to My words which he shall speak in My name, I Myself will require it of him.&#8221;</strong></em> In Old Testament Israel the presence of false prophets did not mean that there were not true prophets to whom Israel had to listen.  Similarly in our day the presence of false predictions of Christ&#8217;s return does not mean that we may ignore all that Bible does teach about Christ&#8217;s return.  We must not allow all the extremism to steal from us the &#8220;blessed hope&#8221; of the appearing of our great God and Savior, Christ Jesus.  If you are here tonight and do not know Jesus Christ, you must not allow the failure of lunatic predictions like those of Camping to make you secure or lull you to sleep.  Camping was wrong about yesterday.  But Jesus is not wrong about someday!  Judgment is coming.  If it were today, would you appear on the right hand before Jesus or would you wake to find yourself on the dreadful left hand of the coming King and doomed to eternal judgment?</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-7/">Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 7 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 6 of 8)</title>
		<link>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-6/</link>
					<comments>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-6/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2011 14:00:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[end times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[harold camping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[may 21]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rapture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1011</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Context is crucial in understanding Matthew 24:36. Here is the circle of context which must be considered. C. The Broader New Testament Context I want you to look at two other passages in the New Testament that are related to the statement of Jesus in Matthew 24:36. The first passage is Acts 1:6, 7. And [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-6/">Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 6 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Context is crucial in understanding Matthew 24:36.  Here is the circle of context which must be considered.</p>
<p><strong>C.	The Broader New Testament Context</strong></p>
<p>I want you to look at two other passages in the New Testament that are related to the statement of Jesus in Matthew 24:36.</p>
<p><em><strong>The first passage is Acts 1:6, 7.</strong></em></p>
<blockquote><p>And so when they had come together, they were asking Him, saying, &#8220;Lord, is it at this time You are restoring the kingdom to Israel? &#8221; He said to them, &#8220;It is not for you to know times or epochs which the Father has fixed by His own authority.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>When the disciples asked about the restoration of the kingdom to Israel, their question was rooted in Old Testament prophecy.  The Old Testament had, indeed, predicted &#8220;the time &#8230; when the saints &#8230; (would take) &#8230; possession of the kingdom&#8221; (Dan. 7:22).  Now it may be that the disciples still had too carnal and nationalistic an idea of what the restoration of the kingdom to Israel would mean, but it is clear that their hope for such a restoration was firmly built on biblical basis (Acts 3:21; Matt. 19:28).  This restoration occurs, of course, in conjunction with the glorious appearance of the Messiah in His second coming.</p>
<p>Thus, the disciples are raising here substantially the same question that Jesus answered in Matt. 24:36.  Not surprisingly, Jesus answers them in language which echoes Matt. 24:36.  He refers to the Father just as He did in Matt. 24:36.  There he said,  &#8220;But of that day and hour no one knows, not even the angels of heaven, nor the Son, but the Father alone&#8221;.  Here He says, &#8220;it is not for you to know times or epochs which the Father has fixed by His own authority&#8221;.  The statements are clearly parallel, but there is one key point at which Jesus enlarges upon and interprets what He said in Matt. 24:36.  You will notice that He does not speak of &#8220;the day and the hour&#8221;. Now He speaks of &#8220;times or epochs&#8221;.</p>
<p>Whatever these words more exactly mean, they plainly confirm the meaning that we have attached to the words of Jesus in Matt. 24:36.  When Jesus denies that we can know the day or hour, He is not contrasting the day and the hour with the week, month, or year.  Rather, He is denying that we can have any knowledge of the date of Christ&#8217;s arrival.  Not the day, nor the hour, nor the time, nor the epoch of Christ’s return can be known, and therefore certainly not the week, month, or year.</p>
<p><em><strong>The second passage is 1 Thessalonians 5:1-4.</strong></em></p>
<blockquote><p>Now as to the times and the epochs, brethren, you have no need of anything to be written to you. For you yourselves know full well that the day of the Lord will come just like a thief in the night. While they are saying, &#8220;Peace and safety!&#8221; then destruction will come upon them suddenly like birth pangs upon a woman with child; and they shall not escape. But you, brethren, are not in darkness, that the day should overtake you like a thief.</p></blockquote>
<p>The meaning of this passage is plain itself and also plain in light of Matt. 24:36 and Acts 1:6, 7.  Paul here uses the same two words used in Acts 1:6, 7:  &#8220;times and epochs&#8221;.  He plainly says that there is no need to write them about such things because they already know that the day of the Lord is coming like a thief in the night.  The phrase, “<em>thief in the night</em>”, echoes a passage in Matthew 24 a few verses after our text:</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;But be sure of this, that if the head of the house had known at what time of the night the thief was coming, he would have been on the alert and would not have allowed his house to be broken into. For this reason you also must be ready; for the Son of Man is coming at an hour when you do not think He will.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>The idea is plainly that Christ&#8217;s coming is sudden and unexpected.  A thief does not announce the time of his burglary.  Neither does Christ announce the time of His coming.</p>
<p>This is confirmed by v. 3.  That verse pictures the ungodly world as promising itself peace and safety when sudden and inescapable judgment overtakes them through Christ&#8217;s return.  Thus, Paul is plainly saying that he need not write them about the time of Christ&#8217;s return, because they already know that its timing is unknown.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-6/">Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 6 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-6/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 5 of 8)</title>
		<link>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-5/</link>
					<comments>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-5/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2011 14:00:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[end times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[harold camping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[may 21]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rapture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1008</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The third thing that must be considered regarding Matthew 24:36 is &#8230; III. Its Contextual Confirmation False teachers have always quoted Scripture. 2 Peter 3:15-16 says: &#8220;and regard the patience of our Lord as salvation; just as also our beloved brother Paul, according to the wisdom given him, wrote to you, as also in all [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-5/">Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 5 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The third thing that must be considered regarding Matthew 24:36 is &#8230;</p>
<p><strong>III.	Its Contextual Confirmation</strong></p>
<p>False teachers have always quoted Scripture.  2 Peter 3:15-16 says:  &#8220;and regard the patience of our Lord as salvation; just as also our beloved brother Paul, according to the wisdom given him, wrote to you, as also in all his letters, speaking in them of these things, in which are some things hard to understand, which the untaught and unstable distort, as they do also the rest of the Scriptures, to their own destruction.&#8221;  The problem with the heretic&#8217;s use of Scripture is that they always quote it out of context.  One of the marks of false teaching is that it quotes Scripture but without regard to its context.</p>
<p>This is also true of the perversion of Scripture that we are now considering.   It quotes and interprets Matt. 24:36 without regard to its biblical context.  It is, therefore, my purpose to show you very carefully what this verse means within its context.  We will look at the immediately preceding context, the immediately succeeding context, and the broader New Testament context.</p>
<p><strong>A.	The Immediately Preceding Context</strong></p>
<p>The significant thing that we learn about verse 36 when we read the preceding context is that it is a part of a contrast.
</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Matthew 24:34-36</strong> &#8220;Truly I say to you, this generation will not pass away until all these things take place. Heaven and earth will pass away, but My words will not pass away. But of that day and hour no one knows, not even the angels of heaven, nor the Son, but the Father alone.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>What is the contrast here?  It is between the &#8220;all these things&#8221; of v. 34 and &#8220;that day and hour&#8221; of v. 36. If &#8220;that day and hour&#8221; refers, as we have seen, to the second coming of Christ, to what does the phrase, &#8220;all these things,&#8221; refer?  To answer this question look at Matt. 24:1-3. Their questions show that the disciples were in danger of confusing two distinct events:  the destruction of Jerusalem and the second coming of Christ.  The contrast of vv. 34-36 is intended to clear up this confusion for them.  &#8220;All these things&#8221;, therefore, refers to all those events associated with the destruction of the temple and Jerusalem.  &#8220;That day and hour&#8221; refers to the events associated with the second coming of Christ proper.</p>
<p>Here we come to the crucial point for our purposes.  How does Christ contrast these two events? He gives a time-sign for the destruction of Jerusalem.  He gives no time-sign for the second coming of Christ.  Notice:  &#8220;This generation will not pass away until all these things take place &#8230; but of that day and hour no one knows&#8230;&#8221;  Do you see the contrast Jesus makes in these verses?  He contrasts the giving of a time-sign for the destruction of Jerusalem with the giving of no time-sign for His Second Coming.  He gives a very broad time-sign for the destruction of Jerusalem&#8212;this generation.  The destruction of Jerusalem, he says, will occur sometime in the next forty years, but I give you no time-sign at all for my own coming.</p>
<p>What does this mean for our interpretation of Matt. 24:36?  Is Jesus saying, what the date-setters assert, that we cannot know the day or hour, but we can know the week, month, or year?  <em><strong>Obviously not!</strong></em> The contrast is not between the day and the month or between knowing week, but not the hour.  It is between a broad time-sign encompassing a period of forty years and no time-sign at all. Jesus determined the date of the destruction of Jerusalem to within forty years, but He gives no time-sign for His coming at all.  What nonsense this makes of the claims of the date-setters to know even the year of Christ&#8217;s coming!  Far from knowing the week, month, or year, we do not even know the generation of Christ&#8217;s coming!</p>
<p><strong>B.	The Immediately Succeeding Context</strong></p>
<p>In the following context Jesus calls upon his disciples to be constantly alert for His return (Matt. 24:42-44, 50; 25:13).  These commands to be alert for His coming assume that even then the timing of His coming was completely unknown.  If the week and month of Christ&#8217;s return could be known, as the date-setters suggest, then the early disciples would not have had to be constantly alert.  Clearly, then, when Jesus says that you do not know the day or hour of my return, He means to say that its timing is completely unknown, therefore you must be always ready.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-5/">Why the Prediction That Christ Would Come May 21 Was Wrong (Part 5 of 8)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/why-the-prediction-that-christ-would-come-may-21-was-wrong-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
