<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (V)	</title>
	<atom:link href="/1030-2/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/1030-2/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2011 03:06:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Erik Christenson		</title>
		<link>/1030-2/#comment-307</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Erik Christenson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2011 03:06:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1030#comment-307</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thanks Rich,

Very well put.  By the way, I loved your book &quot;In Defense of the Decalogue&quot;.

I have a question.  How do you deal with the objection brought by NCT followers that the seventh-day as mentioned in Genesis 2:2-3 is different than the Sabbath?  They will make statements that the seventh-day was a single historical day and that there is no indication in the text of a continous cycle of days.  They perpose that only at the Exodus does the &quot;Sabbath&quot; get put into place.  They completely divorce any Sabbath implications in the Genesis account.  They strongly maintain that the Genesis and Exodus texts completely separate the seventh-day from the Sabbath as being two very different events.

God bless and keep up the great work.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks Rich,</p>
<p>Very well put.  By the way, I loved your book &#8220;In Defense of the Decalogue&#8221;.</p>
<p>I have a question.  How do you deal with the objection brought by NCT followers that the seventh-day as mentioned in Genesis 2:2-3 is different than the Sabbath?  They will make statements that the seventh-day was a single historical day and that there is no indication in the text of a continous cycle of days.  They perpose that only at the Exodus does the &#8220;Sabbath&#8221; get put into place.  They completely divorce any Sabbath implications in the Genesis account.  They strongly maintain that the Genesis and Exodus texts completely separate the seventh-day from the Sabbath as being two very different events.</p>
<p>God bless and keep up the great work.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Midwest Center for Theological Studies: Owensboro, KY &#62; Blog &#62; Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (VI)		</title>
		<link>/1030-2/#comment-306</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Midwest Center for Theological Studies: Owensboro, KY &#62; Blog &#62; Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (VI)]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 05:05:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1030#comment-306</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[[...] Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (V) [...]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] Tom Wells’ book on the Sabbath: Chapter Three (V) [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Mike Waters		</title>
		<link>/1030-2/#comment-305</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Waters]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2011 21:36:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1030#comment-305</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thanks Dr Rich. Excellent. How unwise are we, to fight against something so blessed and beneficial!

These statements especially were thought breeders...

This leads us to the conclusion that man and Sabbath were made at the same time

We don’t serve the Sabbath, it serves us so we can serve God better

And he is Lord of it, not for the purpose of depriving men of that inestimable benefit which the Sabbath bestows, but for the purpose of bringing to the fullest realization on behalf of men that beneficent design for which the Sabbath was instituted (JM)

Christ administrates the Sabbath as the Son of Man during the whole interadvental period–the days of the new covenant. This relates Chris’s teaching on the Sabbath with both previous and future revelation]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks Dr Rich. Excellent. How unwise are we, to fight against something so blessed and beneficial!</p>
<p>These statements especially were thought breeders&#8230;</p>
<p>This leads us to the conclusion that man and Sabbath were made at the same time</p>
<p>We don’t serve the Sabbath, it serves us so we can serve God better</p>
<p>And he is Lord of it, not for the purpose of depriving men of that inestimable benefit which the Sabbath bestows, but for the purpose of bringing to the fullest realization on behalf of men that beneficent design for which the Sabbath was instituted (JM)</p>
<p>Christ administrates the Sabbath as the Son of Man during the whole interadvental period–the days of the new covenant. This relates Chris’s teaching on the Sabbath with both previous and future revelation</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
