<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Preaching | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/preaching/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 22:26:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Preaching | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The Imperative of Preaching Part II</title>
		<link>/scott-meadows-imp-2/</link>
					<comments>/scott-meadows-imp-2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 22:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15554</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This review was originally posted on HeraldofGrace.org and has been re-posted by the permission of the author. The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred RhetoricJohn CarrickBanner of Truth Presence and Implications of the Exemplary Imperative Carrick quotes other respected Reformed theologians on the matter who appear to share his concerns about EW-RHP&#8212;men like Jay [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/scott-meadows-imp-2/">The Imperative of Preaching Part II</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This review was originally posted on HeraldofGrace.org and has been re-posted by the permission of the author.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image {"align":"left","id":759,"linkDestination":"custom"} -->
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft"><a href="https://heraldofgrace.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Imperative_of_Preaching_John_Carrick1.jpg"><img src="https://heraldofgrace.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/Imperative_of_Preaching_John_Carrick1.jpg" alt="Imperative" class="wp-image-759"></a></figure></div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="http://www.trinitybookservice.com/index.php/the-imperative-of-preaching-hardcover-by-john-carrick.html">The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric</a><br>John Carrick<br>Banner of Truth</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Presence and Implications of the Exemplary Imperative</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Carrick quotes other respected Reformed theologians on the matter who appear to share his concerns about EW-RHP&#8212;men like Jay Adams, Hendrik Krabbendam, John R. de Witt, John Frame, and J. Douma. More importantly, Carrick shows that the Apostle Paul used historical examples as the basis for exhorting his hearers (citing 1 Cor 10.1-14), a classic concern of the RH school. Exhorting from example is also found in Hebrews, as P. E. Hughes (Visiting Professor of New Testament at WTS) noted in his excellent commentary:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The simplest sense [of 11.4] remains the best sense, namely, that Abel by his example of faith and righteousness still speaks to us today, even though he has so long been dead. The spectacle of his trustful integrity, even in the face of violence, should inspire us to persevere and to overcome by the same means. His was certainly an example that the faltering readers of this epistle were in need of emulating (123).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Carrick also enlists Dr. Richard Gaffin, who is himself &#8220;unashamedly a passionate exponent of biblical theology&#8221; (144-145), for the cause of applicatory preaching by citing his observation that James 5.16b-18 uses Elijah&#8217;s example of prayer in 1 Kings 18, an &#8220;incidental aspect&#8221; and &#8220;quite subordinate point&#8221; in the OT passage, to make a primary point of application for New Testament believers. Then Carrick raises a provocative question. &#8220;Does the RH school regard James&#8217; reference to Elijah as atomistic and moralistic, or not? If it does, then clearly it is claiming to be wiser than the inspired authors of the Word of God itself; and if it does not, then it is conceding the very point at issue in the original controversy. One of the major problems [if true, an understatement!&#8212;DSM] with the charge made by some within the redemptive-historical school . . . is that this charge actually recoils upon James himself&#8212; it recoils upon the Holy Scriptures of God&#8221; (127-128). Even though this statement is in the middle of the book, I got the impression that Carrick considered it something of a climax comparable to checkmate, the burr under his saddle from which he sought relief, the book&#8217;s raison d&#8217;&ecirc;tre. Christ Himself (128) exhorts tersely from an OT historical example when He urged us to &#8220;remember Lot&#8217;s wife&#8221; (Luke 17.32). Thus, &#8220;Holy Scripture leads the way&#8221; for our method of preaching (quoting Huyser, a proponent of the exemplary approach in the original controversy in the Netherlands, 123).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The exclamation point for the exemplary imperative comes from the NT&#8217;s appeal to Christ as the believer&#8217;s great Example to follow. This comes out in His charge to the disciples when He washed their feet (John 13.15), and in Peter&#8217;s counsel to suffering Christians (1 Pet 2.21, 23-24). Christ is both our Savior and our Example, and so we must hold to Him in both His roles. The RH school in some instances has been paranoid about the exemplary approach because of its historical association with &#8220;liberal theology and its na&iuml;ve Pelagianism,&#8221; but such heresy is not intrinsic to it.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Without embracing the exemplary imperative, we have no satisfactory explanation for passages like Hebrews 11, 1 Corinthians 10, James 5, and Luke 17. Homiletical Christocentricity is a good thing, but EW-RHP has degenerated to Christomonism. [Monism is a theory or doctrine that denies the existence of a distinction or duality in some sphere; here, Christ as gracious Savior and moral Example.]</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Scripture joins the concepts of example and imperative. The letter of any particular example is generally in the indicative, but the spirit of it is always in the imperative, with an implied, &#8220;Go and do likewise!&#8221; for the positive examples, and a tacit warning with the negative ones. Therefore, we should not be surprised that when RHP is uncomfortable with the imperative in preaching, it is also skittish about using examples, as illustrated in the defective preaching of Klaas Schilder, an early RHP advocate.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Expos&eacute; and Indictment of EW-RHP</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Here Carrick gets most personal in assailing the errors of his contemporaries, particularly the Dennison brothers<sup>1</sup>&nbsp;and Lee Irons, all his fellow OPC ministers associated with Kerux: A Journal of Biblical-Theological Preaching, available free online.&nbsp;<sup>2</sup></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In this journal, Carrick observes a striking emphasis upon the double indicatives of Christianity, and a corresponding dearth of the double imperatives (132). He bolsters this with quotations of both Dennison&#8217;s which castigate application per se as &#8220;man-centered&#8221; rather than &#8220;God-centered.&#8221; This is another false antithesis (133).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>James Dennison appeals for support to Geerhardus Vos&#8217; inaugural address already cited (footnote 4), but Carrick notes three problems with this. 1) EW-RHP has an overemphasis on eschatology in preaching. Vos&#8217; statement that &#8220;eschatology is prior to soteriology&#8221; is ambiguous. Vos may only have meant that eschatology is logically prior (God first resolved to glorify Himself in eternity and therefore decreed to saves us), while Dennison presses the slogan to mean eschatology is more important than soteriology (137), another idea altogether. 2) EW-RHP also exhibits an underemphasis on the ethical in preaching which opposes the NT&#8217;s strong emphasis, not to mention Vos&#8217; own characterization of Pauline theology in terms of an &#8220;already&#8212;not yet&#8221; structure. Dennison&#8217;s revels in the &#8220;already&#8221; aspects (indicatives) to the neglect of &#8220;not yet&#8221; aspects (imperatives) in the kingdom of God. 3) EW-RHP idealizes, almost idolizes, Geerhardus Vos, and this is wrong. His preaching was too heavily theological, with sermons resembling essays. Even Dr. J. Gresham Machen had this opinion (source: biography by Stonehouse). Further, Vos&#8217; sermons were also sparse in application, though not as bad as EW-RHP represented in Kerux.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Survey Resumed and Concluded</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>A few sundry observations round out Carrick&#8217;s last chapter. First, biblical salvation is covenantal, and in a bilateral, not unilateral way. Both God and man are parties to the covenant. God reveals, and man responds. EW-RHP fails to appreciate the latter and exposes itself to a fair charge of &#8220;objectivism.&#8221; It is hard to know exactly what Carrick has in mind by this word since he does not explain it; it is related to the idea of &#8220;overlooking man&#8221; (139). EW-RHP exaggerates the concept of &#8220;progress&#8221; while giving short shrift to &#8220;concourse,&#8221; the relationship between God and man, and insight Carrick gleans from scholar C. Trimp.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Second, Carrick uses considerable space reviewing some of Gaffin&#8217;s helpful contributions to the topic, including 1) the relevance of the historia salutis and the ordo salutis and their correspondence to redemption accomplished and redemption applied, with the evident imbalance in EW-RHP, 2) the dual identity of OT characters as both types of Christ and examples for believers, 3) the irreversibility and inseparability of the indicative and imperative moods in Scripture and biblical preaching, and 4) the strong Reformed homiletical tradition of explicatio et applicatio verbi Dei (explication and application of God&#8217;s Word). Carrick concludes that a balance of the indicative and the imperative, of proclamation and appeal, is justified from all considerations, and that this is just what EW-RHP, a &#8220;homiletical innovation&#8221; (144), lacks. This is bound to lead to &#8220;distortions of a more or less serious character&#8221; (146).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>With stunning insight, R. L. Dabney almost seems to have anticipated the controversy and resolved it in 1870 before it erupted in the twentieth century.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>[Christianity&#8217;s] end and aim is holy living (Eph 1.4; Tit 2.14; et passim). Of this holy life, the law of God is the rule. The believer justified in Christ does not, indeed, look to the law for his redeeming merit; but he receives it as his guide to the obedience of faith and love, as fully as though he were still under a covenant of works. He therefore needs practical instruction, as really as the unbeliever. It must stimulate and direct him in the Christian race, and make him a &#8220;peculiar person, zealous of good works.&#8221; The exclusive preaching of doctrine [viz., the indicative&#8212;DSM] to professed Christians tends to cultivate an Antinomian Spirit. The exclusive inculcation of duties [viz., the imperative, or application&#8212;DSM] fosters self-righteousness. The edification of the Church, then, demands the diligent intermixture of both kinds. This precept may be confirmed by the remark, that, as the motives and obligations of all duties are rooted in the doctrines, so the best illustrations of the doctrines are by their application to the duties. The two are inseparably connected as grounds and conclusions, as means and end; and their systematic separation in your instructions would leave your hearers incapable of a correct understanding of either.<sup>3</sup></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This sounds amazingly like Carrick&#8217;s conclusion in the last chapter (146). He may have been influenced by Dabney, without remembering it (since Dabney is not cited), to think along these lines.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The conclusion (ch. 7) is mostly a succinct summary, with the addition of a parting shot: &#8220;It is a regrettable fact that much Reformed preaching operates in a virtual mono-mood&#8212;that of the indicative&#8212; to the virtual exclusion of the imperative&#8221; (151). Whether the charge is fair or a straw man, my limited exposure to contemporary Reformed preaching is not qualified to judge. Surely Carrick is right when he opines that the doctrinal must be balanced by the practical, the historical by the ethical, the historia salutis by the ordo salutis, and the work of Christ by the work of the Spirit (151). His final statement is, &#8220;It is absolutely essential that the great indicatives of Christ&#8217;s accomplishment of redemption be balanced by the great imperatives of the Spirit&#8217;s application of redemption&#8221; (151). May the Lord deliver His church from pulpits devoid of either.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Three appendixes supply further illustrations of the exclamative, the interrogative, and the imperative from Reformed preaching. They may be the most useful to readers who are relatively unfamiliar with the spiritual eloquence of our forefathers, as a provocation to read more of their sermons. I agree with Earl Blackburn&#8217;s two minor criticisms<sup>4</sup>&nbsp;that including illustrative examples from Calvin&#8217;s sermons alongside the five Carrick chose and an appendix dedicated to the indicative mood would have strengthened the book.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Whatever one&#8217;s familiarity with this topic or position taken, this book seems to be an important contribution worthy of consideration by all modern Reformed preachers, and so I recommend it with meek enthusiasm. Its head-on criticisms of some RHP will disturb adherents, but where the tool is sharpened sparks are bound to fly. Let us receive Carrick&#8217;s savory meat and leave any bones on the plate. A well-reasoned and specific response to this book by a worthy champion of RHP would also prove an interesting read and may shed more light upon this homiletical controversy.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>You may find interesting the attached brief report of Carrick debating a RHP proponent named William Dennison (yes, another brother) at the March 2002 theology conference sponsored by Greenville Presbyterian Theological Seminary, where Carrick teaches.<sup>5</sup>&nbsp;It may prove especially useful to us because in it the other side is not mute.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>1. James T. Dennison, Jr. (1943-present), Librarian and Lecturer in Church History at WTS in California from 1980- 2000, currently Professor of Church History and Academic Dean at Northwest Theological Seminary in Lynnwood, Washington; Charles G. Dennison (1945-1999), Pastor of Grace OPC of Sewickley, PA; Lee Irons (see footnote 6).<br>2. www.kerux.com<br>3. Lectures on Sacred Rhetoric, Lecture III, &#8220;Distribution of Subjects,&#8221; pp. 57-58.<br>4. See first review referenced in footnote 1.<br>5. http://www.banneroftruth.org/pages/articles/article_detail.php?119</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/scott-meadows-imp-2/">The Imperative of Preaching Part II</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/scott-meadows-imp-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Book Recommendation &#124; The Imperative of Preaching by John Carrick</title>
		<link>/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/</link>
					<comments>/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 16:20:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15520</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Recently in a discussion about hermeneutics and preaching, the chairman of the Board of CBTS, John Miller, recommended to us John Carrick’s book entitled, The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric. John Carrick is introduced on the Banner of Truth website as follows:&#160; John Carrick is a graduate of Oxford University (BA, 1973; [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/">Book Recommendation | The Imperative of Preaching by John Carrick</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Recently in a discussion about hermeneutics and preaching, the chairman of the Board of CBTS, John Miller, recommended to us John Carrick’s book entitled, <em>The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric.</em></p>



<p>John Carrick is introduced on the Banner of Truth website as follows:&nbsp;</p>



<p>John Carrick is a graduate of Oxford University (BA, 1973; Certificate in Education, 1974; MA, 1978) and studied at London Theological Seminary, 1978-1980. He holds a D.Min. from Westminster Theological Seminary in California (2002). He was formerly Minister of Cheltenham Evangelical Church (1979-1992), briefly Lecturer in the History of Philosophy &amp; Christian Thought at Reformed Theological Seminary, Charlotte, North Carolina (1993), and Minister of Matthews Orthodox Presbyterian Church, Matthews, NC (1992-1994).</p>



<p>He is the author of <em>The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric</em> and <em>The Preaching of Jonathan Edwards</em>, published by the Trust.</p>



<p>I was thinking of writing a review of the book myself, but I found the review of my esteemed friend, D. Scott Meadows online and feel no need to duplicate his fine review.&nbsp; I do want, however, to add my commendation of this book and urge you to read it.</p>



<p>I just finished reading Carrick’s short volume myself.&nbsp; The book is not long and is an easy read. (Even with the appendices, it is less than 200 pages.) It has been helpful to me in several respects. I want you men to be aware of this fine book and also receive help in your preaching from it.</p>



<p>Carrick’s interest is to discuss the biblical balance and relationship between the indicative and the imperative, especially as it affects our preaching.&nbsp; There are five main chapters of the book sandwiched between an introduction and conclusion. He spends the first three of these main chapters discussing the indicative and then two discussing the imperative.</p>



<p>Over the course of the three chapters on the indicative, Carrick discusses the indicative, the exclamative, and the interrogative and gives examples of great preaching from each. He argues in them that the exclamative and the interrogative are forms of the indicative. I found his emphasis on the importance the interrogative in preaching particularly helpful.</p>



<p>Carrick then comes to the beating heart of his book in his two chapters on the imperative. In the first chapter on the imperative, Carrick discusses the imperative generally, its relationship to the indicative, and finally its importance in preaching.&nbsp; In the second chapter, he dives into his critique of the redemptive-historical school of preaching and especially its more extreme forms. I found his historical survey of the controversy surrounding this school of preaching enlightening. I also found his critique of its deficiency with regard to the “imperative preaching” most timely and helpful. I urge you to read the book and give special attention to this chapter.</p>



<p>There it is. My recommended book of the day for you! Shortly, we will post D. Scott Meadows’ review of this fine book.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/">Book Recommendation | The Imperative of Preaching by John Carrick</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-imperative-of-preaching-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</title>
		<link>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/</link>
					<comments>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 20:10:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Church Discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Worship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[church discipline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[practical theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13854</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Bible teaches us that holiness is one of the major marks of a true church. The church&#8217;s holiness is based off the great command found in Leviticus 19:2, &#8220;You shall be holy, for I the LORD your God am holy.&#8221; And the church&#8217;s holiness is the result of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Jesus [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/">Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-drop-cap">The Bible teaches us that holiness is one of the major marks
of a true church. The church&#8217;s holiness is based off the great command found in
Leviticus 19:2, &#8220;You shall be holy, for I the LORD your God am holy.&#8221; And the
church&#8217;s holiness is the result of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Jesus has saved
the church by giving Himself up for her. He saved her by spilling His own
precious blood on the cross. And as a result, the church has become the body
and bride of Jesus Christ. It belongs to Him. He is her Head and her Husband.
And Jesus didn&#8217;t die to purchase a sick body and an ugly bride. He died for the
church to be holy and without blemish. He died so she would reflect His holy
character. He died so that she would be holy as He is holy! Holy in her
profession of the truth and holy in her practice of living out the truth. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But in saying this, a problem should arise in our minds. A
big problem. And it&#8217;s this: the church is not perfect. At least not yet. If you
have but a faint understanding of your own heart, hopefully that&#8217;s not a
surprise. The church is full of saints but saints who are still sinners. Sadly,
saints who still break God&#8217;s commandments. And saints who still hurt one
another with their words and their actions.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Therefore, it must be the priority of every true church to
carry out what is called church discipline. This simply means the church must
have in place a way of dealing with and correcting sin when it rears its ugly
head. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If we are thinking of the church as the body of Christ,
church discipline is like undergoing surgery in order to cut out cancerous
tumors from the body so that the body would be healthy again. Or if we are
thinking of the church as the bride of Christ, church discipline is like
getting a top-of-the-line spa treatment in order for the dirt and filth and
warts and lumps to all be removed so that the bride would be beautiful again.&nbsp;&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Church discipline may not feel good, but it is absolutely
necessary. Church discipline must be enforced if any church wants to remain
pure, and holy, and undefiled before her Lord. If we let the tumors grow and do
nothing about them, the body will eventually die. And if we let the filth build
up without ever cleaning ourselves, the husband may become so disgusted with
his bride that he eventually leaves her! </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The classic passage on church discipline is found in Matthew
18:15-20. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>[15] &#8220;If your brother sins against you, go and tell him his fault, between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained your brother. [16] But if he does not listen, take one or two others along with you, that every charge may be established by the evidence of two or three witnesses. [17] If he refuses to listen to them, tell it to the church. And if he refuses to listen even to the church, let him be to you as a Gentile and a tax collector. [18] Truly, I say to you, whatever you bind on earth shall be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven. [19] Again I say to you, if two of you agree on earth about anything they ask, it will be done for them by my Father in heaven. [20] For where two or three are gathered in my name, there am I among them.&#8221; (ESV)</em></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In future posts, we will consider these verses in greater
detail. But for the present, consider six introductory remarks concerning
Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"large"} -->
<p class="has-large-font-size"><strong>Introductory Remarks</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>1.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline in Matthew 18:15-20 must never be severed from its context. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The context of this passage is very important. Sometimes
Jesus&#8217; overall teaching in this section is not emphasized enough when we think
about and talk about church discipline. This teaching on church discipline
comes in the midst of Jesus&#8217; teaching on how His disciples should love each
other, especially how they should love the least of His disciples. Remember, in
Matthew 18, Jesus teaches His disciples what it means to live as a citizen in
His kingdom. More than that, He teaches them what it means to be great in His
kingdom &#8211; and it has nothing to do with how the world defines greatness.
Greatness for Christ is not about popularity or power or riches or fame or
attractiveness or anything else the world is impressed with. Instead, greatness
in Christ&#8217;s kingdom is shown through humble service &amp; brotherly love. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus teaches this in Matthew 18 in four different ways: First,
His disciples are to show humility to one another (vv. 1-4). Second, His
disciples are to protect each other specifically from sin (vv. 5-9). Third, His
disciples are to highly esteem each other (vv. 10-14). And finally, His
disciples are to continually forgive each other (vv. 15-35). This teaching on
church discipline, then, makes up the first part in the fourth and final
section in this chapter, which deals with forgiveness.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>What does this mean then? It means that church discipline
and forgiveness and true Christian love are all vitally connected. We may be
tempted to think that church discipline and forgiveness have little or nothing
to do with each other. We may be tempted to think that church discipline is all
law while forgiveness is all grace, that church discipline is enslaving while
forgiveness is freeing, that church discipline makes me feel bad while
forgiveness makes me feel good!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Well, this dichotomy, this separation of church discipline
and forgiveness, is nowhere in Jesus&#8217; teaching. In fact, the exact opposite
occurs. Jesus&#8217; teaching on love and forgiveness includes church discipline!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus teaches us here that church discipline is the means of
forgiveness. It is the way of bringing about forgiveness and reconciliation and
restoration! And the goal of church discipline is forgiveness. Why are members
disciplined? So that forgiveness would occur. When forgiveness is not reached
between two people, discipline must be administered so that forgiveness might
become a reality!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Hopefully you see that church discipline and forgiveness
should not be pitted against each other but should work hand-in-hand to glorify
God, to keep the church pure and holy, and to bring about much peace and
happiness in the lives of God&#8217;s people. When we think about church discipline, we
should think about seeking forgiveness. The first is the means of obtaining the
second.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>2.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline concerns professing Christians. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>What Jesus says here concerns those who are brothers and
sisters in Christ. They are those who have made credible professions of faith,
have been baptized, and are members of a local church of Jesus Christ. In other
words, this teaching is for church members, for those who have been publicly
recognized as brothers and sisters in Christ. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>It is not, however, for unbelievers. How would it make any
sense to take your grievances to the church if the person who has sinned
against you is not even in the church to begin with? What can the church do
about it? If your unbelieving coworker sins against you, the only things we can
do is preach the gospel to him and pray for his salvation, but we can&#8217;t
discipline him. He has never been a part of this holy society we call the
church. He is an unbeliever outside of the kingdom of God. So we can&#8217;t put him
out of an organization he has never joined in the first place!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This doesn&#8217;t mean you shouldn&#8217;t seek forgiveness with people
in other areas of life; it simply means this step-by-step process that Jesus
teaches us is given specifically to the church and for the church to use with
its own members. It was not given to families or to schools or to society as a
whole.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are good principles there for anyone to follow, but it
is given specifically for the body and bride of Christ.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>3.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline deals with private sins committed against another brother or sister in Christ.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is important to note. The character of the kind of sin
Jesus is describing is private, not public. And it is against an individual,
not a group. Since it is private, certain measures are put in place by our Lord
to try to keep things as private as possible.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>John Calvin spends much time distinguishing between private
sins and public sins in his section on church discipline in the <em>Institutes</em>.
For sins that have been committed more openly, sins that affect more than just
one or two people but sins done in public where everyone knows about them and
where the whole church is immediately scandalized by them, Calvin argues that
these types of sin don&#8217;t fall within the instructions of Christ here in Matthew
18. People who sin in a public, grievous way are to be swiftly, solemnly, and
immediately rebuked in public, meaning something needs to be said to the church
when they gather together to worship God. We have examples of this happening in
the New Testament. Just think about Peter&#8217;s scandalous sin of distorting the
gospel of grace when he refused to eat with Gentile believers and how Paul
openly rebuked him to his face before the believers in Antioch (Galatians
2:11-14). This was no private meeting between the two apostles. The sin was so
grievous and so public that Paul was forced to rebuke Peter before the church.
And then he writes about it for all to read!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But for sins that have been committed more privately where
very few people know about it and very few people have been offended by it, the
steps laid down by Christ here in Matthew 18 must be followed. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are always exceptions to the rule. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are certain private sins that are so grievous that
immediate public church discipline must be enforced. Some of these sins might
include things that would put a person behind bars for a long time. Even if the
crime was committed in private, sometimes it must be exposed by the light for
all to see and abhor, including the civil authorities. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are also certain people who commit private sins that
must be made public. Here I am thinking about church officers. If a church
officer commits a particular sin that disqualifies him from the office of
either elder or deacon, something needs to be said to the church to give them
the reason why he has stepped down.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But the private sins I am talking about might include the
following: theft of some small amount, deliberately lying to another brother&#8217;s
face for your own personal advantage, unrighteous anger directed at another
believer, a complete lack of respect and honor for an older member of the
church, gossiping and slandering the good name of a Christian, a divisive
spirit that tries to stir up trouble in the church, and being a stumbling block
to one of Christ&#8217;s little ones. These may be small offenses in the eyes of our
society but let me tell you this: they are grave offenses in the sight of our
holy God who commands us to love one another as Christ loves us.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, all public sin should at all times be publicly rebuked;
some private sins should also at all times be publicly rebuked; but most
private sins should at first be privately rebuked. (but of course, it should
lead to a public rebuke in the presence of all if the person persists in sin).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>4.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline gives us a methodical, step-by-step process to deal with unrepentant sin. </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Seeking forgiveness and reconciliation may be a process. I
wish it wasn&#8217;t the case. I wish that when someone sinned against another he or
she would immediately seek forgiveness. But sadly, while we live in this fallen
world, that is not always the case. And if forgiveness does not immediately
occur, there are distinct steps that must be taken in order to secure it. In
fact, there are four steps listed here in Matthew 18 that must be taken in
order to bring about forgiveness from an unrepentant Christian.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, we should not be trigger happy to discipline, and even
more than that, to excommunicate unrepentant members who have sinned in a
private way. As William Hendriksen says, &#8220;Church discipline, when viewed
negatively, is a matter of last resort&#8221; (699, Gospel of Matthew). None of this
should be rushed. Each step takes time to complete. Careful attention must be
taken and certain measures must be exhausted before moving on to the next step.
</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Maybe an illustration might be helpful. Instead of thinking
of these steps as little stair steps like the ones before me which only take a
second to climb (and easy to skip if you have some jumping abilities), think of
these steps to secure forgiveness like riding escalators from floor to floor at
the Mall of America. The Mall of America has four floors. And it has escalators
that will take you up to each floor. But it takes some time to go from one
floor to the next. And it takes a lot of time to go from the bottom floor to
the very top. You have to slowly but surely move from one to the next. Well, in
a similar way, each escalator of church discipline must be ascended before one
moves on to the next. Getting from step one to step four should not be
instantaneous.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>5.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline has, as its goal, the gaining or winning back of a professing Christian who has gone astray.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This step-by-step process of church discipline is
redemptive. The unrepentant professing Christian is like a sheep that has gone
astray. He or she has left the fold of Christ. He or she has sinned and turned
from the Highway of Holiness. And if that person keeps living in unrepentant
sin, if that person keeps walking down crooked, dark paths, he or she will not
reach the Celestial City. He or she will be attacked by deadly predators and will
be completely destroyed.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So seeking forgiveness in the way prescribed by Christ gets them back on the right track. It brings them back to the fold of God. It displays the very heart of Jesus Christ, the Good Shepherd, who leaves the 99 sheep on the mountains in order to search and find the one that went astray. As James says in James 5:19-20:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>&#8220;[19] My brothers, if anyone among you wanders from the truth and someone brings him back, [20] let him know that whoever brings back a sinner from his wandering will save his soul from death and will cover a multitude of sins.&#8221; (ESV)</em></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, in this area of church discipline, we need to check our
hearts. We need to make sure that if we want to walk up these steps, we are
doing so for the glory of God and for the ultimate good of the straying
Christian. It must not be our desire to seek vengeance or to get even with
someone who has wronged us. We also must not revel in another person&#8217;s
downfall. Instead, we must show brotherly love and tender affection to those
who have wronged us. We must remember how wicked our own hearts are, how much
we daily offend our Lord, and how much He has mercy on us. We have to keep ever
before us the goal of church discipline, which is repentance and forgiveness
and restoration, not condemnation and damnation. We want to win our brother and
sister back; not destroy them.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>6.) Jesus&#8217; teaching on church discipline is steeped in OT laws and principles.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Jesus was not one who wanted to unhitch the Old Testament
from the New Testament. There have been teachers throughout church history who
have taught that New Testament believers should move on from the Old Testament
and leave that baggage behind as they follow Christ.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Well, certainly there are some things in the Old Testament
that shouldn&#8217;t be practiced any more in light of the coming of Christ, animal
sacrifices being one of them, but we should never dishonor or take lightly the
teaching of the Old Testament. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Why? Because Jesus didn&#8217;t. Jesus had a high view of the
Scriptures. And He saw a lot of use for the Old Testament in the New Testament
church. In fact, His step-by-step procedure for dealing with sin is based on
teaching from the Mosaic law! Yes, parts of the OT law were to inform and
structure the way the church of Jesus Christ governs itself and functions in
this world. Every step finds its roots in laws given to the nation of Israel.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This makes us think that Jesus may have considered the
church as the New Israel. And it also makes us think that there were more than
just temporary, ceremonial laws in the OT. Some of the laws in the Old
Testament transcend OT Israel and have direct application to the church of
Jesus Christ today. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So, the Old Testament wasn&#8217;t to be thrown out or seen as
irrelevant for Christians. Instead, it was to be studied and examined and
applied to various situations which crop up in the church today. We will see
this as we go through the steps of church discipline.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is how I believe we should look at these steps: Two of them occur privately, and two of them occur publicly, in that order. So in future posts, we will look at the two private steps of seeking forgiveness, and then we will look at the two public steps of seeking forgiveness. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/">Church Discipline: The Way of Forgiveness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/church-discipline-the-way-of-forgiveness/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Training Future Leaders and Preachers</title>
		<link>/training-future-leaders-and-preachers/</link>
					<comments>/training-future-leaders-and-preachers/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2011 15:00:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1089</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Gospel Coalition continues to come out with helpful videos on identifying and training men for the ministry. Their latest is a discussion between David Helm, Bryan Chapell, and Mike Bullmore on how current church leaders should train men to teach and preach. Training Future Leaders and Preachers from The Gospel Coalition on Vimeo. CBTSeminary [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/training-future-leaders-and-preachers/">Training Future Leaders and Preachers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Gospel Coalition continues to come out with helpful videos on identifying and training men for the ministry. Their latest is a discussion between David Helm, Bryan Chapell, and Mike Bullmore on how current church leaders should train men to teach and preach.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/24052087?color=ffffff" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0"></iframe></p>
<p><a href="http://vimeo.com/24052087">Training Future Leaders and Preachers</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/gospelcoalition">The Gospel Coalition</a> on <a href="http://vimeo.com/">Vimeo</a>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/training-future-leaders-and-preachers/">Training Future Leaders and Preachers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/training-future-leaders-and-preachers/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Hero Story (The Messiah in the Old Testament), James Hamilton</title>
		<link>/the-hero-story-the-messiah-in-the-old-testament-james-hamilton/</link>
					<comments>/the-hero-story-the-messiah-in-the-old-testament-james-hamilton/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 14:35:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eschatology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Systematic Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[James Hamilton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Messiah in the Old Testament]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=807</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>"Those notes may be nothing in isolation, but in aggregate they form a song more lovely than the lectures of learned scoffers." James M. Hamilton</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-hero-story-the-messiah-in-the-old-testament-james-hamilton/">The Hero Story (The Messiah in the Old Testament), James Hamilton</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>&#8220;Then come the “experts.” They huff and snort that there is no theme that has been resumed. They deny that this rhythm sounds like that one. They insist that when these notes in this melody are taken apart, they bear no relation to one another. They explain that this beat cannot possibly be related to that one, and that the meaning some heard in that first syncopation was never there in the first place.</p>
<p>But we’ve heard the music, and for all the seeming intelligence of their explanations, we know what the music does to us. Those notes may be nothing in isolation, but in aggregate they form a song more lovely than the lectures of learned scoffers. We know this melody is meant to evoke earlier ones, and as soon as we hear the music again, the denials of the little men behind the microphones lose all power to compel. The strains of hope and longing that we have heard awaken faith and conviction and boldness, even as the academics drone on in their boring refusal to enjoy the music.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="http://jimhamilton.info/2011/04/15/the-hero-story-the-messiah-in-the-old-testament/">You can read the brief article here.</a> I highly recommend it!</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-hero-story-the-messiah-in-the-old-testament-james-hamilton/">The Hero Story (The Messiah in the Old Testament), James Hamilton</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-hero-story-the-messiah-in-the-old-testament-james-hamilton/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Lord&#8217;s Supper as a Means of Grace audio is up</title>
		<link>/the-lords-supper-as-a-means-of-grace-audio-is-up/</link>
					<comments>/the-lords-supper-as-a-means-of-grace-audio-is-up/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2011 22:07:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sacraments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lord's Supper as means of grace]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Means of Grace]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=798</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>How is the Lord's Supper a means of grace?</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-lords-supper-as-a-means-of-grace-audio-is-up/">The Lord&#8217;s Supper as a Means of Grace audio is up</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The audio for the sermon I preached on <a href="http://www.arbca.com/GA2011/thelordssupperasameansofgrace.mp3">The Lord&#8217;s Supper as a Means of Grace</a> is available via audio at the <a href="http://www.arbca.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=80&amp;Itemid=58">ARBCA site</a>. You can download it <a href="http://www.arbca.com/GA2011/thelordssupperasameansofgrace.mp3">here</a>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-lords-supper-as-a-means-of-grace-audio-is-up/">The Lord&#8217;s Supper as a Means of Grace audio is up</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-lords-supper-as-a-means-of-grace-audio-is-up/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		<enclosure url="http://www.arbca.com/GA2011/thelordssupperasameansofgrace.mp3" length="57139961" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="http://www.arbca.com/GA2011/thelordssupperasameansofgrace.mp3" length="57139961" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lawson&#8217;s rebuke of Osteen</title>
		<link>/lawson/</link>
					<comments>/lawson/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2011 02:08:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joel Osteen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Larry King]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[steve lawson]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=754</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Steve Lawson, Joel Osteen, Larry King</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/lawson/">Lawson&#8217;s rebuke of Osteen</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Steve Lawson interacts with some comments made by Joel Osteen on Larry King Live. I don&#8217;t think Lawson will be on Larry King Live anytime soon, but then again&#8230;</p>
<p><object classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" width="480" height="390" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"><param name="src" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/D7n2BObju9M?fs=1&amp;hl=en_US"><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true"></object></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/lawson/">Lawson&#8217;s rebuke of Osteen</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/lawson/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>D. Martyn Lloyd-Jones</title>
		<link>/d-martyn-lloyd-jones/</link>
					<comments>/d-martyn-lloyd-jones/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 13:16:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Martyn Lloyd-Jones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=731</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Rare TV interview of the late great preacher here. Richard Barcellos Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/d-martyn-lloyd-jones/">D. Martyn Lloyd-Jones</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rare TV interview of the late great preacher <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=Z-MBHKREsS8">here</a>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/d-martyn-lloyd-jones/">D. Martyn Lloyd-Jones</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/d-martyn-lloyd-jones/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Him We Proclaim-Preaching Christ From all the Scriptures</title>
		<link>/him-we-proclaim-preaching-christ-from-all-the-scriptures/</link>
					<comments>/him-we-proclaim-preaching-christ-from-all-the-scriptures/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 17:26:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dennis Johnson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[R. Scott Clark]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=721</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>R. Scott Clark interviews Dennis Johnson concerning his book Him We Proclaim. I recommend the book highly, especially chapters 4. The Complication, Chastening, Rejection, and Recovery of Apostolic Preaching in the History of the Church, 5. Challenges to Apostolic Preaching, and 7. Theological Foundations of Apostolic Preaching. The interview can be listened to here. Richard [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/him-we-proclaim-preaching-christ-from-all-the-scriptures/">Him We Proclaim-Preaching Christ From all the Scriptures</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>R. Scott Clark <a href="http://wscal.edu/resource-center/resource/him-we-proclaim">interviews </a>Dennis Johnson concerning his book <a href="http://bookstore.wscal.edu/products/1224">Him We Proclaim</a>. I recommend the book highly, especially chapters 4. The Complication, Chastening, Rejection, and Recovery of Apostolic Preaching in the History of the Church, 5. Challenges to Apostolic Preaching, and 7. Theological Foundations of Apostolic Preaching. The interview can be listened to <a href="http://wscal.edu/resource-center/resource/him-we-proclaim">here</a>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/him-we-proclaim-preaching-christ-from-all-the-scriptures/">Him We Proclaim-Preaching Christ From all the Scriptures</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/him-we-proclaim-preaching-christ-from-all-the-scriptures/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>More thoughts on the gospel</title>
		<link>/more-thoughts-on-the-gospel/</link>
					<comments>/more-thoughts-on-the-gospel/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2011 21:47:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biblical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Preaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[can we live the gospel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=691</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The gospel is not my experience of grace, ...</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/more-thoughts-on-the-gospel/">More thoughts on the gospel</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The gospel is not my experience of grace, not ordo salutis (i.e., the application of salvation to my sin-sick soul), but a message about what God *has done* in Christ for sinners. It is not what God *does* in sinners, what he does for me in my life experience, but what God *has done* for sinners in Christ. We can’t live the gospel, but we sure can believe it, preach it, enjoy the benefits of it and the fruit it produces in and through us. But those things aren’t the gospel. I do not tell people to believe in adoption, or union with Christ, or justification, or sanctification, or glorification (as wonderful as those blessings are!) in order to be saved. I tell them the old, old story &#8211; to believe in Christ because of who He is and what He *did* in history past for sinners.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/richard-barcellos/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2016/10/02211053/richard-barcellos1.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/richard-barcellos/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Richard Barcellos</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos is associate professor of New Testament Studies. He received a B.S. from California State University, Fresno, an M.Div. from The Master’s Seminary, and a Th.M. and Ph.D. from Whitefield Theological Seminary. Dr. Barcellos is pastor of Grace Reformed Baptist Church, Palmdale, CA. He is author of <em>Trinity &amp; Creation</em>, <em>The Covenant of Works</em>, and <em>Getting the Garden Right</em>. He has contributed articles to various journals and is a member of ETS.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/more-thoughts-on-the-gospel/">More thoughts on the gospel</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/more-thoughts-on-the-gospel/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
