<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Apologetics | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/apologetics/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 17:48:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Apologetics | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, Whole Series</title>
		<link>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-whole-series/</link>
					<comments>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-whole-series/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 17:48:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13598</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>After Reading Aquinas! &#8220;Everyone&#8221; knows that recently there has been quite a furor created by the claims of J. V. Fesko (Reforming Apologetics&#8212;Retrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the Faith), Keith Mathison (Christianity and Van Tillianism), Richard Muller (Aquinas Reconsidered), and other critics of Van Til. Their assertion is that Cornelius Van Til substantially [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-whole-series/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, Whole Series</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong><em>After
Reading Aquinas!</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>&#8220;Everyone&#8221;
knows that recently there has been quite a furor created by the claims of J. V.
Fesko (<em>Reforming Apologetics&#8212;Retrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to
Defending the Faith</em>), Keith Mathison (<em>Christianity and Van
Tillianism</em>), Richard Muller (<em>Aquinas Reconsidered</em>), and other critics
of Van Til. Their assertion is that Cornelius Van Til substantially
misunderstood and/or misrepresented Thomas Aquinas in the construction of his
presuppositional apologetics. In turn this exposes to criticism the supposed
&#8220;Copernican&#8221; revolution which presuppositionalism claimed to represent in the
area of Christian Apologetics.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>As
part of my course on Apologetics for CBTS I begin with an historical
introduction to the subject. After that I delve deeply into the significance of
the major, relevant, biblical passages for Christian Apologetics and for the
major issues revealed by this historical introduction.&nbsp; Therefore, after lecturing on the contrast
between Justin Martyr and Tertullian in the Early Church period and before
coming to the contrast between Warfield and Kuyper in the Modern Church, I
lecture on the contrast between Aquinas and Calvin in what I call the period of
the Augustinian Church.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>It
was the lecture on Aquinas that caused me concern.&nbsp; Of course, the contrast for which I argue
between Aquinas and Calvin is called into question by the advocates of Reformed
Scholasticism.&nbsp; But the bigger issue was
the propriety of the way that I (generally following Van Til&#8217;s lead) described
Aquinas&#8217;s views. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>I
was encouraged, however, to see that I rarely quoted Van Til or his assessment
of Aquinas in this lecture.&nbsp; Rather, the
views of Gordon H. Clark, E. J. Carnell, and Kelly James Clark are much more
frequently cited. Substantially, they give the same account of Thomas Aquinas
as Van Til.&nbsp; Still, I felt that I was
myself too reliant on secondary sources for my description of Thomas Aquinas
and not well enough read in Thomas Aquinas to defend my treatment and
description of his &#8220;classical approach&#8221; to Apologetics. I determined to make
sure that I had rectified this before the lecture on Aquinas.&nbsp; Thus, I read the relevant sections of Thomas
Aquinas for myself before giving this lecture. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>I
procured and then scoured the relevant sections of his <em>Summa Contra Gentiles</em>
and<em> Summa Theologica</em>.&nbsp; This
reading caused considerable expansion of that lecture.&nbsp; It actually&#8212;in fact&#8212;expanded it into two
lectures. What it did not do, however, was significantly change my
understanding of Thomas Aquinas &#8220;Classical Apologetics&#8221; at all.&nbsp; I concluded that basically Van Til&#8217;s
presentation of Thomas was right.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This
conclusion should not really surprise anyone. In his recent blog posts on the
subject James Anderson points out that, even <em>if</em> Van Til was not deeply
acquainted with Aquinas&#8217; writings himself, he was at least using the exposition
of Aquinas available from the premier Aquinas scholar of the 20<sup>th</sup>
century.&nbsp; I refer to Etienne Gilson and
his <em>The Christian Philosophy of St. Thomas Aquinas</em>.&nbsp; Here is what Anderson says: &#8220;I think it&#8217;s
also fair to criticize Van Til for relying heavily on secondary sources and not
engaging more directly with Aquinas&#8217;s works. Even so, Van Til engages
frequently with Etienne Gilson, who was one of the leading authorities on
Aquinas during Van Til&#8217;s career, so it&#8217;s not as though his secondary sources
were dubious ones! If Van Til was interacting with Aquinas through the lens of
Gilson and other contemporary scholars, then he was interacting with the
interpretation of Aquinas that was dominant in his day.&#8221;<a href="#_edn1">[1]</a> As I read Gilson, it was
clear to me that his treatment was a closely accurate portrayal of Thomas
Aquinas, his Christian philosophy, and his Apologetics.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In
the posts to follow I want to respond to the criticisms of presuppositionalism based
on the fascination with Aquinas among some contemporary Reformed scholars.&nbsp; I will point out several misguided and unhelpful
directions that are being taken in the current discussion of Aquinas and
Christian Apologetics.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong><em>Why
are we privileging Aquinas over Augustine?</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>One
of the first things that became very clear to me as I read Aquinas was that
with respect to the whole issue of apologetics and the proofs for the existence
of God, he does not agree with Augustine, Anselm, and many other Christian
theologians who preceded him.&nbsp; They
asserted (what Thomas denies) that the existence of God is self-evident or
naturally implanted in man.&nbsp; This is
evident in his whole approach to the subject.&nbsp;
Here is his description of the arguments of those who say that the
existence of God is self-evident in <em>Summa Theologica</em> Question 2, Article
2.&nbsp; (Note that Aquinas is presenting
views <em>he rejects!)</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Objection 2: Further, those things are said to be self-evident which are known as soon as the terms are known, which the Philosopher (1 Poster. iii) says is true of the first principles of demonstration. Thus, when the nature of a whole and of a part is known, it is at once recognized that every whole is greater than its part. But as soon as the signification of the word &#8220;God&#8221; is understood, it is at once seen that God exists. For by this word is signified that thing than which nothing greater can be conceived. But that which exists actually and mentally is greater than that which exists only mentally. Therefore, since as soon as the word &#8220;God&#8221; is understood it exists mentally, it also follows that it exists actually. Therefore the proposition &#8220;God exists&#8221; is self-evident.</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Objection 3: Further, the existence of truth is self-evident. For whoever denies the existence of truth grants that truth does not exist: and, if truth does not exist, then the proposition &#8220;Truth does not exist&#8221; is true: and if there is anything true, there must be truth. But God is truth itself: &#8220;I am the way, the truth, and the life&#8221; (Jn. 14:6) Therefore &#8220;God exists&#8221; is self-evident.&#8221;<a href="#_edn2">[2]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>These
are descriptions of two well-known arguments for the self-evident-ness of the
existence of God.&nbsp; The first is Anselm&#8217;s
ontological argument for the existence of God.&nbsp;
The second is Augustine&#8217;s argument from the existence of truth. He does
not mention here that these arguments were brought forward not only by Anselm,
but by Augustine as well.&nbsp; This, however,
was clear to anyone acquainted with Augustine.&nbsp;
Augustine&#8217;s argument from truth is plain to see in Book 2 of his
treatise on <em>The Free Choice of the Will</em>.&nbsp;
</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Aquinas
denies that the existence of God is self-evident in both his <em>Summa
Theologica </em>and in his <em>Summa Contra Gentiles </em>and rejects the above
arguments. The five proofs are built, then, upon the denial of any innate
knowledge of God.&nbsp; Says Gordon H.
Clark:&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Thomas faced two other contrasting views.&nbsp; One is that the existence of God is self-evident and neither needs nor is susceptible of proof from prior first principles.&nbsp; Those who hold this view argue that God has implanted in all men an elemental knowledge of himself.&nbsp; The idea of God is innate.&nbsp; On this showing any argument or so-called proof could be nothing more than a clarification of already present ideas; and such in effect was the nature of Augustine&#8217;s, Anselm&#8217;s and Bonaventura&#8217;s attempts.&nbsp; Now, in one sense Thomas is willing to admit that God&#8217;s existence is self-evident: it is self-evident in itself, it is self-evident to God; but it is not self-evident to us.&nbsp; God has not implanted ideas in the human mind, and all knowledge must be based on sensory experience.<sup>&#8221;&nbsp;&nbsp; <a href="#_edn3">[3]</a></sup></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>For the substantiation of Clark&#8217;s assertions,
cf. Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologica</em>, Volume 1, Question 2, Article 1; <em>Summa
Contra Gentiles</em>, Book 1, Chapters 10-12.&nbsp;
In these places he mentions other Christian theologians with whom he is
taking issue. Included among them are the ones he calls the Damascene and
Bonaventura.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>All
of this is significant because it means that in favoring the classical
apologetics of Aquinas, contemporary Reformed theologians are selecting one
from among several historically &#8220;scholastic&#8221; positions.&nbsp; They are really crediting Aquinas over
Augustine.&nbsp; They are also privileging
Christian Aristotelianism over Christian Platonism.&nbsp; It is well-known that the idea of the
self-evident-ness of the existence of God appealed to Augustine, Anselm, and
others because of their preference for a form of Christian Platonism which
emphasized the importance of innate ideas over the Christian Aristotelianism of
Aquinas which favored the importance of sensory or empirical evidence.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>My
point is not to argue for Christian Platonism&#8212;any more than I am arguing for
Christian Aristotelianism. It is only to say that in their rush to identify
Reformed Scholasticism with Aquinas, contemporary Reformed theologians may have
forgotten that there was a different and viable option available to our
Reformed fathers that did not involve the adoption of Aquinas&#8217;s view of natural
theology.&nbsp; That alternative was none
other than the view of the one who was recognized by Calvin and others as the
most important predecessor of the Reformation, Augustine himself. Scholastics
such as Anselm and Bonaventura did not reject Augustine&#8217;s views in the way
Aquinas did. They remained more faithful to the Augustinian tradition with
regard to the self-evident nature of the knowledge of God.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There
is certainly clear evidence (from the predominant number of times he quotes him
in the <em>Institutes</em>) that Calvin privileged Augustine.&nbsp; Calvin frequently cites Augustine by name and
generally positively. I think the number is 300 plus times in the <em>Institutes</em>.
Having searched I can find only three places where he cites by name Thomas
Aquinas.&nbsp; The references are not very
positive, but usually rather equivocal.&nbsp;
In spite of this, we are supposed to think that Calvin adopted Aquinas&#8217;s
view of apologetics and the theistic proofs rather than Augustine&#8217;s.&nbsp; This is a really suspect way to reason.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Why
are we privileging Aquinas over Augustine?&nbsp;
Furthermore, why must we privilege either Christian Aristotelianism or
Christian Platonism? Of course, I am not arguing that we return to the
Christian Platonism of Augustine.&nbsp; I am
saying, however, that there were certainly historical-theological alternatives
available to the Reformed Scholastics that did not involve a return to &#8220;the
classical apologetics&#8221; of Thomas Aquinas. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In
further posts I will demonstrate some of the mistakes that are involved in
privileging Aquinas&#8217;s views.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong><em>Aquinas&#8217;
Inadequate Views of Noetic Depravity</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Van
Til and presuppositionalism object to Aquinas&#8217;s approach to natural theology
and apologetics. One major reason given for this is that Thomism exhibits an
over-confidence in fallen human reason. Does Thomas over-rate the ability of
human reason and under-rate the effects of noetic depravity (the depravity of
fallen man&#8217;s mind) in his natural theology?&nbsp;
I think he does, but this requires a little explanation, if we are to be
entirely fair to Thomas.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The
picture that many have of Thomas Aquinas as a typical, semi-Pelagian Roman
Catholic is certainly not correct. At key points on the doctrine of grace he
follows Augustine carefully and deserves in those respects to be regarded as a
strict Augustinian.&nbsp; This is, of course,
a huge problem for modern Roman Catholicism because of its clearly
semi-Pelagian tendencies.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Aquinas, in spite of
modern Thomists&#8217; misconceptions, was thoroughly Augustinian in his view of
predestination.&nbsp; In his treatment of
predestination Aquinas answers a number of questions in the way that only
Augustine and his strict followers would answer. <a href="#_edn4">[4]</a>
Here is a brief summary.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:list -->
<ul><li>&#8220;Whether Men Are Predestined by God?&#8221; <em>Yes!</em></li><li>&#8220;Whether Predestination Places Anything in the
Predestined?&#8221; <em>No! (Men are passive in this matter.)</em></li><li>&#8220;Whether God Reprobates Any Men?&#8221; <em>Yes!</em></li><li>&#8220;Whether the Predestined Are Chosen by God?&#8221; <em>Yes!</em></li><li>&#8220;Whether the Foreknowledge of Merits Is the
Cause of Predestination?&#8221; <em>No!</em></li><li>&#8220;Whether Predestination Is Certain?&#8221; <em>Yes!</em></li><li>&#8220;Whether the Number of the Predestined Is
Certain?&#8221; <em>Yes!</em></li><li>&#8220;Whether Predestination Can Be Furthered by the
Prayers of the Saints?&#8221; <em>No, in that predestination is first determined
regardless of the prayers of the saints. Yes, in that the effect of
predestination&#8212;salvation&#8212;can be furthered by the prayers of the saints as a
means of grace.</em></li></ul>
<!-- /wp:list -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This last question and answer exactly parallels
Augustine&#8217;s argument in his book entitled, <em>Of Rebuke and Grace</em> (as do
all the others). Thomas echoes the anti-Pelagian teaching of Augustine.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Similarly, and not surprisingly, Thomas also
agrees with Augustine about what is now known as &#8220;irresistible grace.&#8221;&nbsp; Once again through his typical and very analytical
treatment Aquinas follows the course laid out by Augustine. <a href="#_edn5">[5]</a> But
the pinnacle is reached when Aquinas teaches what amounts to effectual calling
or irresistible grace: &#8220;&#8230; since God&#8217;s intention cannot fail, according to the
saying of Augustine in his book on the Predestination of the Saints &#8230; that <em>by
God&#8217;s good gifts whoever is liberated is most certainly liberated.</em>&nbsp; Hence if God intends, while moving, that the
one whose heart He moves should attain to grace, he will infallibly attain to
it &#8230;&#8221;<a href="#_edn6">[6]</a> </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>With such evidence in front of us, we may
rather expect that Aquinas will follow out what we know as the Calvinistic
scheme by teaching the perseverance and preservation of the saints and the
other doctrines of grace.&nbsp; Sadly, this
assumption is not the case.&nbsp; Neither
Augustine, his strict follower, Gottschalk, nor Thomas Aquinas affirm the
preservation of the saints.&nbsp; Grace may be
lost unless one is also predestined to persevere.&nbsp; Once more Thomas Aquinas is a good
Augustinian when he says: &#8220;Many have meritorious works who do not obtain
perseverance &#8230;&#8221; <a href="#_edn7">[7]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Similarly, Aquinas also seems to have held
confused and imperfect views of total depravity.&nbsp; Sin, in fact, does not seem to occupy an
important place in Thomas&#8217;s writings.&nbsp; In
Gilson&#8217;s index there is no entry for sin, depravity, the fall, or folly.&nbsp; For a discussion of Thomas&#8217;s view of sin, one
must consult his doctrine of free will and grace. It is not surprising, then,
Thomas argues that natural light is sufficient for natural knowledge.
Consequently, human nature is not altogether corrupted by sin. <a href="#_edn8">[8]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The effects of this view of human nature become
evident in Thomas&#8217;s approach to the existence of God. In several places Thomas
argues that the existence of God is not self-evident because sinful men can
conceive that God does not exist, and if something is self-evident it cannot be
conceived by anyone as not existing.&nbsp; He
proves this by citing &#8220;the ancients,&#8221; that is, the ancient Greek philosophers.
He also cites the fact that the fool denies the existence of God. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Surprisingly, instead of attributing such
denials to the noetic depravity of men and the fact that they suppress the
truth in unrighteousness (Rom. 1:18), Thomas takes these statements of the fool
and the ancients at face value. He then uses them as an argument against the
self-evident character of the existence of God. Nothing could more pointedly
inform us of Thomas&#8217;s inflated view of the powers of fallen human reason.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Here are the quotes from Aquinas: &#8220;And,
contrary to the Point made by the first argument, it does not follow
immediately that, as soon as we know the meaning of the name God, the existence
of God is known. It does not follow first because it is not known to all, even
including those who admit that God exists, that God is that than which a
greater cannot be thought. After all, many ancients said that this world itself
was God.&#8221; <a href="#_edn9">[9]</a>
Cf. also: &#8220;On the contrary, no one can mentally admit the opposite of what is
self-evident; as the Philosopher &#8230; states concerning the first principles of
demonstration. But the opposite of the proposition &#8220;God is&#8221; can be mentally
admitted: The fool hath said in his heart, There is no God (Ps. Lii. 1).
Therefore that God exists is not self-evident.&#8221; <a href="#_edn10">[10]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Thus, despite the promising character of
Thomas&#8217;s views of predestination and grace, he falls short of truly
appreciating the total depravity of man including his reason.&nbsp; This in turn profoundly controls his approach
to apologetics and the theistic proofs. This is why Aquinas can say that the fool
and the ancients disprove the self-evident-ness of the existence of God. This
is clear evidence that Thomas indulged deficient views of human depravity.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong><em>They
Just Keep Missing the Point</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In
my view those currently attacking Van Til and presuppositionalism are engaged
in a gigantic enterprise of missing the point.&nbsp;
They keep interpreting Romans 1:18-23 over and over and again and again <em>wrongly!</em>
To put it differently, they keep making the same exegetical mistake over and
over again.&nbsp; They keep affirming that Romans
1 teaches that we can demonstrate the existence of God to men.&nbsp; They keep saying that men <em>can</em> know
that God exists. But that is emphatically not what the passage says.&nbsp; It does not say that men <em>can</em> know
God.&nbsp; It does not say that <em>we can
demonstrate</em> to men who do not know God that God exists. <em>It says that men
do know God and that they do not need this demonstrated to them.</em>&nbsp; It will probably do no good to quote the
passage&#8212;since this false understanding is so deeply embedded in the thinking of
Classical Apologists&#8212;, but let me do so one more time.&nbsp; Here is what Paul actually says: &#8220;For the
wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and
unrighteousness of men who suppress the truth in unrighteousness, <sup>19</sup>
because that which is known about God is evident within them; for God made it
evident to them. <sup>20</sup> For since the creation of the world His
invisible attributes, His eternal power and divine nature, have been clearly
seen, being understood through what has been made, so that they are without
excuse. <sup>21</sup> For even though they knew God, they did not honor Him as
God or give thanks, but they became futile in their speculations, and their
foolish heart was darkened.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Men
according to Paul not only may know God, they do know God. They know God
because they suppress the truth in unrighteousness.&nbsp; They know God because that which <em>is </em>known
about God <em>is evident</em> <em>within</em> them.&nbsp;
They know God because since the creation of the world His eternal power
and divine nature are clearly seen and understood.&nbsp; They know God because they are without
excuse.&nbsp; (Paul grounds their
accountability on the fact that they know God.&nbsp;
They are not simply potentially without excuse because they may come to
know God.&nbsp; They are without excuse
because they do know God.) Finally, they know God, because they sinfully
refused to honor Him or give thanks.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The
passage is clear. Men do not merely have the capability of knowing God after a
theistic proof is presented.&nbsp; They know
God before such a proof is presented.&nbsp;
Yes, this knowledge is through the things that are made, but this does
not mean that their knowledge of God is the result of a properly constructed
theistic proof.&nbsp; Their knowledge of God
is both mediated to them through creation and implanted in them by creation.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>It
should not be surprising that his modern followers misinterpret Romans 1.&nbsp; They are simply following in the footsteps of
the identical mistake made by Thomas Aquinas.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Listen
to his argument in <em>Summa Theologica </em>Question 2, Article 2: &#8220;The Apostle
says: &#8220;The invisible things of Him are clearly seen, being understood by
the things that are made&#8221; (Rm. 1:20). But this would not be unless the
existence of God could be demonstrated through the things that are made; for
the first thing we must know of anything is whether it exists.&#8221; Thomas takes
(and the surrounding context of his assertion simply emphasizes this) Romans
1:20 to mean that the existence of God is not self-evident or implanted in man,
but can be demonstrated.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Listen
to Thomas in <em>Summa Contra Gentiles</em>, Chapter 12, which is entitled: &#8220;THE
OPINION OF THOSE WHO SAY THAT THE EXISTENCE OF GOD CANNOT BE DEMONSTRATED BUT
IS HELD BY FAITH ALONE.&#8221;&nbsp; Once more in
proving that the existence of God can be demonstrated, he brings up Romans
1:20. He says: &#8220;The falsity of this opinion is shown to us, first, from the art
of demonstration which teaches us to arrive at causes from their effects. Then,
it is shown to us from the order of the sciences. For, as it is said in the
Metaphysics [IV, 3], if there is no knowable substance higher than sensible
substance, there will be no science higher than physics. It is shown, thirdly,
from the pursuit of the philosophers, who have striven to demonstrate that God
exists. Finally, it is shown to us by the truth in the words of the Apostle
Paul: &#8220;For the invisible things of God&#8230; are clearly seen, being understood by
the things that are made&#8221; (Rom. 1:20).&#8221;&nbsp;
Once more, it is clear that Thomas has misunderstood Romans 1.&nbsp; He thinks it means that one can &#8220;arrive at&#8221;
and &#8220;demonstrate&#8221; that God exists.&nbsp; I
have to say it again.&nbsp; This is not what
Romans 1:20 teaches.&nbsp; It teaches men do
know God. It is not something that they &#8220;arrive at&#8221; after it has been
demonstrated to them.&nbsp; To echo Paul&#8217;s
argument in Romans 1:18-21, if the knowledge of God is something to be arrived
at, then their being without excuse is something to be arrived at.&nbsp; According to Paul, all men are without excuse
precisely because they do know God without the necessity of demonstration.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong><em>Calvin
and Aquinas Contrasted</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Richard
Muller is well-known for books like <em>Unaccommodated Calvin</em>.&nbsp; I had to read that book back in the days when
I was studying for my PhD.&nbsp; Muller&#8217;s
point (or at least one of his main points) was that the contrast between Calvin
and the Reformed Scholastics who followed him in the next century had been
overdrawn by many scholars in the 20<sup>th</sup> Century who had bought in to
the Calvin versus the Calvinists movement. Muller showed (I think
successfully.) that there were clear indications of a scholastic methodology in
Calvin that showed much more continuity with his Calvinistic successors and his
Medieval predecessors.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But
now we are confronted with a much more specific claim.&nbsp; It is that Calvin was controlled not only by
a methodology common to the Medieval scholastics, but that he adopted the
Thomist views of natural theology and apologetics.&nbsp; Cf. J. V. Fesko&#8217;s <em>Reforming </em>Apologetics.
</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Sorry,
folks, as they say here in the South, <em>That dog won&#8217;t hunt!</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>As I
said previously in this blog series, I recently read up on and then lectured on
Thomas Aquinas for my class in apologetics.&nbsp;
I immediately followed that with a lecture on Calvin&#8217;s masterful
treatment of the knowledge of God in Book 1, Chapters 1-9 of the <em>Institutes</em>.&nbsp; I think even a novice cannot fail to notice a
massive difference in the ethos of Thomas opening chapters in <em>Summa
Theologica </em>and <em>Summa Contra Gentiles</em>.&nbsp; But this is not a superficial impression
without a substantial basis.&nbsp; In this
case the accessibility and biblicity of Calvin manifests a much different
approach to the subject of the knowledge of God than that of Thomas
Aquinas.&nbsp; Let me lay out the theological
contrasts between Thomas and Calvin.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>First,
Calvin identifies himself with a theological tradition in regard to the
knowledge of God which Thomas rejects.&nbsp;
Thomas rejects the notion that the knowledge of the existence of God is
naturally implanted. He argues, as we have seen, that strictly speaking the
knowledge of God is not self-evident. He admits: &#8220;To know God exists in a
general and confused way is implanted in us &#8230;&#8221; Yet he says that this is &#8220;not to
know absolutely that God exists, just as to know that someone is approaching is
not to know that Peter is approaching, even though it is Peter that is
approaching.&#8221;<a href="#_edn11">[11]</a>
He goes on in the next article to assert: &#8220;Hence, the existence of God, in so
far as it is not self-evident to us, can be demonstrated from those of His
effects which are known to us.&#8221;<a href="#_edn12">[12]</a>&nbsp; &nbsp;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Calvin,
on the other hand, declares explicitly and repeatedly that men have a natural
knowledge of God which they cannot evade or erase. He has much more in common
with the Christian Platonist tradition embodied in Augustine, Anselm, the
Damascene, and Bonaventura which affirmed that the knowledge of the existence
of God was innate or at least naturally implanted in men.&nbsp; Listen to Calvin&#8217;s statements on this
subject. Calvin&#8217;s language here is absolutely incapable of misunderstanding.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>We lay it down as a position not to be controverted that the human mind, even by natural instinct, possesses some sense of a Deity.&nbsp; For that no man might shelter himself under the pretext of ignorance, God hath given to all some apprehension of his existence, the memory of which he frequently and insensibly renews; so that, as men universally know that there is a God, and that he is their Maker, they must be condemned by their own testimony, for not having worshipped him and consecrated their lives to his service.&nbsp; If we seek for ignorance of a Deity, it is nowhere more likely to be found, than among the tribes the most stupid and furthest from civilization.&nbsp; But, as the celebrated Cicero observes, there is no nation so barbarous, no race so savage; as not to be firmly persuaded of the being of a God. <a href="#_edn13">[13]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>We read of none guilty of more audacious or unbridled contempt of the Deity than Caligula; yet no man ever trembled with greater distress at any instance of Divine wrath, so that he was constrained to dread the Divinity whom he professed to despise.&nbsp; This you may always see exemplified in persons of a similar character &#8230;. The impious themselves, therefore, exemplify the observation, that the idea of a God is never lost in the human mind. <a href="#_edn14">[14]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>It will always be evident to persons of correct judgment, that the idea of a Deity impressed on the mind of man is indelible. That all have by nature an innate persuasion of the Divine existence, a persuasion inseparable from their very constitution, we have abundant evidence in the contumacy of the wicked, whose furious struggles to extricate themselves from the fear of God are unavailing. <a href="#_edn15">[15]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The
contrast between Thomas and Calvin on this matter is clear.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong><em>More
Contrasts between Calvin and Aquinas!</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Second,
Calvin emphasizes explicitly and repeatedly the effect of the fall on man&#8217;s
knowledge of God.&nbsp; Though men have a
naturally implanted knowledge of God given to them by and in creation, this
knowledge never develops into a &#8220;true&#8221; knowledge in the sense of a practical
and religious principle which leads them to worship God aright.&nbsp; Let me put that in my own words, but they are
words which, I think, rightly embody Calvin&#8217;s view.&nbsp; He believes that men have a natural
revelation of God, but that this natural revelation never results in a natural
theology which can guide them appropriately in worship or in life in general.
This emphasis is practically absent in Thomas.&nbsp;
Listen to Calvin:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>It must also be remarked, that, though they strive against their own natural understanding, and desire not only to banish him thence, but even to annihilate him in heaven, their insensibility can never prevail so as to prevent God from sometimes recalling them to his tribunal.&nbsp; But as no dread restrains them from violent opposition to the divine will, it is evident, as long as they are carried away with such a blind impetuosity, that they are governed by a brutish forgetfulness of God. <a href="#_edn16">[16]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>At length they involve themselves in such a vast accumulation of errors, that those sparks which enable them to discover the glory of God are smothered, and at last extinguished by the criminal darkness of iniquity.&nbsp; That seed, which it is impossible to eradicate, a sense of the existence of a Deity, yet remains; but so corrupted as to produce only the worst of fruits.&nbsp; Yet this is a further proof of what I now contend for, that the idea of God is naturally engraved on the hearts of men, since necessity extorts a confession of it, even from reprobates themselves.&nbsp; In a moment of tranquility they facetiously mock the Divine Being, and with loquacious impertinence in many derogate from his power.&nbsp; But if any despair oppress them, it stimulates them to seek him, and dictates concise prayers, which prove that they are not altogether ignorant of God, but that what ought to have appeared before had been suppressed by obstinacy. <a href="#_edn17">[17]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Third,
this very different assessment of the effect of the fall on man&#8217;s knowledge of
God comes to concrete expression in the very different use which Thomas and
Calvin make of a classic passage on the subject. I have in mind, of course, Psalm
53:1 which reads in part: &#8220;The fool has said in his heart, &#8220;There is no
God,&#8221; They are corrupt, and have committed abominable injustice; There is
no one who does good.&#8221;&nbsp; Both Thomas and
Calvin cite this text, but how different is the use they make of it!&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Thomas
sees it as proof that the existence of God is not self-evident. He takes at
face value the fool&#8217;s assertion that there is no God. Aquinas says: &#8220;On the
contrary, no one can mentally admit the opposite of what is self-evident; as
the Philosopher &#8230; states concerning the first principles of demonstration. But
the opposite of the proposition &#8220;God is&#8221; can be mentally admitted: The fool
hath said in his heart, There is no God (Ps. Lii. 1). Therefore that God exists
is not self-evident.&#8221; <a href="#_edn18">[18]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Calvin,
on the other hand, takes it as evidence of the deep depravity of the fool.&nbsp; The fool denies a knowledge of God that is
ineradicably implanted in him. Here is Calvin&#8217;s comment in the <em>Institutes </em>on
Psalm 53:1 with some context:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>While experience testifies that the seeds of religion are sown by God in every heart, we scarcely find one man in a hundred who cherishes what he has received, and not one in whom they grow to maturity, much less bear fruit in due season.&nbsp; Some perhaps grow vain in their own superstitions, while others revolt from God with intentional wickedness; but all degenerate from the true knowledge of him.&nbsp; The fact is, that no genuine piety remains in the world.&nbsp; But, in saying that some fall into superstition through error, I would not insinuate that their ignorance excuses them from guilt; because their blindness is always connected with pride, vanity, and contumacy. <a href="#_edn19">[19]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>David&#8217;s assertion, that &#8220;the fool hath said in his heart, There is no God,&#8221; is primarily, as we shall soon see in another place, to be restricted to those who extinguish the light of nature and willfully stupefy themselves. <a href="#_edn20">[20]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong><em>Calvin
and Aquinas Contrasted Yet More!</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Fourth,
there is a very different view of the usefulness of philosophy espoused by
Thomas in contrast to Calvin.&nbsp; Thomas
cites with admiration &#8220;the philosopher,&#8221; Aristotle, throughout his works and
certainly in his treatment of the knowledge of the existence of God. This
statement in the opening pages of Summa Theologica is typical: &#8220;No one can
mentally admit the opposite of what is self-evident; as the Philosopher
(Metaph. iv. lect. vi.) states concerning the first principles of
demonstration.&#8221; <a href="#_edn21">[21]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Calvin,
in contrast, denounces the value of philosophy and the schools. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Cold and frivolous, then, are the speculations of those who employ themselves in disquisitions on the essence of God, when it would be more interesting to us to become acquainted with his character, and to know what is agreeable to His nature. <a href="#_edn22">[22]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>This disease affects, not only the vulgar and ignorant, but the most eminent, and those who, in other things, discover peculiar sagacity.&nbsp; How abundantly have all the philosophers, in this respect, betrayed their stupidity and folly!&nbsp; For, to spare others, chargeable with greater absurdities, Plato himself, the most religious and judicious of them all, loses himself in his round globe &#8230;. I speak exclusively of the excellent of mankind, not of the vulgar, whose madness in the profanation of divine truth has known no bounds. <a href="#_edn23">[23]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Fifth,
and consequently, Calvin sees little value in the theistic proofs brought
forward by scholastics like Thomas. This is, first of all, the case because men
are intuitively and immediately struck by the glory of God in creation in such
a way as to make the theistic proofs unnecessary.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>As the perfection of a happy life consists in the knowledge of God, that no man might be precluded from attaining felicity, God hath not only sown in the minds of men the seed of religion, already mentioned, but hath manifested himself in the formation of every part of the world, and daily presents himself to public view, in such a manner, that they cannot open their eyes without being constrained to behold him.&nbsp; His essence indeed is incomprehensible so that his Majesty is not to be perceived by the human senses; but on all his works he hath inscribed his glory in characters so clear, unequivocal, and striking, that the most illiterate and stupid cannot exculpate themselves by the plea of ignorance. <a href="#_edn24">[24]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>And, in the first place, whithersoever you turn your eyes, there is not an atom of the world in which you cannot behold some brilliant sparks at least of his glory.&nbsp; But you cannot at one view take a survey of this most ample and beautiful machine in all its vast extent, without being completely overwhelmed with its infinite splendour. <a href="#_edn25">[25]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Thomas
acknowledged that some men are incapable of either following or profiting from
his theistic proofs.&nbsp; Listen to what he
says: </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Reply to Objection 1: The existence of God and other like truths about God, which can be known by natural reason, are not articles of faith, but are preambles to the articles; for faith presupposes natural knowledge, even as grace presupposes in Book 1 nature, and perfection supposes something that can be perfected. Nevertheless, there is nothing to prevent a man, <em>who cannot grasp a proof</em>, accepting, as a matter of faith, something which in itself is capable of being scientifically known and demonstrated. <a href="#_edn26">[26]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Calvin,
on the other hand, thinks this evidence is open even to those who are not
experts.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Of his wonderful wisdom, both heaven and earth contain innumerable proofs; not only those more abstruse things, which are the subjects of astronomy, medicine, and the whole science of physics, but those things which force themselves on the view of the most illiterate of mankind, so that they cannot open their eyes without being constrained to witness them.&nbsp; Adepts indeed, in those liberal arts, or persons just initiated into them, are thereby enabled to proceed much further in investigating the secrets of Divine Wisdom.&nbsp; Yet ignorance of those sciences prevents no man from such a survey of the workmanship of God, as is more than sufficient to excite his admirations of the Divine Architect &#8230; since the meanest and most illiterate of mankind, who are furnished with no other assistance than their own eyes, cannot be ignorant of the excellence of the Divine skill, &#8230; it is evident, that the Lord abundantly manifests his wisdom to every individual on earth.&nbsp; (1:5:2)</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This
same emphasis is sounded a few paragraphs later.&nbsp; Here, however, Calvin explicitly decries the
need for long and laborious argumentations to prove the existence of God.&nbsp; If anything ever qualified as long and
laborious argumentation, it was surely Thomas&#8217;s &#8220;Five Ways.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>We see that there is no need of any long or laborious argumentation to obtain and produce testimonies for illustrating and asserting the Divine Majesty; since, from the few which we have selected and cursorily mentioned, it appears that they are every where so evident and obvious, as easily to be distinguished by the eyes, and pointed out with the fingers.&nbsp; (1:5:9)</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Thomas,
of course, elaborates at some length his careful and technical demonstrations
of the existence of God as the foundation for his argument both in <em>Summa
Theologica</em> and in <em>Summa Contra Gentiles</em>. He says:&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>&nbsp;[5] Now, among the inquiries that we must undertake concerning God in Himself, we must set down in the beginning that whereby His Existence is demonstrated, as the necessary foundation of the whole work. For, if we do not demonstrate that God exists, all consideration of divine things is necessarily suppressed. <a href="#_edn27">[27]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Sixth,
not surprisingly as a result of all this, Thomas and Calvin interpret the
apologetic significance of Romans 1:19-20 very differently.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Thomas
sees this classic text as proof that the existence of God may be demonstrated to
men by philosophical arguments.&nbsp; In <a>chapter 12 Aquinas is refuting the &#8220;opinion
of those who say that the existence of God cannot be demonstrated but is held
by faith alone.&#8221;&nbsp; In response he says</a>: &#8220;Finally, it is shown to us by the truth in the words of
the apostle Paul: &#8220;for the invisible things of God&#8230; are clearly seen, being
understood by the things that are made&#8221; (Rom. 1:20).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Calvin,
on the other hand, sees Romans 1:19-20 as proof that all men (&#8220;even the most
stupid tribe&#8221;) know God intuitively or immediately in creation.&nbsp; He says:&nbsp;
</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>The reason why the prophet attributes to the heavenly creatures a language known to every nation [Ps. 19:2 ff.] is that therein lies an attestation of divinity so apparent that it ought not to escape the gaze of even the most stupid tribe.&nbsp; The apostle declares this more clearly: &#8220;What men need to know concerning God has been disclosed to them, . . . for one an all gaze upon his invisible nature, known from the creation of the world, even unto his eternal power and divinity. [Rom. 1:19-20 p.] <a href="#_edn28">[28]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In
the foregoing I have compiled six, plain differences in the apologetic approach
of Thomas and Calvin to the existence of God.&nbsp;
Whatever we may think of finding a <em>scholastic methodology</em> in
Calvin, we do not find a <em>Thomistic natural theology</em>.<br></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref1">[1]</a>
https://www.proginosko.com/2019/08/reforming-apologetics-thomas-aquinas/</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref2">[2]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologica</em>&nbsp;Question 2, Article 2</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref3">[3]</a> Gordon H. Clark, <em>Thales to Dewey</em>, 272-273.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref4">[4]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa
Theologica</em>, Volume 1, Question 23, Articles 1-8.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref5">[5]</a> <em>Summa Theologica</em>, Volume 2,
Question 112, Articles 1-3.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref6">[6]</a> <em>Summa Theologica</em>, Volume 2,
Question 112, Articles 3.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref7">[7]</a> <em>Summa Theologica</em>, Volume 2,
Question 114, Article 9.&nbsp; Since the true
grace of regeneration was given through the sacrament of baptism, and it was
plain that not all the baptized persevered, no one committed to the notion of
baptismal regeneration in any sense could hold the Calvinistic view of the
perseverance of the saints.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref8">[8]</a> <em>Summa Theologica,</em> Volume 2,
Question 109, Article 2.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref9">[9]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Contra
Gentiles</em>, Book 1, Chapter 11, Paragraph 3&nbsp;
</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref10">[10]</a> <em>Summa Theologica</em>, Volume 1,
Question 2, Article 1</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref11">[11]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa
Theologica</em> (Volume 1, Question 2, Article 1) </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref12">[12]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Contra Gentiles</em>
(Book 1, Chapters 10-12).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref13">[13]</a> John Calvin, <em>Institutes of the
Christian Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 3, Section 1)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref14">[14]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 3, Section 2)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref15">[15]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 3, Section 3)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref16">[16]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 4, Section 2)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref17">[17]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 4, Section 4)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref18">[18]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa
Theologica</em> (Volume 1, Question 2, Article 1)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref19">[19]</a> John Calvin, <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 4, Section 1)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref20">[20]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 4, Section 2)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref21">[21]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa
Theologica</em> (Volume 1, Question 2, Article 1)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref22">[22]</a> John Calvin, <em>Institutes of the
Christian Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 2, Section 2)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref23">[23]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 5, Section 11)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref24">[24]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 5, Section 1)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref25">[25]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 5, Section 1)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref26">[26]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa
Theologica</em> (Volume 1, Question 2, Second Article)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref27">[27]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Contra
Gentiles</em> (Book 1, Chapter 9, Paragraph 5)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref28">[28]</a> John Calvin, <em>Institutes of the
Christian Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 5, Section 1)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthurs Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-whole-series/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, Whole Series</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-whole-series/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 7</title>
		<link>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-7/</link>
					<comments>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-7/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 20:05:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Calvin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositional apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositionalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13479</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Calvin and Aquinas Contrasted Yet More! Fourth, there is a very different view of the usefulness of philosophy espoused by Thomas in contrast to Calvin.&#160; Thomas cites with admiration the philosopher, Aristotle, throughout his works and certainly in his treatment of the knowledge of the existence of God. This statement in the opening pages of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-7/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 7</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-large-font-size"><strong><em>Calvin
and Aquinas Contrasted Yet More!</em></strong></p>



<p>Fourth,
there is a very different view of the usefulness of philosophy espoused by
Thomas in contrast to Calvin.&nbsp; Thomas
cites with admiration the philosopher, Aristotle, throughout his works and
certainly in his treatment of the knowledge of the existence of God. This
statement in the opening pages of Summa Theologica is typical: No one can
mentally admit the opposite of what is self-evident; as the Philosopher
(Metaph. iv. lect. vi.) states concerning the first principles of
demonstration. <a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a></p>



<p>Calvin,
in contrast, denounces the value of philosophy and the schools. </p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Cold and frivolous, then, are the speculations of those who employ themselves in disquisitions on the essence of God, when it would be more interesting to us to become acquainted with his character, and to know what is agreeable to His nature. <a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a> </p></blockquote>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>This disease affects, not only the vulgar and ignorant, but the most eminent, and those who, in other things, discover peculiar sagacity. How abundantly have all the philosophers, in this respect, betrayed their stupidity and folly! For, to spare others, chargeable with greater absurdities, Plato himself, the most religious and judicious of them all, loses himself in his round globe &#8230;. I speak exclusively of the excellent of mankind, not of the vulgar, whose madness in the profanation of divine truth has known no bounds. <a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a> </p></blockquote>



<p>Fifth,
and consequently, Calvin sees little value in the theistic proofs brought
forward by scholastics like Thomas. This is, first of all, the case because men
are intuitively and immediately struck by the glory of God in creation in such
a way as to make the theistic proofs unnecessary.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>As the perfection of a happy life consists in the knowledge of God, that no man might be precluded from attaining felicity, God hath not only sown in the minds of men the seed of religion, already mentioned, but hath manifested himself in the formation of every part of the world, and daily presents himself to public view, in such a manner, that they cannot open their eyes without being constrained to behold him. His essence indeed is incomprehensible so that his Majesty is not to be perceived by the human senses; but on all his works he hath inscribed his glory in characters so clear, unequivocal, and striking, that the most illiterate and stupid cannot exculpate themselves by the plea of ignorance. <a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a> </p></blockquote>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>And, in the first place, whithersoever you turn your eyes, there is not an atom of the world in which you cannot behold some brilliant sparks at least of his glory. But you cannot at one view take a survey of this most ample and beautiful machine in all its vast extent, without being completely overwhelmed with its infinite splendour. <a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a> </p></blockquote>



<p>Thomas
acknowledged that some men are incapable of either following or profiting from
his theistic proofs.&nbsp; Listen to what he
says: </p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Reply to Objection 1: The existence of God and other like truths about God, which can be known by natural reason, are not articles of faith, but are preambles to the articles; for faith presupposes natural knowledge, even as grace presupposes in Book 1 nature, and perfection supposes something that can be perfected. Nevertheless, there is nothing to prevent a man, <em>who cannot grasp a proof</em>, accepting, as a matter of faith, something which in itself is capable of being scientifically known and demonstrated. <a href="#_ftn6">[6]</a></p></blockquote>



<p>Calvin,
on the other hand, thinks this evidence is open even to those who are not
experts.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Of his wonderful wisdom, both heaven and earth contain innumerable proofs; not only those more abstruse things, which are the subjects of astronomy, medicine, and the whole science of physics, but those things which force themselves on the view of the most illiterate of mankind, so that they cannot open their eyes without being constrained to witness them. Adepts indeed, in those liberal arts, or persons just initiated into them, are thereby enabled to proceed much further in investigating the secrets of Divine Wisdom. Yet ignorance of those sciences prevents no man from such a survey of the workmanship of God, as is more than sufficient to excite his admirations of the Divine Architect &#8230; since the meanest and most illiterate of mankind, who are furnished with no other assistance than their own eyes, cannot be ignorant of the excellence of the Divine skill, &#8230; it is evident, that the Lord abundantly manifests his wisdom to every individual on earth. (1:5:2)</p></blockquote>



<p>This
same emphasis is sounded a few paragraphs later.&nbsp; Here, however, Calvin explicitly decries the
need for long and laborious argumentations to prove the existence of God.&nbsp; If anything ever qualified as long and
laborious argumentation, it was surely Thomass Five Ways.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>We see that there is no need of any long or laborious argumentation to obtain and produce testimonies for illustrating and asserting the Divine Majesty; since, from the few which we have selected and cursorily mentioned, it appears that they are every where so evident and obvious, as easily to be distinguished by the eyes, and pointed out with the fingers. (1:5:9)</p></blockquote>



<p>Thomas,
of course, elaborates at some length his careful and technical demonstrations
of the existence of God as the foundation for his argument both in <em>Summa
Theologica</em> and in <em>Summa Contra Gentiles</em>. He says:&nbsp; </p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>[5] Now, among the inquiries that we must undertake concerning God in Himself, we must set down in the beginning that whereby His Existence is demonstrated, as the necessary foundation of the whole work. For, if we do not demonstrate that God exists, all consideration of divine things is necessarily suppressed. <a href="#_ftn7">[7]</a> </p></blockquote>



<p>Sixth,
not surprisingly as a result of all this, Thomas and Calvin interpret the
apologetic significance of Romans 1:19-20 very differently.</p>



<p>Thomas
sees this classic text as proof that the existence of God may be demonstrated to
men by philosophical arguments.&nbsp; In <a>chapter 12 Aquinas is refuting the opinion
of those who say that the existence of God cannot be demonstrated but is held
by faith alone.&nbsp; In response he says</a>: Finally, it is shown to us by the truth in the words of
the apostle Paul: for the invisible things of God&#8230; are clearly seen, being
understood by the things that are made (Rom. 1:20).</p>



<p>Calvin,
on the other hand, sees Romans 1:19-20 as proof that all men (even the most
stupid tribe) know God intuitively or immediately in creation.&nbsp; He says:&nbsp;
</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>The reason why the prophet attributes to the heavenly creatures a language known to every nation [Ps. 19:2 ff.] is that therein lies an attestation of divinity so apparent that it ought not to escape the gaze of even the most stupid tribe. The apostle declares this more clearly: What men need to know concerning God has been disclosed to them, . . . for one an all gaze upon his invisible nature, known from the creation of the world, even unto his eternal power and divinity. [Rom. 1:19-20 p.] <a href="#_ftn8">[8]</a></p></blockquote>



<p>In
the foregoing I have compiled six, plain differences in the apologetic approach
of Thomas and Calvin to the existence of God.&nbsp;
Whatever we may think of finding a <em>scholastic methodology</em> in
Calvin, we do not find a <em>Thomistic natural theology</em>.<br></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa
Theologica</em> (Volume 1, Question 2, Article 1) </p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a> John Calvin, <em>Institutes of the
Christian Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 2, Section 2)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 5, Section 11)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref4">[4]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 5, Section 1)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref5">[5]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 5, Section 1)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref6">[6]</a> <em>Summa Theologica</em> (Volume 1, Question 2, Second Article)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref7">[7]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Contra Gentiles</em> (Book 1, Chapter 9, Paragraph 5)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref8">[8]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 5, Section 1)</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthurs Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-7/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 7</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 6</title>
		<link>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-6/</link>
					<comments>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-6/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 16:09:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Calvin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositional apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositionalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13455</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>More Contrasts between Calvin and Aquinas! Second, Calvin emphasizes explicitly and repeatedly the effect of the fall on mans knowledge of God.&#160; Though men have a naturally implanted knowledge of God given to them by and in creation, this knowledge never develops into a true knowledge in the sense of a practical and religious principle [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-6/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 6</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong><em>More
Contrasts between Calvin and Aquinas!</em></strong></p>



<p>Second,
Calvin emphasizes explicitly and repeatedly the effect of the fall on mans
knowledge of God.&nbsp; Though men have a
naturally implanted knowledge of God given to them by and in creation, this knowledge
never develops into a true knowledge in the sense of a practical and
religious principle which leads them to worship God aright.&nbsp; Let me put that in my own words, but they are
words which, I think, rightly embody Calvins view.&nbsp; He believes that men have a natural
revelation of God, but that this natural revelation never results in a natural
theology which can guide them appropriately in worship or in life in general.
This emphasis is practically absent in Thomas.&nbsp;
Listen to Calvin:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>It must also be remarked, that, though they strive against their own natural understanding, and desire not only to banish him thence, but even to annihilate him in heaven, their insensibility can never prevail so as to prevent God from sometimes recalling them to his tribunal. But as no dread restrains them from violent opposition to the divine will, it is evident, as long as they are carried away with such a blind impetuosity, that they are governed by a brutish forgetfulness of God. <a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a> </p></blockquote>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>At length they involve themselves in such a vast accumulation of errors, that those sparks which enable them to discover the glory of God are smothered, and at last extinguished by the criminal darkness of iniquity. That seed, which it is impossible to eradicate, a sense of the existence of a Deity, yet remains; but so corrupted as to produce only the worst of fruits. Yet this is a further proof of what I now contend for, that the idea of God is naturally engraved on the hearts of men, since necessity extorts a confession of it, even from reprobates themselves. In a moment of tranquility they facetiously mock the Divine Being, and with loquacious impertinence in many derogate from his power. But if any despair oppress them, it stimulates them to seek him, and dictates concise prayers, which prove that they are not altogether ignorant of God, but that what ought to have appeared before had been suppressed by obstinacy. <a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a></p></blockquote>



<p>Third,
this very different assessment of the effect of the fall on mans knowledge of
God comes to concrete expression in the very different use which Thomas and
Calvin make of a classic passage on the subject. I have in mind, of course, Psalm
53:1 which reads in part: The fool has said in his heart, &#8220;There is no
God,&#8221; They are corrupt, and have committed abominable injustice; There is
no one who does good.&nbsp; Both Thomas and
Calvin cite this text, but how different is the use they make of it!&nbsp; </p>



<p>Thomas
sees it as proof that the existence of God is not self-evident. He takes at
face value the fools assertion that there is no God. Aquinas says: On the
contrary, no one can mentally admit the opposite of what is self-evident; as
the Philosopher  states concerning the first principles of demonstration. But
the opposite of the proposition God is can be mentally admitted: The fool
hath said in his heart, There is no God (Ps. Lii. 1). Therefore that God exists
is not self-evident. <a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a></p>



<p>Calvin,
on the other hand, takes it as evidence of the deep depravity of the fool.&nbsp; The fool denies a knowledge of God that is ineradicably
implanted in him. Here is Calvins comment in the <em>Institutes </em>on Psalm
53:1 with some context:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>While experience testifies that the seeds of religion are sown by God in every heart, we scarcely find one man in a hundred who cherishes what he has received, and not one in whom they grow to maturity, much less bear fruit in due season. Some perhaps grow vain in their own superstitions, while others revolt from God with intentional wickedness; but all degenerate from the true knowledge of him. The fact is, that no genuine piety remains in the world. But, in saying that some fall into superstition through error, I would not insinuate that their ignorance excuses them from guilt; because their blindness is always connected with pride, vanity, and contumacy. <a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a> </p></blockquote>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>David&#8217;s assertion, that &#8220;the fool hath said in his heart, There is no God,&#8221; is primarily, as we shall soon see in another place, to be restricted to those who extinguish the light of nature and willfully stupefy themselves. <a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a> <br></p></blockquote>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a> John Calvin, <em>Institutes of the
Christian Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 4, Section 2)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 4, Section 4)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologica</em>
(Volume 1, Question 2, Article 1)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref4">[4]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 4, Section 1)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref5">[5]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 4, Section 2)</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-6/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 6</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-6/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 5</title>
		<link>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-5/</link>
					<comments>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-5/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2019 20:50:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Calvin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Knowledge of God]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositional apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13440</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Calvin and Aquinas Contrasted Richard Muller is well-known for books like Unaccommodated Calvin.&#160; I had to read that book back in the days when I was studying for my PhD.&#160; Mullers point (or at least one of his main points) was that the contrast between Calvin and the Reformed Scholastics who followed him in the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-5/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 5</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p class="has-large-font-size"><strong><em>Calvin
and Aquinas Contrasted</em></strong></p>



<p>Richard
Muller is well-known for books like <em>Unaccommodated Calvin</em>.&nbsp; I had to read that book back in the days when
I was studying for my PhD.&nbsp; Mullers
point (or at least one of his main points) was that the contrast between Calvin
and the Reformed Scholastics who followed him in the next century had been
overdrawn by many scholars in the 20<sup>th</sup> Century who had bought in to
the Calvin versus the Calvinists movement. Muller showed (I think
successfully.) that there were clear indications of a scholastic methodology in
Calvin that showed much more continuity with his Calvinistic successors and his
Medieval predecessors.</p>



<p>But now we are confronted with a much more specific claim. It is that Calvin was controlled not only by a methodology common to the Medieval scholastics, but that he adopted the Thomist views of natural theology and apologetics. Cf. J. V. Feskos <em>Reforming Apologetics</em>. </p>



<p>Sorry,
folks, as they say here in the South, <em>That dog wont hunt!</em></p>



<p>As I
said previously in this blog series, I recently read up on and then lectured on
Thomas Aquinas for my class in apologetics.&nbsp;
I immediately followed that with a lecture on Calvins masterful
treatment of the knowledge of God in Book 1, Chapters 1-9 of the <em>Institutes</em>.&nbsp; I think even a novice cannot fail to notice a
massive difference in the ethos of Thomas opening chapters in <em>Summa
Theologica </em>and <em>Summa Contra Gentiles</em>.&nbsp; But this is not a superficial impression
without a substantial basis.&nbsp; In this
case the accessibility and biblicity of Calvin manifests a much different
approach to the subject of the knowledge of God than that of Thomas
Aquinas.&nbsp; Let me lay out the theological
contrasts between Thomas and Calvin.</p>



<p>First,
Calvin identifies himself with a theological tradition in regard to the
knowledge of God which Thomas rejects.&nbsp;
Thomas rejects the notion that the knowledge of the existence of God is
naturally implanted. He argues, as we have seen, that strictly speaking the
knowledge of God is not self-evident. He admits: To know God exists in a
general and confused way is implanted in us  Yet he says that this is not to
know absolutely that God exists, just as to know that someone is approaching is
not to know that Peter is approaching, even though it is Peter that is
approaching.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>
He goes on in the next article to assert: Hence, the existence of God, in so
far as it is not self-evident to us, can be demonstrated from those of His
effects which are known to us. <a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a>&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;</p>



<p>Calvin,
on the other hand, declares explicitly and repeatedly that men have a natural
knowledge of God which they cannot evade or erase. He has much more in common
with the Christian Platonist tradition embodied in Augustine, Anselm, the
Damascene, and Bonaventura which affirmed that the knowledge of the existence
of God was innate or at least naturally implanted in men.&nbsp; Listen to Calvins statements on this
subject. Calvin&#8217;s language here is absolutely incapable of misunderstanding.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>We lay it down as a position not to be controverted that the human mind, even by natural instinct, possesses some sense of a Deity. For that no man might shelter himself under the pretext of ignorance, God hath given to all some apprehension of his existence, the memory of which he frequently and insensibly renews; so that, as men universally know that there is a God, and that he is their Maker, they must be condemned by their own testimony, for not having worshipped him and consecrated their lives to his service. If we seek for ignorance of a Deity, it is nowhere more likely to be found, than among the tribes the most stupid and furthest from civilization. But, as the celebrated Cicero observes, there is no nation so barbarous, no race so savage; as not to be firmly persuaded of the being of a God. <a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a></p></blockquote>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>We read of none guilty of more audacious or unbridled contempt of the Deity than Caligula; yet no man ever trembled with greater distress at any instance of Divine wrath, so that he was constrained to dread the Divinity whom he professed to despise. This you may always see exemplified in persons of a similar character &#8230;. The impious themselves, therefore, exemplify the observation, that the idea of a God is never lost in the human mind. <a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a> </p></blockquote>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>It will always be evident to persons of correct judgment, that the idea of a Deity impressed on the mind of man is indelible. That all have by nature an innate persuasion of the Divine existence, a persuasion inseparable from their very constitution, we have abundant evidence in the contumacy of the wicked, whose furious struggles to extricate themselves from the fear of God are unavailing. <a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a></p></blockquote>



<p>The
contrast between Thomas and Calvin on this matter is clear.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </p>



<p>More
to come<br></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa
Theologica</em> (Volume 1, Question 2, Article 1) </p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Contra
Gentiles</em> (Book 1, Chapters 10-12).</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a> John Calvin, <em>Institutes of the
Christian Religion</em> (Book 1, Chapter 3, Section 1)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref4">[4]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 3, Section 2)</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref5">[5]</a> <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion</em> (Book 1,
Chapter 3, Section 3)</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthurs Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-5/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 5</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 4</title>
		<link>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-4/</link>
					<comments>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-4/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 16:15:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[men know God]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Romans 1]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Van Til]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13390</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>They Just Keep Missing the Point In my view those currently attacking Van Til and presuppositionalism are engaged in a gigantic enterprise of missing the point. They keep interpreting Romans 1:18-23 wrongly, over and over and again and again! To put it differently, they keep making the same exegetical mistake over and over again. They [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-4/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 4</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-large-font-size"><strong><em>They
Just Keep Missing the Point</em></strong></p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">In my view those currently attacking Van Til and presuppositionalism are engaged in a gigantic enterprise of missing the point. They keep interpreting Romans 1:18-23  <em>wrongly</em>, over and over and again and again<em>!</em> To put it differently, they keep making the same exegetical mistake over and over again. They keep affirming that Romans 1 teaches that we can demonstrate the existence of God to men. They keep saying that men <em>can</em> know that God exists. But that is emphatically not what the passage says. It does not say that men <em>can</em> know God. It does not say that <em>we can demonstrate</em> to men who do not know God that God exists. <em>It says that men do know God and that they do not need this demonstrated to them.</em> It will probably do no good to quote the passagesince this false understanding is so deeply embedded in the thinking of Classical Apologists, but let me do so one more time. Here is what Paul actually says: For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men who suppress the truth in unrighteousness, <sup>19</sup> because that which is known about God is evident within them; for God made it evident to them. <sup>20</sup> For since the creation of the world His invisible attributes, His eternal power and divine nature, have been clearly seen, being understood through what has been made, so that they are without excuse. <sup>21</sup> For even though they knew God, they did not honor Him as God or give thanks, but they became futile in their speculations, and their foolish heart was darkened.</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Men
according to Paul not only may know God, they do know God. They know God
because they suppress the truth in unrighteousness.&nbsp; They know God because that which <em>is </em>known
about God <em>is evident</em> <em>within</em> them.&nbsp;
They know God because since the creation of the world His eternal power
and divine nature are clearly seen and understood.&nbsp; They know God because they are without
excuse.&nbsp; (Paul grounds their
accountability on the fact that they know God.&nbsp;
They are not simply potentially without excuse because they may come to
know God.&nbsp; They are without excuse
because they do know God.) Finally, they know God, because they sinfully
refused to honor Him or give thanks.</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">The
passage is clear. Men do not merely have the capability of knowing God after a
theistic proof is presented.&nbsp; They know
God before such a proof is presented.&nbsp;
Yes, this knowledge is through the things that are made, but this does
not mean that their knowledge of God is the result of a properly constructed
theistic proof.&nbsp; Their knowledge of God
is both mediated to them through creation and implanted in them by creation.</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">It
should not be surprising that his modern followers misinterpret Romans 1.&nbsp; They are simply following in the footsteps of
the identical mistake made by Thomas Aquinas.</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Listen
to his argument in <em>Summa Theologica </em>Question 2, Article 2: The Apostle
says: &#8220;The invisible things of Him are clearly seen, being understood by
the things that are made&#8221; (Rm. 1:20). But this would not be unless the
existence of God could be demonstrated through the things that are made; for
the first thing we must know of anything is whether it exists. Thomas takes
(and the surrounding context of his assertion simply emphasizes this) Romans
1:20 to mean that the existence of God is not self-evident or implanted in man,
but can be demonstrated.</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Listen
to Thomas in <em>Summa Contra Gentiles</em>, Chapter 12, which is entitled: THE
OPINION OF THOSE WHO SAY THAT THE EXISTENCE OF GOD CANNOT BE DEMONSTRATED BUT
IS HELD BY FAITH ALONE.&nbsp; Once more in
proving that the existence of God can be demonstrated, he brings up Romans
1:20. He says: The falsity of this opinion is shown to us, first, from the art
of demonstration which teaches us to arrive at causes from their effects. Then,
it is shown to us from the order of the sciences. For, as it is said in the
Metaphysics [IV, 3], if there is no knowable substance higher than sensible
substance, there will be no science higher than physics. It is shown, thirdly,
from the pursuit of the philosophers, who have striven to demonstrate that God
exists. Finally, it is shown to us by the truth in the words of the Apostle
Paul: For the invisible things of God&#8230; are clearly seen, being understood by
the things that are made (Rom. 1:20).&nbsp;
Once more, it is clear that Thomas has misunderstood Romans 1.&nbsp; He thinks it means that one can arrive at
and demonstrate that God exists.&nbsp; I
have to say it again.&nbsp; This is not what
Romans 1:20 teaches.&nbsp; It teaches men do
know God. It is not something that they arrive at after it has been
demonstrated to them.&nbsp; To echo Pauls
argument in Romans 1:18-21, if the knowledge of God is something to be arrived
at, then their being without excuse is something to be arrived at.&nbsp; According to Paul, all men are without excuse
precisely because they do know God without the necessity of demonstration.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthurs Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-4/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 4</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 3</title>
		<link>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-3/</link>
					<comments>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-3/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2019 17:04:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositional apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositionalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Total Depravity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Van Til]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13360</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Aquinas Inadequate Views of Noetic Depravity Van Til and presuppositionalism object to Aquinass approach to natural theology and apologetics. One major reason given for this is that Thomism exhibits an over-confidence in fallen human reason. Does Thomas over-rate the ability of human reason and under-rate the effects of noetic depravity (the depravity of fallen mans [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-3/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 3</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-large-font-size"><strong><em>Aquinas
Inadequate Views of Noetic Depravity</em></strong></p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Van
Til and presuppositionalism object to Aquinass approach to natural theology
and apologetics. One major reason given for this is that Thomism exhibits an
over-confidence in fallen human reason. Does Thomas over-rate the ability of
human reason and under-rate the effects of noetic depravity (the depravity of
fallen mans mind) in his natural theology?&nbsp;
I think he does, but this requires a little explanation, if we are to be
entirely fair to Thomas.</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">The
picture that many have of Thomas Aquinas as a typical, semi-Pelagian Roman
Catholic is certainly not correct. At key points on the doctrine of grace he
follows Augustine carefully and deserves in those respects to be regarded as a
strict Augustinian.&nbsp; This is, of course,
a huge problem for modern Roman Catholicism because of its clearly
semi-Pelagian tendencies.</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Aquinas, in spite of
modern Thomists misconceptions, was thoroughly Augustinian in his view of
predestination.&nbsp; In his treatment of
predestination Aquinas answers a number of questions in the way that only
Augustine and his strict followers would answer. <a href="#_edn1">[1]</a>
Here is a brief summary.&nbsp; </p>



<ul><li>Whether Men Are Predestined by God? <em>Yes!</em></li><li>Whether Predestination Places Anything in the
Predestined? <em>No! (Men are passive in this matter.)</em></li><li>Whether God Reprobates Any Men? <em>Yes!</em></li><li>Whether the Predestined Are Chosen by God? <em>Yes!</em></li><li>Whether the Foreknowledge of Merits Is the
Cause of Predestination? <em>No!</em></li><li>Whether Predestination Is Certain? <em>Yes!</em></li><li>Whether the Number of the Predestined Is
Certain? <em>Yes!</em></li><li>Whether Predestination Can Be Furthered by the Prayers of the
Saints? <em>No, in that predestination is first determined regardless of the
prayers of the saints. Yes, in that the effect of predestinationsalvationcan
be furthered by the prayers of the saints as a means of grace.</em></li></ul>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">This last question and answer exactly parallels
Augustines argument in his book entitled, <em>Of Rebuke and Grace</em> (as do
all the others). Thomas echoes the anti-Pelagian teaching of Augustine.</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Similarly, and not surprisingly, Thomas also
agrees with Augustine about what is now known as irresistible grace.&nbsp; Once again through his typical and very
analytical treatment Aquinas follows the course laid out by Augustine. <a href="#_edn2">[2]</a> But
the pinnacle is reached when Aquinas teaches what amounts to effectual calling
or irresistible grace:  since Gods intention cannot fail, according to the
saying of Augustine in his book on the Predestination of the Saints  that <em>by
Gods good gifts whoever is liberated is most certainly liberated.</em>&nbsp; Hence if God intends, while moving, that the
one whose heart He moves should attain to grace, he will infallibly attain to
it <a href="#_edn3">[3]</a> </p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">With such evidence in front of us, we may
rather expect that Aquinas will follow out what we know as the Calvinistic
scheme by teaching the perseverance and preservation of the saints and the
other doctrines of grace.&nbsp; Sadly, this
assumption is not the case.&nbsp; Neither
Augustine, his strict follower, Gottschalk, nor Thomas Aquinas affirm the
preservation of the saints.&nbsp; Grace may be
lost unless one is also predestined to persevere.&nbsp; Once more Thomas Aquinas is a good
Augustinian when he says: Many have meritorious works who do not obtain
perseverance  <a href="#_edn4">[4]</a></p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Similarly, Aquinas also seems to have held
confused and imperfect views of total depravity.&nbsp; Sin, in fact, does not seem to occupy an
important place in Thomass writings.&nbsp; In
Gilsons index there is no entry for sin, depravity, the fall, or folly.&nbsp; For a discussion of Thomass view of sin, one
must consult his doctrine of free will and grace. It is not surprising, then,
Thomas argues that natural light is sufficient for natural knowledge.
Consequently, human nature is not altogether corrupted by sin. <a href="#_edn5">[5]</a></p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">The effects of this view of human nature become
evident in Thomass approach to the existence of God. In several places Thomas
argues that the existence of God is not self-evident because sinful men can
conceive that God does not exist, and if something is self-evident it cannot be
conceived by anyone as not existing.&nbsp; He
proves this by citing the ancients, that is, the ancient Greek philosophers.
He also cites the fact that the fool denies the existence of God. </p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Surprisingly, instead of attributing such
denials to the noetic depravity of men and the fact that they suppress the
truth in unrighteousness (Rom. 1:18), Thomas takes these statements of the fool
and the ancients at face value. He then uses them as an argument against the
self-evident character of the existence of God. Nothing could more pointedly
inform us of Thomass inflated view of the powers of fallen human reason.</p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Here are the quotes from Aquinas: And,
contrary to the Point made by the first argument, it does not follow
immediately that, as soon as we know the meaning of the name God, the existence
of God is known. It does not follow first because it is not known to all, even
including those who admit that God exists, that God is that than which a
greater cannot be thought. After all, many ancients said that this world itself
was God. <a href="#_edn6">[6]</a>
Cf. also: On the contrary, no one can mentally admit the opposite of what is
self-evident; as the Philosopher  states concerning the first principles of
demonstration. But the opposite of the proposition God is can be mentally
admitted: The fool hath said in his heart, There is no God (Ps. Lii. 1). Therefore
that God exists is not self-evident. <a href="#_edn7">[7]</a></p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">Thus, despite the promising character of
Thomass views of predestination and grace, he falls short of truly
appreciating the total depravity of man including his reason.&nbsp; This in turn profoundly controls his approach
to apologetics and the theistic proofs. This is why Aquinas can say that the fool
and the ancients disprove the self-evident-ness of the existence of God. This
is clear evidence that Thomas indulged deficient views of human depravity.<br></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><a href="#_ednref1">[1]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa
Theologica</em>, Volume 1, Question 23, Articles 1-8.</p>



<p><a href="#_ednref2">[2]</a> <em>Summa Theologica</em>, Volume 2,
Question 112, Articles 1-3.</p>



<p><a href="#_ednref3">[3]</a> <em>Summa Theologica</em>, Volume 2,
Question 112, Articles 3.</p>



<p><a href="#_ednref4">[4]</a> <em>Summa Theologica</em>, Volume 2,
Question 114, Article 9.&nbsp; Since the true
grace of regeneration was given through the sacrament of baptism, and it was
plain that not all the baptized persevered, no one committed to the notion of
baptismal regeneration in any sense could hold the Calvinistic view of the
perseverance of the saints.</p>



<p><a href="#_ednref5">[5]</a> <em>Summa Theologica,</em> Volume 2,
Question 109, Article 2.</p>



<p><a href="#_ednref6">[6]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Contra
Gentiles</em>, Book 1, Chapter 11, Paragraph 3&nbsp; </p>



<p><a href="#_ednref7">[7]</a> <em>Summa Theologica</em>, Volume 1,
Question 2, Article 1</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthurs Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-3/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 3</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-3/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 2</title>
		<link>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-2/</link>
					<comments>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 16:29:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Augustine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositional apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositionalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13340</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Why are we privileging Aquinas over Augustine? One of the first things that became very clear to me as I read Aquinas was that with respect to the whole issue of apologetics and the proofs for the existence of God, he does not agree with Augustine, Anselm, and many other Christian theologians who preceded him.&#160; [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-2/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 2</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-large-font-size"><strong><em>Why
are we privileging Aquinas over Augustine?</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">One
of the first things that became very clear to me as I read Aquinas was that
with respect to the whole issue of apologetics and the proofs for the existence
of God, he does not agree with Augustine, Anselm, and many other Christian
theologians who preceded him.&nbsp; They
asserted (what Thomas denies) that the existence of God is self-evident or
naturally implanted in man.&nbsp; This is
evident in his whole approach to the subject.&nbsp;
Here is his description of the arguments of those who say that the
existence of God is self-evident in <em>Summa Theologica</em> Question 2, Article
2.&nbsp; (Note that Aquinas is presenting
views <em>he rejects!)</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Objection 2: Further, those things are said to be self-evident which are known as soon as the terms are known, which the Philosopher (1 Poster. iii) says is true of the first principles of demonstration. Thus, when the nature of a whole and of a part is known, it is at once recognized that every whole is greater than its part. But as soon as the signification of the word &#8220;God&#8221; is understood, it is at once seen that God exists. For by this word is signified that thing than which nothing greater can be conceived. But that which exists actually and mentally is greater than that which exists only mentally. Therefore, since as soon as the word &#8220;God&#8221; is understood it exists mentally, it also follows that it exists actually. Therefore the proposition &#8220;God exists&#8221; is self-evident.</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:quote {"className":"is-style-default"} -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-style-default"><p>Objection 3: Further, the existence of truth is self-evident. For whoever denies the existence of truth grants that truth does not exist: and, if truth does not exist, then the proposition &#8220;Truth does not exist&#8221; is true: and if there is anything true, there must be truth. But God is truth itself: &#8220;I am the way, the truth, and the life&#8221; (Jn. 14:6) Therefore &#8220;God exists&#8221; is self-evident.&#8221;<a href="#_edn1">[1]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">These
are descriptions of two well-known arguments for the self-evident-ness of the
existence of God.&nbsp; The first is Anselm&#8217;s
ontological argument for the existence of God.&nbsp;
The second is Augustine&#8217;s argument from the existence of truth. He does
not mention here that these arguments were brought forward not only by Anselm,
but by Augustine as well.&nbsp; This, however,
was clear to anyone acquainted with Augustine.&nbsp;
Augustine&#8217;s argument from truth is plain to see in Book 2 of his
treatise on <em>The Free Choice of the Will</em>.&nbsp;
</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">Aquinas
denies that the existence of God is self-evident in both his <em>Summa
Theologica </em>and in his <em>Summa Contra Gentiles </em>and rejects the above
arguments. The five proofs are built, then, upon the denial of any innate
knowledge of God.&nbsp; Says Gordon H.
Clark:&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote {"className":"is-style-default"} -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-style-default"><p>Thomas faced two other contrasting views.&nbsp; One is that the existence of God is self-evident and neither needs nor is susceptible of proof from prior first principles.&nbsp; Those who hold this view argue that God has implanted in all men an elemental knowledge of himself.&nbsp; The idea of God is innate.&nbsp; On this showing any argument or so-called proof could be nothing more than a clarification of already present ideas; and such in effect was the nature of Augustine&#8217;s, Anselm&#8217;s and Bonaventura&#8217;s attempts.&nbsp; Now, in one sense Thomas is willing to admit that God&#8217;s existence is self-evident: it is self-evident in itself, it is self-evident to God; but it is not self-evident to us.&nbsp; God has not implanted ideas in the human mind, and all knowledge must be based on sensory experience.<sup>&#8221;&nbsp;&nbsp; <a href="#_edn2">[2]</a></sup></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">For the substantiation of Clark&#8217;s assertions,
cf. Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologica</em>, Volume 1, Question 2, Article 1; <em>Summa
Contra Gentiles</em>, Book 1, Chapters 10-12.&nbsp;
In these places he mentions other Christian theologians with whom he is
taking issue. Included among them are the ones he calls the Damascene and
Bonaventura.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">All
of this is significant because it means that in favoring the classical
apologetics of Aquinas, contemporary Reformed theologians are selecting one
from among several historically &#8220;scholastic&#8221; positions.&nbsp; They are really crediting Aquinas over
Augustine.&nbsp; They are also privileging
Christian Aristotelianism over Christian Platonism.&nbsp; It is well-known that the idea of the self-evident-ness
of the existence of God appealed to Augustine, Anselm, and others because of
their preference for a form of Christian Platonism which emphasized the
importance of innate ideas over the Christian Aristotelianism of Aquinas which
favored the importance of sensory or empirical evidence.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">My
point is not to argue for Christian Platonism&#8212;any more than I am arguing for
Christian Aristotelianism. It is only to say that in their rush to identify
Reformed Scholasticism with Aquinas, contemporary Reformed theologians may have
forgotten that there was a different and viable option available to our
Reformed fathers that did not involve the adoption of Aquinas&#8217;s view of natural
theology.&nbsp; That alternative was none
other than the view of the one who was recognized by Calvin and others as the
most important predecessor of the Reformation, Augustine himself. Scholastics
such as Anselm and Bonaventura did not reject Augustine&#8217;s views in the way
Aquinas did. They remained more faithful to the Augustinian tradition with
regard to the self-evident nature of the knowledge of God.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">There
is certainly clear evidence (from the predominant number of times he quotes him
in the <em>Institutes</em>) that Calvin privileged Augustine.&nbsp; Calvin frequently cites Augustine by name and
generally positively. I think the number is 300 plus times in the <em>Institutes</em>.
Having searched I can find only three places where he cites by name Thomas
Aquinas.&nbsp; The references are not very
positive, but usually rather equivocal.&nbsp;
In spite of this, we are supposed to think that Calvin adopted Aquinas&#8217;s
view of apologetics and the theistic proofs rather than Augustine&#8217;s.&nbsp; This is a really suspect way to reason.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">Why
are we privileging Aquinas over Augustine?&nbsp;
Furthermore, why must we privilege either Christian Aristotelianism or
Christian Platonism? Of course, I am not arguing that we return to the
Christian Platonism of Augustine.&nbsp; I am
saying, however, that there were certainly historical-theological alternatives
available to the Reformed Scholastics that did not involve a return to &#8220;the
classical apologetics&#8221; of Thomas Aquinas. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">In
further posts I will demonstrate some of the mistakes that are involved in
privileging Aquinas&#8217;s views.<br></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref1">[1]</a> Thomas Aquinas, <em>Summa Theologica</em>&nbsp;Question 2, Article 2</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref2">[2]</a> Gordon H. Clark, <em>Thales to Dewey</em>, 272-273.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthurs Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-2/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 2</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 1</title>
		<link>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-1/</link>
					<comments>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-1/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 23:40:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Classical Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[J.V. Fesko]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositional apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositionalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thomas Aquinas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Van Til]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=13311</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>After Reading Aquinas! &#8220;Everyone&#8221; knows that recently there has been quite a furor created by the claims of J. V. Fesko (Reforming Apologetics&#8212;Retrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the Faith), Keith Mathison (Christianity and Van Tillianism), Richard Muller (Aquinas Reconsidered), and other critics of Van Til. Their assertion is that Cornelius Van Til substantially [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-1/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 1</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-large-font-size"><strong><em>After
Reading Aquinas!</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">&#8220;Everyone&#8221;
knows that recently there has been quite a furor created by the claims of J. V.
Fesko (<em>Reforming Apologetics&#8212;Retrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending
the Faith</em>), Keith Mathison (<em>Christianity and Van Tillianism</em>),
Richard Muller (<em>Aquinas Reconsidered</em>), and other critics of Van Til.
Their assertion is that Cornelius Van Til substantially misunderstood and/or
misrepresented Thomas Aquinas in the construction of his presuppositional
apologetics. In turn this exposes to criticism the supposed &#8220;Copernican&#8221;
revolution which presuppositionalism claimed to represent in the area of Christian
Apologetics.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">As
part of my course on Apologetics for CBTS I begin with an historical
introduction to the subject. After that I delve deeply into the significance of
the major, relevant, biblical passages for Christian Apologetics and for the
major issues revealed by this historical introduction.&nbsp; Therefore, after lecturing on the contrast
between Justin Martyr and Tertullian in the Early Church period and before
coming to the contrast between Warfield and Kuyper in the Modern Church, I
lecture on the contrast between Aquinas and Calvin in what I call the period of
the Augustinian Church.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">It
was the lecture on Aquinas that caused me concern.&nbsp; Of course, the contrast for which I argue between
Aquinas and Calvin is called into question by the advocates of Reformed
Scholasticism.&nbsp; But the bigger issue was the
propriety of the way that I (generally following Van Til&#8217;s lead) described
Aquinas&#8217;s views. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">I
was encouraged, however, to see that I rarely quoted Van Til or his assessment
of Aquinas in this lecture.&nbsp; Rather, the
views of Gordon H. Clark, E. J. Carnell, and Kelly James Clark are much more
frequently cited. Substantially, they give the same account of Thomas Aquinas
as Van Til.&nbsp; Still, I felt that I was myself
too reliant on secondary sources for my description of Thomas Aquinas and not
well enough read in Thomas Aquinas to defend my treatment and description of
his &#8220;classical approach&#8221; to Apologetics. I determined to make sure that I had rectified
this before the lecture on Aquinas.&nbsp;
Thus, I read the relevant sections of Thomas Aquinas for myself before
giving this lecture. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">I
procured and then scoured the relevant sections of his <em>Summa Contra Gentiles</em>
and<em> Summa Theologica</em>.&nbsp; This
reading caused considerable expansion of that lecture.&nbsp; It actually&#8212;in fact&#8212;expanded it into two
lectures. What it did not do, however, was significantly change my
understanding of Thomas Aquinas &#8220;Classical Apologetics&#8221; at all.&nbsp; I concluded that basically Van Til&#8217;s
presentation of Thomas was right.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">This conclusion should not really surprise anyone. In his recent blog posts on the subject James Anderson points out that, even <em>if</em>  Van Til was not deeply acquainted with Aquinas&#8217; writings himself, he was at least using the exposition of Aquinas available from the premier Aquinas scholar of the 20<sup>th</sup> century.&nbsp; I refer to Etienne Gilson and his <em>The Christian Philosophy of St. Thomas Aquinas</em>.&nbsp; Here is what Anderson says: &#8220;I think it&#8217;s also fair to criticize Van Til for relying heavily on secondary sources and not engaging more directly with Aquinas&#8217;s works. Even so, Van Til engages frequently with Etienne Gilson, who was one of the leading authorities on Aquinas during Van Til&#8217;s career, so it&#8217;s not as though his secondary sources were dubious ones! If Van Til was interacting with Aquinas through the lens of Gilson and other contemporary scholars, then he was interacting with the interpretation of Aquinas that was dominant in his day.&#8221; <a href="#_edn1">[i]</a> As I read Gilson, it was clear to me that his treatment was a closely accurate portrayal of Thomas Aquinas, his Christian philosophy, and his Apologetics.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size">In
the posts to follow I want to respond to the criticisms of presuppositionalism based
on the fascination with Aquinas among some contemporary Reformed scholars.&nbsp; I will point out several misguided and unhelpful
directions that are being taken in the current discussion of Aquinas and
Christian Apologetics.<br></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ednref1">[i]</a> https://www.proginosko.com/2019/08/reforming-apologetics-thomas-aquinas/</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthurs Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-1/">Presuppositional Ponderings after Reading Thomas Aquinas, part 1</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/presuppositional-ponderings-after-reading-thomas-aquinas-part-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>J. V. Feskos Reforming ApologeticsRetrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the FaithA Critical Review (4 of 4)</title>
		<link>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-4-of-4/</link>
					<comments>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-4-of-4/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2019 12:01:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[J.V. Fesko]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositionalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Van Til]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11733</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Part 1: Preface Part 2 Introduction Part 3: Overview Evaluation Commendation There is certainly much that is challenging in Fesko&#8217;s work.&#160; There is definitely much to be learned.&#160; Furthermore, given the directions Reformed historiography has taken in recent years, it seems to me that a book like this had to be written.&#160; Let me commend [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-4-of-4/">J. V. Feskos Reforming ApologeticsRetrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the FaithA Critical Review (4 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-1-of-4/">Part 1: Preface</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-2-of-4/">Part 2 Introduction</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-3-of-4/">Part 3: Overview</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"large"} -->
<p class="has-large-font-size"><strong>Evaluation </strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong><em>Commendation</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There
is certainly much that is challenging in Fesko&#8217;s work.&nbsp; There is definitely much to be learned.&nbsp; Furthermore, given the directions Reformed
historiography has taken in recent years, it seems to me that a book like this <em>had</em> to be written.&nbsp; Let me commend a number of things in it.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>First,
as I have just said, his summary of what a biblical and covenantal epistemology
looks like was well done. Presuppositionalist that I am, I still find it a very
helpful summary of the scriptural approach to how we know.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Second,
I much appreciated his account of the purposes of apologetics. Here is what he
says:&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Apologetics, narrowly construed as a rational defense of Christianity, does not convert fallen sinners. &#8230; I argue that apologetics has a threefold purpose: (1) to refute intellectual objections to the Christian faith, (2) to clarify our understanding of the truth, and (3) to encourage and edify believers in their faith. (203-04)</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>I
think Fesko here helpfully articulates the fact that apologetics (narrowly
construed) has a negative and kind of secondary purpose.&nbsp; It does not and ought not to pretend to
create arguments for the existence of God which positively ground the believer&#8217;s
faith.&nbsp; Without pretending to understand
all that was in Fesko&#8217;s mind when he wrote this, it does suggest to me a number
of important features of the apologetic endeavor.&nbsp; First, apologetics is properly
defensive.&nbsp; It is an apologia or defense
of the faith.&nbsp; It is not, then, properly
(or narrowly) speaking a positive attempt to argue discursively for the
existence of God or the truth of Christianity.&nbsp;
It assumes the faith and defends the faith so assumed against
attack.&nbsp; Second, this suggests to me,
secondly, that the much disputed arguments for the existence of God appear
quite differently depending (1) on whether they are construed as the positive
ground or origin of the Christian&#8217;s faith in God or (2) whether they are
construed as defenses of a faith already assumed.&nbsp; I think that Bavinck and others have seen
something of this distinction when they have argued that these arguments are <em>confirmations of</em> or <em>testimonies to</em> the existence of God rather than proofs.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a> As testimonies and
properly constructed, the traditional &#8220;proofs&#8221; may have a certain defensive
value toward unbelievers and confirming value for believers. Third, it seems to
me that we may want to distinguish in our discussions of the existence of God
between apologetics more broadly considered as epistemology (how we know that
God exists) and more narrowly considered as apologetics (how we defend our
faith in the existence of God to unbelievers).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Thirdly
by way of commendation, it must be said that Fesko&#8217;s book exhibits many, fine
scholarly qualities.&nbsp; It manifests widely
read scholarship. It shows that he attempts to fairly represent those with whom
he differs.&nbsp; Though complicating his
argument, Fesko still nuances his views and especially his assessment of Van
Til. (108, 137, 141, 144)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Fourth,
I thought his account of faith seeking understanding was well said.&nbsp; In particular, I appreciated his statement to
the effect that &#8220;trusting authority lies at the root of all epistemology.&#8221;
(195)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong><em>Critiques</em></strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>First,
from the beginning of his book till its end Fesko consistently fails to
understand the distinction between natural revelation and natural theology in
Presuppositionalism.&nbsp; There is no more
crucial distinction than this for Presuppositionalism in my opinion.&nbsp; When Van Til rejects natural theology, he is
not rejecting or giving up on the book of nature.&nbsp; With regard to the book of nature or natural
revelation, Van Til never tires of saying that believers and unbelievers have <em>everything in common.&nbsp; </em>The reader should consult Van Til&#8217;s essay
entitled, &#8220;Nature and Scripture,&#8221; in <em>The
Infallible </em>Word cited previously and his many other assertions to this
effect.<a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a>&nbsp; It simply is not true that Van Til denies the
commonality between believers and unbelievers with regard to common notions and
the like.&nbsp; This is, however, what Fesko
assumes everywhere. (4, 9, 12, 26, 48, 65, 68-69, 99, 100, 109, 110, 111, 114,
125, 126, 135-36, 146-147, 149, 194, 212, 219) Only if common notions are made
to consist in a natural theology created by depraved men, would Van Til oppose
such common notions.&nbsp; This critique
cannot be pursued without mentioning a second difficulty.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Secondly,
then, Fesko fails to weigh properly the apologetic effects of Thomas&#8217;
sub-biblical view of sin. (34, 72, 75, 78, 80, 84, 85, 94, 104) This is
important because it is exactly this factor which distinguishes Van Til&#8217;s
assessment of natural revelation from his assessment of natural theology.&nbsp; Natural revelation is the divine given of
human existence which at a basic level of awareness all men cannot escape.&nbsp; Natural theology is the human interpretation
of natural revelation.&nbsp; Because Van Til
holds with Reformed theology that men are totally depraved and that this
depravity affects their mind and reason radically, he cannot allow that a
natural theology can be any kind of preamble to faith.&nbsp; By definition such a natural theology is an
interpretive endeavor pursued by men who are totally depraved.&nbsp; Thus, it cannot be successful. Rather,
depraved human reason must and will inevitably corrupt the meaning of natural
revelation in any natural theology it creates.&nbsp;
Such a natural theology cannot serve in any sense as a preamble to
faith.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Let
me mention here that my own reading has convinced me that the categories and
terminologies with which Reformed Scholasticism discussed natural theology were
inadequate.&nbsp; They were inadequate
precisely because they did not clearly distinguish between natural revelation
and natural theology.&nbsp; Sometimes natural
theology is used by Reformed scholastics to mean natural revelation.&nbsp; Van Til&#8217;s apologetics pressed a distinction
between these two things that is, in my view, massively important.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This
brings up a third criticism.&nbsp; Unless
Fesko is willing to say that Thomas Aquinas has a fully biblical and Reformed
view of sin, and he does not seem to say this, he cannot expect Reformed
Christians to find in Aquinas a model for apologetic endeavor.&nbsp; Yet, clearly, Fesko offers Aquinas as a model
for Christian apologetics. (96) The whole hinge of the distinction between a
true natural revelation and a proper natural theology resides in one&#8217;s doctrine
of sin.&nbsp; If Thomas Aquinas&#8217;s doctrine of
sin was inadequate, then his view of natural theology cannot be correct.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Fourth,
Fesko probably depreciates Calvin&#8217;s critique of scholasticism. (52, 53, 68, 69)
It seems to me that a statistical study of Calvin&#8217;s Institutes will show that Calvin
frequently cites Augustine with enthusiasm, but rarely cites Aquinas positively
or at all.<a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a>&nbsp; Furthermore, his references to scholastic
theology are mostly critical.&nbsp; One does
not have to disagree with Muller&#8217;s thesis of a scholastic method in Calvin to
argue that Calvin consistently rejected their doctrinal conclusions. (53) It
remains to be seen, in my view, what Calvin&#8217;s view of Aquinas&#8217;s theology might
have been.&nbsp; I am not convinced that
Calvin&#8217;s statements about the existence of God which are characterized as <em>rhetorical </em>by Muller (64) are the same in
character as Thomas&#8217;s five proofs for the existence of God.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Fifth,
Fesko engages repeatedly in the common, evidentialist misunderstanding of key
texts of Scripture and Calvin which assert the knowledge of God.&nbsp; He sees in these statements warrants for
arguments for God rather than statements of the fact that men know God without
discursive arguments.&nbsp; (62, 63, 64, 77,
89, 90) The fact is that Romans 1:18-23 does not teach that men may come to
know God or that men may argue for the existence of God from natural
reason.&nbsp; This passage and similar ones
teach rather that men <em>actually do know
God from natural revelation</em> without the complicated and lengthy arguments
of Anselm or Aquinas.&nbsp; We have heard
evidentialist and post-Enlightenment classically oriented apologists make this
mistake too often to overlook it when Fesko makes precisely the same mistake.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Sixth,
Fesko&#8217;s argument for Christians not claiming comprehensive knowledge of
everything on the basis of the Bible is imbalanced.&nbsp; Of course, the Reformed confessional
tradition makes clear that the sufficiency of Scripture is not its
omni-sufficiency for every science.&nbsp; Cf.
the Westminster and 1689 at 1:6. What Fesko fails to see, however, in his
polemic against Idealism and Worldview theory is that what the Bible does teach
sufficiently is basic and foundational for every other area of study.&nbsp; Fesko does not clearly state that, while
Christians do not claim that the Bible is sufficient for all knowledge, they do
believe that it is basic or foundational to all knowledge and that nothing is
properly understood unless understood theistically.&nbsp; While unbelievers have a functional or
working knowledge of some things, they have a proper theological knowledge of
nothing. (67, 98, 99, 104, 127, 129, 209, 215, 216, 217) Sometimes Fesko seems
to notice this.&nbsp; He makes clear, for
instance, that Scripture truth claims do create givens for the science of human
origins and universal origins. (216) It does this, however, because scriptural
knowledge, while not sufficient for non-religious and non-theological sciences,
is foundational for them.&nbsp; How can what
we believe about God <em>not</em> be basic for
all human knowledge?&nbsp; Yet, Fesko can say
that the covenantal exile in which they live does not mean that &#8220;everything
they do is wrong.&#8221; (210) We know what he means, but surely what he says is not
all the truth.&nbsp; In another sense and in
the most important sense, everything they do is wrong.&nbsp; Their covenant exile does affect everything
they do.&nbsp; Surely if any generation of
Americans should see this, we should.&nbsp;
Our culture is falling apart.&nbsp; In
the midst of the cultural disaster all around us&#8212;with its devastating effects
on everything and even on something so basic as gender identity&#8212;shall our
message be to unbelievers that <em>not
everything you do is wrong</em>.&nbsp; They are
wrong basically and foundationally about God, and this does affect
everything.&nbsp; But with his concern to
counter the triumphalism of some Christians and their excessive claims, Fesko
denies the antithesis between Christianity and other worldviews and the devastating
effects of this antithesis culturally and educationally. (120, 123, 130, 133,
194, 210, 211, 215)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>We
are glad for the emphasis of Fesko and others that there is a generally agreed
upon classical theism that resides in the scholastic tradition of the church.&nbsp; We agree that 21<sup>st</sup> century
Christians do not get to re-define the Christian God.&nbsp; The Reformation itself, however, shows that
the scholastic tradition could deviate into bypaths.&nbsp; It also shows that one must account for
positive doctrinal development in the church.&nbsp;
For myself, and I suspect others, I am not ready to return to the
natural theology of Aquinas.&nbsp; I find in
Calvin, in the Reformed tradition, and Van Til&#8217;s Presuppositionalism a progress
of doctrine which improves upon the natural theology of Thomism.<br></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a>John Frame, The Doctrine of God
(Phillipsburg, NJ:&nbsp; P&amp;R Publishing,
2002), 740; Herman Bavinck, ed. John Bolt, trans. Jon Vriend, Reformed
Dogmatics First(Grand Rapids: Baker, 2004), 2:90, 91. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a><em>The Infallible Word:
a Symposium</em>, (Philipsburg,
NJ: Presbyterian and Reformed, 1978), &#8220;Nature and Scripture,&#8221; 263-301.&nbsp; Cf. the tract by Cornelius Van Til, <em>Common Grace and Witness-bearing</em> (Lewis
J. Grotenhuis, Belvedere Road, Phillipsburg, NJ), 8f. Cf. his <em>The Defense of Christianity and My Credo</em>
(Philipsburg, NJ: Presbyterian and Reformed, n.d.), 11: &#8220;Natural revelation is
perfectly clear. Men <em>ought </em>through it
to see al other things as dependent on God. But only one who looks at nature
through the mirror of Scripture <em>does</em>
understand natural revelation for what it is. Furthermore, no one can see
Scripture for what it is unless he is given the ability to do so by the
regenerating power of the Holy Spirit.&#8221;&nbsp;
Cf. also page 24 of the same tract where Van Til approvingly cites
Calvin and says: &#8220;Calvin makes a sharp distinction between the revelation of
God to man and man&#8217;s response to that revelation.&nbsp; This implies the rejection of a natural
theology such as Aquinas taught.&#8221; He goes on to distinguish the responses to
God&#8217;s revelation by (1) man in his original condition, (2) mankind, whose
&#8220;understanding is subjected to blindness and the heart to depravity&#8221; (3) those
that are &#8220;taught of Christ&#8221; through Scripture and whose eyes have been opened
by the Holy Spirit.&#8221; In Van Til&#8217;s syllabus entitled, &#8220;An Introduction to
Systematic Theology,&#8221; reprinted in 1966 pages 75-109 emphasize the importance
of general or natural revelation. Cf. also Greg Bahnsen, <em>Van Til&#8217;s Apologetic </em>(Phillipsburg, NJ: P&amp;R Publishing, 1998),
177-194. &nbsp;In these pages Bahnsen
documents Van Til&#8217;s commitment to &#8220;the inescapable knowledge of God in nature&#8221;
and the distinction between natural revelation and natural theology.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a>I did a count of Book 1 of the <em>Institutes</em> (McNeil-Battles edition) [John
Calvin, <em>Institutes of the Christian
Religion </em>ed. By John T McNeill; trans. by Ford Lewis Battles (Philadlephia:
The Westminster Press, MCMLX) to confirm for myself the evidence.&nbsp; Here are the results of my own count.&nbsp; Calvin never mentions by name Thomas
Aquinas.&nbsp; There is one possible and
positive reference to his writings that I found (210).&nbsp; Calvin mentions Plato one time positively
(46).&nbsp; He mentions Aristotle by name 4
times once neutrally (82) and three times negatively (56, 194, 194).&nbsp; Calvin, on the other hand, mentions Augustine
by name and always positively 25 times (5, 76, 77, 77, 78, 92, 105, 106, 106,
110, 113, 126, 126, 127, 143, 144, 144, 144, 158, 207, 207, 208, 213, 234, 237)
and there is an additional possible reference to Augustine but not by name
(217). Augustine is massively the most cited church father in Book 1.&nbsp; I think this continues throughout Books 2-4.
I would say that these statistics present an obstacle for the idea of a
Thomistic Calvin.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthurs Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-4-of-4/">J. V. Feskos Reforming ApologeticsRetrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the FaithA Critical Review (4 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-4-of-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>J. V. Feskos Reforming ApologeticsRetrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the FaithA Critical Review (3 of 4)</title>
		<link>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-3-of-4/</link>
					<comments>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-3-of-4/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2019 12:08:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[J.V. Fesko]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositionalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Van Til]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11730</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>part 1 , part 2 Overview Reforming Apologetics consists of an introduction and eight chapters.&#160; The introduction provides a survey of the book with the intention of summarizing its argument. The first three chapters have for their purpose the rehabilitation of natural theology.&#160; Fesko argues in Chapter 1 which is entitled, &#8220;The Light of Nature,&#8221; [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-3-of-4/">J. V. Feskos Reforming ApologeticsRetrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the FaithA Critical Review (3 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-1-of-4/">part 1</a> ,   <a href="http://j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-2-of-4/">part 2</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Overview</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><em>Reforming Apologetics</em> consists of an
introduction and eight chapters.&nbsp; The
introduction provides a survey of the book with the intention of summarizing
its argument.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The
first three chapters have for their purpose the rehabilitation of natural
theology.&nbsp; Fesko argues in Chapter 1
which is entitled, &#8220;The Light of Nature,&#8221; that natural theology has played a
vital role in high Reformed theology or Reformed Scholasticism.&nbsp; Utilizing Burgess&#8217;s lectures on the light of
nature (24), he rebuts scholarly views of a previous generation that Reformed
theology was opposed to natural theology and argues that the Reformed were one
with the &#8220;common catholic heritage&#8221; found in Aquinas and Augustine which
affirmed natural theology (25-26).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In
Chapter 2 Fesko discusses the idea of common notions.&nbsp; Once more from Anthony Burgess&#8217;s lectures on
the law he shows that &#8220;common notions&#8221; were a part of the theology of the
Puritans. He proceeds to argue that &#8220;common notions&#8221; were taught by the Greek
philosophers and were &#8220;the proximate source&#8221; of the concept in high Reformed
theology. (32)&nbsp; Once more Fesko concludes
that Reformed theology held a form of natural theology. (48)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In
Chapter 3 Fesko specifically addresses &#8220;Calvin.&#8221;&nbsp; That is the title of the chapter.&nbsp; Calvin&#8217;s views must be discussed because Calvin
is frequently seen as the opponent of natural theology. Fesko associates Van
Til with Barth&#8217;s famous rejection of natural theology. (51-52) This leads Fesko
to reiterate some of Richard Muller&#8217;s work showing that Calvin utilized a
scholastic methodology, though not so overtly as some later Reformed
theologians.&nbsp; He is careful to
distinguish between the use of this methodology and &#8220;specific doctrinal
outcomes.&#8221; (54) Nevertheless, Fesko argues that the traditional arguments for
the existence of God are implicit in Calvin&#8217;s writing. (63-65) Thus, he once
more concludes that Calvin held and taught a form of natural theology in
continuity with the catholic tradition. (68-69)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In
Chapters 4-7 Fesko turns to several specific issues raised by his claim that natural
theology is part and parcel of the Reformed tradition beginning with Calvin
himself.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Chapter
4 is simply entitled, &#8220;Thomas Aquinas.&#8221;&nbsp;
Fesko&#8217;s treatment of Van Til and Aquinas is strangely both blunt and
nuanced.&nbsp; Early in the chapter with
reference to Van Til&#8217;s critique of Aquinas&#8212;a critique that is basic to his
apologetic project&#8212; Fesko asserts: &#8220;Is Van Til&#8217;s critique accurate? The short
answer is no.&#8221; (72) Specifically, with reference to Aquinas&#8217; five proofs for
the existence of God, Fesko argues that Van Til has wrongly characterized
Thomas as rationalistic.&nbsp; (75-80)
Obviously, this is an important point to which we must return in the evaluation
of Fesko&#8217;s arguments.&nbsp; But at this point
Fesko attempts to explain why Van Til has misread Thomas.&nbsp; Fesko&#8217;s interesting explanation for this is
threefold.&nbsp; &#8220;There are three chief
reasons: (1) reading Thomas in the light of postmedieval developments,
particularly a post-enlightenment reading; (2) trying to divide Aquinas the
philosopher from Aquinas the theologian; and (3) failing, ultimately, to
examine clearly the primary sources.&#8221; (81)&nbsp;
These are serious criticisms of Van Til.&nbsp;
Fesko, however, attempts to soften the blow for his Van Tillian
readers.&nbsp; He avers: &#8220;Just because Van Til
misread Aquinas does not mean that we must embrace everything that Thomas said.
Conversely, it does not mean that everything that Van Til said on these matters
is categorically wrong. Rather, the truth lies somewhere in the middle.&#8221;
(93)&nbsp; In another place he remarks:&nbsp; &#8220;Although he erroneously evaluated Aquinas&#8217;s
views, this does not invalidate all of Van Til&#8217;s insights about the problematic
nature of autonomous reason.&#8221; (95) In spite of these concessions,
Presuppositionalists are treated with this hair-raising assessment in the very
last sentences of this chapter: &#8220;Aquinas and other theologians of the Middle
Ages and patristic period belong equally to Protestants.&nbsp; They have insights to offer, and we have much
to learn from them regarding theology and, perhaps especially, apologetics.&#8221;
(96)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In Chapter
5 which is simply entitled, &#8220;Worldview,&#8221; Fesko provides us one of the more
unique subjects and viewpoints in his book.&nbsp;
Startlingly, he argues that the emphasis of James Orr, Abraham Kuyper,
and Cornelius Van Til on the idea that one&#8217;s worldview controls how one thinks
about everything is mistaken.&nbsp; It is, he
affirms, a mistaken viewpoint owing to the adoption of Idealist
perspectives.&nbsp; This contradicts,
according to Fesko, the idea of &#8220;common notions&#8221; for which he has been at such
pains to defend in his earlier chapters.&nbsp;
Here we see an attempt (typical of Westminster West) to resist the
claims of some Presuppositionalists, especially those of a Theonomic bent, to
make the Scriptures speak to everything in the world.&nbsp; With Van Drunen and others Fesko is
interested in reserving a place for natural law and showing that the Scriptures
are intended to have a limited range of authority to matters of religion and
Christian duty.&nbsp; One of the more
controversial claims of Fesko in this chapter is that Moses is dependent in his
exposition of the civil law of Israel either on the Code of Hammurabi or on
material that predates that code. (121-122) I find myself deeply ambivalent
about Fesko&#8217;s view in this interesting chapter.&nbsp;
Once more it needs discussion in the evaluative section of this review.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Chapter
6 treats &#8220;Transcendental Arguments.&#8221;&nbsp;
Once more Fesko seeks to bring Van Til and Apologetics back to the
touchstone of natural theology as taught by the Reformed Scholastics.&nbsp; He begins by citing Turretin who affirms a
natural theology partly innate and derived from common notions and partly
acquired by being drawn from the book of nature by discursive reasoning.
(135-136) This is one of the more difficult chapters in Fesko&#8217;s book because of
the fairly constant necessity of qualifying his critique of Van Til.&nbsp; He cannot say that the transcendental
argument is wrong. He acknowledges it to be a useful tool. (137)&nbsp; He cannot quite say that Van Til rejected the
use of evidence. He must limit this claim to &#8220;some Van Tillians&#8221; and suggest
that it follows from certain statements of Van Til. (137)&nbsp; Perhaps the most important and consistent
claim of this chapter is that the transcendental argument is not the Copernican
Revolution in apologetics which both Van Til and Van Tillians have claimed.
(136) </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The
pivotal paragraph in this chapter deserves quoting and reads as follows:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>This chapter deals with three issues, namely whether (1) Van Til engages in synthetic thinking; (2) some overemphasize the coherence theory of truth at the expense of the correspondence theory; and (3) the TAG is wedded to outdated philosophical trends. Van Til accused Thomas Aquinas (1225-1274) of employing synthetic thinking, combining pagan and Christian thought in order to defend the faith. But although Van Til rejected Aquinas&#8217;s methodology, in truth his own TAG is similar.&nbsp; Both Aquinas and Van Til employed the dominant philosophies of their day in order to build an intellectual bridge to unbelievers; Aquinas and Van Til spoke with Aristotelian and Kantian accents, respectively. (137-138)</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This
is a challenging chapter for Presuppositionalists.&nbsp; It exposes tensions on issues like the use of
evidence and the claims made for the TAG between Van Tillians (140-141);
between Knudsen and Van Til; (144) and between Van Til&#8217;s two main interpreters
Frame and Bahnsen. (136-137)&nbsp; The exposure
of such divergences is serious for Presuppositionalism. It certainly raises
interesting and important issues that require resolution. At the same time the
penetrating power of this chapter&#8217;s critique is limited by the fact that on
these issues Presuppositionalism is a moving target. Or perhaps it would be
better to say that it presents several different targets!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Chapter
7, &#8220;Dualisms,&#8221; is of less interest to this reviewer.&nbsp; The reason is, as Fesko himself says, &#8220;This
chapter &#8230; primarily interacts with the claims of Herman Dooyeweerd.&#8221; (8) The
link here with Van Til and mainstream Presuppositionalism is tenuous. Still Fesko
seeks to make the connection through the association of Van Til with Dutch
Neo-Calvinism (161-164).&nbsp; At any rate,
this chapter is of less significance to me because Dooyeweerd and his
philosophy is only distantly related to Van Til, difficult to the point of incomprehensibility,
and criticized by Cornelius Van Til himself.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Fesko
reaches the conclusion of his volume in Chapter 8, &#8220;The Book of Nature and
Apologetics.&#8221;&nbsp; Reading this chapter was
an unusual experience.&nbsp; I began the
chapter saying &#8220;yes, yes, and yes.&#8221; (195-206) I closed my reading of it by
saying &#8220;no, no, and no.&#8221;&nbsp; (206-219) How
and why did my response change so drastically?&nbsp;
I think the reason is that in the first part of the chapter Fesko simply
expounds the nature and the contours of a biblical and covenantal epistemology,
but in the second he critiques Presuppositionalism.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The
exposition of what Fesko calls &#8220;starting point, the necessary commitments for a
biblical apologetic methodology&#8221; and &#8220;the nature of epistemology &#8230; within the
framework of classic covenant theology: the covenants of redemption, works, and
grace&#8221; and &#8220;the two goals of a covenant epistemology, namely, love and
eschatology&#8221; is one of the best parts of the book. (194) I worried a little
about how closely Fesko related the covenant to creation.&nbsp; I believe there is an important and
confessional distinction between creation and the covenant. Cf. the Westminster
Confession of Faith chapter 7, paragraph 1.&nbsp;
The covenant was technically an addition to creation, but I can live
with Fesko&#8217;s statement of this because teleologically creation was for the
covenant and intended as the theatre of special revelation (as Calvin avers).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Fesko
began to lose and frustrate me when he began to critique Van Til and
Presuppositionalism on the basis of this epistemology.&nbsp; Once more I felt that there was a drastic misunderstanding
of Presuppositionalism in play here.&nbsp;
Fesko clearly has Presuppositionalism and Van Til in mind when he says,
&#8220;Apologetically, this means that believers can present the gospel in
conjunction with rational arguments and evidence and know that believers can
intellectually receive and comprehend the message.&#8221; (212)&nbsp; Whoever thought otherwise?&nbsp; Certainly not Van Til who teaches that
unbelievers &#8220;get it&#8221; very well!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>The most depraved of men cannot wholly escape the voice of God.&nbsp; Their greatest wickedness is meaningless except upon the assumption that they have sinned against the authority of God.&nbsp; Thoughts and deeds of utmost perversity are themselves revelational, that is, in their very abnormality.&nbsp; The natural man accuses or else excuses himself only because his own utterly depraved consciousness continues to point back to the original natural state of affairs.&nbsp; The prodigal son can never forget the father&#8217;s voice.&nbsp; It is the albatross forever about his neck.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But
on this point this review must next turn to an evaluation of Fesko&#8217;s important
book.<br></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a><em>The Infallible Word</em> (Philipsburg, NJ: Presbyterian and
Reformed, 1978) Cornelius Van Til, &#8220;Nature and Scripture,&#8221; 274-75.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthurs Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-3-of-4/">J. V. Feskos Reforming ApologeticsRetrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the FaithA Critical Review (3 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-3-of-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
