<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Soteriology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/soteriology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 13:48:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Soteriology | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>A Critical Review of Donald Macleod&#8217;s &#8220;The Person of Christ&#8221;</title>
		<link>/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/</link>
					<comments>/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 13:48:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ben Carlson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donald Macleod]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Person of Christ]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7656</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Introduction Do the ancient creeds of Nicea and Chalcedon accurately describe the person of Christ? Is He truly, very God and very man as these documents teach? Donald Macleod, principal and professor of systematic theology at the Free Church of Scotland College in Edinburgh, Scotland, defends the reliability of these creeds against the onslaught of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/">A Critical Review of Donald Macleod&#8217;s &#8220;The Person of Christ&#8221;</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Introduction</span></strong></p>
<p>Do the ancient creeds of Nicea and Chalcedon accurately describe the person of Christ? Is He truly, very God and very man as these documents teach? Donald Macleod, principal and professor of systematic theology at the Free Church of Scotland College in Edinburgh, Scotland, defends the reliability of these creeds against the onslaught of higher criticism in his book <em>The Person of Christ</em>. Macleod states, “This book…reflects my belief that the great creeds, far from betraying the gospels, faithfully encapsulate their central concern to portray Jesus as the incarnate Son of God” (15). Concerning his approach, Macleod begins his treatment of Christology with one that is &#8220;from above&#8221; and not &#8220;from below.&#8221; As he states himself, &#8220;The New Testament, almost unanimously, presents us with a Christology from above. It starts from the side of his deity, not from that of his humanity&#8221; (22). Part one, then, covers the deity of Christ while part two covers His humanity.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Summary</span></strong></p>
<p>Chapter one deals with the meaning and defense of the virgin birth. Macleod shows how the virgin birth is a miraculous sign that points to the supernatural nature of Christ and the gospel message, the judgment on sinful man, and a new humanity. It also serves to teach us about the divine sonship of Christ, His sinlessness, and the positive roles of the Holy Spirit and Mary. In chapter two, Macleod moves backward one logical step from the virgin birth to the pre-existence of Christ. The Gospel of John, the Epistle to the Hebrews, the Pauline corpus of writings, and parts of the synoptic Gospels provide enough evidence for even the skeptic to conclude that Jesus possessed a self-consciousness prior to His being sent into the world by the Father. But can Christ’s pre-existence be affirmed apart from His deity? Macleod says no: “no formal distinction can be drawn between deity and pre-existence” (57)…A person who was divine could not but be pre-existent. His godhead proved that he could not have come into being in 4 BC” (70). Chapter three presents the reader with a necessary implication of Christ’s pre-existence: His divine sonship. Macleod begins by explaining the term <em>monogenes hyios </em>as it relates to Christ: it refers to the uniqueness, and not the begottenness, of Jesus. He then goes on to deny any ontological subordinationism in the Son and affirms the co-equalness of the Son with the Father. He does, however, affirm economical subordination as it came to be in the covenant of redemption. Chapter four deals with the reliability of the church&#8217;s witness to the deity of Christ. Macleod argues that the Jesus of history is the Christ of faith. The written testimonies of the early church concerning Jesus are both genuine and reliable, but only the testimony of the Holy Spirit will persuade men of their divine authenticity. Macleod comments, &#8220;Scholarship can give a substantial vindication of the facts, but it cannot enable us to see compelling beauty in the face of Jesus. That is possible only when God the Father, through the Holy Spirit, shares with us his own view of his Son&#8221; (118). Chapter five is concerned with explaining the theology of and circumstances surrounding the Nicean Creed&#8217;s famous declaration that &#8220;Christ, as the Son of God, was <em>homoousios</em> (consubstantial) with the Father&#8221; (121). The Arian heresy, which denied Jesus&#8217; self-existence, eternity, and co-equality with God the Father, was the reason for such a statement to be drawn at the Council of Nicea in 325 AD. If Christ was not God, Christianity was a failed and doomed religion. Macleod then goes on to define the contours of the Son&#8217;s consubstantiality with the Father: He is a distinct person, He was eternally begotten of the very essence of the Father (what he terms &#8216;eternal sonship&#8217;), and He was eternally generated, not originated or made. Macleod next explains that <em>homoousios</em> means that the Father and Son are &#8220;one being and one God&#8221; or &#8220;identically one and the same substance&#8221; (139), defines <em>perichoresis</em> in this manner: &#8220;within the one godhead the three persons co-inhere in each other and interpenetrate each other&#8221; (140), argues that <em>filioque</em> should be understood as the procession of the Spirit from the Father and Son relationally, not causally, and affirms that the essence of the Son and the Spirit is <em>autotheos</em> and not subordinate to the Father&#8217;s in any way.</p>
<p>Chapter six begins part two of the book, which is entitled “Very God, Very Man”—Chalcedon &amp; Beyond. In this chapter he covers the incarnation. The heresies of Docetism and Apollinarianism drove the early church to formulate its doctrine of the incarnation around two premises: “Christ took a true human body and he took a reasonable human soul” (161). In other words, Christ partook of all human attributes, including ignorance and emotions, save sin alone in order to save us “from alongside us” (180). Chapter seven addresses the relationship of Christ’s two natures in the Council of Chalcedon. The heresies of Nestorianism and Eutychianism were combatted with the formulation of the hypostatic union of Christ’s two natures. This formula encapsulates three truths: “that Christ is one person; that the union between his two natures arises from the fact that they both belong to one and the same person; and that this one person, the Son of God, is the Agent behind all of the Lord’s actions, the Speaker of all his utterances and the Subject of all his experiences” (189). Macleod ends with an extended discussion of the <em>communication idiomatum </em>in the person of Christ and the <em>enhypostasia </em>of His human nature. Chapter eight deals with the concept of <em>kenosis</em>. In this act of making Himself nothing, Christ did not abandon, retract, or transpose certain attributes of His deity to assume humanity but instead the pre-incarnate Christ, who “occupied a position of the highest imaginable eminence” (212), did not insist on His rights to be served, worshipped, and glorified but voluntarily veiled His glory and made Himself nothing (or vanity) by taking upon Himself a human nature and dying under the curse and wrath of God. Chapter nine touches on the inherent and actual sinlessness of Christ. It is to be remembered that He assumed a perfect human nature, not a fallen one, when He entered into a state of humiliation. Finally, chapter ten presents several modern approaches to the doctrine of Christ divorced from the Chalcedonian Creed. Denials of the incarnation, resurrection, and uniqueness of Christ from different nineteenth and twentieth-century theologians are discussed and dismantled by Macleod.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Critique</span></strong></p>
<p>            Macleod certainly interacts with the entire spectrum of Christological issues and their differing viewpoints in this book. The sheer breadth of the theologians he quotes from and is conversant with is quite impressive. In other words, Macleod has done his homework! But if his goal was to uphold the creeds of the past, I think he was close but missed the bullseye of his target. As stated in the introduction of this paper, Macleod declares his belief that the Nicaean and Chalcedonian creeds “faithfully encapsulate [the gospels’] central concern to portray Jesus as the incarnate Son of God” (15). It is true that throughout this book Macleod constantly battles against those who reject these ancient confessions of faith in order to vindicate them as true summaries of what the Bible teaches concerning the person of Christ. I heartily commend him for entering into the arena of higher criticism and coming out the victor. But in the process, he does seem to modify or even reinterpret certain concepts and terms in these creeds to fit his own theological system. Nowhere is this illustrated more clearly than with Macleod&#8217;s understanding of the Son&#8217;s begottenness.</p>
<p>Macleod is quite clear about rejecting the historical and traditional meaning of the begottenness of Christ. Though he affirms His eternal sonship and begottenness, Macleod takes a modern approach to understanding the term <em>monogenes</em>. He states, “But what is that concept? There is little doubt that <em>monogenes</em> expresses the uniqueness of Jesus. He is the only one of his kind” (72). He goes on to ask,</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">But is there a uniqueness more fundamental than that the Son is uniquely loved? Is he uniquely loved because there is something either in the origin of his existence or in the mode of his existence that is unique? It is extremely doubtful where <em>monogenes</em> by itself refers to uniqueness of origin (73).</span></p></blockquote>
<p>He also states that <em>monogenes </em>carries with it little conceptual content: “It is doubtful that <em>begotten</em> adds anything to <em>Son</em>, apart from laying down that he is Son in a unique way” (73). In another place he states,</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The problem, as we have seen, is that although we know that the Son is distinguished by the fact that he is begotten, we know little or nothing of what divine begottenness is. It carries us little beyond, &#8216;Is the Son of&#8217;&#8230;The truth is, we are lost. We know that the Son is distinguished by the fact that he is begotten, but we do not know what <em>begotten</em> is&#8221; (137).</span></p></blockquote>
<p>He then concludes,</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">The following conclusions, then, seem safe. First, <em>monogenes</em> says nothing about origins because the Son is unoriginated. Secondly, it emphasizes the uniqueness of Jesus’ sonship. Thirdly, this uniqueness consists in four things: he is an object of special love, he is the Father’s equal, he is the Father’s likeness and he is an eternal, not an adopted, Son (74).</span></p></blockquote>
<p>Here are my issues with such an approach:</p>
<p>(1) This sort of agnosticism to the term <em>mongenes </em>is absolutely unnecessary. Certainly, if begotten only means “unique” I can understand the mountainous problems Macleod faces. All one would know is that the Son is unique from the Father, but the content of that uniqueness remains shrouded in mystery and only slightly revealed in God&#8217;s plan of redemption. If begottenness is stripped of derivation, causation, or origination, this term really has no meaning at all! In fact, &#8220;Son&#8221; loses all its practical meaning as well! We do, however, know what this term means if we don&#8217;t limit its definition to merely &#8220;unique&#8221; but include the necessary ideas of generation and subordination. Etymologically, there is a good case to be made that <em>monogenes </em>is related to <em>gennao </em>and not <em>ginomai</em>. Although he asserts the opposite, he is mistaken. The King James Version does not “probably rest on a misapprehension” (73) but on the correct interpretation of the word. Sadly, he even goes so far as to quote Raymond Brown, avowed critic of the orthodox faith, to back up his claim! If Macleod would simply allow begottenness to retain its etymological and historical meaning, the derivation and subordination of the Son to the Father would serve as a key distinction between the two divine persons. Begottenness then would supply us with rich content that helps explain the personal distinctions inherent in the immanent Trinity.</p>
<p>(2) Macleod seems to think that the Patristic Fathers believed in an ontological subordination of the Son to the Father which tainted not only their writings but also their creeds. He says that “Christian orthodoxy has been only too willing to allow a subordinationist strain to remain in its own confession, just beside the insistence on Jesus’ deity” (76). He quotes Chrysostom as saying, “If anyone say that the Father is greater, inasmuch as he is the cause of the Son, we will not contradict this.” But Chrysostom was not saying this about the Son’s essence but His person! There is a whole world of difference between saying that the Father is greater than the Son according to His subsistence rather than according to His being!</p>
<p>(3) Though Macleod believes the Greek fathers were wrong to translate <em>monogenes </em>as “only-begotten,” he later criticizes the modern-day theologian Hugh Montefiore for not opting to translate <em>apaugasma </em>as “effulgence” like the Greek fathers did by stating, “The Greek fathers (who, after all, spoke the language) were surely in a better position to evaluate such grammatical niceties” (79). But didn’t virtually all the Greek fathers translate <em>monogenes </em>as only-begotten? If so, Macleod may benefit from a taste of his own medicine!</p>
<p>(4) At times Macleod seems to oppose the very thesis he sets out to defend. His stance is this: “If the Son and the Spirit are God then they are unoriginate (<em>agenetos</em>), that neither generation nor procession can mean origination and hence that all talk of derivation and causation are inappropriate (145).” But he admits that the general position of Patristic theology (and by implication the express teaching of the ancient creeds of Nicaea and Chalcedon) was that the eternal generation of the Son implied derivation, and therefore some sort of subordination (76). Isn’t Macleod contradicting and even arguing against his own claim that these documents “faithfully encapsulate [the gospels’] central concern to portray Jesus as the incarnate Son of God” (15) when he unwittingly charges them with incorrect views on the Son’s generation? The fact is, talk of derivation and causation are in these creeds, and if Macleod is consistent, he would have to call them (or at least parts of them) “inappropriate” instead of “faithful” to the teaching of the New Testament, thereby undermining his entire thesis and siding with the Enlightenment instead of the early church.</p>
<p>(5) It seems to me that Macleod functions as if the categories of subordination are only economical and ontological. It appears that he entirely bypasses the category of subordination of hypostases/modes of subsistences. This is seen when he fails to distinguish between the persons of the Trinity and the being of the Trinity as he denies generation and subordinationism. He claims that since Christ is the eternal Son He has no origin. That of course is true concerning the Son of God’s essence. He is <em>homousias </em>with the Father and <em>autotheos</em>. But what about the Son’s <em>hypostasis</em>? Is his personal subsistence without origin as well? Macleod says nothing. He has no issue with affirming an economical subordination of the Son to the Father brought about in the <em>pactum salutis </em>but goes no further than that. He explicitly states this when he says, “New Testament subordinationism is federal, not ontological” (78). But what about hypostatical? Again, this category seems to be missing from Macleod’s understanding.</p>
<p>(6) Macleod believes the language of derivation and origination &#8220;is fatal to the co-equal deity of the Son&#8221; (144). He thinks it creates &#8220;a totally asymmetrical Trinity in which the Father held the essence underived, while the Son and Spirit held it as derived from him&#8221; (144). He accuses John of Damascus and Augustine of enmeshing themselves &#8220;hopelessly in the language of causality&#8221; (144). For him, this language was influenced more by &#8220;Origen&#8217;s subordinationism&#8221; (145) than by biblical exegesis. Any hint of causality within the godhead reeks of &#8220;tritheism&#8221; (144). Since generation and procession have nothing to do with causality, Macleod believes &#8220;there is nothing inherently shocking about&#8221; speaking of the Son proceeding from the Father and Spirit (147). In fact, the Father Himself &#8220;owes it to the Son and Spirit that he is what he is (Father) as much as they owe to him and to each other that they are what they are (respectively Spirit and Son)&#8221; (149). Although Macleod attempts to avoid the pitfall of essential subordinationism, he falls into another by erasing any distinctions within the Godhead. If causality implies tritheism, Macleod’s view implies modalism!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">Conclusion</span></strong></p>
<p>            In conclusion, Macleod’s treatment of the person of Christ is generally balanced and in line with the creedal statements of Nicea and Chalcedon. Though I disagree with him on his view of the Son’s begottenness and believe he strays from the ancient creeds at this point, his overall defense of historic Christian beliefs against the theologians of the Enlightenment assists the modern-day church in its proclamation that God descended from heaven and assumed flesh “<em>for us men and for our salvation</em>” (250).</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/ben/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2020/04/02212814/Ben-Carlson2.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/ben/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Ben Carlson</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><h3>Ben has been one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, Kentucky, since June 2017. In February 2018, he received his Master of Divinity from Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary. Ben has been married to his lovely wife Ali since September 2011. They have four children together: Liam, Luther, Cosette, and Maezie. In his spare time, Ben enjoys playing with his kids, coaching, doing yard work, and Friday family nights.</h3>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/">A Critical Review of Donald Macleod&#8217;s &#8220;The Person of Christ&#8221;</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-critical-review-of-donald-macleods-the-person-of-christ/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growth in Grace 18 — Summary Applications</title>
		<link>/growth-in-grace-18/</link>
					<comments>/growth-in-grace-18/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2014 15:00:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sanctification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Works]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1653</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In this series I have been writing about what I called the Bible&#8217;s most systematic and detailed call to growth in grace.&#160; It is found in 2 Peter 1:5-7,&#160; &#8220;Now for this very reason also, applying all diligence, in your faith supply moral excellence, and in your moral excellence, knowledge,&#160; 6 and in your knowledge, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-18/">Growth in Grace 18 — Summary Applications</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this series I have been writing about what I called the Bible&#8217;s most systematic and detailed call to growth in grace.&nbsp; It is found in 2 Peter 1:5-7,&nbsp; &#8220;Now for this very reason also, applying all diligence, in your faith supply moral excellence, and in your moral excellence, knowledge,&nbsp; 6 and in your knowledge, self-control, and in your self-control, perseverance, and in your perseverance, godliness,&nbsp; 7 and in your godliness, brotherly kindness, and in your brotherly kindness, love.&#8221; &nbsp;&nbsp;In this blog it is my purpose to set before you first a summary illustration and then five summary applications of these verses.</p>
<p><b>I.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Summary Illustration</b></p>
<p>I remember being quite bothered by this passage when I first began to study it.&nbsp; Here is why.&nbsp; I have told you a number of times especially early on in this series that it cannot and does not teach the building block or lego-block view of sanctification and growth in grace.&nbsp; Now I have had to say that because at first hearing the passages may sound like that to many people.&nbsp; Are we not to add or supply these graces to one another?&nbsp; This sounds like laying one brick of sanctification on top of another.&nbsp; Now we know that this building block view of growth in grace is wrong.&nbsp; Let me give you two good reasons for this.
</p>
<ul>
<li>First, this is a description of what Peter calls &#8220;growing in grace.&#8221;&nbsp; Look at 2 Peter 3:18:&nbsp; &#8220;But grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.&#8221;&nbsp; Indisputably 2 Peter 1:5-7 is Peter&#8217;s extended description of what it means to grow in grace.&nbsp; Growth is not a building block kind of thing.&nbsp; It is an organic development kind of thing.</li>
<li>Second, we know that none of these graces is genuine unless it is only in connection with the others.&nbsp; Faith is not genuine unless it is attended with moral excellence.&nbsp; Peter cannot mean to imply that at some time or for some period faith is without moral excellence.&nbsp; If that were the case, it would not be true faith.&nbsp; This is true for all of these graces.&nbsp; For instance, Paul says that if we don&#8217;t have love we are nothing and no true Christians in 1 Corinthians 13:1-3.&nbsp; &#8220;I am nothing,&#8221; he says.&nbsp; Thus, the building block image of what Peter is saying here cannot be correct.&nbsp; It would contradict everything we know about the inter-relatedness of all saving grace.</li>
</ul>
<p>After considerable thought trying to find an image or illustration which did more justice than the building block image to what Peter is saying here, the illustration that finally came to me was very helpful to me.&nbsp; I hope it is to you.&nbsp; It is drawn from the arena of plant life and better fits with the image of growth in grace with which Peter is working.</p>
<p>It is the image of wonderful flower.&nbsp; You have seen how flowers, say roses, which you may buy in the bud gradually open wider and wider revealing more and more petals within the initial bud.&nbsp; Suppose a flower in which each opening internal circle of petals was a new and splendid color.&nbsp; The initial bud might be white, but as it opened the next petals visible might blue, and then yellow, and finally at the center of it all perhaps red petals would be revealed.&nbsp; You could say that as the flower opened it was supplying the initial and external white petals with blue, yellow, and red petals.&nbsp; Thus, it is with growth in grace.&nbsp; It is not as though faith is without moral excellence, but as it opens it reveals within moral excellence.&nbsp; It is not as though moral excellence is ever truly without knowledge, but as it opens within it you see knowledge.&nbsp; It is not as though knowledge is ever without self-control, but as it opens you see self-control within the knowledge.&nbsp; I want you to think of growth in grace like this wonderful gradually opening flower.&nbsp; Love is the innermost bud, but it is contained in the faith which is the first visible grace.&nbsp; Thus what you have is an artificial and external building block structure, but a gradually unfolding organic development in which the full splendor of grace is progressively revealed in its full glory.&nbsp; So Peter is saying to the Christian grow, unfold, bloom, and reveal in your life the full splendor of the glory of the grace of Christ!&nbsp; <i>Each of my summary applications builds on the image and illustration of this beautiful flower.</i></p>
<p><em><strong>The Basis of Progressive Sanctification</strong>:&nbsp; This beautiful flower of which I have been speaking can only be opened up by the power of God&#8217;s grace!</em></p>
<p>Under this heading it is my burden to remind you and press upon you the emphasis with which Peter began this exhortation.&nbsp; It is that growth in grace is not a self-help program, but a gospel program that takes place by grace through faith.&nbsp; This is why faith is first.&nbsp; This is why nothing goes before it.&nbsp; This is the whole point of verses 1-4.&nbsp; God by His sovereign grace lays the foundation for the Christian life by giving us faith, putting us into possession of faith.&nbsp; Then it is through this faith trusting the great promises of God that we grow in grace.</p>
<p>The Christian life is not a bicycle.&nbsp; It is an automobile.&nbsp; Its power is not your spiritual muscles, but God&#8217;s sovereign grace.&nbsp;&nbsp; Its secret is not the exhausting pumping of your spiritual legs, but the pressure of faith on the accelerator of grace.&nbsp; The engine of faith running on the gasoline of grace powers the Christian life.&nbsp; This is the power plant of the Christian life.&nbsp; God purifies our hearts by faith.&nbsp; He breaks into the human heart by creating the doorway of faith and through that doorway come the resources of His sovereign grace.&nbsp; The life that we live in the flesh, then, we live by faith in the Son of God.&nbsp; We must keep on believing in the power of God&#8217;s grace to forgive and subdue our sins and keep taking that grace by the empty hand of faith.&nbsp; By faith we keep putting on the Lord Jesus Christ.&nbsp; This is Peter&#8217;s point in beginning the list with faith.&nbsp; Nothing goes before faith, because we are saved by grace through faith, and we live the Christian life by grace through faith.</p>
<p><i><b>The Danger of Spiritual Complacency (especially for mature Christians):</b>&nbsp;This beautiful flower must be continually opening throughout the Christian life!</i></p>
<p>2 Peter is written to those who have been Christians for some period of time.&nbsp; It is written to those who are viewed as established Christians.&nbsp;&nbsp; Just a few verses later than our passage in the first chapter and then again in the third chapter Peter himself makes this application to established Christians.</p>
<blockquote><p>2 Peter 1:12 Therefore, I shall always be ready to remind you of these things, even though you <i>already </i>know <i>them</i>, and have been established in the truth which is present with <i>you.</i></p>
<p>2 Peter 3:17 You therefore, beloved, knowing this beforehand, be on your guard lest, being carried away by the error of unprincipled men, you fall from your own steadfastness</p></blockquote>
<p>One of Peter&#8217;s clear purposes in this exhortation to growth in grace is, then, to warn established Christians about the danger of spiritual complacency.</p>
<p><em><strong>The Identity of Christian Priorities</strong>:&nbsp;The opening up of this beautiful flower in our lives is the true priority of the Christian life!</em></p>
<p>Another great value of this exhortation and its list of virtues is that it reminds us what the true priorities of the Christian life are.&nbsp; Every brand of Christianity is in danger of degenerating into a kind of formalism and externalism that equates Christianity with things that may be fine in themselves, but are not its true priorities.&nbsp; Thus, witnessing becomes the mark of maturity in some churches.&nbsp; In others it has been not going to movies, or super-strict Sabbath observance, or not smoking, or not dancing, or not drinking.&nbsp; In others it is a certain style of dress to which you must conform.&nbsp; In other churches the mark of Christian maturity is being active in church-work, Christian service, or Christian volunteer organizations.&nbsp; I am not commenting on the merits or demerits of any of these things.&nbsp; My simple point is that Peter&#8217;s list of virtues puts the priority on the heart, heart-graces, and spiritual virtues.&nbsp; It is possible to be perfectly conformed to all the externals I mentioned and many others, and not be growing in grace at all.</p>
<p><em><strong>The Mark of Authentic Christianity</strong>:&nbsp;If the flower of a supposed faith opens only to show a black center, what you have is not the Christian flower or genuine Christianity!</em></p>
<p>In the immediate context of this exhortation Peter lays out five reasons why growth in these graces is so important.&nbsp; The substance of each one is that these graces are the indispensable mark of genuine Christianity.&nbsp; Let me quickly summarize those reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li><i>1st Reason &#8211; Growth in grace constitutes us those who are not fruitless (v. 8).</i></li>
<li><i>2nd Reason &#8211; Growth in grace means that we are not spiritually blind (v. 9).</i></li>
<li><i>3rd Reason &#8211; Growth in grace makes certain that God has called and chosen us (v. 10a).</i></li>
<li><i>4th Reason &#8211; Growth in grace assures us that we will never apostatize (v. 10b).</i></li>
<li><i>5th Reason &#8211; Growth in grace assures us of an entrance into the eternal kingdom (v. 11).</i></li>
</ul>
<p>You see the point?&nbsp; It is the face of a monster and not a human face if it is without a chin, or a forehead, or two eyes, or a nose, or a mouth.&nbsp; Even so it is not genuine Christianity if any of these graces are simply missing.&nbsp; True Christianity may not be mature, but it is complete.&nbsp; Every false way is hated.&nbsp; Every true virtue is pursued.</p>
<p><em><strong>The Attractiveness of Growing Grace</strong>:&nbsp;Growth in grace is the secret of an attractive and useful Christian life.&nbsp; Each grace unfolds within the previous like a flower opens to display more and more of its beauty.&nbsp; Such a flower is attractive to men.&nbsp; Such growth in grace is useful and attractive as well.</em></p>
<p>Look at 2 Peter 1:8.&nbsp; Two words are used in this verse to describe the state of uselessness that is the opposite of the attractive and useful condition of the growing in Christian.</p>
<p>The professing Christian who is not supplying these graces in his faith is described as <em>useless</em>.&nbsp; The word also means <em>unprofitable, worthless, idle, or unemployed</em>.</p>
<p>The professing Christian who is not supplying these graces in his faith is also described in verse 8 as <i>unfruitful</i>.&nbsp; The word also means <i>barren, useless, or unproductive</i>.</p>
<p>If we have this wonderful flower of grace opening more and more in our lives.&nbsp; It will make us both useful and fruitful Christians.&nbsp; There is a tremendous attraction and usefulness in the Christian who is genuinely growing in grace.&nbsp;There is no contradiction between growing in grace and being truly useful and fruitful to others.&nbsp; Growth in grace is the path to true usefulness.</p>
<p>The secret to increased fruitfulness and usefulness in the kingdom of God is growth in grace.&nbsp; Do you mourn over your comparative unfruitfulness?&nbsp; Here is what you can do about it.&nbsp; Grow in grace.&nbsp; Supply these graces in your faith.&nbsp; Grow in moral excellence, knowledge, self-control, perseverance, godliness, brotherly kindness, and love.&nbsp; These qualities in you and increasing will according to Peter make you fruitful and useful.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-18/">Growth in Grace 18 — Summary Applications</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/growth-in-grace-18/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growth in Grace 17 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied with Love 2</title>
		<link>/growth-in-grace-17/</link>
					<comments>/growth-in-grace-17/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2014 14:00:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sanctification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Works]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1650</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We are considering 2 Peter 1:7 and its teaching that brotherly kindness (or love) must be supplied with love.&#160; In expounding this text I am answering three questions. I.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; What is this love? II.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Why must brotherly kindness be supplied with it? III.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Why is this love the last virtue mentioned and in no need of being [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-17/">Growth in Grace 17 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied with Love 2</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We are considering 2 Peter 1:7 and its teaching that brotherly kindness (or love) must be supplied with love.&nbsp; In expounding this text I am answering three questions.</p>
<p><i>I.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; What is this love?</i><br />
<i>II.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Why must brotherly kindness be supplied with it?</i><br />
<i>III.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Why is this love the last virtue mentioned and in no need of being supplied with another virtue?</i></p>
<p>Having answered the first of these questions in the last post, I come to the second:</p>
<p><b>II.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Why must brotherly kindness be supplied with it?</b></p>
<p>We have observed again and again that the reason Peter follows the precise order that he does in these verses is that the previous grace or virtue has a deformed twin with the same name.&nbsp; Faith un-supplied with moral excellence is the faith of demons.&nbsp; True faith is always permeated with moral excellence.&nbsp; Now what deformity does brotherly kindness turn into without love?&nbsp; In other words, what counterfeit with the name of brotherly love&#8212;that some people call brotherly love&#8212;is marked by the fact that it is empty and devoid and un-supplied with universal benevolence?&nbsp; It turns into the kind of exclusivistic preference for our own kind which is manifested in prejudice and racism.&nbsp; It is this kind of racial preference and prejudice and hatred which made the Jews reject the Gentiles as unworthy of any love or concern.</p>
<p>Thus, even brotherly kindness is capable of being perverted and being turned into an exclusivistic preference for those who are like us. It is the need for supplying brotherly kindness with love which was in Jesus&#8217; mind when he exhorted his disciples to love their enemies (Matt. 5:43-48).&nbsp; The Jews provide the example of those who claimed to love the brethren, but were devoid of this universal benevolence.&nbsp; They even perverted the Old Testament Scriptures in favor of their spiritual deformity.
</p>
<blockquote><p>Matthew 5:43 &#8220;You have heard that it was said, &#8216;YOU SHALL LOVE YOUR NEIGHBOR, and hate your enemy.&#8217; 44 &#8220;But I say to you, love your enemies, and pray for those who persecute you 45 in order that you may be sons of your Father who is in heaven; for He causes His sun to rise on <i>the </i>evil and <i>the </i>good, and sends rain on <i>the </i>righteous and <i>the </i>unrighteous. 46 &#8220;For if you love those who love you, what reward have you? Do not even the tax-gatherers do the same? 47 &#8220;And if you greet your brothers only, what do you do more <i>than others</i>? Do not even the Gentiles do the same? 48 &#8220;Therefore you are to be perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>Any so-called brotherly love that does not overflow in a spirit of genuine good will towards its enemies and towards those outside its little spiritual circle is counterfeit.&nbsp; The true grace of brotherly kindness overflows in the grace of universal benevolence.</p>
<p><b>III.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Why is this love the last virtue mentioned and in no need of being supplied with another virtue?</b></p>
<p>The peculiar thing about love in this list of virtues is that it is the last one.&nbsp; This is significant because all the other virtues Peter is careful to say must be supplied with some balancing and completing grace.&nbsp; Not so love!&nbsp; Love is not completed or supplied by any further grace.&nbsp; Love is the end and goal.&nbsp; The reason is that love is the essence of Christian maturity.&nbsp; When love is reached, the finish line is crossed.&nbsp; If we are familiar with the New Testament, it will not surprise us that with love the goal is attained.&nbsp; There are at least three other passages that speak of love as the goal and perfection and fulfillment of Christian grace.</p>
<blockquote><p>Colossians 3:14 And beyond all these things <i>put on </i>love, which is <i>the perfect bond of unity</i> <b>(literally, the bond of perfection or completeness)</b>.</p>
<p>Romans 13:8 Owe nothing to anyone except to love one another; for he who loves his neighbor has fulfilled <i>the </i>law. 9 For this, &#8220;YOU SHALL NOT COMMIT ADULTERY, YOU SHALL NOT MURDER, YOU SHALL NOT STEAL, YOU SHALL NOT COVET,&#8221; and if there is any other commandment, it is summed up in this saying, &#8220;YOU SHALL LOVE YOUR NEIGHBOR AS YOURSELF.&#8221; 10 Love does no wrong to a neighbor; <i>love therefore is the fulfillment of the law.</i></p>
<p>1 Timothy 1:5 But <i>the goal of our instruction is love</i> from a pure heart and a good conscience and a sincere faith.</p></blockquote>
<p>Has the goal of the gospel been achieved in you? You love those who are like you and perhaps many of them are Christians.&nbsp; That is not bad.&nbsp; But the farthest end of the gospel is not fulfilled in this.&nbsp; The farthest end of the gospel is only attained in universal benevolence or love.&nbsp; True brotherly kindness will overflow in a desire for the welfare and blessing of all men.&nbsp; In this the heart of God possesses our hearts and we become perfect like our Father in heaven is perfect.</p>
<p>We have here a wonderful magnifying glass with which to examine ourselves.&nbsp; It is so easy to justify ourselves in arguments with our spouses and in the breakdown of marital relationships.&nbsp; A simple lack of benevolent love is so often the problem.&nbsp; We cannot see our own sinfulness.&nbsp; We are focused on how unlovely and unloving our mate is being. But even if this is the case, you still must look at your own attitudes and conduct under the magnifying glass of the love we are talking about this morning&#8212;universal benevolence!&nbsp; Do you see how your words, conduct, and behavior are lacking in this simple love of sheer good will which does not depend on the other person&#8217;s character or conduct?&nbsp; Rebuke yourself and repent and ask forgiveness through the blood of Christ and confess your sin of a lack of love to your spouse or friend or child.&nbsp; Only then will you put the relationship in question on the road to recovery.</p>
<p>A heart for the evangelism of the lost is rooted in this love of universal benevolence.&nbsp; A lack of heart for evangelism is a dreadful manifestation of the lack of this love.&nbsp; How in your life is such love manifesting itself? How are you helping to forward the church&#8217;s fulfillment of the Great Commission?</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-17/">Growth in Grace 17 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied with Love 2</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/growth-in-grace-17/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growth in Grace 16 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied with Love</title>
		<link>/growth-in-grace-16/</link>
					<comments>/growth-in-grace-16/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2014 14:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sanctification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Works]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1648</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The old popular song, you know who sang it, goes like this: “All you need is love, All you need is love, All you need is love, love, Love is all you need.”  Sadly, the generation which grew up with these lyrics has shown that it actually understands so little about love.  This alone should [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-16/">Growth in Grace 16 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied with Love</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The old popular song, you know who sang it, goes like this: “All you need is love, All you need is love, All you need is love, love, Love is all you need.”<i>  </i>Sadly, the generation which grew up with these lyrics has shown that it actually understands so little about love.  This alone should attract our intention to what the Bible teaches about this whole matter of love.  This especially is true because in the passage which we have been studying two kinds of love are contrasted.  Please consider 2 Peter 1:7 and its teaching that brotherly kindness (or love) must be supplied with love.  In expounding this text I want to ask, answer, and apply three questions.  The three questions are …</p>
<p><i>I.       What is this love?</i><br />
<i>II.      Why must brotherly kindness be supplied with it?</i><br />
<i>III.     Why is this love the last virtue mentioned and in no need of being supplied with another virtue?</i></p>
<p><b>I. What is this love?</b></p>
<p>The word used here is the famous Greek word, <em>agape</em>.  Everyone who has been a  Bible-believing Christian for any amount of time has probably heard some preacher or other refer to God’s agape love.  Of course, in our text it is not God’s love in itself that is in view, but a love that is a grace found in the heart and lives of Christians.  I will argue later that there is no more important grace than this one.  I will do so under five D’s.</p>
<p>A. Its Distinction</p>
<p>This love is clearly distinguished by Peter from brotherly love or kindness.  The previous grace is translated by the NASB, brotherly kindness.  But if you look at the word in the original, it is literally, brotherly love.  But the word for love used in this word is different than the one we have been studying.  Remember it is <i>Philadelphia</i>. In <i>philadelphia</i> the <i>phil</i> part is from a Greek word which also means love, but it is not the word we are studying this morning, agape.  Agape is to be supplied into brotherly love and, therefore, must be different than brotherly love or kindness.  A different word is used, and a different concept is in view.   John Brown states the distinction of this love from the previous love when he says, <i>Brotherly kindness is to be the social character of the Christian in reference to the church&#8211;…love, in reference to the world.</i>  It is not love for the brethren, but a love that includes the whole world that is here in view.</p>
<p>B. Its Demand</p>
<p>This love is demanded by the express and fundamental command of God.  Many times the Creator requires that we love our <i>neighbor</i> and not just our <i>brother</i>.  This command is presented as one of the basic requirements of the law of God.</p>
<blockquote><p>Leviticus 19:18 &#8216;You shall not take vengeance, nor bear any grudge against the sons of your people, but you shall love your neighbor as yourself; I am the LORD.</p>
<p>Matthew 22:35 And one of them, a lawyer, asked Him <i>a question, </i>testing Him, 36 &#8220;Teacher, which is the great commandment in the Law?&#8221; 37 And He said to him, &#8220;&#8216;YOU SHALL LOVE THE LORD YOUR GOD WITH ALL YOUR HEART, AND WITH ALL YOUR SOUL, AND WITH ALL YOUR MIND.&#8217; 38 &#8220;This is the great and foremost commandment. 39 &#8220;The second is like it, &#8216;YOU SHALL LOVE YOUR NEIGHBOR AS YOURSELF.&#8217; 40 &#8220;On these two commandments depend the whole Law and the Prophets.&#8221;</p>
<p>Luke 10:29 But wishing to justify himself, he said to Jesus, &#8220;And who is my neighbor?&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>The biblical answer to the question, Who is my neighbor? Is the one we teach our children in their catechism:  <i>All my fellow men are my neighbors.</i>  We are to love our fellow men because they are made in the image of God and bear His likeness.  One of the most interesting passages in the Bible with which to illustrate this is Genesis 9:1-6.   The very theme of this passage is that God loves people.  This is why He commands that the earth be filled with people by procreation.  This is why He makes provision for people to be fed by giving them both plants and animals to eat.  This is why He institutes the death penalty for those who kill people.  The whole Noahic Covenant teaches plainly that God loves people, and the Noahic Covenant tells us why God loves people.  He loves people because they are made in the image of God (Gen. 9:6).  It is important to realize that people are still made in the image of God in a fallen world.  Speaking of fallen and sinful human beings God commands that they not be murdered because they are made in the image of God.  Even fallen human beings are made in the image of God and are to be loved because of it.  <i>Anything that cheapens human life is contrary to one of the most basic commands of the Bible. </i></p>
<p>C. The Definition</p>
<p>So far we have talked about the distinction of this love as love for the whole world of men and not just for Christian brothers.  We have also talked about the fact that this love is demanded by God simply because men are made in the image of God.  Now we must ask, <i>What exactly is this love?</i>  How should this love be defined?</p>
<p>Here again we must note that this love is contrasted with brotherly kindness.  The nature of brotherly love, as I said last week, is that it is rooted in the fact that I am a Christian brother and the one I am loving is a Christian brother.  Because we are both born again, we love each other.  Thus, this brotherly love has its basis in who and what the other person is.  It is a love of delight that finds something spiritually worthy of love in the other person.</p>
<p>Now the love to be supplied in this brotherly kindness is according to Peter something different.  This love may be defined as good-will, a desire for the good and happiness of the other person, no matter what they are.  A philosopher or theologian might call it <i>universal benevolence</i>.  In the church we speak of giving a person benevolence.  We mean that we are going to give them some charity.  Benevolence or charity is not given to someone because they earned it.  Benevolence is not pay.  It is charity.  Now this love of which Peter is speaking is <i>universal benevolence</i>.  It is love shown to men just because they are men and no matter what their spiritual or moral character might be.  <i>It is not a love of delight.  It is a love of benevolence.</i>  These are two different kinds of love. And we learn, thus, from 2 Peter 1:5-7 that there are two different kinds of love.</p>
<p>Let me illustrate this distinction to you.  Suppose you and your wife volunteer once a week at one of the institutions which feeds and houses druggies and drunks.  Now suppose you and your wife wanted to spend a relaxing evening of fellowship with friends.  Who would you choose to spend it with?  Would you go down to that local half-way house and spend your evening talking with criminals and druggies?  No?  You would prefer to spend it with Christian brethren.  Well, what’s your problem?  Don’t you love the people in that half-way house?  Well, you do, and your life proves you do, but there is a difference between the love of delight you have for your Christian friends and the love of benevolence you have for the inhabitants of the local half-way house.</p>
<p>The Bible, in fact, teaches that we are not to love the world with a love of delight, even though we are to love the world with a love of benevolence.  Recall 1 John 2:15: “Do not love the world, nor the things in the world. If anyone loves the world, the love of the Father is not in him.”  We are to have a love of delight for our brethren.  We are not to have a love of spiritual delight for the world.  For the world we are to feel good will and benevolence, but not delight.  We are to wish for their happiness.  We are to pity them, but we are not to delight in them spiritually.  It is a love of benevolence for all mankind of which Peter is speaking in our text.</p>
<p>D. Its Demonstration</p>
<p>How is such a love of benevolence manifested or demonstrated?  Negatively, it is manifested by doing no injury to our fellow men.  Romans 13:10 teaches:  “Love does no wrong to a neighbor; love therefore is the fulfillment of <i>the</i> law.”  Positively, love is demonstrated when we relieve the needs and especially the spiritual needs of our fellow men.</p>
<p>Matthew 5:44 &#8220;But I say to you, love your enemies, and pray for those who persecute you&#8221;</p>
<p>Luke 6:35 &#8220;But love your enemies, and do good, and lend, expecting nothing in return; and your reward will be great, and you will be sons of the Most High; for He Himself is kind to ungrateful and evil <i>men.</i>&#8221;</p>
<p>It is not just to our fellow believers that we are to be benevolent.  There is to be a benevolent place in our heart for any of our fellow men that we see in need.  Galatians 6:10 makes this clear:  <i>So then, while we have opportunity, let us do good to all men, and especially to those who are of the household of the faith.</i></p>
<p>E. Its Divinity</p>
<p>It is important to realize that in calling us to this love Peter is asking us to be like God.  There is something peculiarly divine about universal benevolence.  God’s love for men is sincere and universal.  Listen to the words of John Brown on this subject:</p>
<blockquote><p>As to the characteristic qualities of this love, they may all be described in one word.  This love to the world of mankind, should resemble God’s.  It should be sincere and universal.  God does not, cannot love the world, as he loves His own.  Christians do not, cannot, love the world as they love the brotherhood.  But God does love the world; He loves man as man; His love is philanthropy—the love of man; and so should be the Christians.  That man is wicked, is no reason that I should not love him: when men were sinners, Christ, God’s Son, died for them.  He makes His sun to shine, and His rain to fall, on the unthankful and evil.  It is no reason why I should not love a man, that he is my enemy: when men were enemies, they were reconciled to God through the death of His son.  God’s love to the world is an <i>active</i> love.  What human being does not enjoy innumerable fruits of His love?  And this is the most remarkable fruit of His love—He gave His only-begotten Son to suffer and die, that <i>any</i> man—<i>every</i> man, however guilty and depraved, believing in Him, “might not perish but have everlasting life.”  Our love to man should be fruitful love , and one of its chief fruits should be the carrying to all men the soul-saving truth—that God loves the world, and that whosoever believes in His Son who died, the just in the room of the unjust, shall not perish.  God’s love to the world is <i>patient, long-suffering </i>love.  Had it been otherwise, where would our guilty race have been?—Not in the land of the living, not in the place of hope.  “It is of the Lord’s mercies that we are not consumed, because His compassions fail not.”  Our love to a perishing world should “suffer long and be kind;” our compassions should not fail.  No obstinacy nor ingratitude should induce us to relinquish, or even to abate, our labours of love among our guilty, depraved, perishing brethren.  They can never try us as we have tried God—we never can bear with them as He has borne with us.</p></blockquote>
<p><b>Several Applications:</b></p>
<p>First, let me apply this by way of instruction.  Confusion has reigned among some Calvinists over whether God loves everybody.  Those who deny this do not have a hard time finding texts which tell Christians not to love the world.  They do not even have a hard time finding texts which say that God does not love the ungodly.</p>
<blockquote><p>Psalm 5:5 The boastful shall not stand before Your eyes; You hate all who do iniquity.</p>
<p>Psalm 11:5  The LORD tests the righteous and the wicked, And the one who loves violence His soul hates.</p></blockquote>
<p>But these texts are not the whole of the story.  “Does God love the wicked?” is not one of those questions that can be answered in just one word.  If you say either “yes” or “no,” you are wrong.  Why?  Because there is more than one kind of love!  So both the tract that tells unconverted men that God loves them and has a wonderful plan for their life, and the tract that tells them that God hates them and has a terrible plan for their life—both of them are wrong and one-sided.  The fact is that God does not love the wicked with a love of delight, but He does love them with a love of benevolence.</p>
<p>Second, let me apply this by way of clarification.  I have said in the previous application <b>Be like God—love the unlovely!  </b>Now here I want to say <b>Be like God in the way you love the unlovely and the ungodly.</b>  Do not feel that you have to like the wicked or delight in them in order to truly love them.  I believe that sincere Christians often struggle with the command to love their ungodly enemies.  I know I did when I had to rub shoulders with some of them every day at work in Amway’s Central Warehouse in Ada, Michigan.  This distinction between a love of delight and a love of benevolence is one great help in those struggles.  You are not called to like the wicked or delight in them.  If they are ungodly, you cannot and you should not delight in them or like them.  You are called to have good will toward them.  You are called to pray for them.  You are called to greet them.  You are called to do good to them.  You are not called to delight in them!</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-16/">Growth in Grace 16 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied with Love</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/growth-in-grace-16/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growth in Grace 15 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied into Godliness 2</title>
		<link>/growth-in-grace-15/</link>
					<comments>/growth-in-grace-15/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 14:00:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sanctification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Works]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1633</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>2 Peter 1:7 commands, “and in your godliness, (supply) brotherly kindness.”  My outline is similar to that of previous posts on this passage.  We have considered: The Virtue Viewed.  Now consider The Connection Clarified. Again and again we have observed that there is a reason for the careful order that Peter observes in his list [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-15/">Growth in Grace 15 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied into Godliness 2</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>2 Peter 1:7 commands, “and in your godliness, (supply) brotherly kindness.”  My outline is similar to that of previous posts on this passage.  We have considered: <i>The Virtue Viewed</i>.  <i></i></p>
<p>Now consider <i>The Connection Clarified.</i></p>
<p>Again and again we have observed that there is a reason for the careful order that Peter observes in his list as he tells to supply one grace after another in the previously mentioned grace.  Why does brotherly kindness follow godliness?  And why is it precisely godliness into which brotherly kindness must be supplied?</p>
<p>John Brown proposes that the connection between godliness and brotherly kindness is that brotherly kindness grows out of godliness.  He says:</p>
<blockquote><p>There can be no brotherly kindness where there is no godliness.  It is by God’s becoming our spiritual Father that we become spiritual brethren.   While I am ungodly, godly men are not my brethren; I am of my father the devil, and his children are my brethren.  It is by becoming godly that I am brought into God’s family…</p></blockquote>
<p>Now all that Brown says is truth, but it is not in my opinion the truth taught in our text.  The text does not say brotherly kindness originates in godliness, but that godliness must be supplied with brotherly kindness.  It is the <i>possible deficiency</i> of godliness, not its <i>positive fruitfulness</i> that is under discussion.</p>
<p>Godliness must be supplied with brotherly kindness because too often the profession of religion, the form of godliness, has been associated with the most harsh and unfeeling attitudes towards other Christians.  May I put it this way?  Some people become so <i>godly</i> that they become inhuman.  Remember the synagogue official in Luke 13:14 who became indignant because Jesus had healed on the Sabbath?  Here was a man who certainly had the form of godliness.  He did not become what the Greek calls the synagogue ruler by being irreligious, you can be sure.   He no doubt was very dedicated to the public worship of the synagogue. No doubt he attended worship carefully, gave His tithes religiously, and was meticulous in seeing that worship was carried according to the strict traditions of the Jews. Most manifestly, he observed God’s Sabbath.</p>
<p>Remember the Pharisees’ view of Sabbath-keeping.  Their religious Sabbath-keeping had become so strict, that Jesus had to remind them of several important qualifications to the complete rest required on the Sabbath.  He reminded them that the Sabbath was made for man—not man for the Sabbath (Mark 2:27).  He reminded them that God desired compassion and not sacrifice (Matt. 12:7) in the keeping of the Sabbath.  He told them that works of necessity and mercy do not violate God’s Sabbath (Matt. 12:3, 4, 11, 12).</p>
<p>Here, then, was a man—a Pharisee—who had failed to supply in his godliness brotherly kindness.  Such godliness, such religion, is the reason James said, &#8220;This is pure and undefiled religion in the sight of our God and Father, to visit orphans and widows in their distress&#8230;&#8221; (Jas. 1:27)</p>
<p>It is the characteristic of this series of blogs with each new grace I have to qualify what I have previously.  The reason is that Peter after naming each grace tells us that it must be supplemented or supplied with another.<i>  </i>Previously, I stressed to you the importance of godliness.  I told you how empty self-control and even perseverance were if they were not the kind of self-control and perseverance permeated with godliness.  Now I have to tell you that there is a false kind of godliness or religiosity that is just as empty if it is not supplemented and supplied with brotherly love.<i> </i></p>
<p>Here we are reminded of the importance of balance in the Christian life.  I will let Lloyd-Jones speak to this matter:</p>
<blockquote><p>We see that each of these qualities adds and contributes to the others; every one has its own importance and yet each one influences the others.  We see the importance vigour, and yet we see the importance of controlling vigour by knowledge.  Every one has its own function, and yet each affects the others and therefore contributes to the whole.  In other words, what impresses me most of all about this list is its perfect balance.  There is no other life that has this balance.  There are people who are highly intellectual and very cultured, but perhaps not moral; there are others who are morally blameless, but not very intelligent; and there are those who have great will power, but somehow there is something lacking.  There is no life that shows this perfect balance but the Christian life that is depicted here.</p></blockquote>
<p>All the graces that Peter refers to in this list are marks and signs of election.  Cf. the following passage, 2 Peter 1:8-11, especially v. 10.  I believe, however, that the New Testament lays special emphasis on brotherly love as an especially helpful mark of being born of God.  We have already looked at two passages that clearly suggest this.  1 Thessalonians 4:10 and 1 Peter 1:22 closely associate coming to love the brethren with the great change that takes place when a man is truly converted to Jesus Christ.  But the greatest and most concentrated emphasis is on love for the brethren as a mark of the new birth, and it comes in 1 John.</p>
<p>Consider 1 John 3:10-14:</p>
<blockquote><p>10 By this the children of God and the children of the devil are obvious: anyone who does not practice righteousness is not of God, nor the one who does not love his brother.  11 For this is the message which you have heard from the beginning, that we should love one another;  12 not as Cain, who was of the evil one and slew his brother. And for what reason did he slay him? Because his deeds were evil, and his brother&#8217;s were righteous.  13 Do not be surprised, brethren, if the world hates you.  14 We know that we have passed out of death into life, because we love the brethren. He who does not love abides in death.</p></blockquote>
<p>Love for the brethren is a two-edged sword.  Its presence shows that we are the children of God and have come into life.  Its absence shows that we have are the children of the devil and abide in death.  Do you see the implication?  It is not that love for the brethren is a good sign of conversion, but that if we lack it we may still be Christians.  No!  Love for the brethren is an essential necessary mark of being born again.  Its absence means that we are lost.</p>
<p>Faithfulness requires me here to speak to the subject of the marks of grace.  Whenever people hear about the marks of grace or the signs that someone is really a Christian, they have a tendency to focus on those signs and practically forget everything they ought to know about the gospel of Christ.  Before, therefore, I come to press this subject; I want to take the opportunity to remind you that salvation is by grace alone.  We do nothing to earn God’s favor.  We do nothing to make God be kindly disposed towards our salvation.  Our righteousness before God by which we are justified in His sight does not consist in anything we do, and it certainly does not consist in our righteously loving our brethren.  Our righteousness is the obedience of Christ imputed to us, put to our account.  It is an alien righteousness that we did not make or earn, but a righteousness that is simply given to us.</p>
<p>The question I am addressing is not how someone can be righteous in the sight of God.  The answer to that question is by faith in Christ alone. The question I am addressing is a different.  I am addressing the question: How can I be sure that I have genuine faith in Christ?  The problem is a real one, because the Bible teaches that there is a kind of faith that is not saving.  There is a false faith that is not supplied with moral excellence and that James says is dead being by itself.  This is a reality of which the Bible speaks.  It presents a real problem for the assurance of some Christians.  Chief among those who struggle with this problem are those raised in Christian homes and who have not had a dramatic conversion experience from a life in the world to a life in Christ.  I know because I myself struggled with just such a problem of assurance as one raised in a Christian home.  The question with which someone like that may struggle is: Do I have genuine faith?  Or do I have the false faith of the devils that believe and tremble? There is no avoiding such questions.  I think it is good to face them and answer them before God with judgment day honesty.</p>
<p>The New Testament teaches that one of the most helpful things for such a person to do is to look at themselves in light of this whole matter of brotherly love or love for the brethren.  It can be hard to see if you love a God who is an unseen, but it is not so hard to see if you love God’s people.  Your relationship to God and Christ will be outwardly and tangibly and clearly reflected in your relationships with people.  In the world there are two and only two kinds of people.  There are believers and there are unbelievers.  There are the righteous and the wicked.  There are the children of God, and there are the children of the devil.  The question is simply this.  Which group do you love?  Do you gravitate to people that you look at as Christians?  Do you seek friendship and relationships among those who in your opinion are believers?  Or do you find in the secret of your heart a desire to be with those whom you know are worldly?  This is not a difficult question to answer, and it becomes more and more clear the more you become an adult.  You can tell who someone is by looking at his friends.  If he loves the brethren, he has passed from death to life.  If he loves the world, the love of the Father is not in him.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-15/">Growth in Grace 15 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied into Godliness 2</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/growth-in-grace-15/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growth in Grace 14 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied into Godliness</title>
		<link>/growth-in-grace-14/</link>
					<comments>/growth-in-grace-14/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 16:00:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sanctification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Works]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1631</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>One of the most important and practical questions that any Christian can face is: How can I know if I am a Christian?  There is a kind of spiritual instinct by which any one in earnest about his soul is intensely interested in such a question.  In our study of growth in grace, we come [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-14/">Growth in Grace 14 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied into Godliness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the most important and practical questions that any Christian can face is: <i>How can I know if I am a Christian?</i>  There is a kind of spiritual instinct by which any one in earnest about his soul is intensely interested in such a question.  In our study of growth in grace, we come to consider a virtue that is of great help in answering the question: <i>How can I know if I am a Christian?</i>  2 Peter 1:7 commands, “and in your godliness, (supply) brotherly kindness.”  My outline is similar to that of previous posts on this passage.  We will consider:</p>
<p><i>I.       The Virtue Viewed</i><br />
<i>II.     The Connection Clarified</i><br />
<i>III.   </i><i>The Distinction Displayed</i></p>
<p><b>I.                  The Virtue Viewed</b></p>
<p>A.      Its Focus</p>
<p>The NASB translates the Greek word for the virtue under discussion as <i>brotherly kindness</i>.  This is a fine translation, but it may disguise the fact that the Greek word is literally brotherly love.  We have a famous city in our country the name of which is an exact English transliteration of the Greek word used.  The birthplace of our nation is called the city of brotherly love.  It is called that because its name, Philadelphia, means that in the Greek language.  <i>Philadelphia </i>is the Greek word used in our text.</p>
<p>Now the brother in view here in 2 Peter 1:7 is our fellow Christian.  It is perfectly possible, of course, for this word, brotherly love, elsewhere in Greek literature and in the  Bible to be used of affection for our physical brothers—either our siblings or our countryman.  This is, however, clearly not how the word is used in the New Testament.  In the New Testament it is always used of love for our spiritual brothers, our fellow believers in Christ.  A simple reading of the other four texts will, I think, persuade you of this.</p>
<blockquote><p>Romans 12:10 Be devoted to one another in brotherly love; give preference to one another in honor</p>
<p>1 Thessalonians 4:9 Now as to the love of the brethren, you have no need for <i>anyone </i>to write to you, for you yourselves are taught by God to love one another</p>
<p>Hebrews 13:1 Let love of the brethren continue.</p>
<p>1 Peter 1:22 Since you have in obedience to the truth purified your souls for a sincere love of the brethren, fervently love one another from the heart</p></blockquote>
<p>Another thing that assures us that it is love for our fellow believers that is in view in this passage is that Peter distinguishes this brotherly love from love.   Brotherly affection or kindness, as we will see in future posts, is to be supplied with love.  Thus, Peter distinguishes the two.</p>
<p>Finally, love for our physical brothers is one of those things that the Bible describes as a natural affection.  In this passage, however, Peter is talking about Christian graces.  He is exhorting Christians to grow in grace.  In such a list it does not make sense for him to refer to something that is merely a natural affection and not a Christian grace.  Everything about this passage persuades us that the love in view is love for our spiritual brothers, our fellow believers in Christ.</p>
<p align="left">The media-molders of our society may talk bravely about loving everybody, but I have noticed that they have a hard time practicing what they preach when it comes to born again Christians.  Every other minority finds a special place in their affections.  It is just born again Christians that they have a hard time saying a decent word about.</p>
<p align="left">The distinctive virtue we are looking at today is just the opposite.  It has a special place in its heart exactly for born again Christians and the more consistently they act like born again Christians the more this special affection is kindled in their hearts.  The great question I am raising today has to do with whether this grace is in your heart and growing there, or whether any love you have is more like that of the world.</p>
<p>B.               Its Foundations</p>
<p align="left">This love is grounded in the fact that God has given spiritual birth to both individuals—the one loving and the one loved—and they view each other as God’s sons and their Christian brothers.  The key passage is 1 Peter 1:22, 23:  “Since you have in obedience to the truth purified your souls for a sincere love of the brethren, fervently love one another from the heart, for you have been born again not of seed which is perishable but imperishable, <i>that is, </i>through the living and abiding word of God.”</p>
<p>Here the love of the brethren is closely associated with being saved.  Strikingly, verse 22 speaks of conversion when it says that <i>in obedience to the truth you purified your souls for a sincere love of the brethren</i>.  Brotherly love is the direct result of being converted.  Verse 23 goes on to explain why we should have a fervent love for our brethren by saying <i>for you have been born again of imperishable seed</i>.  One of the great marks or results of being born again is love for the brethren.</p>
<p>This same thing is implied in 1 Thessalonians 4:9: Now<i> as to the love of the brethren, you have no need for anyone to write to you, for you yourselves are taught by God to love one another</i>.  The language of <i>taught by God</i> refers to the work of God in drawing men to come to Christ (John 6:44, 45).  Thus, Paul is saying that one of the basic results of coming to Christ is learning to love the brethren.</p>
<p>Now an understanding that these are the foundations of Christian love is crucial for understanding that brotherly love is universal <i>or catholic</i>.  In other words a unique feature of this brotherly love is that it is extended to <i>all</i> Christian brothers simply because they are Christian brothers.</p>
<p>This is a deduction from the foundations of this love.  Men are loved in and because of their identity as born again Christians.  Thus, brotherly love is love for all and only those who are born again.  Mistakes may be made in two directions with regard to this matter.  There is the mistake of sectarianism and the mistake of ecumenism.</p>
<p>There is the sectarian mistake.  Here the problem is that no one is recognized as a Christian Brother except those of my own denomination or movement.  Here we must remind ourselves that our love is for those who are born again.  It is not simply for those who share my distinctive doctrinal or practical understanding of the Bible.</p>
<p>There is the ecumenical mistake.  Here the problem is that brotherly love is extended in an unprincipled way to all that profess Christ’s name.  Brotherly love is affection for the reality and not merely for the name.  It is a love of delight for those who bear Christ’s image and show the spiritual marks of the new birth.  Yet more, brotherly love is even love for those who are most like Christ in their living and their thinking.  Thus, there are clear doctrinal and practical limits and motives to brotherly love.</p>
<p>Sectarianism and ecumenism are not the brotherly love of our text.  They do, however, often masquerade as if they are.  We must beware of both extremes.</p>
<p>C.               Its Fervency</p>
<p>There is a tremendous emphasis in the passages where this word is used in the New Testament on the fervency or zeal or intensity by which this love for the brethren should be characterized (Romans 12:10, 1 Thess. 4:10, 1 Peter 1:22).</p>
<blockquote><p>1 Peter 1:22 Since you have in obedience to the truth purified your souls for a sincere love of the brethren, <b><i>fervently</i></b> love one another from the heart</p>
<p>Romans 12:10 <b><i>Be devoted</i></b> to one another in brotherly love; give preference to one another in honor</p>
<p>1 Thessalonians 4:10 for indeed you do practice it toward all the brethren who are in all Macedonia. But we urge you, brethren, to <b><i>excel still more</i></b></p></blockquote>
<p>In these three texts the fervency of this love is emphasized in three ways:  <i>fervently, be devoted, excel still more</i> are the emphasizing words.  The word fervently comes from a word that means <i>to extend</i>.  The word devoted comes from a word used of <i>the loyalty and commitment</i> we should feel to our own family.  The word excel comes from a word that means <i>to abound or increase</i>.   Our love for the brethren should be characterized by great extent, loyal commitment, and abounding increase.</p>
<p>D.               Its Fruit</p>
<p>The Bible teaches that brotherly love will have many and various fruits.  A number of passages impress us with the biblical emphasis on the many and various kinds of fruit that the tree of brotherly love will bear.</p>
<blockquote><p>Romans 12:10 Be devoted to one another in brotherly love; give preference to one another in honor; 11 not lagging behind in diligence, fervent in spirit, serving the Lord; 12 rejoicing in hope, persevering in tribulation, devoted to prayer, 13 contributing to the needs of the saints, practicing hospitality. 14 Bless those who persecute you; bless and curse not. 15 Rejoice with those who rejoice, and weep with those who weep. 16 Be of the same mind toward one another; do not be haughty in mind, but associate with the lowly. Do not be wise in your own estimation.</p>
<p>Hebrews 13:2 Do not neglect to show hospitality to strangers, for by this some have entertained angels without knowing it. 3 Remember the prisoners, as though in prison with them, and those who are ill-treated, since you yourselves also are in the body.</p>
<p>1 Peter 3:8 To sum up, let all be harmonious, sympathetic, brotherly, kindhearted, and humble in spirit</p>
<p>1 John 3:16 We know love by this, that He laid down His life for us; and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren. 17 But whoever has the world&#8217;s goods, and beholds his brother in need and closes his heart against him, how does the love of God abide in him? 18 Little children, let us not love with word or with tongue, but in deed and truth.</p></blockquote>
<p>Let me close this post with several applicatory questions:  <i>What are the tangible expressions of this brotherly love for other believers in your life?  How can you abound still more in love for the brethren?  How can you practice the brotherly kindness which is the grace on which God will command a blessing in your church? (See Psalm 133.) </i></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-14/">Growth in Grace 14 — Brotherly Kindness Must Be Supplied into Godliness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/growth-in-grace-14/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growth in Grace 13 — Perseverance Must Be Supplied with Godliness 2</title>
		<link>/growth-in-grace-13-perseverance-must-be-supplied-with-godliness-2/</link>
					<comments>/growth-in-grace-13-perseverance-must-be-supplied-with-godliness-2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 14:00:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sanctification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Works]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1622</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The danger of Satanic counterfeiting that was in the back of Peter’s mind when he penned the passage which has occupied this blog for the last few weeks, 2 Peter 1:5-7.  In this post we continue to consider the phrase in verse 6, and (supply) in your perseverance godliness.  I am opening up this phrase [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-13-perseverance-must-be-supplied-with-godliness-2/">Growth in Grace 13 — Perseverance Must Be Supplied with Godliness 2</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The danger of Satanic counterfeiting that was in the back of Peter’s mind when he penned the passage which has occupied this blog for the last few weeks, 2 Peter 1:5-7.  In this post we continue to consider the phrase in verse 6, <i>and (supply) in your perseverance godliness</i>.  I am opening up this phrase with me under three headings:</p>
<p><i>I.               </i><i>The Virtue Viewed</i><br />
<i>II.              </i><i>The Connection Clarified</i><br />
<i>III.             </i><i>The Lessons Learned</i></p>
<p>Having seen that godliness is according to the Bible (to use Louw and Nida’s helpful definition): <i>behaviour reflecting correct religious beliefs and attitudes – ‘piety, godliness.’  </i>In this post we consider</p>
<p><b>II.      The Connection Clarified</b></p>
<p>We have said many times that there is a clear rationale for the order Peter follows here in 2 Peter 1:5-7.  Thus we now ask, What is the connection between godliness and perseverance?  What is the reason for the order of Peter?  Why in particular is it important that perseverance and before perseverance, self-control, be supplied with godliness?</p>
<p>The answer is this.  Self-control and perseverance can turn into a kind of mere dogged determination and proud moralism unless their focus is upon worshipping and rendering service to God.  This is the meaning of godliness.  There were ancient, pagan Greek philosophers who exalted self-control and doing your duty despite all the opposition and scorn of men.  The name of those philosophers is still a part of the English language.  It describes someone <i>who shows austere indifference to joy, grief, pleasure, or pain;  one who is calm and unflinching under suffering</i>.  It is the name, Stoic.  The pagan, stoic philosopher taught an ethic that exalted self-control and perseverance in the face of suffering and pain and scorn.  Some non-Christians show amazing self-control and perseverance.  Yet all of their self-control and perseverance were not the virtues to which Peter had just referred. The true Christian who is out of shape and overweight has more genuine self-control and perseverance than the pagan who has disciplined himself to run 26 mile marathons. The fact that such self-control and perseverance are the genuine fruit of the Spirit will be manifested by their being supplied with godliness.  Christian self-control and perseverance originates from and is pervaded by correct religious beliefs.  We must never allow our efforts at self-control and perseverance in the face of opposition to degenerate into something irreligious, ungodly, and proud.  While we are supplying perseverance in our self-control, we must supply in our perseverance godliness.</p>
<p>Look at it this way.   True Christianity requires that we be in a right relation both to God and man and ourselves.  Self-control describes the right relation to ourselves.  Perseverance describes the right relationship to other men.  Godliness describes the right relation to God.  Where one of these graces is lacking the other two must be counterfeit.  Where there is deficiency in one of these graces the others must be affected.</p>
<p>Lloyd-Jones helpfully articulates the connection between perseverance and godliness.</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;In other words, while you are controlling these things within, and while you are going on in the spirit of patient endurance, remember why you are doing it all; remember that it is all for the glory of God.  Self-culture must not be practised for its own sake, and the danger is to be falling back on our disciplined nature in and of itself.  But if we worship discipline we are not being godly.  There is no point in any of these things unless they are centrally related to God.  Godliness, therefore, first.  Before I think of my relationship to anybody else, I must always be certain that my main motive and ambition in life is to honour God, is to glorify God, and to tell forth His praise.&#8221; (<i>2 Peter</i>, 30)</p></blockquote>
<p>Alford adds that perseverance is not &#8220;mere brute stoical endurance, but united with God-fearing and God-trusting.&#8221; (<i>Commentary</i>, 392)</p>
<p><b>III.    The Lessons Learned</b></p>
<p><b><i>First, we learn to beware of being deceived by the counterfeit self-ism of our culture.</i></b>  Even while most Americans manifest an increasing lack of self-control and an increasing inability to stand against the peer pressure of our culture, there are those dedicated to the worship of self that preach all sorts of self-discipline and resistance to the system.  The perfect body and perfect independence are the ideals of this worship of self.  It is possible to be exercising self-control and resisting peer pressure for all the wrong reasons.  Such self-control and perseverance are no evidence of growth in grace.  You should not be happy if your diet is going great and your devotions are going into the toilet.  You should definitely not think you are growing in grace.</p>
<p><b><i>Second, we learn the priority of godliness and our relation to God.</i></b>  Lloyd-Jones said it,   G<i>odliness, therefore, first!  </i>Are you living for God?  No matter how well you seem to be doing in other areas.  No matter how successful you are.  Unless you are living for God, you are completely missing the boat.  One mark of such a life will be that God is given all the glory.  Are you characterized by constantly giving God praise for what you have been enabled to do?  For your success?  For your blessings?  Let us renew our determination to live for the glory of God and to give God the glory of our lives!</p>
<p><b><i>Third, we learn that we must rehabilitate religion in our thinking.</i></b>  Religion—godliness—is a vital part of growing in grace.  It is a vital part of Christianity.  Do not let anyone sell you a religion-less Christianity.  A religion-less Christianity is not the Christianity of the Bible.  All of life is worship.  Every day is holy.  Christianity is not a religion.  These are half-truths that are destroying American Christianity!</p>
<p>When we rehabilitate religion in our thinking, we will be able to see how very wrong the casual and informal culture is which we have imbibed.  If there really is a difference between the sacred and the secular, then we will not treat religious duty with the same kind of casual-ness and informality with which Americans treat everything else.  We will reject the lazy and slovenly approach to worship which we see in churches.  We will prepare our hearts for worship, we will try to be early for worship, because we think that religious duty is sacred and holy and to be treated with great respect.  We will practice the three P’s:  priority, preparation, and punctuality as flowing directly out of godliness.  If your reaction to my saying such things is that I am being stuffy, formal, and legalistic, let me reply that the worship culture of many churches is irreligious and profane.  Part of what it means to supply godliness in your perseverance is to purge from your life the prevailing irreligious and profane attitudes I am warning you about!</p>
<p><b><i>Fourth, you may be religious and not be saved, but if you are not religious, you will not be saved!</i></b>  Are you religious?  If you have no form of godliness, you certainly cannot have the power of godliness.  You may have the form without the power, but you cannot have the power without the form.</p>
<p><b><i>Fifth, we learn that a mark of genuine Christianity is true religion or godliness.</i></b>  Do you understand and appreciate godliness?  Are you at home in the house of God?  Are you in your element in the place of prayer?  Do you find delight in the duty of prayer?  Is there a sense in which you find it a blessing, a delight, a relief to pray?  Are you happy to give to the church and to its benevolent causes?  Do you rejoice even in the laws of God that limit your freedom?  His laws about modesty?  His laws about masculine and feminine roles?  Do you delight in the law of God in the inward man?  Yes, I know you enjoy seeing your friends when you come to church.  But the real question is, Do you enjoy drawing near to God when you come to church?</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-13-perseverance-must-be-supplied-with-godliness-2/">Growth in Grace 13 — Perseverance Must Be Supplied with Godliness 2</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/growth-in-grace-13-perseverance-must-be-supplied-with-godliness-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growth in Grace 12 — Perseverance Must Be Supplied with Godliness</title>
		<link>/growth-in-grace-12-perseverance-must-be-supplied-with-godliness/</link>
					<comments>/growth-in-grace-12-perseverance-must-be-supplied-with-godliness/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 19:00:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sanctification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Works]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1617</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Satan is the great liar and deceiver.&#160; The most effective lies always have an element of truth in them.&#160; In line with this Satan is the great counterfeiter, and you know that counterfeiting always requires something of real, substantial value to make it worthwhile.&#160; Few would bother to counterfeit some third world currency with an [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-12-perseverance-must-be-supplied-with-godliness/">Growth in Grace 12 — Perseverance Must Be Supplied with Godliness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Satan is the great liar and deceiver.&nbsp; The most effective lies always have an element of truth in them.&nbsp; In line with this Satan is the great counterfeiter, and you know that counterfeiting always requires something of real, substantial value to make it worthwhile.&nbsp; Few would bother to counterfeit some third world currency with an inflation rate of 100% per year, but many find it worthwhile to counterfeit the American Dollar.&nbsp; It is the danger of Satanic counterfeiting that was in the back of Peter&#8217;s mind when he penned the passage which has occupied this series for the last several weeks, 2 Peter 1:5-7.&nbsp; In this post we take up the phrase in verse 6, &#8220;<i>and (supply) in your perseverance godliness</i>.&#8221; &nbsp;In this phrase Peter is attempting to warn Christians against the Satanic counterfeits of perseverance and self-control by telling them that the genuine Christian virtues of perseverance and self-control are permeated by and have supplied in them the virtue of godliness.&nbsp; Self-control and perseverance barren of godliness, devoid of godliness, are Satanic counterfeits with which no Christian should rest satisfied.</p>
<p>I will consider this phrase over the next few days under three headings:</p>
<p><i>I. &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; </i><i>The Virtue Viewed</i><br />
<i>II.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i><i>The Connection Clarified</i><br />
<i>III.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </i><i>The Lessons Learned</i></p>
<p>The first thing to be considered is &#8230;</p>
<p><b>I.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The Virtue Viewed</b></p>
<p>What is this virtue or grace called in the phrase we are studying godliness? When you look at all the places in the New Testament where the word, godliness, and its various relatives occur and also at many of the places where these words occur in the Greek version of the Old Testament in use in New Testament times, the short and sweet definition of this word given by Louw and Nida seems correct.&nbsp; Here it is: <b><i>behaviour reflecting correct religious beliefs and attitudes &#8211; &#8216;piety, godliness.&#8217;&nbsp; </i></b>I want to unpack this definition in three stages.</p>
<p><b><i>First</i></b>, this virtue has to do with <b><i>religious beliefs and attitudes &#8211; &#8216;piety, godliness.&#8217;</i></b>&nbsp; In our day and age words like religion and religious and piety and pious are often said with a sneer even by Christians.&nbsp; <i>You may hear things like l am not religious.&nbsp; I am a Christian.</i>&nbsp; It would be a kind of religious slur if you called someone <i>pious</i>.&nbsp; This kind of dislike of the words, religion and piety, indicates how far we are from a biblical mindset.&nbsp; Peter in our text calls us to add religion to our perseverance, to supply piety in our endurance.&nbsp; Therefore, Christians must stop treating <i>religion</i> and <i>piety</i> like dirty words.&nbsp; Whatever the word, <i>godliness, religion, or piety</i>, meant for Peter.&nbsp; It was a virtue, not a vice.</p>
<p>Now the very idea of religion or godliness assumes a distinction.&nbsp; It assumes a distinction between what I will call the religious and the secular, the holy and the common.&nbsp; Now notice that I did not say the holy and the profane.&nbsp; Nor did I say the religious and the irreligious.&nbsp; Rather I spoke of godliness assuming a distinction between the religious and the secular, the holy and the common.&nbsp; (One definition of secular is having to do with this age or world or temporal rather than having to do with the age to come or the church or religion.)</p>
<p>All of life is, of course, to be lived for God.&nbsp; Therefore, in a certain qualified sense you may say that all of life is holy.&nbsp; There are, however, some aspects or parts of life in which we have dealings more directly with God.&nbsp; Those aspects of life are the arena of religion or godliness.&nbsp; I trust you live for God at your school or plant or business.&nbsp; I trust you are living for God on the golf course.&nbsp; But I also trust that you know the difference between the plant, the golf course, and the church.&nbsp; I trust that you live for God every day of the week.&nbsp; But I also trust that you know the difference between Monday and the Lord&#8217;s Day.&nbsp; When Peter refers to godliness and religion, he assumes the difference between the religious and the secular.</p>
<p>Look at a number of texts that use this word, godliness or religion, where this distinction is visible and even clear.</p>
<p>Romans 1:18 For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all <b><i>ungodliness</i></b> and unrighteousness of men, who suppress the truth in unrighteousness,&nbsp; <i>There is a difference between ungodliness and unrighteousness.&nbsp;&nbsp; The wrath of God is revealed against both, but unrighteousness has to do with all deviations from the requirements of God&#8217;s law.&nbsp; Ungodliness has to do particularly with violations of the first four commandments that have to do directly with our relationship to God Himself.</i></p>
<p>1 Timothy 6:5 and constant friction between men of depraved mind and deprived of the truth, who suppose that godliness is a means of gain.&nbsp; <b><i>Ask yourself the question, What is Paul saying?&nbsp; How could godliness be a means of gain?&nbsp; Clearly, Paul is talking about men using organized religion to make money. &nbsp;Godliness has to do with organized religion or religious services.</i></b></p>
<p>1 Timothy 6:11 But flee from these things, you man of God; and pursue righteousness, godliness, faith, love, perseverance <i>and </i>gentleness.&nbsp; <i>Here Paul proceeds to instruct the man of God about a number of different virtues he is to pursue.&nbsp; Of course, all of these virtues are related.&nbsp; Yet faith and love and righteousness are not the same thing.&nbsp; Even so godliness is a distinct virtue as well and has to do with observance of the ordinances and institutions of the Christian religion.</i></p>
<p>Titus 2:12 instructing us to deny ungodliness and worldly desires and to live sensibly, righteously and godly in the present age,&nbsp; <i>Twice in this text the distinctiveness of religion is clear.&nbsp; Paul distinguishes between ungodliness and worldly desires.&nbsp; The one has to do with sins of impiety related to God directly.&nbsp;&nbsp; The other has to do with a lack of self-control.&nbsp; In the last part of the verse Paul distinguishes living sensibly and righteously from living godly.&nbsp; Each refers to a distinct dimension of the Christian life.&nbsp; Even so in 2 Peter 1:6 Peter distinguishes between self-control and perseverance, on the one hand, and godliness, on the other.</i>
</p>
<p align="left">2 Peter 1:3 seeing that His divine power has granted to us everything pertaining to life and godliness, through the true knowledge of Him who called us by His own glory and excellence.&nbsp; <i>Here again Peter plainly distinguishes life in general from godliness in particular.&nbsp; God&#8217;s divine power has enabled us to live for God in the whole of life and also and especially in the religious aspect of life.</i><b></b></p>
<p>The virtue referred to in the phrase we are studying this morning has to do with <b><i>religious beliefs and attitudes &#8211; &#8216;piety, godliness.&#8217;&nbsp; First</i></b>, this virtue has to do with <b><i>religious beliefs and attitudes &#8211; &#8216;piety, godliness.&#8217;</i></b>&nbsp; <i>But &#8230;</i></p>
<p><b><i>Second</i></b>, this virtue has to do with <b><i><span style="text-decoration: underline;">correct</span> religious beliefs and attitudes &#8211; &#8216;piety, godliness.&#8217;</i></b>&nbsp; In English we have to speak of <i>true religion</i>.&nbsp; But the Greek word for religion or godliness contains within it&#8212;conveys innately&#8212;the idea of true religion.&nbsp; You don&#8217;t have to say <i>true</i> religion in Greek because the word itself says it or assumes it.&nbsp; In this way the Greek word, godliness, is slightly different than the English word, religion.&nbsp; Peter does not say supply in your perseverance genuine godliness.&nbsp; He just says, godliness, because the word conveys correct religious beliefs.&nbsp; Let me show you that this virtue has to do with <i>correct religious beliefs </i>in the rest of the Scriptures.</p>
<p>1 Timothy 3:16 And by common confession great is the mystery of godliness: He who was revealed in the flesh, Was vindicated in the Spirit, Beheld by angels, Proclaimed among the nations, Believed on in the world, Taken up in glory.&nbsp; <i>Paul does not say great is the mystery of genuine godliness or of the true religion.&nbsp; He simply says great is the mystery of godliness, because the word assumes that the religion or godliness under discussion is the true religion the genuine godliness.</i>&nbsp; Cf. also 1 Timothy 4:7-8; 6:6; Titus 1:1</p>
<p>In the <i>third</i> stage of this definition of godliness we note that godliness is <b><i><span style="text-decoration: underline;">behavior reflecting</span> correct religious beliefs and attitudes &#8211; &#8216;piety, godliness.&#8217;&nbsp; </i></b>Here we come to the heart of our study of godliness.&nbsp; For here we ask the question, What is the godliness exactly that Peter says we must supply in our perseverance and self-control?&nbsp; There are five texts in the New Testament that I think give us a very clear and full description of what behavior manifests this godliness is.</p>
<p>2 Timothy 3:5 holding to a form of godliness, although they have denied its power; and avoid such men as these.&nbsp; <i>Here Paul teaches that there is a correct, outward form of true religion that even some who are strangers to the power of godliness may exhibit.&nbsp; Clearly, a merely external form of true religion is no evidence of genuine conversion.&nbsp; Nevertheless, the passage teaches that godliness does involve a commitment to this form.&nbsp; I cannot take the time to give you chapter and verse for all that I will assert right here.&nbsp; I doubt if I need to.&nbsp; What is this form of godliness to which Paul refers?&nbsp; Well, a study of the Scriptures shows that true religion involves a number of visible, outward religious actions.&nbsp; First, it certainly involves attendance upon the corporate worship of God&#8217;s people.&nbsp; Second, piety toward God clearly involves being baptized in the name of Christ, a public sign of identifying with God&#8217;s religion.&nbsp; Third, true religion involves being formally identified with a local church.&nbsp; Fourth, it involves taking the Lord&#8217;s Supper in that church regularly.&nbsp; Fifth, it involves the religious observance of the Lord&#8217;s Day.&nbsp; Sixth, it involves giving financially to support the church&#8217;s worship and its benevolence to the poor.&nbsp; Seventh, it involves upholding orthodox Christian doctrine.&nbsp; Now remember doing all of these things does not mean that you are godly, but all these things are part of the biblical form of godliness.</i></p>
<p>Acts 10:2 a devout (<b><i>godly</i></b>) man, and one who feared God with all his household, and gave many alms to the <i>Jewish </i>people, and prayed to God continually.&nbsp; <i>Here Cornelius is described as a devout or godly man.&nbsp; Then what this meant is explained.&nbsp; The fact Cornelius was a godly man meant:&nbsp; (1)&nbsp; that he feared God.&nbsp; His whole life manifested that he lived under the eye of God.&nbsp; (2)&nbsp; that he practiced family religion.&nbsp; He feared God with his entire household.&nbsp; Whatever else this means, it must mean at least that Cornelius somehow led his household in worship.&nbsp; You could not be in Cornelius&#8217; household for any time without noticing that they were religious and without feeling a holy pressure to join them in their religious exercises.&nbsp; (3)&nbsp; that he practiced charitable giving to God&#8217;s people.&nbsp; This is what it means that he gave alms to the Jews.&nbsp; Perhaps, he helped support the needy among the Jews.&nbsp; Perhaps, like the Gentile in the gospels he had given to help the Jews construct or enlarge a synagogue.&nbsp; (4)&nbsp; that he prayed continually.&nbsp; Godliness means that you pray continually.&nbsp; That is to say, godliness in the heart makes a man a man of prayer.&nbsp; Such a man lives in a spirit of prayer.&nbsp; He engages regularly and daily in both stated times of prayer and a constant spirit of prayer.&nbsp; Godliness is manifested by the behavior of prayer.</i></p>
<p>1 Timothy 2:10 but rather by means of good works, as befits women making a claim to godliness.&nbsp; <i>Godliness is manifested by certain, specific behaviors in women.&nbsp; In other words, there is an outward conduct by women that vindicates their claim to be godly.&nbsp; In this passage three such behaviors are mentioned.&nbsp; First, feminine godliness is manifested by a practical commitment to the good works of charity (v. 10b).&nbsp; Second, it is manifested by a manifest commitment to Christian standards of adornment (v. 9).&nbsp; The appearance of a godly woman attests her claim to godliness.&nbsp; Her appearance reflects a rejection of immodesty, impropriety, and showiness or ostentation.&nbsp; Her appearance manifests that her priorities are set by a desire to please God.&nbsp; Third, feminine godliness is manifested by a submissive commitment to biblical roles in the church (vv. 11-12).&nbsp; She does not chafe at, she rather rejoices in God&#8217;s ordination of masculine leadership in the church.&nbsp; She regularly and thankfully takes her place in the church to be instructed by its God-appointed teachers.</i></p>
<p>2 Timothy 3:12 Indeed all who desire to live a godly life in Christ Jesus will be persecuted,&nbsp; <i>The context of this statement makes clear what Paul means here by living a godly life.&nbsp; Look at verses 9-11. Godliness means living for the purpose of telling others about Christ and seeing the gospel of Christ spread.&nbsp; A godly person has embraced God&#8217;s holy purpose for the spread of the gospel.&nbsp; Though we do not have either the calling or gifts of the Apostle, every Christian is to live for the spread of the gospel.&nbsp; He looks for opportunities to further gospel himself.&nbsp; He fills his part in the body of Christ to enable others more gifted or with a different calling to do what he cannot do himself.&nbsp; This is what it means to live a godly life here in 2 Timothy 3:12.</i></p>
<p>Godliness is: <b><i>behavior reflecting correct religious beliefs and attitudes &#8211; &#8216;piety, godliness.&#8217;&nbsp; </i></b>John Brown very ably summarizes godliness in this perceptive paragraph.</p>
<p>&#8220;The worship of God is either internal or external.&nbsp; The internal worship of God is just the habitual cultivation of the sentiments and feelings we have just been illustrating.&nbsp; Supremely to love, fear, trust in Him?-to be ever ready to believe what he reveals, because He reveals it?-to do what He commands, because He commands it?-and to submit to what He appoints because He appoints it:&nbsp; this is to worship with our spirits Him who is a Spirit, and to worship Him in truth.&nbsp; The ordinary state of a godly man&#8217;s mind is thus silent, habitual worship; and he expresses this state of mind in the appointed offices of religion.&nbsp; He loves the habitation of God&#8217;s house, and the place where His honour dwells.&nbsp; He dares not neglect the holy assembly for divine worship, as too many do.&nbsp; He goes into His tabernacle; he worships at His footstool; he is glad when it is said to him, &#8220;Let us go up to the house of the Lord.&#8221;&nbsp; &#8220;The voice of rejoicing and salvation,&#8221;?-of prayer and praise &#8220;is in the tabernacles&#8221; of the godly; and his family is kept beyond the reach of the curse that lies on &#8220;the families that call not on God&#8217;s name;&#8221; and he enters into his closet, and shuts his door, and prays to his Father who seeth in secret.&#8221; (<i>Parting Counsels, </i>100)</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-12-perseverance-must-be-supplied-with-godliness/">Growth in Grace 12 — Perseverance Must Be Supplied with Godliness</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/growth-in-grace-12-perseverance-must-be-supplied-with-godliness/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growth in Grace 11 — Self-control Must Be Supplied with Perseverance</title>
		<link>/growth-in-grace-11/</link>
					<comments>/growth-in-grace-11/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 14:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sanctification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Works]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1604</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>One of the dangers that Christians face, especially as they get older, is the danger of becoming too comfortable in the world.  They become unaccustomed to suffering, trial, and affliction for the sake of Christ and the gospel.  They forget perhaps the suffering and the loss of friends they experienced when they first became Christians.  [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-11/">Growth in Grace 11 — Self-control Must Be Supplied with Perseverance</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the dangers that Christians face, especially as they get older, is the danger of becoming too comfortable in the world.  They become unaccustomed to suffering, trial, and affliction for the sake of Christ and the gospel.  They forget perhaps the suffering and the loss of friends they experienced when they first became Christians.  They learn too well how just to get along with the world.  They lose their edge.</p>
<p>In the letter of 1 Peter we are studying, Peter is addressing those who have been Christians for some time and have become established in their faith.</p>
<blockquote><p>2 Peter 1:12  Therefore, I will always be ready to remind you of these things, even though you already know them, and have been established in the truth which is present with you.</p>
<p>2 Peter 3:17  You therefore, beloved, knowing this beforehand, be on your guard so that you are not carried away by the error of unprincipled men and fall from your own steadfastness</p></blockquote>
<p>In the opening exhortation of this letter to these Christians to grow in grace, he warns them that perseverance under the afflictions of a hostile world is one of the crucial ingredients of growth in grace.  2 Peter 1:5-7 warns Christians that they must <i>supply perseverance in their self-control.  </i>Let’s look at this phrase under four headings</p>
<p><i>I.                 </i><i>The Precise Translation</i><br />
<i>II.               </i><i>The Possible Connections</i><br />
<i>III.             T</i><i>he Proper Interpretation</i><br />
<i>IV.             </i><i>The Pressing Applications</i></p>
<p><b>I.       The Precise Translation</b></p>
<p>The NASB translates the key word in our text, perseverance.  The KJV translates the word, patience.  This is not a bad translation, but <i>patience</i> to our modern ears can convey the idea of being patient and kind and forbearing with those who annoy or provoke us.  There is a word in the New Testament that clearly conveys that idea.  It is the one that means and is translated longsuffering.  But that is not the word used here.  The word used here means exactly what the translation of the NASB conveys, <i>perseverance</i>.  The Greek word is defined as “steadfast adherence to a course of action in spite of difficulties and testings <i>perseverance, endurance, fortitude.</i>”</p>
<p><b>II.      The Possible Connections</b></p>
<p>One could interpret the idea of perseverance being supplied into self-control as implying that to exercise self-control is easy for a brief period of time, but that this is inadequate and self-control must be persevering if it is to be completed.  It is hard to stick to those diets we start.  Thus, self-control must be persevering.  This interpretation would be true and would be supported by a passage like Hosea 6:4: “What shall I do with you, O Ephraim? What shall I do with you, O Judah? For your loyalty is like a morning cloud And like the dew which goes away early.”</p>
<p>Or, the sense could be that to our ability to control our own selves (self-control) must be added the ability to endure the trials, the insults, the ridicule, and the persecutions of others which our faith brings upon us (perseverance).  We must both control our inward desires and persevere under our outward trials if we are to grow in grace.  Only with both these qualities will our Christianity be whole and complete and authentic.</p>
<p>This is the interpretation adopted by John Brown in his commentary on 2 Peter 1:</p>
<blockquote><p>Temperance and patience, as we have explained them are intimately connected.  They are, indeed, but two manifestations of the same spirit—unworldliness; in reference to what is desirable in the world, unworldliness is temperance, moderation; in reference to what is undesirable, it is patience.  The man who is temperate, is not likely to be impatient.  An inordinate attachment to the good things of life, is a bad preparation for the endurance of its evils.  He who has accustomed himself to recline in the lap of indulgence, is more likely to be fretful and desponding than patient, when visited with affliction.  They who rejoice as though they rejoiced not, are, when called to weep, most likely to weep as though they wept not.</p></blockquote>
<p>I believe this is the right understanding of the connection.</p>
<p><b>III.    The Proper Interpretation</b></p>
<p>I have really only one major argument that the connection I have asserted is the right one.  It is simply this.  <i>In the New Testament this word (which may be translated either as endurance or perseverance) never refers to continuing to exercise self-control over our inward desires. It usually refers, however, to the endurance of trials and persecutions which come upon us from without or others for our faith.  </i>Look at some of the places where this is seen to be so.</p>
<blockquote><p>Luke 21:19 &#8220;By your <b><i>endurance</i></b> you will gain your lives.</p>
<p>Romans 5:3 And not only this, but we also exult in our tribulations, knowing that tribulation brings about <b><i>perseverance</i></b></p>
<p>2 Corinthians 1:6 But if we are afflicted, it is for your comfort and salvation; or if we are comforted, it is for your comfort, which is effective in the <b><i>patient enduring</i></b> of the same sufferings which we also suffer</p>
<p>2 Corinthians 6:4 but in everything commending ourselves as servants of God, in much <b><i>endurance</i></b>, in afflictions, in hardships, in distresses</p>
<p>2 Thessalonians 1:4 therefore, we ourselves speak proudly of you among the churches of God for your <b><i>perseverance</i></b> and faith in the midst of all your persecutions and afflictions which you endure.</p>
<p>2 Timothy 3:10 But you followed my teaching, conduct, purpose, faith, patience, love, <b><i>perseverance</i></b></p>
<p>2 Timothy 3:11 persecutions, and sufferings, such as happened to me at Antioch, at Iconium and at Lystra; what <b><i>persecutions</i></b> I endured, and out of them all the Lord delivered me!</p>
<p>Hebrews 10:36 For you have need of <b><i>endurance</i></b>, so that when you have done the will of God, you may receive what was promised.</p>
<p>James 1:2 Consider it all joy, my brethren, when you encounter various trials, 3 knowing that the testing of your faith produces <b><i>endurance</i></b>.</p>
<p>Revelation 1:9 I, John, your brother and fellow partaker in the tribulation and kingdom and <b><i>perseverance</i></b> which are in Jesus, was on the island called Patmos, because of the word of God and the testimony of Jesus.</p>
<p>Revelation 13:10 If anyone is destined for captivity, to captivity he goes; if anyone kills with the sword, with the sword he must be killed. Here is the <b><i>perseverance</i></b> and the faith of the saints.</p></blockquote>
<p>In these many places perseverance is always connected not with exercising self-control, but with enduring tribulation, affliction, and trials in a hostile world on account of the gospel.</p>
<p>There is a very relevant, biblical example of what Peter is talking about here:  <i>his own!</i> Martyn Lloyd-Jones reminded me of this.  Here is what he said:</p>
<blockquote><p>Oh, the need of patience—patient endurance!  Peter again was probably falling back on his own experiences.  He it was who had said to our Lord, ‘Though all men forsake thee, I will follow thee’; and then, poor Peter had denied Him three times.  There is not much point in making great professions and great promises if we do not carry them out.</p></blockquote>
<p>The account of which Lloyd-Jones reminds us is Luke 22:31-34, 54-62.  Peter had loudly professed his willingness to persevere under trial, but he sadly defected at the moment of truth.  Who would have thought that bold Peter of all people would fail to endure ridicule and danger for Christ?  Yet at the questioning of a lowly servant-girl, he renounced Christ. Christ had, however, prayed that his faith would not fail.  The faith is denied when one fails to persevere.  Had he not repented he would not have been saved finally.  Because of the power of Christ’s intercession, however, he repented and persevered even to martyrdom for the sake of Christ.</p>
<p><b>IV.    The Pressing Applications</b></p>
<p><b><i>There is a good reason why perseverance needs to be added to self-control. </i></b></p>
<p>There is a defective kind of self-control that is unable to cope with the ridicule of a scoffing world.  Such self-control is no mark of true grace.  The self-control of such a person may not give into the pressures of their own desires, but it may give in to the pressures of his scoffing peers to indulge in their own kinds of a lack of self-control.  There is a kind of natural self-control that may be a result of someone having a certain temperament or a good upbringing.  But such self-control is not the virtue of which Peter is speaking.  How many young people have given into every kind of sinful indulgence not because they were particularly interested in the things they were offered, but simply because they did not want to be different.</p>
<p><b><i>Genuine Christianity will always bring upon us trial and affliction in the world.</i></b></p>
<p>John 16:33 says this plainly, &#8220;These things I have spoken to you, that in Me you may have peace. In the world you have tribulation, but take courage; I have overcome the world.&#8221;  So does 2 Timothy 3:12,  <i>And indeed, all who desire to live godly in Christ Jesus will be persecuted.</i></p>
<p>I do not want to fail to rejoice at any genuine work of God going on in the world.  But I have to tell you frankly, that there is a very popular kind of Christianity that is little different from the world.  It is a very appealing to adopt such a Christianity, because the world will love its own.  The world does not care what name you call yourself.  You may call yourself a Christian, but if you are no different from the world, the world will not reject you.  It will love you.</p>
<p>Let me warn you.  Any Christianity that does not alienate you from the world and bring on you tribulation is not genuine Christianity.  Don’t adopt it.  Don’t identify with it.  Don’t be deceived by it.  Don’t tell genuine Christians they are too strict and too narrow because you have bought a kind of Christianity that the world loves.  Some of you may be saying, <i>I just don’t want to be odd, weird, different like some Christians I know.  </i>But could it be that you what you are saying is odd or weird is just what Christians will have to look like from the viewpoint of the world?  Could it be that the kind of being different you fear is really and simply what it takes to be Christian at all in the world?  <i>All genuine Christianity demands the virtue of perseverance.</i></p>
<p><b><i>We are reminded that perseverance is the sovereign gift of Christ to His people.</i></b></p>
<p align="left">Perseverance is not that one thing which we must add to Christ’s finished work.  We have not come here finally to that one thing with which we must supplement God’s grace.  We are not supplying in our grace perseverance.  We are supplying in the grace of self-control the grace of perseverance.  To supply perseverance in our self-control is according to Peter to “grow in grace.”  It is not addition to God’s grace.  It is God’s grace!  In the words of John Piper’s great hymn “all the elect in Christ prevail.”  Thus, in telling you that you must persevere in the face of the world’s opposition, I am not telling you that it is all up to you.  I am telling you to go to Christ and cry for the perseverance without which you will not make it to heaven.  The result of this message should not be to look within yourself for courage, but to look up to Christ for grace.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-11/">Growth in Grace 11 — Self-control Must Be Supplied with Perseverance</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/growth-in-grace-11/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growth in Grace 10 — Knowledge Must Be Supplied with Self-control 3</title>
		<link>/growth-in-grace-10-knowledge-must-be-supplied-with-self-control-3/</link>
					<comments>/growth-in-grace-10-knowledge-must-be-supplied-with-self-control-3/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 14:00:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Soteriology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sanctification]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Works]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1595</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In previous posts I have answered two of the three questions about the self-control which Peter says must be supplied into knowledge in 2 Peter 1:5-7: Why must knowledge be supplied with self-control? and What is the self-control with which knowledge must be supplied?  Here I take up the third question: III.    How can such [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-10-knowledge-must-be-supplied-with-self-control-3/">Growth in Grace 10 — Knowledge Must Be Supplied with Self-control 3</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In previous posts I have answered two of the three questions about the self-control which Peter says must be supplied into knowledge in 2 Peter 1:5-7: <i>Why must knowledge be supplied with self-control?</i> and <i>What is the self-control with which knowledge must be supplied?</i>  Here I take up the third question:</p>
<p><b>III.    How can such self-control be attained?</b></p>
<p>A number of times already I have quoted you the text that says that the fruit of the Spirit is self-control (Gal. 5:23).  Have you ever thought of the fact that it contains a paradox?  How can <b><i>the fruit of the Spirit be self-control</i></b>?  But this paradox embodies the essence of what it means to live the Christian life and grow in grace.  What can you do practically to attain self-control?</p>
<p><b><i>The first thing</i></b> you must do is confront the issue.  In attaining self-control we must face up to the fact that we are in need of it in some area.  When the Spirit convicts us of an area where we need self-control, we must frankly confess it as sin and own up to it.  We must say to ourselves <i>I am sinning by a lack of self-control in _____</i>.</p>
<p><b><i>The second thing</i></b> you must do is to simply realize that you do not have of yourself the will power of the strength to acquire self-control in the needed area.  You must also confess your spiritual inability and weakness.  You must remember the teaching of Philippians 2:12 and 13 that both the will and the work necessary to conquer sins comes from the Holy Spirit.</p>
<p><b><i>The third thing </i></b>you must do, then, is to receive Christ for the sin of a lack of self-control.  Now you notice how I put that.  I did not say simply to ask God to forgive you for Christ’s sake for that sin.  That is part of receiving Christ in relation to the sin, but it is not all of it.  I said that you must receive Christ.  Faith does not merely take something from Christ.  It takes Christ himself.  So receiving Christ for the sin involves receiving Him as two things.  You must receive Him as the forgiveness of this particular sin.  But you must also receive Christ as the one in Whom the Spirit of God dwells and who gives the Spirit of God to His people.  We have seen that the Spirit alone can give a person self-control.  But you do not receive the Spirit by working for Him or meriting Him or fasting for Him.  You receive the Spirit by faith in Christ.  If you would receive the Spirit, you must receive Him in Christ.</p>
<p><b><i>The fourth thing</i></b> is that when you in this way put on Christ for your need of self-control, there are some unbelieving attitudes that you are putting off.  You must utterly reject the unbelieving attitude that says that no matter what you will never attain the self-control you want and need.  Part of believing in Christ is believing that he can give you such self-control.  You must really believe that Christ can deliver you from your sinful lack of self-control. You must also reject the attitude that says that without the sin you are seeking to kill you can never be happy.  Sin and Satan will try to tell you that if you really do exercise self-control in this area life will be bleak and unhappy.  In receiving Christ you are rejecting the idea that you need sin to make you happy.  You are accepting Christ as able to make you happy.  Part of exercising self-control in any area is being happy and content in Christ and His gifts.</p>
<p>But having confessed your sin and received Christ, and put off these sinful attitudes, <b><i>the fifth thing</i></b> is that you must put your faith to work.  You must in reliance on the grace of Christ refuse to indulge your sin.  Your faith must work.  You must work out your own salvation.  You must fight the good fight of faith.  You must run looking unto Jesus.</p>
<p><b><i>The sixth and last thing</i></b> is that you must remember that Peter makes clear that this whole matter of sanctification is not attained instantly.  He tells us to <b><i>grow</i></b> in grace.  God does not promise that if we once face our sin, receive Christ, and put our faith to work, we will be forever perfectly self-controlled.  No, he tells us the exact opposite.  He tells that it is a matter of growth.  Growth is a gradual process.  I have not told you how to attain instant self-control overnight today. I have told you how to grow in self-control.  Don’t forget that.  Keep on facing your sin.  Keep on receiving Christ. Keep on putting faith to work.  Christ does not promise you that you will see plants 14 feet tall overnight.  He does promise you that you will grow and the fruit of the Spirit will ripen in your slowly but surely in your life.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/growth-in-grace-10-knowledge-must-be-supplied-with-self-control-3/">Growth in Grace 10 — Knowledge Must Be Supplied with Self-control 3</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/growth-in-grace-10-knowledge-must-be-supplied-with-self-control-3/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
