<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>New Testament | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/new-testament/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 17:08:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>New Testament | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Why is Theonomy Unbiblical?</title>
		<link>/why-is-theonomy-unbiblical/</link>
					<comments>/why-is-theonomy-unbiblical/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tom Hicks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 17:08:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Civil Government]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Covenant Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=18787</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Before critiquing theonomy, we need a good definition. Some people today who use the word “theonomy” don’t mean anything more than “God’s law” because the etimology of the word theonomy is “theos” which means God, and “nomos” which means law. They only want to affirm that God’s law is supreme over man’s law. And they’re right about that. God’s transcendent moral law is the norm that norms all norms. Governmental laws should always be consistent with God’s law and human law must never violate God’s law.</p>
<p>But in this post, I’ll be using the word “theonomy” in a more technical sense, which is rooted in the historic usage of the term.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-is-theonomy-unbiblical/">Why is Theonomy Unbiblical?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_0 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_0">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_0  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_0  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p>Before critiquing theonomy, we need a good definition. Some people today who use the word “theonomy” don’t mean anything more than “God’s law” because the etimology of the word theonomy is “theos” which means God, and “nomos” which means law. They only want to affirm that God’s law is supreme over man’s law. And they’re right about that. God’s transcendent moral law is the norm that norms all norms. Governmental laws should always be consistent with God’s law and human law must never violate God’s law.</p>
<p>But in this post, I’ll be using the word “theonomy” in a more technical sense, which is rooted in the historic usage of the term. Theonomy, in the technical sense, teaches that Old Covenant judicial laws are the universal moral standard of civil law for all Gentile nations. The basic presupposition of theonomy is that God gave the judicial law to the nation of Israel as a universal law of perfect justice for all nations because it is a perfect reflection of God’s own moral character. Some of the most prominent early proponents of this kind of theonomy include Greg Bahnsen, Rousas Rushdoony and Gary North. For a discussion of “general equity theonomy,”<span> </span><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://pastortomhicks.com/2021/03/16/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/" target="_blank">see here</a>.</p>
<p>I’m convinced that theonomy is unbiblical for a number of reasons.</p>
<h3><em><strong>1. Theonomy has a flawed hermeutic of Old Testament priority.</strong></em></h3>
<p>Theonomy arrives at its conclusions by insisting that particular Old Testament laws persist, unless they are specifically abrogated by the New Testament. But this reads the Bible improperly. Theonomy’s hermeneutic is consistent with paedobaptism, which says that since the New Testament does not abrogate the Old Testament inclusion of infants, then infants must be given the sign of baptism. Theonomy is also consistent with the Old Testament priority<span> </span><a href="https://www.the-highway.com/theonomy-hermeneutic_Irons.html">hermeneutic of dispensationalism</a>, which teaches that the promises God made for Israel cannot be typologically fulfilled in Christ and the church, but must be literally fulfilled in national Israel. But theonomy’s hermeneutic isn’t consistent with<span> </span><a href="https://founders.org/2016/05/26/hermeneutics-new-testament-priority/">the hermeneutic of New Testament priority</a>.</p>
<p>It is true that earlier revelation is vital for understanding the context of later revelation. In that sense, earlier revelation is logically prior to later revelation. But sound hermeneutical principles recognize that later revelation has interpretive priority over earlier revelation. Therefore, when later Old Testament texts explain earlier parts of the Old Testament, we should pay close attention to what the later texts say and allow them to explain and draw out implications of earlier Old Testament texts, making explicit what was only previously implicit. Similarly, when the New Testament explains Old Testament passages of Scripture, the New Testament has priority of interpretation over the Old Testament.</p>
<p>If the New Testament says an Old Testament passage has a particular meaning, we should assign that meaning to the Old Testament passage. The same is true of New Testament letters, which explain the earlier life and work of Jesus Christ in the Gospels.</p>
<p>This is nothing other than what Augustine taught when he said, “The New is in the Old concealed; the Old is in the New revealed.” The light of revelation is brighter as we move toward the end of the Bible (Louis Berkhof,<span> </span><em>Principles of Interpretation</em>, pp. 54, 133, 135, 137). Berkhof says, “The New Testament is implicit in the Old, so the Old is explicit in the new” (135). And “The more perfect revelation of the New Testament illumines the pages of the Old” (137-138).</p>
<p>This isn’t really any different from the way we read any book by a single author. We allow the later parts of a book to interpret the earlier parts of the book. Orthodox theology is rooted in the idea that the one true God authored the whole of the Scriptures. Thus, we should pay close attention to His intended meaning in light of His explanation of His own Word.</p>
<h3><em><strong>2. Theonomy does not account for the fact that Gentile nations are not and never were under the Old Covenant.</strong></em></h3>
<p>The laws peculiar to the Old Covenant do not bind Gentile nations. Gentile nations are under natural law, which is the work of the moral law written on the hearts of all human beings. Romans 2:14 says, “For when the Gentiles, who do not have the law, by nature, do what the law requires, they are a law to themselves, even though they do not have the law. They show that the work of the law is written on their hearts.”</p>
<p>When God judged the Gentile nations in the Old Testament, He never judged them for violating Old Covenant judicial law. Rather, He judged them for violating His moral law, as summarized in the Ten Commandments (Jerermiah 46-51; Ezekiel 25-32; Amos 1-2; Obadiah; Jonah; Nahum; Habakkuk 2 – a taunt song against the Babylonians for violating God’s moral law; Zephaniah 2).</p>
<h3><em><strong>3. Theonomy doesn’t properly account for the fact that the Old Covenant as a whole, together with all of its laws, has been abolished.</strong></em></h3>
<p>Numerous passages of Scripture teach that the Old Covenant has been fulfilled and abolished with the coming of Christ and the establishment of the New Covenant.</p>
<ul>
<li>Hebrews 7:12 says, “For when there is a change in the priesthood, there is necessarily a change in the law as well.”</li>
<li>Hebrews 7:18 says, “A former commandment is set aside because of its weakness and uselessness.”</li>
<li>Hebrews 8:13 says, “In speaking of a new covenant, he makes the first one obsolete.”</li>
<li>Hebrews 10:9 says, “He abolishes the first in order to establish the second.”</li>
<li>Ephesians 2:14-15 says that Christ “has broken down in his flesh the dividing wall of hostility, by abolishing the law of commandments and ordinances.”</li>
</ul>
<p>To be clear, the moral law, which is summarized in the Ten Commandments,<span> </span><a href="https://pastortomhicks.com/2020/01/22/are-the-ten-commandments-distinct-from-other-old-testament-law/">has not been abolished</a>. The moral law is rooted in God’s own eternal moral character and is part of the image of God in human beings. Moral aspects of Old Covenant law can never be abolished because they are rooted in nature, not merely in a covenant. But the positive laws of the Old Covenant have been abolished. Theonomy does not properly account for this fact.</p>
<p>Rich Barcellos correctly notes, “The New Testament clearly abrogates the whole Old Covenant, including the Decalogue, as it functioned within the Old Covenant, and yet borrows from its documents as the basis for New Covenant ethics (see for instance 1 Cor. 9:9-10; 14:34; 2 Cor 13:1; Eph 6:2-3, and many other texts)” (<em>In Defense of the Decalogue</em>, p. 68).</p>
<h3><em><strong>4. Theonomy doesn’t acknowledge the existence of positive law in contrast to moral or natural law.</strong></em></h3>
<p>This is related to numbers 2 and 3 above. Natural law is law that people know innately. Romans 2:14-15 is clear that God writes the work of His natural law on the hearts of all men, and Romans 2:21-24 shows that natural law is summarized in the Ten Commandments. Natural law is nothing other than the reflection of God’s moral character in human beings who are made in His image.</p>
<p>Positive law, on the other hand, is law that God posited by way of special revelation in a particular covenant. No one would have known that they ought to obey positive law, unless it had been revealed to them in a biblical covenant.</p>
<p>To give you an example of the distinction between natural/moral and positive law, consider Adam in the Garden of Eden. Adam knew by nature not to worship false gods, not to steal, not to murder, etc. He knew these laws because he was made in the image of God. But Adam would never have known not to eat of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, if God had not revealed and commanded that positive law to him in the covenant of works.</p>
<p>To give you another example, Abraham knew by nature that it was wrong to lie to Pharoah about Sarah being his wife. God never had to tell Abraham that lying was wrong because all images of God know it’s wrong to lie, even if they suppress that truth in unrighteousness. But Abraham would never have known that he had to be circumcised except for the fact that God revealed that law to him and commanded him to be circumcised in the covenant of circumcision. Natural law is known innately, but positive law would never be known apart from covenantal revelation.</p>
<p>Natural or moral law transcends all covenants. It’s immutably rooted in the nature and character of God and also in human nature. Fallen human beings suppress their knowledge of natural law, which is why we need Scripture to reassert and clarify it. But even fallen human beings are not completely ignorant of natural law. Positive law, on the other hand, is covenantal, must be specially revealed to be known, and serves a particular purpose within the covenant in which it is given. When covenants change, positive laws change, but moral or natural law does not.</p>
<p>Theonomy does not grasp this crucial distinction. The judicial laws of the Old Covenant are not transcendent moral or natural law, but positive laws, which God commanded in the Old Covenant for a particular reason.</p>
<h3><em><strong>5. Theonomy does not account for the fact that the judicial laws of Israel were only to be practiced in the land of Canaan.</strong></em></h3>
<p>It’s impossible to separate Israel’s judicial law from the land of Canaan. The Old Covenant law was given to the Old Covenant people, who were to keep the law in the Old Covenant land. Deuteronomy 4:14 says, “And the LORD commanded me at that time to teach you statues and rules that you might do them<span> </span><em>in the land</em><span> </span>that you are going over to possess.”</p>
<p>To give one example, consider the law of the parapet. Deuteronomy 22:8 says, “When you build a new house, you shall make a parapet for your roof, that you may not bring the guilt of blood upon your house, if anyone should fall from it.” This judicial law, which is based on blood-guilt, only makes sense because the land of Israel is holy. According to the Old Covenant, blood-guilt defiles the land and results in the expulsion of the people. Deuteronomy 19:10 warns that if blood guilt comes upon the land, the guilt of blood shall be shed upon the people.</p>
<p>While there is certainly an element of perpetual moral law (general equity, “do not murder”) in the law of the parapet, the law itself could only be practiced in the land of Canaan, which is the case for all Old Covenant judicial law.</p>
<h3><em><strong>6. Theonomy misunderstands the reason for the death penalties in Old Covenant judicial law.</strong></em></h3>
<p>Before discussing the death penalty in Old Covenant judicial law, it’s important to understand that the covenant of common grace establishes the death penalty for murder. The death penalty for murder is part of universal moral law. In Genesis 9:6, the Noahic covenant of common grace says, “Whoever sheds the blood of man, by man shall his blood be shed, for God made man in his own image.” That is a transcendent moral principle: the punishment must fit the crime. It is<span> </span><em>lex talionis</em>, which is the “law of the same,” often expressed as “an eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth.” It refers to equal weights and measures in justice. So, the death penalty for murder is moral law.</p>
<p>But other Old Testament death penalties are tied to Old Covenant worship. The term “devoted to destruction” or “devoted to the ban” (Hebrew:<span> </span><em>cherem</em>) involves the death penalty, and it is connected to the purity of the land, holy war, and Old Covenant worship.</p>
<p>Deuteronomy 13:12-16 says:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>“If you hear in one of your cities, which the Lord your God is giving you to dwell there, that certain worthless fellows have gone out among you and have drawn away the inhabitants of their city, saying, ‘Let us go and serve other gods,’ which you have not known, then you shall inquire and make search and ask diligently. And behold, if it be true and certain that such an abomination has been done among you, you shall surely put the inhabitants of that city to the sword, devoting it to destruction, all who are in it and its cattle, with the edge of the sword. You shall gather all its spoil into the midst of its open square and burn the city and all its spoil with fire, as a whole burnt offering to the Lord your God. It shall be a heap forever. It shall not be built again.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is saying that if a city comes under the influence of idolaters, there is to be a careful inquiry, and if it’s found to be true that the city is under the influence of idolaters, then the whole city is to be put to death, together with the cattle.</p>
<p>This law is not simply a matter of moral justice. Verse 16 says that the city becomes a “whole burnt offering to the Lord your God.” It’s an offering to God. This is a law about holy war and Israel’s possession of the holy land. It’s a kind of ceremonial purification.</p>
<p>It also anticipates Judgment Day. The New Testament seems to teach that the death penalties of the Old Covenant are types of eternal condemnation.</p>
<p>Hebrews 10:28 says:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>“Anyone who has set aside the law of Moses dies without mercy on the evidence of two or three witnesses. How much<span> </span><em>worse</em><span> </span>punishment, do you think, will be deserved by the one who has trampled underfoot the Son of God, and has profaned the blood of the covenant by which he was sanctified, and has outraged the Spirit of grace? For we know him who said, “Vengeance is mine; I will repay.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In other words, under the Old Covenant, the penalty for breaking the law was physical death. But the corresponding doctrine of the New Testament is eternal condemnation for those without Christ.</p>
<p>So, the death penalties of the Old Testament are associated with Israel’s unique place in redemptive history. I’m convinced that scholars have shown that all of the death penalties of the Old Covenant are based on the distinctive purposes of the Old Covenant. I recommend Vern Poythress’s book,<span> </span><em>The Shadow of Christ in the Law of Moses</em>, which illustrates this very well. I don’t agree with everything in that book, but it is a good resource to have.</p>
<p>Due to their special character, therefore, it would be unjust to apply Old Covenant death penalties in a Gentile nation. It was perfectly just for Israel to put people to death for all sorts of reasons because God has the right to command the death of any sinner, and He commanded the death of many sinners via the Old Covenant for reasons that were unique to that covenant. But we have no right to implement such penalties in Gentile nations.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the death penalties of the Old Covenant are reflective of the fact that it is a “work for the right to inheritance” covenant. Leviticus 18:5 says, “You shall therefore keep my statutes and my rules; if a person does them, he shall live by them: I am the LORD.” But the new covenant gives the inheritance by grace, not by works. Galatians 3:12-13 denies this works principle under the gospel, “But the law is not of faith, rather, ‘the one who does them shall live by them.’ Christ redeemed us from the curse of the law by becoming a curse for us — for it is written, ‘Cursed is everyone who is hanged on a tree.&#8217;”</p>
<h3><em><strong>7. Theonomy does not account for the fact that the Old Covenant law was intentionally severe to preserve the line of promise.</strong></em></h3>
<p>The nation of Israel was largely an unbelieving nation. The people needed a severe legal system to chasten them and to preserve them as a nation until Christ would come from them. The severity of Old Covenant judicial law is especially evident in the liberal use of the death penalty. The death penalty was prescribed for false-worship and apostasy (Deut 13:6-11; 17:5), blasphemy (Lev 24:10-16, 23), sabbath-breaking (Num 15:31-36), rebellious sons (Deut 21:18-21), fornication (Deut 22:20-23), adultery (Lev 20:10-11), homosexuality (Lev 20:13) and many other sins. These are very heavy penalties.</p>
<p>Galatians 3:19 explains one of the reasons for such laws: “Why then the law? It was added because of transgressions,<span> </span><em>until</em><span> </span>the offspring should come to whom the promise had been made.” Similarly, Galatians 3:24-25 says, “So, then the law was our guardian<span> </span><em>until</em><span> </span>Christ came, in order that we might be justified by faith. But<span> </span><em>now</em><span> </span>that faith has come, we are no longer under a guardian.”</p>
<p>Scripture is saying that the severe Old Covenant law was given because of the sins of the people of Israel. It was given to them as a nation, to chasten them, and to act as a deterrent for outward sin, and to keep them from destroying themselves,<span> </span><em>until</em><span> </span>Christ came from them.</p>
<p>The Jerusalem council discussed the fact that some wanted the church to practice circumcision. Acts 15:10 says, “Now, therefore, why are you putting God to the test by placing a yoke on the neck of the disciples that neither our fathers nor we have been able to bear?” The covenant of circumcision, and the Old Covenant as a whole, was a heavy legal yoke. Those who try to impose it upon Christians or Gentile nations are heaping a heavy burden upon them. Now that Christ has come, there is no reason for it. The yoke of the Old Covenant has been fulfilled and abolished with the coming of Christ.</p>
<h3><em><strong>8. In each case, when the New Testament applies one of the judicial laws of the Old Covenant, it applies the law’s general equity to the church, and never to the government of a Gentile nation.</strong></em></h3>
<p>This is important because of the hermeneutical principle of New Testament priority. The New Testament teaches us how to interpret and use the Old Testament, which means we need to pay attention to how the New Testament applies Old Covenant judicial laws. You will never find a single New Testament example of an Old Covenant judicial law being applied to a Gentile government.</p>
<p>For example, 1 Timothy 5:17-18 says, “Let the elders who rule well be considered worthy of double honor, especially those who labor in preaching and teaching. For the Scripture says, ‘You shall not muzzle an ox when it treads out the grain,’ and ‘the laborer deserves his wages.” “Do not muzzle the ox while it treads out the grain” is a judicial law that comes from Deuteronomy 25:4. But here, Paul applies the law’s general equity (do not steal) to paying pastors properly in the church. He does not apply it to a Gentile government.</p>
<p>Another example comes from 1 Corinthians 5:13, where Paul is discussing church discipline, and he says, “Purge the evil person from among you.” That’s a judicial law from Deuteronomy 13:5, 17:7, 12, and many other places. In the Old Covenant, “purging the evil person from among you” referred to the death penalty. But in the New Covenant, that judicial law is applied to church discipline, not to the civil death penalty.</p>
<p>So, if we allow the New Testament to teach us how to interpret Old Covenant judicial laws, then we will think of their general equity first as applying to the church, not primarily to Gentile civil governments.</p>
<h3><em><strong>9. To sum up, theonomy’s central mistake is believing that God gave the judicial law of Israel as a universal norm of societal justice for all nations.</strong></em></h3>
<p>Certainly, the moral law of the Old Covenant is a universal norm for all nations. And we ought to use the Old Testament to help us understand God’s moral law. But the positive laws of the Old Covenant had many different functions according to Scripture, and all of them were bound to the unique objectives of the Old Covenant.</p>
<p>As we have seen, the judicial law was tied to the land, to ceremonial worship, and to the preservation of Christ’s line of promise. Some of the judicial laws were simply designed to create a distinct culture for Israel that separated them from the nations. Others were about preserving family lines for the sake of property and inheritance. But all of the positive laws of the Old Covenant were related to the typological character of the Old Covenant and/or to its unique cultural situation and place in redemptive history.</p>
<p>In conclusion, theonomy, in the technical sense of the term is not a biblical idea. Scripture itself refutes the theonomic position, such that in fact, theonomy is not in favor of God’s law at all, but adds to the good law of God positive covenantal precepts that were designed to expire with the coming of the Lord Jesus.</p>
<p>While this article has been a critique of Theonomy, and I have not outlined a positive biblical theology of civil government, the<span> </span><em>Second London Baptist Confession of Faith</em>, chapter 24, provides a wonderful framework for civil government. I wrote an exposition of that chapter here:<span> </span><a href="https://pastortomhicks.com/2020/04/02/what-is-the-role-of-civil-government/">What is the role of civil government?</a></p>
<p>For another good resource on Theonomy<span> </span><a href="https://contrast2.wordpress.com/2020/09/18/theonomy/">see this article by Brandon Adams</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section -->
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/tom-hicks/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2018/03/02211852/TomHicks.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/tom-hicks/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Tom Hicks</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><div class="header">
<div class="description">Tom serves as the Senior Pastor of First Baptist Church of Clinton, LA. He&#8217;s married to Joy, and they have four children: Sophie, Karlie, Rebekah, and David. He received his MDiv and PhD degrees from The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary with a major in Church History, emphasis on Baptists, and with a minor in Systematic Theology. Tom is the author of The Doctrine of Justification in the Theologies of Richard Baxter and Benjamin Keach (PhD diss, SBTS). He serves on the board of directors for Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary and is an adjunct professor of historical theology for the Institute of Reformed Baptist Studies.</div>
</div>
<div id="featured">
<div class="hero"></div>
</div>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/why-is-theonomy-unbiblical/">Why is Theonomy Unbiblical?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/why-is-theonomy-unbiblical/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is &#8220;General Equity Theonomy&#8221; a Confessional and Biblical Doctrine?</title>
		<link>/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/</link>
					<comments>/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tom Hicks]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 21:28:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Civil Government]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Covenant Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Old Testament]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=18755</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Some of those who identify as theonomists today refer to themselves as “general equity theonomists,” believing that this identification lands them within the boundaries of Reformed confessional orthodoxy. But if it does, then the term “general equity” needs to be defined the same way the tradition defined it. The technical term “general equity” is used in both the Westminster Confession and the Second London Baptist Confession.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/">Is &#8220;General Equity Theonomy&#8221; a Confessional and Biblical Doctrine?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="et_pb_section et_pb_section_1 et_section_regular" >
				
				
				
				
					<div class="et_pb_row et_pb_row_1">
				<div class="et_pb_column et_pb_column_4_4 et_pb_column_1  et_pb_css_mix_blend_mode_passthrough et-last-child">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_1  et_pb_text_align_left et_pb_bg_layout_light">
				
				
				<div class="et_pb_text_inner"><h2><em><strong>Is “General Equity Theonomy” a Confessional and Biblical Doctrine?</strong></em></h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Some of those who identify as theonomists today refer to themselves as “general equity theonomists,” believing that this identification lands them within the boundaries of Reformed confessional orthodoxy. But if it does, then the term “general equity” needs to be defined the same way the tradition defined it. The technical term “general equity” is used in both the <em>Westminster Confession</em> and the <em>Second London Baptist Confession</em>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em>The Westminster Confession of Faith</em> 19.4 says, “To them also, as a body politic, He gave sundry judicial laws, which expired together with the State of that people; not obliging any other now, further than the <em>general equity</em> thereof may require.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Following the <em>Savoy Declaration</em>, the <em>Second London Baptist Confession of Faith</em> 19.4 says, “To them also he gave sundry judicial laws, which expired together with the state of that people, not obliging any now by virtue of that institution; their <em>general equity</em> only being of moral use.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>So, while the confessions teach that the “general equity” of the judicial law obliges us, the question remains as to whether “general equity theonomists” mean the same thing by general equity that the confessions mean.  I have found it hard to nail down a single clear definition of “general equity theonomy” that universally describes those who say they hold to it. The term seems to be defined variously and even in contradictory ways. So, rather than focus on the personalities involved in this debate, or cite definitions from a number of different adherents, I want to address what some appear to mean by “general equity theonomy,” which is that the essential or core principles of Old Testament judicial laws have binding authority today. That is, many say that the Old Testament judicial laws have been abrogated, but the essential principles of the judicial laws continue to bind all people today. </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><em> 1. <strong style="font-size: 22px;">The Historic Meaning of the Term “General Equity”</strong></em></h3>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The question as to the meaning of the term “general equity” is a matter of historical research. I am indebted to Brandon Adams for several of the quotations found in this section.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>John Calvin identifies the term “equity” with moral law. “It is a fact that the law of God which we call the <em>moral law</em> is nothing else than a testimony of <em>natural law</em> and of that conscience which God has engraved upon the minds of men. Consequently, the entire scheme of this <em>equity</em> of which we are now speaking has been prescribed in it. Hence, <em>this equity alone must be the goal and rule and limit of all laws</em>” (<em>Institutes</em> 4.20.15-16, italics in the text are mine).</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Calvin’s successor in Geneva, Theodore Beza, wrote, “Although we do not hold to the forms of the Mosaic polity, yet when such <em>judicial laws</em> prescribe <em>equity</em> in judgments, <em>which is part of the decalogue</em>, we, not being under obligation to them insofar as they were prescribed by Moses to only one people, are nevertheless bound to observe them to the extent that they embrace that <em>general equity</em> which should everywhere be in force . . . . Because it follows <em>natural equity</em>, and expounds that <em>perpetual precept of the decalogue</em>, Thou shalt not steal, to this extent all are bound to fulfill them both” (<em>De Haereticis a civili Magistratu puniendis Libellus, </em>Geneva: Robert Stephanus, 1554, pp. 222-23, italics in the text are mine). Beza clearly linked general equity to the decalogue and natural law.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>William Perkins wrote, “Judicial laws so far as they have in them the <em>general or common equity</em> of the <em>law of nature</em> <em>are moral</em> and therefore binding in conscience as <em>the moral law</em>” (<em>A Discourse on Cases of Conscience</em> in <em>The Whole Works, </em>London, 1631, 1.520).</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Thus, the historic meaning of the term “general equity” refers exclusively to the moral law, summarized in the Ten Commandments, which is also revealed in the law of nature. The crucial thing to understand about the general equity of the old covenant judicial law is that the judicial law’s general equity is not first to be found in the judicial laws themselves. If there is general equity in any given old covenant judicial law, it is first found in nature, in creation and conscience, and it is also summarily taught in the Ten Commandments. Therefore, we should not approach old covenant judicial laws to discover distinctive or new principles of law, which are not already revealed in creation, conscience, or the decalogue. Old covenant judicial laws do not establish timeless principles of law; rather, to the extent that there is any general equity in them, it is based on the larger trans-covenantal moral law of nature, which is found outside of those laws.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Therefore, if “general equity theonomy” means that the core principles of the judicial laws remain in force, but those principles do not necessarily entail God’s transcendent moral and natural law summarized in the Ten Commandments, then that definition of general equity is contrary to the Reformed confessional tradition. According to the confessional tradition, we must not begin with judicial law to discover principles of general equity. Rather, we must begin with the decalogue and see whether there is any moral or natural law principle in any given judicial law.</p>
<p><em style="font-size: 22px;"><strong></strong></em></p>
<p><em style="font-size: 22px;"><strong>2. The New Testament Use of Judicial Law</strong></em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>If it’s true that the essential core principles of the judicial laws remain binding for us today, then consider how we might interpret Deuteronomy 25:4, which says, “You shall not muzzle an ox when it is treading out the grain.” Without the inspired New Testament commentary on this passage, we might say that a core principle of this passage is “You should allow your animals to feed while they are working.” One way to apply this law might be to say that people should see to it that their hunting dogs always have access to a portion of the meat they kill during the hunt as a matter of biblical law. That would seem to be a reasonable application of the core principle of this judicial law, recognizing that the law itself has been abrogated, but that the essence of it is perpetually binding.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>And yet, the New Testament does not derive any such essential principle from Deuteronomy 25:4. Rather, the New Testament finds the eighth commandment embedded in Deuteronomy 25:4, which is an element of transcendent moral and natural law, “You shall not steal” (Ex 20:15). 1 Timothy 5:17-18 says, “Let the elders who rule well be considered worthy of double honor, especially those who labor in preaching and teaching. For the Scripture says, ‘You shall not muzzle an ox when it treads out the grain,’ and, ‘The laborer deserves his wages.’” The general equity of the law of the muzzled ox is that you must not steal wages from the one who works. Paul saw that the general equity of Deuteronomy 25:4 is nothing other than the eighth commandment, which means that churches should pay their pastors. The same general equity of Deuteronomy 25:4 would apply to refusing to use unjust weights and balances, to forbidding customers from stealing from merchants, merchants from stealing from customers, etc.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In conclusion, any version of “general equity theonomy,” which does not look for prior transcendent moral law within the judicial law, which is summarized in the decalogue and/or revealed in nature, uses a hermeneutic contrary to the New Testament. The issue at stake is the controls on our interpretation and application of judicial law.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em style="font-size: 22px;"><strong>3. The Way to Find and Apply General Equity of Judicial Law</strong></em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Take Deuteronomy 22:8 as an example. It says, “When you build a new house, you shall make a parapet for your roof, that you may not bring the guilt of blood upon your house, if anyone should fall from it.” Someone wrote, “We are not morally required to build a parapet around our roof line because we don’t go up there. But general equity would require a rail around your second story deck.” In this instance, the application of general equity theonomy seems to keep tightly to the essential core principles of the judicial law in question. Not a roof, but a second story deck. Not a parapet, but a railing. It’s not the particulars of the law that are binding, but the essential principles.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>But it’s crucial to understand that the general equity of the law of the parapet isn’t merely a matter of the essential principles of that particular judicial law. The general equity of the law of the parapet is nothing other than the sixth commandment, “You shall not murder” (Ex 20:13). Does the law’s general equity require a railing around a second story deck to protect the lives of people who go up there? Absolutely. But railings on second story decks are not required because of the law of the parapet itself. Rather, general equity requires a railing on a second story deck because of the transcendent moral law, summarized in the decalogue, which stands behind the law of the parapet: “You shall not murder.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Understood properly, the general equity of the law of the parapet requires us to protect other people’s lives, and not merely do what is expedient, cheaper, or more convenient for ourselves. The general equity of the law of the parapet applies in a number of circumstances. People who use guns should practice gun safety principles. If you have a deadly illness, take precautions not to spread it to others as far as it depends on you. Salt your sidewalks after an ice storm. Drive safely so as not to endanger others. Don’t leave live electrical wires exposed in your home. The sixth commandment requires that you not be concerned merely for yourself, but must always live so as to protect the lives of other people. That is the general equity of the law of the parapet, the sixth commandment, “do not murder.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2><em><strong>Conclusion</strong></em></h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In conclusion, any understanding of the term general equity, which neglects the decalogue, or natural law revealed in creation or conscience, as the essence of general equity is not accurately defining the term according to its historic and confessional sense. Any version of general equity theonomy that does not look for a moral law that transcends Old Testament judicial law but instead sees Old Testament judicial law as itself a subset of moral law that remains binding is not following the example of the New Testament.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The greatest mistake of such a hermeneutic is that it does not begin with the universal transcendent norms of natural and moral law, summarized in the Ten Commandments, seeking to find those moral principles within judicial law. Rather, it begins with the judicial laws themselves and tries to uncover the essential principles within those laws, wrongly assuming they are all moral, in order to apply them universally.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p></div>
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_text -->
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_column -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_row -->
				
				
			</div> <!-- .et_pb_section -->
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/tom-hicks/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2018/03/02211852/TomHicks.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/tom-hicks/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Tom Hicks</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><div class="header">
<div class="description">Tom serves as the Senior Pastor of First Baptist Church of Clinton, LA. He&#8217;s married to Joy, and they have four children: Sophie, Karlie, Rebekah, and David. He received his MDiv and PhD degrees from The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary with a major in Church History, emphasis on Baptists, and with a minor in Systematic Theology. Tom is the author of The Doctrine of Justification in the Theologies of Richard Baxter and Benjamin Keach (PhD diss, SBTS). He serves on the board of directors for Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary and is an adjunct professor of historical theology for the Institute of Reformed Baptist Studies.</div>
</div>
<div id="featured">
<div class="hero"></div>
</div>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/">Is &#8220;General Equity Theonomy&#8221; a Confessional and Biblical Doctrine?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/is-general-equity-theonomy-a-confessional-and-biblical-doctrine/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 7 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</title>
		<link>/9-john-mark/</link>
					<comments>/9-john-mark/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 21:32:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15515</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is the 9th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here:&#160;1,&#160;2,&#160;3,&#160;4,&#160;5,&#160;6,&#160;7, 8. Chapter 7 of John Mark&#8217;s Remarkable Career&#8212;His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark The unanimous testimony of the early church is that the Gospel of Mark was written by John Mark. The earliest [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/9-john-mark/">Chapter 7 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is the 9th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here:&nbsp;<a href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">1</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">2</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/mark-career-3/">3</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/chapter-3-mark/">4</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/john-mark-5/">5</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/6-john-mark/">6</a>,&nbsp;<a href="/7-john-mark/">7</a>, <a href="/8-john-mark/">8</a>.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2><strong>Chapter 7 of John Mark&#8217;s Remarkable Career&#8212;His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</strong></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The unanimous testimony of the early church is that the Gospel of Mark was written by John Mark. The earliest testimony to this comes from two well-known Christians of the second century.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The first is a man named Papias. His testimony likely comes from around the years 110-120. He said:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><em>Mark, the interpreter of Peter, wrote down carefully what he remembered, both the sayings and the deeds of the Christ, but not in chronological order, for he did not hear the Lord nor did he accompany him. At a later time, however, he did accompany Peter, who adapted his instructions to the needs, but not with the object of making a connected series of discourses of our Lord. So, Mark made no mistake in writing the individual discourses in the order in which he recalled them. His one concern was not to omit a single thing he had heard or to leave any untruth in this account.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The second significant testimony comes from the early church father, Irenaeus. Writing around 180, he said:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><em>Matthew also issued a written Gospel among the Hebrews in their own dialect, while Peter and Paul were preaching at Rome, and laying the foundations of the Church. After their departure, Mark, the disciple and interpreter of Peter, did also hand down to us in writing what had been preached by Peter. Luke also, the companion of Paul, recorded in a book the Gospel preached by him. Afterwards, John, the disciple of the Lord, who also had leaned upon His breast, did himself publish a Gospel during his residence at Ephesus in Asia.</em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The best and the necessary conclusion with regard to the authorship of the Gospel of Mark is summarized in the words of another scholar:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Though the author does not directly identify himself, there is still strong evidence to attribute the Gospel to John Mark. In addition to Markan composition, church fathers also state that Mark was the interpreter of Peter, which would give reason to believe that he wrote his Gospel under the guidance or assistance of the apostle &#8230; the title &#8220;According to Mark&#8221; (KATA MARKON) is found in the earliest manuscripts. &nbsp;[https://www.blueletterbible.org/study/intros/mark.cfm]</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>John Mark&#8212;that John Mark who abandoned Christ and deserted Barnabas and Saul and was the source of the scandal of the disagreement between Paul and Barnabas&#8212;that John Mark was so restored in Christ&#8217;s church that by the grace of Christ he rose to be one of the four evangelists who penned inspired chronicles of the life of Christ!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong><em>We learn that because of Christ people of smaller talents and lesser grace can still hold useful places of service in the kingdom of God!&nbsp; </em></strong>John Mark was surrounded throughout his life by giants. Barnabas, Paul, and Peter&#8212;such giant Christians no doubt constantly reminded him of how meager and small his own talent was.&nbsp; He no doubt would have called himself a one-talent man as he compared himself to such greats! But he did not make this a reason to bury his talent. He kept on. He kept plodding. He kept serving God. And one day he became the penman of one of the four gospels! What hope and consolation and encouragement this should give to the rest of us. We also see ourselves as people of small gift, but God may also make us eminently useful like John Mark if we will be faithful to use the gift we have been given.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong><em>We learn that because of Christ you can still be greatly useful in spite of your messing up in the past!&nbsp; </em></strong>Not only did John Mark see himself as possessing very meager gifts, he surely also saw himself as having royally messed up in his past.&nbsp; And it was true.&nbsp; There was no denying it.&nbsp; Yet, despite this, Mark became greatly useful! You must not allow your view of yourself be ruled by your past messes, but by Christ&#8217;s present graces!</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/9-john-mark/">Chapter 7 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Likely and Momentous Authorship of the Gospel of Mark</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/9-john-mark/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</title>
		<link>/8-john-mark/</link>
					<comments>/8-john-mark/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 20:18:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15505</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is the 8th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter 1 Peter 5:13 reads: “She who is in Babylon, chosen together with you, sends you greetings, and so does my son, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/8-john-mark/">Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>This is the 8th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 7 parts here: <a href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">1</a>, <a href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">2</a>, <a href="/mark-career-3/">3</a>, <a href="/chapter-3-mark/">4</a>, <a href="/john-mark-5/">5</a>, <a href="/6-john-mark/">6</a>, <a href="/7-john-mark/">7</a>.</em></p>



<h2><strong>Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</strong></h2>



<p>1 Peter 5:13 reads: “She who is in Babylon, chosen together with you, sends you greetings, and so does my son, Mark.” No serious doubt may be entertained that Peter here refers to the John Mark we have been studying.&nbsp; And he refers to him in the most affectionate terms. He calls him “his son.” Most conservative scholars date 1 Peter around AD 64-65. Thus, this remark of the Apostle Peter may have taken place a year or two before that of Paul’s remark in AD 67, but at about the same time.</p>



<p>We learn, then, that John Mark’s reputation had been rehabilitated not only with Paul and the wing of the church that he led.&nbsp; It had also been restored in the part of the church led by Peter. What a clear testimony to the renewed usefulness and respected status of John Mark in the early church!</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn that by the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ you can receive deliverance from past sins and not be doomed by your past mistakes!&nbsp; </em></strong>The example of John Mark ought to encourage those who live with a sneaking suspicion that they have forfeited God’s best for their lives. It should give hope to those who think that their past mistakes have condemned them to a useless life and sad existence. If deliverance could come through Christ to John Mark, it can come to you.</p>



<p>But this statement is not the greatest testimony to God’s restoring grace in John Mark’s remarkable career. That is rather his authoring of the Gospel of Mark. We will consider that in the next blog.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/8-john-mark/">Chapter 6 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Subsequent and Significant Relation with the Apostle Peter</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/8-john-mark/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 4 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Pivotal and Tragic Place in the Disagreement between Barnabas and Saul</title>
		<link>/6-john-mark/</link>
					<comments>/6-john-mark/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 21:55:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15496</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chapter 4 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Pivotal and Tragic Place in the Disagreement between Barnabas and Saul This is the 6th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 5 parts here: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. It is the account of the disagreement between Barnabas and Saul in Acts 15:37-39 [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/6-john-mark/">Chapter 4 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Pivotal and Tragic Place in the Disagreement between Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3><strong>Chapter 4 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Pivotal and Tragic Place in the Disagreement between Barnabas and Saul</strong></h3>



<p><em>This is the 6th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 5 parts here: <a href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">1</a>, <a href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">2</a>, <a href="/mark-career-3/">3</a>, <a href="/chapter-3-mark/">4</a>, <a href="/john-mark-5/">5</a>.</em></p>



<p>It is the account of the disagreement between Barnabas and Saul in Acts 15:37-39 which we are now considering. It is not my purpose to analyze that disagreement in detail. We do need to look at it with regard to our present purpose of understanding the life of John Mark.</p>



<p><em>Acts 15:37 Barnabas wanted to take John, called Mark, along with them also. 38 But Paul kept insisting that they should not take him along who had deserted them in Pamphylia and had not gone with them to the work. 39 And there occurred such a sharp disagreement that they separated from one another, and Barnabas took Mark with him and sailed away to Cyprus.</em></p>



<p>Have you ever thought about this situation from the viewpoint of John Mark? I had not until I was thinking about it recently. Ask yourself, What would it have been like for John Mark in this situation? He was rejected by the Apostle Paul; the cause of sharp disagreement between Paul and Barnabas; the subject of prolonged discussion between Paul and Barnabas; and—no doubt—the focus of public conversation in the Christian community at Jerusalem. You can imagine how difficult the situation became for John Mark!&nbsp; Whatever we think of Barnabas leaving as he did, leaving was almost a necessity for John Mark.&nbsp; How could he stay in Jerusalem?&nbsp; He would be the occasion of disagreement, discussion, suspicion, and endless questions.&nbsp; This would not be good for him or for the church. Barnabas’s decision to take John Mark with him to Cyprus and get him out of this emotional pressure-cooker—whatever else it was—was a deliverance for John Mark. It removed him from a very difficult, perhaps unbearable, and certainly embarrassing situation.&nbsp; Far away in Cyprus where this difficulty was not well-known, John Mark might have time to pray, reflect, and, if necessary, to repent.</p>



<p>At this point in our account of the life of John Mark one could not be blamed for thinking that any usefulness for John Mark was finished.&nbsp; The days of effective labor for the kingdom would never return for John Mark—that is what we must, it would seem, necessarily conclude. Nevertheless, praise God, the career of John Mark turned out much differently than we might have expected or feared.</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn how easy it is to be stained with a bad reputation and the difficulties it may create for you!&nbsp; </em></strong>Can you imagine people shaking their heads at the mention of John Mark? Abandoning the Lord, deserting the missionaries, he was thought to be unstable as water. And then the terrible disagreement it provoked between Paul and Barnabas! What a scandal and he was in the middle of it! Little and surely not sufficiently had John Mark the difficulties that would result from his unstable desire to run home to Momma in Jerusalem. And perhaps the most spiritually deadly aspect of it all was that John Mark deeply struggled with believing this assessment and agreeing with the worst opinion of himself.</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn how badly we need sympathetic Christian brothers to help us see our sins and repent and find restoration through Christ! </em></strong>I cannot resist the notion that Barnabas, the son of encouragement, was the means in no small measure of John Mark’s recovery. He took John Mark to a place where he could recover.&nbsp; He gave him the sympathetic ear which enabled him not to be crushed into despair by his sins. I am sure he was faithful to guide him to the place of repentance, faith, and forgiveness in Christ.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/6-john-mark/">Chapter 4 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Pivotal and Tragic Place in the Disagreement between Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/6-john-mark/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career Continued—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</title>
		<link>/john-mark-5/</link>
					<comments>/john-mark-5/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 19:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15322</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career Continued—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul In the last blog we looked at how John Mark began his travels with Barnabas and Paul.&#160; In this blog we considered the text which speaks of the sad conclusion of those travels. Acts 13:13 Now Paul and his [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-mark-5/">Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career Continued—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career Continued—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</h2>



<p>In the last blog we looked at how John Mark began his travels with Barnabas and Paul.&nbsp; In this blog we considered the text which speaks of the sad conclusion of those travels.</p>



<p><em>Acts 13:13 Now Paul and his companions put out to sea from Paphos and came to Perga in Pamphylia; but John left them and returned to Jerusalem.</em></p>



<p>Now, by itself, you might not put a negative construction on John’s departure from Barnabas and Saul recorded here.&nbsp; The text merely says that John departed.&nbsp; There is no necessary negative connotation to place upon this word.&nbsp; One might, in fact, imagine good reasons for him to return to Jerusalem. There is, however, good reason to think that this decision on John’s part was not one to be admired.&nbsp; Why must we say this? There are several reasons.</p>



<ul><li>First and notoriously, the Apostle Paul saw it in a very negative light. Famously, he resisted the idea of taking John Mark along on the proposed second missionary journey.&nbsp; In Acts 15:38 he describes John Mark’s departure in Acts 13:13 as “desertion.” Paul uses a word that can even in some cases mean to apostatize. Paul surely would not have reacted so firmly to a departure that was justifiable.</li><li>Second, the decision of John Mark to leave for Jerusalem seems double-minded.&nbsp; He had agreed to accompany and help the missionaries.&nbsp; We may assume that this help was felt necessary for them and this experience was deemed important to his development.&nbsp; Yet, before the missionary journey was hardly begun, John heads for home. It seemed like desertion to Paul and probably to everybody else.&nbsp; He judged it to reveal instability in John’s character. Yes, Barnabas was willing to forgive and forget. That was his big-hearted generosity as the son of encouragement (Acts 4:36). Paul could not regard such “flakiness” so lightly.</li><li>Third, while I do not believe that we should judge Barnabas too harshly, the fact is that there seems to be a precipitous or rushed feeling about Barnabas taking John Mark and leaving for Cyprus in Acts 15.&nbsp; On the other hand, Luke takes the time to tell us that Paul and Silas were committed by the brethren to the grace of Lord.&nbsp; There is no such notation with regard to Barnabas and John when they left for Cyprus.&nbsp; Once more, this seems to say that the generality of the church in Jerusalem agreed with Paul’s reservations about John Mark.&nbsp; This means that they also felt that there was a kind of “desertion” in John’s departure from the missionaries.</li></ul>



<p>There is, then, another red flag raised about John Mark in our passage.&nbsp; Not only had he deserted the Lord in the Garden, he had deserted the missionaries in Cyprus. Of such repeated events reputations are made.&nbsp; This reputation was not a good one.</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn the dreadful consequences of abandoning your solemn responsibilities and how shameful it is to do so!&nbsp; </em></strong>Do you think that Mark ever thought he would bring on himself the kind of shame that he did by deserting the missionaries?&nbsp; Who knows what easy rationalizations he had for doing so? But the shame that he brought upon himself surely was a constant reminder of his unfaithfulness.</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn also that anyone—no matter their religious pedigree or background may fall into unfaithfulness!</em></strong>&nbsp; John Mark was at the center of the Christian movement.&nbsp; He had physically seen the Lord.&nbsp; He had been in the house when the Last Supper was celebrated.&nbsp; He was the close relative of prominent Christians.&nbsp; Yet he forsook his post and proved unfaithful.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/john-mark-5/">Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career Continued—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/john-mark-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</title>
		<link>/chapter-3-mark/</link>
					<comments>/chapter-3-mark/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 15:04:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15296</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul When I speak of Mark’s “interesting” and “abortive” travels with Barnabas and Saul, I have three texts in mind.&#160; In this blog I want to look at them in order of their occurrence in the Book of Acts. The first [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/chapter-3-mark/">Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</strong></p>



<p>When I speak of Mark’s “interesting” and “abortive” travels with Barnabas and Saul, I have three texts in mind.&nbsp; In this blog I want to look at them in order of their occurrence in the Book of Acts. The first is …</p>



<p><em>Acts 12:25 And Barnabas and Saul returned from Jerusalem when they had fulfilled their mission, taking along with them John, who was also called Mark.</em></p>



<p>Remember that Barnabas and Saul had been in Jerusalem on a relief mission from Antioch because of the famine in Jerusalem. While Barnabas had renewed his acquaintance with Mark, his cousin. Perhaps the emissaries from Antioch had even stayed at the home of Mary, the aunt of Barnabas.&nbsp; It would at least have been natural for them to do so. Somehow during their stay in Jerusalem, the idea had been birthed that it would be good for John Mark to accompany Barnabas and Saul back to Antioch.&nbsp; If we are right about the young man in Mark’s gospel being John Mark himself, then a dozen years later Mark had to be in his mid-20’s at least.</p>



<p><em>Acts 13:5 When they reached Salamis, they began to proclaim the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews; and they also had John as their helper.</em></p>



<p>We are informed in this text that John accompanied Barnabas and Saul on the first missionary journey.&nbsp; Nothing is said of this in the account in verses 1-3. In verse 4 it is Barnabas and Saul who are sent out by the Holy Spirit. They were the missionaries—not John Mark.</p>



<p>But, we are told, they had John as their “helper.” A great deal of discussion has taken place with regard to the exact role John occupied in the missionary band and what it meant for him to be their “helper.”&nbsp; Let me say a number of things about this that may help to clear up this question.</p>



<ul><li>First, let me tell you about the word, helper. Its literal meaning originally was <em>under-rower</em>. It referred to a very subordinate seaman—a rower of the lowest rank. But this meaning had probably receded into the background by Luke’s day.&nbsp; By then it simply emphasized that someone was an underling or subordinate.&nbsp; John is thus identified somewhat emphatically as the subordinate of Barnabas and Saul—one who supported them in their role as missionaries.</li><li>Second, consider what his subordinate-servant-helper role might have involved more specifically. <em>Well, actually I think it is wrong to be very specific.&nbsp; It involved many things and might have developed in important respects.</em> It certainly involved taking care of all the menial and mundane tasks that would have distracted Barnabas and Saul from their main ministerial and missionary responsibilities. What such tasks might have involved in that day and age I do not know exactly. But without telephones and laptops and internet there were no doubt many errands to be run, many messages to be carried, and many things to be purchased in the local marketplace.&nbsp;</li></ul>



<p>But did John Mark assist in more spiritual and ministerial ways?&nbsp; I think it is possible that he did.&nbsp; Certainly, if someone began to ask questions about the gospel, John Mark was, on the basis of his personal experience, in a position to answer many such questions.&nbsp; Though it is clear that he would not have been one of the main speakers and preachers, he likely would have occasionally assisted in such roles as well.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Furthermore, I think it is likely that in connection with such occasional, spiritual assistance that Barnabas and Saul intended John Mark’s traveling with them to be a maturing experience. They probably hoped that he would develop as a Christian minister and missionary.&nbsp; We do not need to assume that John Mark’s role was static.&nbsp; The goal might have been for him to assist at first mainly with the menial and mundane tasks of life that would distract Barnabas and Saul, but also under their mentoring gradually to develop as a minister of the gospel.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Now there is a word for this that we use in the church today.&nbsp; We call a person who fulfills a similar role an intern.&nbsp; We have a pastoral intern at GRBC. What does he do? The old joke is <em>Anything your pastors do not want to do</em>! More accurately I should say, anything that your pastors do not have time to do without distraction. He puts together the notes for the semi-annual meeting. He runs errands for us that we do not have time to take care of. He assists with and upgrades the website—a task that none of us can get to.&nbsp; He is a kind of diaconal assistant.&nbsp; But we also hope to see him develop as a minister of the gospel.&nbsp; Thus, he speaks at the nursing home for us.&nbsp; Thus also, he may teach an adult SS class or two for us in the near future.&nbsp; This is what our intern does.&nbsp; He is our own John Mark.&nbsp; Of course, we hope that he turns out better in his role than John Mark did in his. But that thought brings us to the third and last text of this third chapter of John Mark’s life.&nbsp; We will consider that text and the conclusion of this chapter of John Mark’s life in our next blog.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/chapter-3-mark/">Chapter 3 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Interesting and Abortive Travels with Barnabas and Saul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/chapter-3-mark/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 2 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—Relation and Position in the Church at Jerusalem (Acts 12:12)</title>
		<link>/mark-career-3/</link>
					<comments>/mark-career-3/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 16:20:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15287</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chapter 2 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—Relation and Position in the Church at Jerusalem (Acts 12:12) We left John Mark huddled in his home in Jerusalem. We discover him again in the same exact location about twelve years later.&#160; Not only is the place the same, the occasion is similar.&#160; It is another occasion of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mark-career-3/">Chapter 2 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—Relation and Position in the Church at Jerusalem (Acts 12:12)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>Chapter 2 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—Relation and Position in the Church at Jerusalem (Acts 12:12)</h2>



<p>We left John Mark huddled in his home in Jerusalem. We discover him again in the same exact location about twelve years later.&nbsp; Not only is the place the same, the occasion is similar.&nbsp; It is another occasion of threatening persecution.&nbsp; Acts 12:12 reads: “And when he realized this, he went to the house of Mary, the mother of John who was also called Mark, where many were gathered together and were praying.”</p>



<p>Remember that James, the brother of John and one of the Sons of Thunder, had just before this prayer meeting been put to death by Herod.&nbsp; Peter himself had then been arrested and imprisoned just before Passover. This was the very same time of year that Jesus had been arrested.&nbsp; It was probably about twelve years later.&nbsp; Herod was probably waiting till after Passover to bring him to trial and then execution. Many Christians were gathered at the house of Mary the mother of John Mark to pray.&nbsp; This Mary must have been the aunt of Barnabas if John Mark was Barnabas’s cousin. I am persuaded that this was very likely the very house in the upper room of which the Last Supper had been held.&nbsp; Luke makes a point of introducing John Mark in his account of the early church on this occasion.&nbsp;</p>



<p>You see how deeply John Mark was associated with the church in Jerusalem.&nbsp; He occupied a deep relationship to and central place in the original church at Jerusalem and among the original disciples of Christ.&nbsp; If we understand that, then what happens next will not surprise us!</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mark-career-3/">Chapter 2 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—Relation and Position in the Church at Jerusalem (Acts 12:12)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mark-career-3/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Remarkable Career of John Mark and What It Says Especially To Pastors and Pastoral Students: Pt. 2 &#8211; His Probable and Improbable Escapade as a Young Man (Mark 14:51-52)</title>
		<link>/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/</link>
					<comments>/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 15:09:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15247</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>His Probable and Improbable Escapade as a Young Man (Mark 14:51-52) Look first at Mark 14:51-52: “A young man was following Him, wearing nothing but a linen sheet over his naked body; and they seized him. But he pulled free of the linen sheet and escaped naked.” The Mark referenced in the title of this [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">The Remarkable Career of John Mark and What It Says Especially To Pastors and Pastoral Students: Pt. 2 &#8211; His Probable and Improbable Escapade as a Young Man (Mark 14:51-52)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>His Probable and Improbable Escapade as a Young Man (Mark 14:51-52)</h2>



<p>Look first at Mark 14:51-52: “A young man was following Him, wearing nothing but a linen sheet over his naked body; and they seized him. But he pulled free of the linen sheet and escaped naked.” The Mark referenced in the title of this gospel is, of course, John Mark.&nbsp; We will look later at the reasons why we say this and the significance of this, but right now it is important because it impacts the interpretation of these somewhat obscure verses.</p>



<p>I have called this escapade or peculiar incident <strong><em>both probable and improbable</em></strong>.&nbsp; Let me explain why.</p>



<p><strong><em>It is probable in the sense that this is probably Mark’s own cryptic reference to himself in his gospel. </em></strong>Why do I say this?&nbsp; Why do I believe that this a reference to John Mark himself? My foundation for believing this is that this story is found in the Gospel of Mark himself.</p>



<ul><li>There are similar cryptic references in the Gospel of John to John the author of that gospel.&nbsp; Cf. John 19:26-27. Just as John did not name himself in his gospel, so also modesty forbid Mark to say with reference to the young man in this story, “This young man was I.”</li><li>This account of the young man fleeing naked from the Garden of Gethsemane is only given in Mark.&nbsp; The implication is that this incident had some particular importance for Mark. That particular importance is easily explained if the young man was Mark himself.&nbsp; Hendriksen says: “Neither Matthew nor Luke has retained this item. It does not appear to have been of special interest to them. But to Mark, to him alone, it was of sufficient importance to be included in the Gospel. This is understandable if he himself was that young man.”</li><li>The story told here of the young man really does seem a somewhat strange thing to include in the gospel story. What might be important about this crazy and madcap story of a young man streaking naked late at night through the streets of Jerusalem? This strangeness disappears, however, if the young man was Mark himself.&nbsp; Once more Hendriksen remarks: “By itself the item is rather insignificant, except if it refers to what the author, Mark, himself experienced that solemn night.”</li></ul>



<p>Bottom-line?&nbsp; This young man was probably John Mark himself. That is the most <strong><em>probable</em></strong> interpretation of the passage. On the other hand …</p>



<p><strong><em>It is improbable, because this story contains details which are strange and peculiar.</em></strong>&nbsp; Let me just recount it, and you will see what I mean.&nbsp; The setting of this story in the Gospel of Mark follows the account of the Garden of Gethsemane. That ended, you remember, with the flight of the disciples after Jesus’s arrest. We are then told that another follower of Jesus was there in the Garden. He had sneaked off from his home after the Last Supper following Jesus and the eleven.&nbsp; Most likely he had been in bed asleep or trying to sleep when he heard them all leaving.&nbsp; This means that the very old tradition that the Last Supper was held in the home of Mary the mother of John Mark is probably true.&nbsp; If he had been in bed in the very house where the Last Supper was held by Jesus and his disciples, this would explain both the fact that he follows Jesus and the eleven and that he was wearing nothing but a linen.&nbsp; That is the broad meaning of the Greek word used here. This linen was either a linen bed sheet; or it could also possibly be a linen undergarment or even pajamas. Cf. the use of this word in Proverbs 31:24 (where it means garment) and Luke 23:53 (where it is used of the sheet in which Jesus body was wrapped.) This very young man followed Jesus and the eleven. He saw the arrest of Jesus and the flight of the disciples from the darkness of his hiding place.&nbsp; Then he was spotted by someone in the crowd sent to arrest Jesus.&nbsp; They actually seized him and got their hands on him.&nbsp; But slipping off his linen (whether it was a sheet, undergarment, or pajamas), he was able to escape.&nbsp; His escape was both dramatic and accomplished with not a little agility and dexterity. It was also entirely lacking in dignity. We are forced to imagine him late at night streaking stark naked through the streets of Jerusalem and finally rushing into his home and perhaps huddling and shuddering in bed from the near and close escape.&nbsp; Now certainly this is a weird, wacky, and bizarre story that makes us shake our heads and, in spite of the seriousness of the event of Jesus’ death, smile at the naked streaker as he flees from the Garden through the streets of Jerualem to his home.</p>



<p><strong>What are we supposed to make of all this practically? &nbsp;</strong>Why does Mark include this account? Of course, it had personal importance for him, but he must have felt it was significant for his readers as well. Why did he think it was important to include in his account of the gospel?</p>



<ul><li>John Mark is confessing humbly his own fear and flight. Perhaps he is deprecating himself by making a little joke at his own expense. At any rate, he is saying that like the other disciples he too had been a spiritual coward. He also had fled the scene of Jesus’s capture and abandoned the Savior.</li><li>At the same time, perhaps he felt that his escape, cowardly though it was, was also due to the providential protection of God who allowed the other disciples to escape as well. Jesus had told the crowd which had come to arrest him to let his disciples go (John 18:8). Mark no doubt saw his escape as arranged also by the providence of the Son of God. He wants to glorify God for his escape.</li><li>Another spiritual lesson of this account would surely be to underscore the majestic bravery of Jesus as compared to the fearfulness of His disciples.&nbsp; Hendriksen speaks in this connection of the “unshakable and majestic composure of Jesus.”</li><li>But more directly to our purposes, we begin to learn something about John Mark.&nbsp; He is a young disciple growing up in the very middle of the historical revelation of the gospel. He is there at the Last Supper—at least in the house.&nbsp; He is there in the Garden of Gethsemane.&nbsp; He is a witness, though not in the same sense as the apostles of Christ, of the original facts of the gospel.&nbsp; He is also revealed to be what we might call a curious coward.&nbsp; He is inquisitive and adventurous enough to follow Jesus to the Garden of Gethsemane late at night. Yet he is a fickle and fearful young man. At the cost of the loss of his dignity and self-respect, he runs away from the arrest of Jesus and abandons him.</li></ul>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">The Remarkable Career of John Mark and What It Says Especially To Pastors and Pastoral Students: Pt. 2 &#8211; His Probable and Improbable Escapade as a Young Man (Mark 14:51-52)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Remarkable Career of John Mark And What it Says Especially to Pastors &#038; Pastoral Students: Pt. 1 &#8211; The Bible Tells Stories About People</title>
		<link>/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/</link>
					<comments>/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 22:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New Testament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Mark]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pastors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Students]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15185</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Bible Tells Stories About People One of the special things about the Bible is that it tells stories—stories not just about God, but about human beings. This makes it much more interesting actually than the Koran which simply provides saying after saying and is in my opinion not only terribly wrong but deadly boring.&#160; [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">The Remarkable Career of John Mark And What it Says Especially to Pastors &#038; Pastoral Students: Pt. 1 &#8211; The Bible Tells Stories About People</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>The Bible Tells Stories About People</h2>



<p>One of the special things about the Bible is that it tells stories—stories not just about God, but about human beings. This makes it much more interesting actually than the Koran which simply provides saying after saying and is in my opinion not only terribly wrong but deadly boring.&nbsp; Usually stories in the Bible about particular persons are told in one book.&nbsp; Sometimes you will get the same story in two books of the Bible.&nbsp; Occasionally, as in the supremely important story of the Christ, these stories are told in four gospels.</p>



<p>But the story of the person I want to talk about in this blog series is actually told in bits and pieces across the New Testament. It is not told in any one, continued account. These bits and pieces of the story I have in mind are told in six books of the New Testament.&nbsp; This is the unusual way in which the Holy Spirit decided to tell the story of the man called, John Mark.</p>



<p>I have been preaching on the Book of Acts on and off for a couple of years now to GRBC Owensboro.&nbsp; Recently, I took the time to enlarge on the little statement in Acts 13:5 about John Mark. It reads as follows: “When they reached Salamis, they began to proclaim the word of God in the synagogues of the Jews; and they also had John as their helper.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>As I have studied the references to this man in the New Testament, I have divided the story told of his life into seven chapters.&nbsp; I have entitled them, <em>The Remarkable Career of John Mark.</em>&nbsp; But before I come to that, there are a couple of things to be said by way of introduction:</p>



<p>The first thing is that there are actually four different Johns in the New Testament.&nbsp;</p>



<ul><li>The first and least known John is the father of Simon Peter. He is only mentioned in the Gospel of John. Cf. John 1:42; 21:15-17.</li><li>The second is well-known. It is John the Baptist, the forerunner of Jesus.&nbsp; He is the son of Zacharias and Elizabeth, the relative of Mary, the mother of Jesus.</li><li>There is John the Apostle, the brother of James.&nbsp; James and John were “the Sons of Thunder” and the sons of Zebedee.</li><li>There is also John Mark. As we will discover, he was the cousin of Barnabas.</li></ul>



<p>We will discover a great deal about John Mark from the several mentions of him in the New Testament.&nbsp; But there is something else you need to know.</p>



<p><strong><em>John Mark is not always identified in the same way.</em></strong>&nbsp; There are passages that refer to him as John Mark (Acts 12:12, 25; 15:37). There are passages that refer to him as John (Acts 13:5; 13). And there are passages that refer to him simply as Mark (Acts 15:39; Col. 4:10; Phm. 1:24; 2 Tim. 4:11; 1 Pet. 5:13). There is even a passage which I think speaks of him without giving us his name (Mark 14:51-52).</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">The Remarkable Career of John Mark And What it Says Especially to Pastors &#038; Pastoral Students: Pt. 1 &#8211; The Bible Tells Stories About People</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
