<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Ephesians 1:4 &#8211; Where does the phrase &#8220;in love&#8221; belong?	</title>
	<atom:link href="/ephesians-14-where-does-the-phrase-in-love-belong/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/ephesians-14-where-does-the-phrase-in-love-belong/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 06:57:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Richard Daniels		</title>
		<link>/ephesians-14-where-does-the-phrase-in-love-belong/#comment-211</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Daniels]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 06:57:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=770#comment-211</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Just a couple more comments more directly in response to Hoehner.  First, to say &quot;within the present context the verbs and participles describing God’s actions always precede the qualifying phrases&quot; begs the question.  Secondly, in most (not all) the examples cited they have to follow because they actually complete the particular verb and do not merely modify it.  In love may give a reason why I was engaged to my fiance, but &quot;to my fiance&quot; belongs to the verb &quot;engaged&quot; in a sense that &quot;in love&quot; does not.  The same can be said for most of the other examples cited.  I.e., &quot;to adoption&quot; is inseperable from predestined, describing the destination of it, but not modifying it in the sense that &quot;in love&quot; would provide a reason for the action but the action is &quot;predestining to adoption&quot; not an open-ended predestination.  Of course redemption is through his blood; you wouldn&#039;t expect Paul to say, &quot;through his blood, redemption.&quot;   Point: if the phrases naturally follow as completing the thought of the verb, one cannot argue that modifying phrases must be following phrases.&quot; 


All that having been said, however, I did check out the Greek (Nestle)and EVERY other occasion for &quot;en agape&quot; in the N.T. (all but one are from Paul) was about the human exercise of divine love except Eph. 3:17, which I think undoubtedly refers to the love of Christ (cf 3:19) It is also found in Jude 21 &quot;in the love of God,&quot; which is another debated one.

This second point of your argument is the stronger, I believe. Thanks again for making me re-think this, even though it means I may just have to change my exposition of the passage.   

BTW I keep enjoying and profiting from the facebook contributions very much, even though I don&#039;t get around to commenting on many.  Keep up the great work.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Just a couple more comments more directly in response to Hoehner.  First, to say &#8220;within the present context the verbs and participles describing God’s actions always precede the qualifying phrases&#8221; begs the question.  Secondly, in most (not all) the examples cited they have to follow because they actually complete the particular verb and do not merely modify it.  In love may give a reason why I was engaged to my fiance, but &#8220;to my fiance&#8221; belongs to the verb &#8220;engaged&#8221; in a sense that &#8220;in love&#8221; does not.  The same can be said for most of the other examples cited.  I.e., &#8220;to adoption&#8221; is inseperable from predestined, describing the destination of it, but not modifying it in the sense that &#8220;in love&#8221; would provide a reason for the action but the action is &#8220;predestining to adoption&#8221; not an open-ended predestination.  Of course redemption is through his blood; you wouldn&#8217;t expect Paul to say, &#8220;through his blood, redemption.&#8221;   Point: if the phrases naturally follow as completing the thought of the verb, one cannot argue that modifying phrases must be following phrases.&#8221; </p>
<p>All that having been said, however, I did check out the Greek (Nestle)and EVERY other occasion for &#8220;en agape&#8221; in the N.T. (all but one are from Paul) was about the human exercise of divine love except Eph. 3:17, which I think undoubtedly refers to the love of Christ (cf 3:19) It is also found in Jude 21 &#8220;in the love of God,&#8221; which is another debated one.</p>
<p>This second point of your argument is the stronger, I believe. Thanks again for making me re-think this, even though it means I may just have to change my exposition of the passage.   </p>
<p>BTW I keep enjoying and profiting from the facebook contributions very much, even though I don&#8217;t get around to commenting on many.  Keep up the great work.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Richard Daniels		</title>
		<link>/ephesians-14-where-does-the-phrase-in-love-belong/#comment-210</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Richard Daniels]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 05:36:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=770#comment-210</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I appreciate the case made here, and will have to think more on it, but just to broach another consideration.  If we imagine that Paul would have thought like a speaker of Hebrew, even though writing in Greek, it is not hard to imagine that the idea of foreknowledge would carry with it the idea of a preceeding love (rather than having prior information).  With this in mind, &quot;In love he predestinated,&quot; is a perfect parallel to &quot;whom he foreknew he predestinated&quot; of Rom. 8:29, also Peter&#039;s &quot;elect according to the foreknowledge of God.&quot;  Also, Paul seems to be turning the gem of grace and looking at its facets in this passage, and so the blessing of grace is related to the gracious disposition of God which issues in that gift of grace (cf. also 2:4-7).  All is &quot;according to the riches of his grace,&quot; &quot;according to his purpose&quot; &quot;according to the purpose of his will.&quot;  If &quot;in love&quot; is taken to modify the nearest antecedent, then it would appear that &quot;in love&quot; modifies US, and refers to the character of our holiness and blamelessness which would be consistent with his teaching elsewhere (3:17; 4:15-16; Col. 3:12-14 and of course 1 Cor. 13), but to me it seems to break too much the God-centered character of the doxology of Eph. 1.  Still, you have given me cause to re-think.  Thanks.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I appreciate the case made here, and will have to think more on it, but just to broach another consideration.  If we imagine that Paul would have thought like a speaker of Hebrew, even though writing in Greek, it is not hard to imagine that the idea of foreknowledge would carry with it the idea of a preceeding love (rather than having prior information).  With this in mind, &#8220;In love he predestinated,&#8221; is a perfect parallel to &#8220;whom he foreknew he predestinated&#8221; of Rom. 8:29, also Peter&#8217;s &#8220;elect according to the foreknowledge of God.&#8221;  Also, Paul seems to be turning the gem of grace and looking at its facets in this passage, and so the blessing of grace is related to the gracious disposition of God which issues in that gift of grace (cf. also 2:4-7).  All is &#8220;according to the riches of his grace,&#8221; &#8220;according to his purpose&#8221; &#8220;according to the purpose of his will.&#8221;  If &#8220;in love&#8221; is taken to modify the nearest antecedent, then it would appear that &#8220;in love&#8221; modifies US, and refers to the character of our holiness and blamelessness which would be consistent with his teaching elsewhere (3:17; 4:15-16; Col. 3:12-14 and of course 1 Cor. 13), but to me it seems to break too much the God-centered character of the doxology of Eph. 1.  Still, you have given me cause to re-think.  Thanks.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
