<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Student Profiles | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/student-profiles/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 20:00:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Student Profiles | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>A Letter from CBTS Graduate</title>
		<link>/letter-from-cbts-graduate/</link>
					<comments>/letter-from-cbts-graduate/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 20:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Student Profiles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1681</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Eric Coher is a recent graduate of&#160;Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary, having received our&#160;Master of Arts in Theological Studies&#160;degree. In the letter below, Eric writes about his studies with us. Dear Prayer Partners and Supporters, As I reflect back over the past few years of my theological training at&#160;Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary&#160;(CBTS), I am both humbled [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/letter-from-cbts-graduate/">A Letter from CBTS Graduate</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Eric Coher is a recent graduate of&nbsp;<a href="/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>, having received our&nbsp;<a href="/academics/program-offerings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Master of Arts in Theological Studies</a>&nbsp;degree. In the letter below, Eric writes about his studies with us.</em></p>
<p>Dear Prayer Partners and Supporters,</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" alt="" src="https://ci5.googleusercontent.com/proxy/SnGEiWpFPMFF0C7B2_k5GYknv5XTg5TS9r0JD3uXYoEJcx81Af0YW1N77Mlo5noAfZicVKK4AOcFuPFNg1eLSiV7TRmFFIwT00Cu2_MMsiOt0Boufng0D5Vx-haj2nAkS7GFPh2QMtPujXxIYsl9ZGAXXyXFLDqZH-3X_Ww=s0-d-e1-ft#https://gallery.mailchimp.com/11118de60955d83b1e4e6bea8/images/4e13d5e6-c784-498a-8ba0-c1082ac6a3f5.jpg" width="175" height="175" align="right">As I reflect back over the past few years of my theological training at&nbsp;<a href="/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>&nbsp;(CBTS), I am both humbled and immensely blessed by the instruction that I received. As a full-time pastor, I was unable to uproot my family and leave my church to pursue seminary. Consequently, I was thrilled to learn that there was an institution right in my &#8220;backyard&#8221; that was theologically orthodox, distinctively reformed, and academically rigorous. CBTS provided an opportunity for me to pursue a theological education while simultaneously serving in the local church. This meant that not only did I benefit from what I was learning, but the sparks of my education fell on those who sat under my teaching, preaching, counseling, and discipleship.</p>
<p>While CBTS was the vehicle for my theological training, it was the men who invested in my education for which I am most grateful.&nbsp; Each professor, resident or visiting, that I had the privilege of learning from sought to equip my mind, challenge my heart, encourage my soul, and better prepare me to shepherd the flock of God. They deeply cared for, intentionally thought for, and loved me well in very tangible ways. Being surrounded by men who passionately love Christ, valiantly uphold the truth of the gospel, and desire to see the Church rooted, built up, and established has served crystalize my calling, chisel my theological convictions, hone my spiritual gifts. In short, I am a better husband, father, pastor, shepherd, teacher, counselor, disciple-maker, and friend as a result of my seminary training at CBTS!</p>
<p>At the end of the day, having a degree on the wall or letters following my name is insignificant. What is significant, on the other hand, is the sharpening that I received through my studies at CBTS. The instruction that I received will help me to better fulfill Paul&#8217;s exhortation, &#8220;Him we proclaim, warning everyone and teaching everyone with all wisdom, that we may present everyone mature in Christ&#8221; (Colossians 1:28 ESV).</p>
<p>For the glory of Christ and the beauty of His Bride,<br />
Eric C. Coher,&nbsp;Associate Pastor<br />
<a href="http://fbcevansville.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Faith Bible Church</a><br />
Evansville, IN</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/letter-from-cbts-graduate/">A Letter from CBTS Graduate</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/letter-from-cbts-graduate/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Another Encouraging Letter from CBTS Student</title>
		<link>/letter-from-cbts-student/</link>
					<comments>/letter-from-cbts-student/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2015 19:30:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student Profiles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1662</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dear Prayer Partners and Supporters, In God&#8217;s good providence, being a distance learning student at&#160;Covenant Baptist&#160;Theological Seminary&#160;has helped me grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ in ways that I would have never imagined otherwise. If I could summarize into one concrete thought what the seminary has done for my soul [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/letter-from-cbts-student/">Another Encouraging Letter from CBTS Student</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dear Prayer Partners and Supporters,</p>
<p>In God&#8217;s good providence, being a distance learning student at&nbsp;<a href="http://goo.gl/yDzNo4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Covenant Baptist&nbsp;Theological Seminary</a>&nbsp;has helped me grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ in ways that I would have never imagined otherwise. If I could summarize into one concrete thought what the seminary has done for my soul it would be this &#8211;<em>it has made my soul abound with love for the bride of Christ, the church</em>. She is ruddy but beautiful and she is being adorned by her Lord with splendor, majesty, and glory. He is making her the fragrance of Christ to the world (Song 4:7, 16; 2 Cor. 2:15).&nbsp;Hallelujah!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" class="alignright" alt="" src="https://gallery.mailchimp.com/11118de60955d83b1e4e6bea8/images/20a0d6c2-704f-471b-bf94-f371559dfb5f.jpg" width="175" height="177" align="right">My soul has come to see these truths more vividly through the seminary&#8217;s&nbsp;<a href="http://goo.gl/KpUV2t" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Basic Training Program</a>. This program has helped me step into seminary life at a pace that isn&#8217;t intimidating, but rather encouraging. The program is designed to give aspiring pastors a taste for what seminary studies are like and to aid in discerning the will of the Lord regarding education. I have found the material refreshing, challenging, edifying and encouraging. Every book recommended for course material is a keeper. Every professor is worth his weight in gold. Best of all, the orthodoxy of the courses is supplemented by the orthopraxy required of the program in the local church. This has tended to keep me balanced with regard to learning at the seminary level, and it gives me an outlet for the things I am learning to be used in the building up of the body.</p>
<p>Distance learning from a technical standpoint for some can be intimidating, but CBTS has streamlined this processing using a&nbsp;<a href="http://www.cbtspathway.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">step-by-step path</a>&nbsp;for prerecorded material, and simple&nbsp;<a href="http://new.livestream.com/cbtseminary" target="_blank" rel="noopener">video streaming</a>&nbsp;for live courses. If you can navigate the popular video sharing websites out there you can easily work your way through the courses.</p>
<p>Recently my local fellowship partnered with CBTS in their&nbsp;<a href="http://goo.gl/zoj4Em" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Church Partnership Program</a>&nbsp;which has, by God&#8217;s good grace, relieved me of many seminary costs. Imagine that! Top notch Reformed Baptist studies paid for once your church partners with the seminary. The cost for partnership is extremely reasonable, by the way. Praise God for His infinite, matchless grace! If there are men in your congregation that are aspiring to the ministry then the Church Partnership Program is an excellent way to receive godly instruction at a great price. It also opens the door up for your church to receive material to use in instructing the church (great options for deeper studies).</p>
<p>At CBTS it is truly informed scholarship with a pastoral heart. Someone once said that burning hearts are not nourished by empty heads. If your heart is burning to learn Christ, in whom are hidden all the treasures of wisdom and knowledge, then there is no better place to set your mind on things that are above.</p>
<p>Grace and Peace to You All,<br />
Scott Autry<br />
<a href="http://www.rockdalecommunitychurch.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Rockdale Community Church</a><br />
Conyers, GA</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/letter-from-cbts-student/">Another Encouraging Letter from CBTS Student</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/letter-from-cbts-student/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Encouraging Letter from MCTS Student</title>
		<link>/letter-mcts-student/</link>
					<comments>/letter-mcts-student/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2014 16:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Student Profiles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1513</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>To the Prayer Partners and Supporters of MCTS, I have been taking classes at MCTS as a distance learning student since September 2012. Even though I have only taken a few classes up to this point in my education, what I have learned has been indispensable for me in my role as an associate pastor [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/letter-mcts-student/">Encouraging Letter from MCTS Student</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To the Prayer Partners and Supporters of MCTS,</p>
<p>I have been taking classes at MCTS as a distance learning student since September 2012. Even though I have only taken a few classes up to this point in my education, what I have learned has been indispensable for me in my role as an associate pastor at my church.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://gallery.mailchimp.com/11118de60955d83b1e4e6bea8/images/Ron_Wood.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="200" align="right">Dr. Waldron&#8217;s&nbsp;<a href="http://www.mctspathway.com/school/catalog/course/systematic-theology/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Systematic Theology</a>&nbsp;class was the first class that I took. From a technical and interactive standpoint, I didn&#8217;t know what to expect with an online class because I have taken online classes before where I didn&#8217;t really feel much connection with the professor. I was pleasantly surprised with how this class was run. Even though I was almost a thousand miles away in Orlando, Florida, I felt as if I was in the classroom the whole time. The video and audio worked extremely well and Dr. Waldron&#8217;s consistency of allowing the distance-learning students to ask questions and then answering them himself was very beneficial. From a theological standpoint, I was massively encouraged by the depth of the content and the opportunity that this would give me to turn around and share with those in my congregation the great truths of the Christian faith.</p>
<p>My second class was&nbsp;<a href="http://www.mctspathway.com/school/catalog/course/pastoral-counseling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pastoral Counseling</a>&nbsp;with Dr. Tedd Tripp, and my first trip to Owensboro. Dr. Tripp&#8217;s many years of pastoral counseling made this class extremely edifying for me, as well as equipping me for the consistent counseling that I do here at my local church. The foundation that he laid in this class of the Bible&#8217;s sufficiency to answer all matters of faith and life has strengthened my resolve to completely trust the Word of God in each and every counseling situation that I face.</p>
<p>The most recent class that I took (and my second trip to Owensboro) was&nbsp;<a href="http://www.mctspathway.com/school/catalog/course/biblical-theology-i/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Biblical Theology</a>&nbsp;with Dr. Richard Barcellos. Starting from Genesis and working through Revelation, Dr. Barcellos clearly explained to us why the Bible must be viewed as one book that is all about the glory of Jesus Christ. Having taken this class, I feel much more equipped in how to help people in my congregation to accurately study the Word of God.</p>
<p>On behalf of the MCTS students, I would like to say thank you for your continued prayers and financial support of this God-honoring, theological institution. When I share with people the quality of teaching that I am getting and the price that I am paying for it, they are astounded. That wouldn&#8217;t be possible without God using you to help us. May God continue to bless this school and its desire to see men sufficiently trained so that they in turn may equip the saints for the work of ministry.</p>
<p>In Christ,<br />
Pastor Ron Wood<br />
<a href="http://www.faithbaptistorlando.com/Index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Faith Baptist Church</a><br />
Orlando, Florida</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/letter-mcts-student/">Encouraging Letter from MCTS Student</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/letter-mcts-student/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MCTS Student Profile: Blake Cassell</title>
		<link>/mcts-student-profile-blake-cassell/</link>
					<comments>/mcts-student-profile-blake-cassell/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Oct 2010 03:33:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Student Profiles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/?p=161</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Believing myself called to Christian ministry, I returned from the foreign mission field in 2007 ready to pursue further ministry training. I had assumed I would be going to a large, denominationally-run seminary....</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-student-profile-blake-cassell/">MCTS Student Profile: Blake Cassell</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-162  aligncenter" title="blake" src="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2010/10/blake1.jpg" alt="" width="430" height="242"></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Believing myself called to Christian ministry, I returned from the foreign mission field in 2007 ready to pursue further ministry training. I had assumed I would be going to a large, denominationally-run seminary which has a reputation for training thoughtful, doctrinally-correct ministers. I assumed this was the only way that a young man who cared about being doctrinally precise could adequately prepare to serve the church. Finding myself attending Heritage Baptist Church, Owensboro, KY, I was somewhat skeptical of their small ministerial training school. However, after becoming more familiar with the program of study at the Midwest Center, I began to consider it an option. I realized that I knew of all the men on the faculty and that these men had been used mightily of God both in local church ministry as well as in more academic theological pursuits.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">I was sold after I caught the vision of completing my education in the context of a local church setting. As I began to think about it, I realized that training in a small, local church setting has definite advantages. A common pitfall for some seminarians is to disconnect from a local church body. Even those who faithfully attend and serve in a local church setting don&#8217;t benefit from an organic connection like I have at MCTS.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">My two main MCTS professors, Drs. Waldron and Barcellos, are also my pastors. These men teach me the skills needed to carefully exegete the Scriptures as well as the theology of Christian Orthodoxy. In addition, my theological education is organically connected to a local church body. My professors are greatly concerned that their students not be just well-informed, but that they would be men qualified according to 1 Timothy 3. As my pastors, my professors get to see me serving the body and evaluate my gifts and fitness for ministry over a significant period of time.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">However, my professors are not handing down a &#8220;cold, dead orthodoxy.&#8221; MCTS&#8217;s motto is &#8220;Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart&#8221; and that is what I have seen from these men. My professors have invited me into their lives and I have seen men who have a great burden and love for the sheep given to them by God. My professors are always careful to remind us that the purpose of our studies is to know God better in order to make Him better known, with the ultimate goal of helping to fulfill the Great Commission.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Through Pastoral Mentoring, monthly Table Talk sessions, and accompanying the pastors as they minister to the congregation, MCTS students get an up close look at the &#8220;nuts and bolts&#8221; of local church ministry. The small size of MCTS that I looked upon with suspicion before has become the greatest benefit of my education so far!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In addition to all of these benefits, MCTS hosts guest professors and lecturers who are among the leaders of Reformed Christianity. I have had wonderful opportunities to sit under the teaching of some of the best Reformed minds today. Through godly and brilliant pastor/professors, as well as leading guest professors, I feel confident that I am being well-prepared for ministry in a local church.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-student-profile-blake-cassell/">MCTS Student Profile: Blake Cassell</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mcts-student-profile-blake-cassell/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
