<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Mike Horton: What is the Gospel?	</title>
	<atom:link href="/mike-horton-what-is-the-gospel/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/mike-horton-what-is-the-gospel/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2011 20:03:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Brandon Q.		</title>
		<link>/mike-horton-what-is-the-gospel/#comment-170</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Brandon Q.]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2011 20:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=676#comment-170</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I think that it&#039;s clear from Romans 10:16 that we obey the Gospel by believing it. It says, &#039;But they have not all obeyed the gospel. For Isaiah says, &quot;Lord, who has believed what he has heard from us?&quot;&#039; When Paul uses that phrase, he&#039;s talking about faith. How do you obey news? You believe it!

That being said, I think using the phrase, &quot;DO the gospel&quot; is helpful. I agree that categorically, we actually &quot;do&quot; the law. But, it&#039;s helpful to talk about &#039;doing&#039; the Gospel, because that makes it clear where our motivation and spiritual resources come from to do good works. Usually, when people talk about &quot;DOING the gospel&quot; they mean working out the social implications of the Gospel. We should care for poor people, because when we were spiritually poor, Jesus cared for us. We love people that don&#039;t deserve it, because that&#039;s how Jesus loved us. We pray for and forgive our enemies, because that&#039;s what Jesus did for us. We care for orphans, because we are spiritually adopted. Etc.

I think that we must keep the Law and the Gospel separate in some respects, but not in others. They are co-dependent and very intertwined. When James refers to the &quot;Law of Liberty&quot; in chapters 1&#038;2 of his epistle, I believe that he&#039;s talking about the Gospel, but in &quot;law&quot; terms. We indeed are to &quot;live out&quot; the Gospel. We are to &quot;Gospel&quot; others. The Gospel, the good news is primarily one of radical love to sinners from God. When we &quot;do&quot; that Gospel, we are simply bending that love out to our fellow man. That&#039;s why our good works are evidence of our faith. To the degree we aren&#039;t showing love for others, we don&#039;t understand the love of God to us. I hope that all made sense..   :)]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think that it&#8217;s clear from Romans 10:16 that we obey the Gospel by believing it. It says, &#8216;But they have not all obeyed the gospel. For Isaiah says, &#8220;Lord, who has believed what he has heard from us?&#8221;&#8216; When Paul uses that phrase, he&#8217;s talking about faith. How do you obey news? You believe it!</p>
<p>That being said, I think using the phrase, &#8220;DO the gospel&#8221; is helpful. I agree that categorically, we actually &#8220;do&#8221; the law. But, it&#8217;s helpful to talk about &#8216;doing&#8217; the Gospel, because that makes it clear where our motivation and spiritual resources come from to do good works. Usually, when people talk about &#8220;DOING the gospel&#8221; they mean working out the social implications of the Gospel. We should care for poor people, because when we were spiritually poor, Jesus cared for us. We love people that don&#8217;t deserve it, because that&#8217;s how Jesus loved us. We pray for and forgive our enemies, because that&#8217;s what Jesus did for us. We care for orphans, because we are spiritually adopted. Etc.</p>
<p>I think that we must keep the Law and the Gospel separate in some respects, but not in others. They are co-dependent and very intertwined. When James refers to the &#8220;Law of Liberty&#8221; in chapters 1&amp;2 of his epistle, I believe that he&#8217;s talking about the Gospel, but in &#8220;law&#8221; terms. We indeed are to &#8220;live out&#8221; the Gospel. We are to &#8220;Gospel&#8221; others. The Gospel, the good news is primarily one of radical love to sinners from God. When we &#8220;do&#8221; that Gospel, we are simply bending that love out to our fellow man. That&#8217;s why our good works are evidence of our faith. To the degree we aren&#8217;t showing love for others, we don&#8217;t understand the love of God to us. I hope that all made sense..   🙂</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Pastor Alpheus Atkins		</title>
		<link>/mike-horton-what-is-the-gospel/#comment-169</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pastor Alpheus Atkins]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2011 15:10:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=676#comment-169</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How does 2 Thess. 1:8 &#038; 1 Peter 4:17 fit with Dr. Horton&#039;s theme that we do not &quot;do&quot; the Gospel, if the Bible claims we are to &quot;obey&quot; the Gospel?

Sincerely,
Pastor Alpheus Atkins
Blacksburg Va.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>How does 2 Thess. 1:8 &amp; 1 Peter 4:17 fit with Dr. Horton&#8217;s theme that we do not &#8220;do&#8221; the Gospel, if the Bible claims we are to &#8220;obey&#8221; the Gospel?</p>
<p>Sincerely,<br />
Pastor Alpheus Atkins<br />
Blacksburg Va.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
