<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Missions | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/missions/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 19:00:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Missions | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Important New Missions Documentary</title>
		<link>/important-new-missions-documentary/</link>
					<comments>/important-new-missions-documentary/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 19:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Audio/Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1366</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Today, Red Futon Films released the official trailer for an important new documentary on missions to be released next month: Half-Devil Half-Child. If you care at all about the spread of the gospel among Muslim peoples around the world, then you will not want to miss this documentary. The trailer gives you a taste of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/important-new-missions-documentary/">Important New Missions Documentary</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today, <a title="Red Futon Films" href="http://redfutonfilms.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Red Futon Films</a> released the official trailer for an important new documentary on missions to be released next month: <a title="Half-Devil Half-Child" href="http://www.halfdevilhalfchild.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>Half-Devil Half-Child</em></a>. If you care at all about the spread of the gospel among Muslim peoples around the world, then you will not want to miss this documentary. The trailer gives you a taste of this critical issue in international missions today:</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/OlVG2FQCfl8?rel=0" frameborder="0" width="560" height="315"></iframe></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/important-new-missions-documentary/">Important New Missions Documentary</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/important-new-missions-documentary/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 5)</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness-5/</link>
					<comments>/should-we-witness-5/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 15:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Evangelism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1331</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Matthew 12:30a says:  “He who is not with Me is against Me…”  This is the uncompromising assertion of the text.  What we may call the unmistakable amplification of these words comes next:  “and he who does not gather with Me scatters.”  The implication that every Christian must and does have a heart and concern for [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/should-we-witness-5/">Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Matthew 12:30a says:  “He who is not with Me is against Me…”  This is the <em>uncompromising assertion</em> of the text.  What we may call the <em>u</em><em>nmistakable amplification</em> of these words comes next:  “and he who does not gather with Me scatters.”  The implication that every Christian must and does have a heart and concern for evangelism finds <em>indisputable confirmation</em> in the rest of the New Testament.  1 Cor. 10:33-11:1 says:  “Just as I also please all men in all things, not seeking my own profit but the <em>profit </em>of the many, so that they may be saved.  Be imitators of me, just as I also am of Christ.”</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p>All of this then requires that we think about the <em>unavoidable application</em>.  It is this:  Every Christians must and does have a heart for biblical evangelism.   This heart must be at the center of the lifestyle of every Christian.  Let me mention several specific applications of this.</p>
<p><em>1.       Biblical evangelism is an important responsibility of every Christian.</em></p>
<p>No Christian can exempt himself from the requirement of our text.  Each of us—the text clearly implies—have the responsibility to be gathering with Christ.</p>
<p><em>2.       Biblical evangelism is an identifying mark of every Christian.</em></p>
<p>The main point of our text is not, however, that Christians <em>should</em> gather with Christ.  It is that Christians <em>do</em> gather with Christ.  Every Christian gathers with Christ.  That is to say, biblical evangelism is his lifestyle.  He has a heart to see men gathered to Christ.  His heart is manifested in some efforts in his life to gather men to Christ.</p>
<p>Now I do not say what I have just said lightly.  I say it carefully.  I say it trembling for myself and for those I love.  Having a heart for biblical evangelism is a necessary mark of being a Christian.  If you rarely or never think about the salvation of the lost, if you have no concern for them or for the glory of Christ in their salvation, if you have no heart to gather with Christ, then I may tell you, I must tell you, straightforwardly that you are no Christian.</p>
<p><em>3.       Biblical evangelism is a means of grace for every Christian.</em></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p>Some struggle a great deal with assurance of your salvation.  One reason may be that you are not giving yourself to this responsibility and grace as you ought.  Start doing something to gather with Christ.  John Piper once articulated at “Together for the Gospel” the common experience of Christians when they have an opportunity to speak for Christ:  He said after such an opportunity which God had given him that he went home thinking: <em>I really am a Christian!</em></p>
<p><em>4.       Biblical evangelism may not be what you think.</em></p>
<p>The text defines evangelism as gathering with Christ.  Passing out tracts or going door to door may be good for some people.  “From scratch” evangelistic conversations may be possible for some gifted Christians.  They may not work out well for the rest of us.  They may not be societally or culturally effective ways of promoting the gospel of Christ.  So let me give you some advice about how to do biblical evangelism.</p>
<ul>
<li>Biblical evangelism is consistent with and promoted by the diligent pursuit of your callings.  Some think of their jobs as a hindrance to evangelism or even as an alternative to evangelism. For some the best way to do biblical evangelism is to do as well as you can at your vocations and professions.  This will open doors to gather with Christ to you.</li>
<li>Biblical evangelism means cultivating relationships with unconverted people.  One good way to do that is by showing mercy to people and ministering to their felt needs.</li>
<li>Biblical evangelism means plugging your gifts into an evangelistically minded local church and supporting others with better evangelistic gifts than our own.  This thought has often encouraged and motivated me to use whatever gifts I have for my local church.  I end on the point which I made in my first blog.  We must not think of thee work of evangelism individualistically, but as the work of the church, the body of Christ.  We can gather with Christ by using the gifts God has given us in the church which is His body.</li>
</ul>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/should-we-witness-5/">Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 5)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/should-we-witness-5/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 4)</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness-4/</link>
					<comments>/should-we-witness-4/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2012 15:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Evangelism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1329</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Matthew 12:30a says:  “He who is not with Me is against Me…”  This is the uncompromising assertion of the text.  What we may call the unmistakable amplification of these words comes next:  “and he who does not gather with Me scatters.”  The implication that every Christian must and does have a heart and concern for [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/should-we-witness-4/">Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Matthew 12:30a says:  “He who is not with Me is against Me…”  This is the <em>uncompromising assertion</em> of the text.  What we may call the <em>u</em><em>nmistakable amplification</em> of these words comes next:  “and he who does not gather with Me scatters.”  The implication that every Christian must and does have a heart and concern for evangelism finds <em>indisputable confirmation</em> in the rest of the New Testament.</p>
<p>Notice 1 Corinthians 10:33 &#8211; 11:1:  “Just as I also please all men in all things, not seeking my own profit but the <em>profit </em>of the many, so that they may be saved.  Be imitators of me, just as I also am of Christ.”</p>
<p>1 Corinthians 9:1-11:1 among other things is speaking of how Paul gave up the exercise of His Christian liberty in order to work for the salvation of men.  He as an Apostle of Christ had joined Christ in the great mission of gathering men.  In the text to which I have turned you we learn that it is not just Apostles or Pastors or even some group of elite Christians who must join Christ in this work of gathering.  Immediately upon saying that he tried to please all men in all things in order that they may be saved, he proceeds to call the Corinthian church as a whole to imitate his lifestyle.  In living a lifestyle of trying to gather men to Christ, he says, I am following Christ.  He says to them, <em>Now I call you to imitate my lifestyle, just as I am trying to imitate His.</em> What is the lesson?  He who is not with me is against me.  He who does not gather with me scatters.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/should-we-witness-4/">Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/should-we-witness-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 3)</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness-3/</link>
					<comments>/should-we-witness-3/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2012 15:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Evangelism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1325</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Matthew 12:30a says:  “He who is not with Me is against Me…”  This is the uncompromising assertion of the text.  What we may call the unmistakable amplification of these words comes next:  “and he who does not gather with Me scatters.”  In these words Jesus amplifies and explains what he means by being with him [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/should-we-witness-3/">Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Matthew 12:30a says:  “He who is not with Me is against Me…”  This is the <em>uncompromising assertion</em> of the text.  What we may call the <em>u</em><em>nmistakable amplification</em> of these words comes next:  “and he who does not gather with Me scatters.”  In these words Jesus amplifies and explains what he means by being with him and not against him.  Being with Christ means gathering with Him.  Being against Christ means scattering.  Both the word, gather, and the word, scatter, need careful explanation.</p>
<p><em>Gather</em></p>
<p>The verb translated, gather, here is used 59 times in the New Testament.  24 of these, or about 40% of the entire total uses in the New Testament, are in Matthew.  Parallel uses in Matthew to the one in our text are these:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Matthew 3:12</strong> &#8220;His winnowing fork is in His hand, and He will thoroughly clear His threshing floor; and He will gather His wheat into the barn, but He will burn up the chaff with unquenchable fire.&#8221;</li>
<li><strong>Matthew 13:30</strong> &#8220;Allow both to grow together until the harvest; and in the time of the harvest I will say to the reapers, &#8216;First gather up the tares and bind them in bundles to burn them up; but gather the wheat into my barn.'&#8221;</li>
<li><strong>Matthew 13:47</strong> &#8220;Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a dragnet cast into the sea, and gathering <em>fish </em>of every kind.&#8221;</li>
<li><strong>Matthew 18:20</strong> &#8220;For where two or three have gathered together in My name, I am there in their midst.&#8221;</li>
<li><strong>Matthew 22:10</strong> &#8220;Those slaves went out into the streets and gathered together all they found, both evil and good; and the wedding hall was filled with dinner guests.&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>Listen to other relevant uses of “gather” in the New Testament.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>John 4:36</strong> &#8220;Already he who reaps is receiving wages and is gathering fruit for life eternal; so that he who sows and he who reaps may rejoice together.&#8221;</li>
<li><strong>John 11:52</strong> and not for the nation only, but in order that He might also gather together into one the children of God who are scattered abroad.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><em> </em></p>
<p>Evangelism biblically defined is to gather men into Christ and His people.  Every Christian needs to have in a part in that work and gather with Christ!</p>
<p><em> </em></p>
<p><em>Scatter</em></p>
<p>The verb translated, scatter, is also an important New Testament word with a meaning you may not immediately understand.</p>
<p>It is used of the dispersion of the Jews under the judgment of God.</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Ezekiel 5:12</strong> &#8216;One third of you will die by plague or be consumed by famine among you, one third will fall by the sword around you, and one third I will scatter to every wind, and I will unsheathe a sword behind them.</li>
</ul>
<p>It is used of what a wolf does to a flock of sheep.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>John 10:12</strong> &#8220;He who is a hired hand, and not a shepherd, who is not the owner of the sheep, sees the wolf coming, and leaves the sheep and flees, and the wolf snatches them and scatters <em>them</em>.</li>
<li><strong>John 16:32</strong> &#8220;Behold, an hour is coming, and has <em>already </em>come, for you to be scattered, each to his own <em>home</em>, and to leave Me alone; and <em>yet </em>I am not alone, because the Father is with Me.</li>
</ul>
<p>The bottom-line is that gathering is the work of a shepherd or friend, while scattering is the work of a wolf or enemy.</p>
<p>Jesus in Matthew 12:30 describes His ministry and work in the world as gathering men.  He gathers them first to Himself as the good shepherd of their souls.  But he also gathers them together into His church—the place or fold where He can protect His sheep from the wolf.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>John 10:16</strong> &#8220;I have other sheep, which are not of this fold; I must bring them also, and they will hear My voice; and they will become one flock <em>with </em>one shepherd.&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>To gather with Christ, then, is to join Him in his effort to gather sheep into the safety of His protection.  This includes ultimately gathering them into the safety of the fold, a reference to His church.  To scatter is to act the part of a wolf and oppose Christ’s work and mission in the world.  Only certain destruction can befall such a wicked sinner and enemy of Christ.</p>
<p>Hendriksen argues:</p>
<blockquote><p>To be “with” Jesus means to be instrumental in gathering people to be his followers (Prov. 11:30; Dan. 12:3; Matt. 9:37, 38; Luke 19:10; John 4:35, 36; 1 Cor. 9:22).  To be “against” him means to be unwilling to follow him in his mission to gather the lost.  It means to leave them in their shepherdless, scattered condition, an easy prey for Satan.</p></blockquote>
<p>EGNT contains this comment:</p>
<blockquote><p>But in all cases, when one man scatters what another gatheres their aims and interests are utterly diverse.  Satan is the arch-waster, Christ the collector, Saviour.</p></blockquote>
<p>All this is confirmed by the context of Jesus’ assertion here in Matthew 12.  The Pharisees opposed Christ and attempted to scatter what He was gathering by claiming that He was doing what He did by the power of Satan.  In so rejecting the miraculous evidence of the Spirit to Jesus’ divine mission and identity, they were bringing upon themselves a sin that could never be forgiven.  But Christ states in our text a further thought.  Anyone who does not join Him in the work of bringing salvation to the world is actually on the side of His enemies.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/should-we-witness-3/">Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/should-we-witness-3/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 2)</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness-2/</link>
					<comments>/should-we-witness-2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2012 15:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Evangelism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1322</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>My first blog post on &#8220;witnessing&#8221; for Christ might leave the impression that I am among those who suggest that evangelism is something only pastors and/or those with a special call to evangelism need to worry about.  I am not.  In fact, I think the Bible raises serious questions about the genuineness of a person’s [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/should-we-witness-2/">Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 2)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My first blog post on &#8220;witnessing&#8221; for Christ might leave the impression that I am among those who suggest that evangelism is something only pastors and/or those with a special call to evangelism need to worry about.  I am not.  In fact, I think the Bible raises serious questions about the genuineness of a person’s Christianity if he has no heart or concern for evangelism.  A text I came across in my devotions a few years ago raises such questions.  It has triggered in me a deeper insight into my own failures and a determination to be a more biblical Christian in this area.  That text is Matthew 12:30.  In the NASB it reads this way:  “He who is not with Me is against Me; and he who does not gather with Me scatters.”</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p>Notice <strong><em>the uncompromising assertion</em></strong> found in the text:  “He who is not with Me is against Me.”</p>
<p>On the surface the first half of Matthew 12:30 might seem to require little explanation.  It is straightforward:  “He who is not with Me is against Me.”  It teaches that with regard to commitment to Christ there is no neutrality.  You are with Him or you are against Him.</p>
<p>But some may be thinking of a passage which utters a sentiment which seems exactly opposite to the one contained in our text.  What about Mark 9:40: &#8220;For he who is not against us is for us”?  What about Luke 9:50: “But Jesus said to him, &#8220;Do not hinder <em>him</em>; for he who is not against you is for you.&#8221;  You may want to look at one of these passages.</p>
<p>In these passages a man is casting out demons in the name of Jesus, and the disciples try to stop him.  In response Jesus tells them not to hinder him and gives the reason that he who is not against us is for us.  This is clearly a very different situation than the one in our text.  The Pharisees here claimed that Jesus was casting out demons by Beelzebul, the prince of demons.  Jesus is actually saying ion Mark 9:40 and Luke 9:50 that if a man is using my name to cast out demons, then you should not oppose him because he is actually for our cause and helping in my work.  Jesus does not mean in these texts, then, that if a man is simply neutral then he is not against us.  The man in question in these other texts is clearly not neutral.  He is actually proclaiming the name of Christ as a name of power by which to do miracles.  <em>In this way he is actually gathering with Christ.</em></p>
<p>Lenski supports this view when he says:  “In the battle against Satan every man who does not side with Jesus is against Him and for Satan.  Luke 9:50 and Mark 9:40 agree with this view: for to do a miracle or a kind deed &#8216;in Jesus name&#8217; is neither neutral nor hostile to Jesus.”</p>
<p>The real point of both in Matthew 12 and its parallel passage in Luke 11:23 is this reality that there is no neutrality with regard to Christ:  &#8220;He who is not with Me is against Me; and he who does not gather with Me, scatters.”  There is no neutrality with regard to Christ or his mission in the world.  You are either supportive of it and join with Christ in it.  Or you are his enemy.</p>
<p>Alford remarks:  “As usual, this saying of our Lord reached further than the mere occasion to which it referred, and spoke forcibly to those many half-persuaded hesitating persons who flattered themselves that they could strike out a line equally avoiding the persecution of men and the rejection of Christ.”</p>
<p>MacArthur concurs:  “It is not necessary to oppose Christ in order to be <strong>against</strong> Him; it is only necessary <strong>not</strong> to be <strong>with</strong> Him.  Nor is it necessary to actively interfere with His work in order to be one who <strong>scatters</strong>; it is only necessary to <strong>not gather with</strong> Him.”</p>
<p>Many think they are neutral with regard to Christ.  They say, “I’m not against Jesus!”  I think it would be hard to find a person in my Bible-belt county who would say <em>I am against Jesus. </em>But the question is whether they have entrusted their never-dying soul to him as Savior?  Are they gathering with Him?  Jesus says,  “If you are not with me, you, my dear lady, my dear girl, my dear child, my dear young man, my dear man, are against me.” There is no neutrality with regard to Christ.  If you do not follow Him, you fight Him.  If you have not committed your soul to Him, you have rejected Him, and you must unavoidably face the consequences!</p>
<p>Men must aspire to be with Christ in all the other He has appointed.  They must be with Him in baptism, in the church, and in his mission to the world.  If we are really with Christ, then we ought to be with Him in every way you can!</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/should-we-witness-2/">Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 2)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/should-we-witness-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 1)</title>
		<link>/should-we-witness/</link>
					<comments>/should-we-witness/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2012 14:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecclesiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Practical Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Evangelism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1303</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>As I read books on missions and evangelism, I often feel that important, biblical distinctions are getting lost in the shuffle.  The New Testament root which in its verbal infinitive form means to witness or testify is often and without explanation applied to the whole church and to the activity of the church’s evangelism or [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/should-we-witness/">Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 1)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As I read books on missions and evangelism, I often feel that important, biblical distinctions are getting lost in the shuffle.  The New Testament root which in its verbal infinitive form means to witness or testify is often and without explanation applied to the whole church and to the activity of the church’s evangelism or speaking of the gospel to the world.  Let me hasten to say that I do believe that the whole church till the end of the age is called to the work of evangelism and missions.  I just don’t think that the word used to describe our evangelism and missions in the New Testament is witnessing-testifying.  Let me explain why.</p>
<p>Several forms of the root meaning witness or testify are used as follows in the NT:</p>
<p>19 witness or testimony (<em>marturion</em>)<br />
76 bear witness or testify (<em>martureo</em>)<br />
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">35 witnesser or testifier </span>(<em>martur</em>)<br />
130 uses of this root in the NT</p>
<p>As I have said, we commonly use this word of the activity and duty of Christians in general.  When we speak the gospel we say that we are “witnessing” for Christ.  Witnessing is speaking the truth of the gospel to sinners.  While this may be a “natural” extension of the uses of this word in the New Testament, <em>the root is never used this way in the NT</em>.  The reason for this is that the root denotes personal or eye-witness.  Here is how the BAG defines the word for one who witnesses (<em>martur</em>):</p>
<blockquote><p><em>witness</em>—<strong>1. </strong>in a legal sense Mt 18:16; Mk 14:63; Ac 6:13; 7:58; Heb 10:28.—<strong>2. </strong>in a nonlegal sense, esp. in reference to attestation in response to noteworthy performance or communication Lk 11:48; Ac 1:8, 22; 26:16; Ro 1:9; 2 Cor 1:23; 1 Ti 6:12; Heb 12:1; 1 Pt 5:1; Rv 11:3.—<strong>3. </strong>of one whose witness or attestation ultimately leads to death (the background for the later technical usage ‘martyr’) Ac 22:20; Rv 1:5; 2:13; 3:14; 17:6. [pg 122]</p></blockquote>
<p>A witness is (1) one who in trial is qualified to give testimony on the basis of personal or eye-witness.  Or (3) it is one who is a witness by giving his life because of his testimony to Christ.  Or (2) it is someone who can attest to the truth of some important event.  This second category might seem to offer some support to the popular usage, but when the texts cited are examined, none of them actually do.  In several of them, for instance, God is called to witness (Romans 1:9) or the reference is to the Apostles as witnesses (Acts 1:8, 22).</p>
<p>Witness is one of the names for the office of apostle of Christ in the New Testament. Acts 1:22 affirms:  “… beginning with the baptism of John until the day that He was taken up from us&#8211; one of these <em>must <strong>become</strong></em> a witness with us of His resurrection.&#8221;  Likewise Acts 10:41 asserts:  “not to all the people, but to witnesses who were chosen beforehand by God, <em>that is</em>, to us who ate and drank with Him after He arose from the dead.”  Cf. also Acts 1:8; 10:39.</p>
<p>All Christians cannot in the above sense bear witness to Christ.  Only Apostles can!  I suspect that this is why it is never used in the NT of the kind of speaking of the gospel incumbent on all Christians.  We are not all eye-witnesses of the gospel.  Our “testimony” is not the testimony of the gospel.  The testimony is not what we say about the gospel.  It is what the apostles say about the gospel.  <strong><em>It is the gospel.</em></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Acts 4:33: And with great power the apostles were giving testimony to the resurrection of the Lord Jesus, and abundant grace was upon them all.</li>
<li>1 Corinthians 1:6: even as the testimony concerning Christ was confirmed in you</li>
<li>1 Timothy 2:6: who gave Himself as a ransom for all, the testimony <em>given </em>at the proper time.</li>
<li>2 Timothy 1:8: Therefore do not be ashamed of the testimony of our Lord or of me His prisoner, but join with <em>me </em>in suffering for the gospel according to the power of God</li>
</ul>
<p>Our “testimony” is only our affirmation of “the testimony of the gospel.” True, every Christian has some experience of the gospel.  To this experience he can bear personal testimony.  (It is after all his experience.)  But this is not what the NT ever means by this important word.  Our experience is not the same as the gospel testimony.</p>
<p>“So,” I can hear someone demand of me, “if our duty is not to <em>testify</em> to the gospel, what is it?  Are you saying that it is not the duty of Christians to tell the gospel to the world?”  Well, great question!  I do believe that it is every Christian’s duty to participate in the mission of the church to the world and as he has opportunity himself to speak the gospel to the world.  There is, furthermore, a NT word which is used frequently of what every Christian—indeed every person who would be saved—must do with regard to speaking of the gospel to the world.  It is the word confess (<em>homologeo</em>).</p>
<ul>
<li>Matthew 10:32: &#8220;Therefore everyone who confesses Me before men, I will also confess him before My Father who is in heaven.&#8221;</li>
<li>Luke 12:8: &#8220;And I say to you, everyone who confesses Me before men, the Son of Man will confess him also before the angels of God.&#8221;</li>
<li>John 9:22: His parents said this because they were afraid of the Jews; for the Jews had already agreed that if anyone confessed Him to be Christ, he was to be put out of the synagogue.</li>
<li>Romans 10:9: that if you confess with your mouth Jesus <em>as </em>Lord, and believe in your heart that God raised Him from the dead, you will be saved</li>
<li>Romans 10:10: for with the heart a person believes, resulting in righteousness, and with the mouth he confesses, resulting in salvation.</li>
<li>1 Timothy 6:12: Fight the good fight of faith; take hold of the eternal life to which you were called, and you made the good confession in the presence of many witnesses.</li>
<li>1 John 2:23: Whoever denies the Son does not have the Father; the one who confesses the Son has the Father also.</li>
<li>1 John 4:15: Whoever confesses that Jesus is the Son of God, God abides in him, and he in God.</li>
</ul>
<p>It would be more biblical and less confusing of biblical categories if we began to call Christians to confess Christ before the world, rather than calling them to “testify” to Christ.  Testifying to Christ is something which they can only do in a way that sits very loose to the meaning of this word in the NT.  It would make for more clarity in a lot of books and preaching on missions if the New Testament distinction between testimony and confession was more carefully kept in mind.</p>
<p>One problem with simply taking the witness of Acts 1:8 and willy-nilly applying it to all Christians is that we lose the corporate character of the Great Commission.  We cannot “bear witness” to the gospel as private or individual Christians.  We can only participate in the mission of the church built on the apostolic witness.  The Great Commission is given to the church built on the apostles and prophets (Eph. 2:20).  Remembering this helps us to keep clear that the Great Commission is given to the church corporately.  Every private Christian individually is not responsible to go into all the world, make disciples, baptize them, and teach them to observe all that Christ commanded.  The church is responsible to do that, and every Christian is required to have a heart for that mission of the church and to be a vital part of a church which is on that mission.  The body of Christ is to take the gospel to all nations, and every Christian is to participate in that mission <em>in accordance with who God has made him as a gifted member of the body of Christ</em>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/should-we-witness/">Should We Witness for Christ? (Part 1)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/should-we-witness/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>5</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Theology Matters: Dr. Waldron Teaching in Colombia</title>
		<link>/theology-matters-teaching-in-colombia/</link>
					<comments>/theology-matters-teaching-in-colombia/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 15:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Theology Matters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Divito]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1188</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In this week&#8217;s Theology Matters, Dr. Sam Waldron discusses his recent opportunity to teach in Colombia. adminCBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/theology-matters-teaching-in-colombia/">Theology Matters: Dr. Waldron Teaching in Colombia</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this week&#8217;s Theology Matters, Dr. Sam Waldron discusses his recent opportunity to teach in Colombia.</p>
<p><object width="440" height="330"><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true"><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"><param name="movie" value="http://vimeo.com/moogaloop.swf?clip_id=32025141&amp;server=vimeo.com&amp;show_title=0&amp;show_byline=0&amp;show_portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff&amp;fullscreen=1&amp;autoplay=0&amp;loop=0"></object></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/theology-matters-teaching-in-colombia/">Theology Matters: Dr. Waldron Teaching in Colombia</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/theology-matters-teaching-in-colombia/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Serving Christ in Namibia, Africa</title>
		<link>/serving-christ-in-namibia-africa/</link>
					<comments>/serving-christ-in-namibia-africa/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2011 15:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Divito]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Namibia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1128</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dear Brothers and Sisters in Christ, Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ! Dr. Richard Barcellos and I were privileged to serve our Savior in Namibia, Africa earlier this month. At the request of several Reformed Baptist pastors and missionaries, we were asked to equip pastors and church [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/serving-christ-in-namibia-africa/">Serving Christ in Namibia, Africa</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dear Brothers and Sisters in Christ,</p>
<p>Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ!</p>
<p>Dr. Richard Barcellos and I were privileged to serve our Savior in Namibia, Africa earlier this month. At the request of several Reformed Baptist pastors and missionaries, we were asked to equip pastors and church leaders in theological training at the newly formed Grace Ministerial Academy in Windhoek. Through the week of August 8th through the 12th, Rich taught a course on Hermeneutics in the morning while I followed up in the afternoon with a course on Worldviews. We had several pastors and church leaders as students as well as a few others auditing our courses.  They were hungry to grow in their knowledge of God&#8217;s Word and our prayer is that we helped each of them to &#8220;hold firm to the trustworthy word as taught, so that he may be able to give instruction in sound doctrine and also to rebuke those who contradict it&#8221; (Titus 1:9).  One of the students made my week when he commented after one of my classes something like, &#8220;I took a class on Worldviews at [a seminary in Africa]. They taught it philisophically. You are teaching it biblically. Thank you.&#8221; I know Rich also received encouraging feedback.</p>
<p>Additionally, we both had opportunities to preach in local churches while in Namibia. Between the two of us, we preached several times at three different churches. Furthermore, Eastside Baptist Church in Windhoek asked me to teach twice during evening meetings at their church. Because I am a former Mormon, their pastors asked me to teach on Mormonism and witnessing to cultists during their midweek service. They also requested that I cover Decision Making and the Will of God at a special Thursday meeting, a topic that I care deeply about. After finishing my message on biblical decision making, the church where Rich and I preached on our second Lord&#8217;s Day in Swakopmund requested that I repeat my message at their church. By God&#8217;s grace, our preaching and teaching was warmly received. As you can see, these pastors and churches were clearly hungry to spiritually feast on God&#8217;s truth taught from His Word. Praise God!</p>
<p>We thank all of you who prayed for us while we were in Africa. The Lord definitely heard your prayers! Our travels went smoothly, we remained in good health, and our families did well while we were away. But most importantly, we were able to serve Christ and His churches in Namibia. Now we look forward to seeing the fruit of our labors. May Christ richly bless His kingdom in Namibia and beyond for His glory!</p>
<p>&#8220;Now to him who is able to do far more abundantly than all that we ask or think, according to the power at work within us, to him be glory in the church and in Christ Jesus throughout all generations, forever and ever. Amen&#8221; (Ephesians 3:20-21).</p>
<p>Because of His grace,<br />
John Divito<br />
Member, Heritage Baptist Church, Owensboro, KY<br />
Administrator, Midwest Center for Theological Studies</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/serving-christ-in-namibia-africa/">Serving Christ in Namibia, Africa</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/serving-christ-in-namibia-africa/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Please Pray for Our Training in Namibia</title>
		<link>/please-pray-for-our-training-in-namibia/</link>
					<comments>/please-pray-for-our-training-in-namibia/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2011 16:00:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Current Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hermeneutics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Divito]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Namibia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1111</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Next week, Dr. Richard Barcellos and I will be flying to Namibia, Africa to teach two modular courses to indigenous pastors and church leaders at Grace Ministerial Academy. He will be covering hermeneutics while I will handle worldviews. Please pray for us! In training these pastors, we have a wonderful opportunity but also a humbling [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/please-pray-for-our-training-in-namibia/">Please Pray for Our Training in Namibia</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-1114" title="GraceMinisterialAcademy" src="http://www.mctsowensboro.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/GraceMinisterialAcademy-300x225.jpg" alt="Grace Ministerial Academy" width="300" height="225" align="right">Next week, Dr. Richard Barcellos and I will be flying to Namibia, Africa to teach two modular courses to indigenous pastors and church leaders at <a href="http://buddyandjulianamibia.blogspot.com/2011/04/grace-ministerial-academy.html">Grace Ministerial Academy</a>. He will be covering hermeneutics while I will handle worldviews.</p>
<p>Please pray for us! In training these pastors, we have a wonderful opportunity but also a humbling responsibility entrusted to us. To help you in your prayers, I have included below my course syllabus. May we glorify Christ through the equipping of His people for the growth of His kingdom!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Christianity and Its Competitors:</strong><br />
<em>Contending for the Christian Worldview</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Course Purpose</strong><br />
The purpose of this course is to equip each pastor and church leader to &#8220;hold firm to the trustworthy word as taught, so that he may be able to give instruction in sound doctrine and also to rebuke those who contradict it&#8221; (Titus 1:9).  This will be accomplished through establishing a Biblical foundation of contending for the faith, explaining the Christian worldview, and evaluating other competing worldviews.</p>
<p><strong>Course Reading</strong><br />
James W. Sire, <em>Scripture Twisting: 20 Ways the Cults Misread the Bible</em> (Downers Grove IL, USA: Intervarsity Press, 1980).<br />
Richard Gehman, <em>Who are the Living Dead? A Theology of Death, Life After Death and the Living-Dead</em> (Nairobi, Kenya: Evangel Publishing House, 1999).</p>
<p><strong>Course Requirements</strong><br />
<em> Four Quizzes</em>: each quiz is worth 25 points, 100 points total<br />
A quiz will be given each day on Tuesday through Friday covering the previous day&#8217;s lectures.  The quizzes will have multiple choice, true or false, matching, fill-in-the-blank, short answer, and listing questions included.  Together, they will cover all of the lecture material for the course.</p>
<p><em>Final Exam</em>: each essay is worth 50 points, 100 points total<br />
A final exam will assess overall competence in the topics covered in the course. Two essay questions will be completed which integrate the course reading with critical reflection on the lecture content and supplemental material.</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Final Essay Questions</span><br />
1)	Using Sire&#8217;s <em>Scripture Twisting</em>, select ten Scripture reading errors. For each misreading, identify and define it, give an example of it from the lectures or supplemental materials (<em>not</em> included in Sire&#8217;s book), and provide a biblical response. 5 pages minimum.<br />
2)	Summarize and compare the theology of death, life after death, and the living-dead between three worldviews: 1) African Traditional Religion (using Gehman&#8217;s <em>Who are the Living Dead?</em>), 2) a Christian competitor (chosen from the course lectures or the supplemental materials), and 3) the biblical worldview. 5 pages minimum.</p>
<p><strong>Course Evaluation</strong><br />
The student&#8217;s final grade will be determined by dividing his total points earned in half. A student will have successfully completed this course by achieving a cumulative grade of 75 percent or above for his course work. The letter equivalents for the percentile grades assigned are as follows:</p>
<table border="0">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>A	&#8212;	96-100</td>
<td>B-	&#8212;	81-84</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>A-	&#8212;	91-95</td>
<td>C+	&#8212;	78-80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>B+	&#8212;	88-90</td>
<td>C	&#8212;	75-77</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>B	&#8212;	85-87</td>
<td>C-	&#8212;	71-74</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>Course Outline</strong><br />
<em>First Unit: Christianity</em><br />
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 1: Biblical Foundations</span><br />
I. 	Jude 1-4<br />
II.	1 Peter 3:14-16<br />
III.	Romans 1:18-32<br />
IV.	Acts 17:16-34<br />
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 2: The Christian Worldview</span><br />
I.	What is a Worldview?<br />
II.	What is the Christian Worldview?</p>
<p><em>Second Unit: Its Competitors</em><br />
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 1: Recognizing False Worldviews</span><br />
I. 	The Five Keys of Biblical Discernment<br />
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Part 2: Evaluating False Worldviews</span><br />
I.	Roman Catholicism<br />
II.	Prosperity Gospel<br />
III.	Seventh-Day Adventism<br />
IV.	Jehovah&#8217;s Witnesses<br />
V.	Mormonism</p>
<p><em>Appendix</em></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/please-pray-for-our-training-in-namibia/">Please Pray for Our Training in Namibia</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/please-pray-for-our-training-in-namibia/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MCTS Podcast 16: Training Pastors in Namibia</title>
		<link>/mcts-podcast-16/</link>
					<comments>/mcts-podcast-16/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2011 00:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Announcements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Missions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Divito]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MCTS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Namibia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Barcellos]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.mctsowensboro.org/?p=1050</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In this week&#8217;s video podcast, Richard Barcellos and John Divito discuss their upcoming mission trip to train pastors in Nambia: Q&#38;A with Dr. Barcellos and John Divito from MCTS on Vimeo. adminCBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-podcast-16/">MCTS Podcast 16: Training Pastors in Namibia</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this week&#8217;s video podcast, Richard Barcellos and John Divito discuss their upcoming mission trip to train pastors in Nambia:<br />
<object classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" width="400" height="300" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true"><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"><param name="src" value="http://vimeo.com/moogaloop.swf?clip_id=25374990&amp;server=vimeo.com&amp;show_title=0&amp;show_byline=0&amp;show_portrait=0&amp;color=ffffff&amp;fullscreen=1&amp;autoplay=0&amp;loop=0"></object></p>
<p><a href="http://vimeo.com/25374990">Q&amp;A with Dr. Barcellos and John Divito</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/mcts">MCTS</a> on <a href="http://vimeo.com/">Vimeo</a>.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/admin/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/admin/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">admin</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/mcts-podcast-16/">MCTS Podcast 16: Training Pastors in Namibia</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mcts-podcast-16/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
