<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Uncategorized | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/uncategorized/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Informed Scholarship with Pastoral Heart</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 17:10:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/cropped-ios-57-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Uncategorized | Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>CBTS Statement on Sexuality and Sexual Ethics</title>
		<link>/cbts-statement-on-sexuality-and-sexual-ethics/</link>
					<comments>/cbts-statement-on-sexuality-and-sexual-ethics/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2021 22:26:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=16161</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Rev. 1.19.2021 Our confession, the London Baptist Confession of Faith of 1689, in summarizing the teaching of Scripture, clearly affirms in chapter 25, paragraph 1 that “Marriage is to be between one man and one woman; neither is it lawful for any man to have more than one wife, nor for any woman to have [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/cbts-statement-on-sexuality-and-sexual-ethics/">CBTS Statement on Sexuality and Sexual Ethics</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Rev. 1.19.2021</em></p>



<p>Our confession, the London Baptist Confession of Faith of 1689, in summarizing the teaching of Scripture, clearly affirms in chapter 25, paragraph 1 that “Marriage is to be between one man and one woman; neither is it lawful for any man to have more than one wife, nor for any woman to have more than one husband.”&nbsp; It seems necessary because of the present widespread degradation of sexual morality in our culture to state our views of this matter more specifically and formally.</p>



<ul><li>We believe that the term “marriage” has only one meaning, and that is marriage sanctioned by God, which joins one genetic male and one genetic female in a single, exclusive, covenantal union, as delineated in Scripture.</li><li>We believe that God intends sexual intimacy to only occur between one genetic male and one genetic female who are married to each other. We believe that God has commanded that no intimate sexual activity be engaged in outside of a marriage between a genetic male and a genetic female.</li><li>We believe that any form of sexual immorality, such as adultery, fornication, homosexual conduct, bisexual conduct, bestiality, incest, any use of pornography or any attempt to change one’s sex, or disagreement with one’s genetic sex, is sinful and offensive to God.</li><li>We believe that God offers redemption and restoration to all who confess and forsake their sin, seeking His mercy and forgiveness through Jesus Christ.</li><li>We believe that every person must be afforded compassion, love, kindness, respect, and dignity. Hateful and harassing behavior or attitudes directed toward any individual are to be repudiated and are not in accord with Scripture nor the doctrines of the church.&nbsp;</li><li>We believe, nevertheless, in spite of the kindness to be shown to sinners, impenitence in the aforementioned sins is inconsistent with a Christian’s biblical profession of faith and conduct. Therefore, any prospective or current student of CBTS must not profess belief or impenitently act in a manner incompatible with the 1689 Confession and the above statements at the risk of denial of entry or expulsion. Any prospective or current employee of CBTS will forfeit employment eligibility if they profess belief or impenitently act in a manner incompatible with the 1689 Confession and any of the above statements.</li></ul>



<p>Major portions of Scripture from which these beliefs are drawn are as follows:&nbsp; Genesis 1:27-28; Genesis 2:18-25; Exodus 20:14; Matthew 19:3-12; Romans 1:26-27; 1 Corinthians 6:9-20; Ephesians 5:22-33; Hebrews 13:4.</p>



<p>This statement has been adapted from Section 2 of the constitution of our host church, Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. For further exposition of Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary’s views on sexuality, including affirmations and denials, please see the Nashville Statement. (<a href="https://cbmw.org/nashville-statement">https://cbmw.org/nashville-statement</a>)</p>



<p>May God help us as we seek to remain faithful to Him in proclaiming His truth in this generation. </p>



<p>The Lord Reigns, </p>



<p>John Miller, Chairman of the Board<br>Jim Savastio, Board Member<br>Mike Spickard, Board Member<br>Mike Waters, Board Member<br>Christopher Sheffield, Board Member<br>Ron Miller, Board Member<br>Ben Carlson, Board Member<br>Tom Hicks, Board Member<br>Jorge Rodriguez, Board Member<br>John Divito, Board Member<br>Jon Hueni, Board Member<br>Fred Malone, Board Member<br>Sam Waldron, President and Academic Dean<br>Rex Semrad, Dean of Students and Director of Administration<br></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/cbts-statement-on-sexuality-and-sexual-ethics/">CBTS Statement on Sexuality and Sexual Ethics</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/cbts-statement-on-sexuality-and-sexual-ethics/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Review: The Imperative of Preaching Part I &#124; D. Scott Meadows</title>
		<link>/scott-meadows-imp-1/</link>
					<comments>/scott-meadows-imp-1/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 14:25:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15541</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This review was originally posted on HeraldofGrace.org and has been re-posted by the permission of the author. The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric1John Carrick2Banner of Truth Book Review by D. Scott Meadows Introduction Since &#8220;imperative&#8221; can mean vital importance and urgency, the title of this book could signal a general defense of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/scott-meadows-imp-1/">Review: The Imperative of Preaching Part I | D. Scott Meadows</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-small-font-size"><em>This review was originally posted on HeraldofGrace.org and has been re-posted by the permission of the author. </em></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="http://www.trinitybookservice.com/index.php/the-imperative-of-preaching-hardcover-by-john-carrick.html">The Imperative of Preaching: A Theology of Sacred Rhetoric<sup>1</sup></a><br>John Carrick<sup>2</sup><br>Banner of Truth</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Book Review by D. Scott Meadows</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Introduction</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Since &#8220;imperative&#8221; can mean vital importance and urgency, the title of this book could signal a general defense of preaching&#8212;a welcome subject in our prevalent anti-preaching cultural milieu, but already addressed frequently in many other homiletical books.<sup>3</sup>Carrick&#8217;s concern is more narrow, yet also momentous. He devotes attention to the grammatical moods of biblical preaching with their theological significance, emphasizing the necessity of preaching in the imperative voice of command or exhortation. While he may not have intended the title as a double-entendre, in a curious way it is. Applicatory preaching is of vital importance today, not just preaching in general.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This book affected me in a way no other ever has. When I finished it in April 2003, my first thought was, &#8220;I wish I had written that!&#8221; The terse assessment I penciled at that time on the first page was, &#8220;One of the finest books on preaching I have ever read! Very helpful.&#8221; It is excellent in so many respects. It is clear and presents strong Scriptural support for its thesis. Carrick often quotes the New King James Version translation and the authoritative Oxford English Dictionary, which would have been my own choices. He has a style of writing that is engaging and confrontational without rancor. Besides giving serious preachers much pleasure, this book provokes thoughtful reflection on one&#8217;s own pulpit ministry, with much encouragement of continued reformation toward the biblical standard.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Proverbs 26.17 says, &#8220;He who passes by and meddles in a quarrel not his own is like one who takes a dog by the ears.&#8221; Let go of either ear and you get bitten! If the controversy raised by this book review did not belong to me, wisdom would preclude my involvement&#8212;but alas, as a Reformed preacher I have been sucked into it. We have the two ears of redemptive-historical preaching (RHP) and imperative-applicatory preaching, and I find myself holding onto both simultaneously, unwilling to release either. Some may charge me with hermeneutical and homiletical inconsistency. My own opinion is that the best Reformed preachers agree in the most important points, whichever side they take, and that the extreme elements in both may be legitimate causes of concern. Perhaps some ardent advocates of a particular perspective have been unnecessarily divisive from zeal to protect their Shibboleth (Judges 12.6). Did I pronounce that right? Let all things be done with love and unto the edification of the church.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Biblical Theology and Redemptive Historical Preaching</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>A brief description of RHP may prove helpful. It is that preaching which grows out of the emphasis on redemptive history in biblical theology (BT) in its technical sense, although some who espouse BT do not endorse all the distinctives of RHP (e.g., Gaffin, 145). Geerhardus Vos (1862-1949), champion and popularizer of BT, offered a terse definition. It is &#8220;the exhibition of the organic progress of supernatural revelation in its historic continuity and multiformity.&#8221;<sup>4</sup>&nbsp;It is distinguished from systematic theology in &#8220;that it discusses both the form and contents of revelation from the point of view of the revealing activity of God Himself.&#8221;<sup>5</sup></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Systematic theology pulls together within a circle all the biblical data on a given topic, with little regard to chronology, so that the truth is flattened. BT moves along a historical line, noting well the providential context of any salvation-event and anticipating its issue in the completion of God&#8217;s redemptive purpose through Christ. RHP, therefore, is typically sweepingly panoramic and conspicuously Christocentric.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Carrick&#8217;s book raises his concerns about some advocates and practitioners of RHP. He does not denounce RHP per se, nor does he advocate an approach to preaching in the name of power and relevance with the typical naivet&eacute; of evangelicals embracing an &#8220;application bridge&#8221; mentality, with its clumsy attempt to make Scripture relevant by ill-founded exhortations that miss the point of what the text really urges.<sup>6</sup></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>His &#8220;theology of sacred rhetoric&#8221; almost rises above the fray (except in chapter 6) to make keen and undeniable observations about the grammatical forms of homiletical statements both in Scripture and in the tradition of some of the greatest preachers since the Reformation. Indeed, he raises some of the very same concerns as RHP advocates like Lee Irons (e.g., the indicative-grounded imperative). The most polemical section of the book is chapter 6, &#8220;The Imperative&#8212;Part 2,&#8221; and even here he praises advocates of the RH approach like Edmund Clowney of Westminster Theological Seminary, who &#8220;to many . . . represents the more moderate wing of RHP&#8221; (116). Carrick seems most concerned about some RHP advocates who have unduly minimized if not altogether eliminated &#8220;the imperative of preaching.&#8221;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In an article published before the release of his book, Carrick offered a concise assessment: The redemptive-historical school has much to commend it&#8212;namely, its high view of the inspiration and inerrancy of the Scriptures, its commitment to the concept of the unity of the Scriptures, and its profound Christ-centeredness. It does appear, however, to have generated a style of preaching which is, regrettably, neither directly evangelistic nor directly hortatory and which is, therefore, not calculated to have very much impact upon sinner or saint. And yet this lack of application within the redemptive-historical tradition is surely an unfortunate de facto concomitant; it is as surely not a necessary concomitant. There is no reason in principle why the redemptive-historical preacher should not apply the Word of God; and apply the Word he must, if his preaching is not indeed to degenerate into mere &#8220;aesthetic contemplation.&#8221;<sup>7</sup></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>So it appears that Carrick himself holds to both ears. As one investigating the controversy, reading Carrick&#8217;s book made me more interested, not less, in the RH approach. He sparked my greater interest in the writings of Clowney and Geerhardus Vos.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Please bear with a personal testimony. The first time I spoke of Carrick&#8217;s book publicly was before a group of mostly OPC pastors in the RHP mold, men whom I anticipated would be less than sympathetic with Carrick&#8217;s thesis, men who actually know some of the men Carrick criticizes. To prepare for meaningful interaction, several of them read Carrick&#8217;s book beforehand. They told me they were mostly appreciative, to their surprise. Now I have realized that we need not take an either-or approach in this controversy. Passionate men of both persuasions have made worthwhile contributions to be seriously considered. Whatever our own views, biblical integrity constrains us to honesty in representing others and charity in relating to all. In that environment, &#8220;iron sharpens iron&#8221; (Prov 27.17), and all stand to benefit from the spirited dialogue. Sadly, one involved in this debate has said a cloud of suspicion hangs over it.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In the remainder of this book review, I would describe its substance and interact modestly with Carrick&#8217;s ideas. Your feedback is welcome since you are my esteemed fellow pastors and I am a student still forming opinions about this topic.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Survey</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Between an introduction and a conclusion, the author presents four parts related to the grammatical form of homiletical statements: the indicative, the exclamative, the interrogative, and the imperative. The section on the imperative seems to have been the author&#8217;s main concern, and here he allows himself two chapters instead of one, the first of which, like the single chapters on the other three grammatical forms, essentially notes the traits of the form, its warrant and theological significance from Scripture, and citations of sermons both canonical and from five exemplary Reformed preachers, viz., Jonathan Edwards, George Whitefield, Samuel Davies, Asahel Nettleton, and Martyn Lloyd-Jones.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The introduction (ch. 1) begins with a plea for the legitimacy of a concept of &#8220;sacred rhetoric,&#8221; despite its negative connotations in the minds of some, since it is only religious speech calculated to persuade. This is not incompatible with a conscious dependence upon the Holy Spirit, so necessary in preaching which glorifies God. We must have Spirit-filled rhetoric. Then the author states his central thesis: &#8220;The essential pattern or structure which God himself has utilized in the proclamation of New Testament Christianity is that of the indicative-imperative. In other words, God himself has, in the gospel of Christ, harnessed these two fundamental grammatical moods and invested them with theological and homiletical significance&#8221; (5). Besides these Carrick notes the existence of the exclamative and the interrogative which he considers aspects of the indicative. He proposes to define, illustrate, and exemplify these four in the remainder of the book, and he succeeds in this.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>&#8220;Christianity begins with a triumphant indicative&#8221; (7). So he begins the chapter (ch. 2) on this grammatical mood with the justly-famous statement of J. Gresham Machen in Christianity and Liberalism. In that titanic struggle, Machen sagely observed that liberalism begins by telling the sinner what he must do; Christianity begins by telling the sinner what God has done. The indicative is a grammatical term &#8220;that points out, states, or declares&#8221; (8). The biblical gospel is in the indicative form, and this heavenly declaration of God&#8217;s redeeming work accomplished in Christ is the foundation of all biblical preaching. One of this book&#8217;s strengths is its frequent appeal to the biblical text cited in full for the reader&#8217;s convenient examination and reflection. Carrick praises Herman Ridderbos&#8217; insight that apostolic preaching had the nature of witnessing (12). This is also seen in the Apostles&#8217; Creed.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The indicative is well-suited to instruction, a major part of the faithful preacher&#8217;s task if not the whole. Nevertheless, we must remember the distinction between redemption accomplished and redemption applied (19-20). This paradigm suggests the indicative-based imperative. The grammatical form of the Scriptural message is rich in theological significance. The New Testament message can be summarized as two pairs of indicative-imperatives, one aimed at sinners and the other at saints:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Christ died for sinners (indicative) &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;- Repent and believe the gospel (imperative)<br>Saints have died to sin (indicative) &#8212;- Reckon yourselves to be dead indeed to sin (imperative)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Hence there is the double indicative of what God has done for sinners and for believers, and the double imperative of what their response must be on the basis of God&#8217;s work. The first is redemption accomplished; the second is redemption applied.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The exclamative (ch. 3) amounts to an emotional indicative (30-31). It possesses an element of excitement and is often signaled by words like how, what, and oh. A section of Scriptural illustration is devoted to each of these, followed by eloquent examples from the great preachers aforementioned. For example, Jonathan Edwards once wrote, &#8220;What multiplied and aggravated sins some men are guilty of!&#8221; (39).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The imperative (part 1, ch. 5) follows the basic content pattern of the previous chapters. The imperative is defined as a grammatical form expressing command, request, or exhortation (83). Clearly the New Testament is filled with apostolic preaching in the imperative form. At this point Carrick elaborates impressively on the twin indicative-imperatives found especially in Acts and the canonical epistles. Indeed, the entire structure of some epistles is obviously indicative-imperative (e.g., Romans, Ephesians). Hebrews uses a repeating pattern of indicative-imperative sections, and James is dominated by imperatives. Not surprisingly, great Reformed preaching has also been characterized by the indicative- based imperative, with powerful exhortations to sinners and saints alike, as the author demonstrates.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The imperative (part 2, ch. 6) boldly presents Carrick&#8217;s concerns about RHP. He traces its history from the Netherlands in the 1930s and 1940s. Klaas Schilder (1890-1952) and B. Holwerda (1909-1952) spearheaded the RH school of thought which gave rise to RHP (108-109). These men were concerned with an &#8220;atomistic&#8221; approach to interpretation and preaching which took texts out of context, failed to grasp the sweeping meta-narrative of Scripture understood synthetically, and then applied them arbitrarily and manipulatively. The biblical text was becoming putty in such a preacher&#8217;s hands, which he could mold at his pleasure, even to the degree it lost its original and legitimate significance. The RH school helped to restore an appreciation for the unity of redemptive history and its Christocentricity (111). It also decried the creeping moralism of preaching in the modern era, in which the grand indicative is conspicuously absent or lacking appropriate emphasis. It is a sad thing when grand gospel indicatives disappear from sermons and the preacher&#8217;s constant concern is that his hearers &#8220;be good and do good,&#8221; without frequent reference to the grace of Christ and our dependence on Him.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>However, some RHP advocates have taken this too far, and according to Carrick their suspicion of exhortation and application recoils upon the Scriptures themselves (113). Traces of this Dutch Reformed influence remain at both Westminster Theological Seminaries (in Pennsylvania and California), where BT and RHP with its reticence in application are not absent. Even WTS Professor Clowney himself, an ardent exponent of both, has warned,</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>We do well to avoid setting up a false antithesis between the RH approach and what might be called the ethical approach to the Scriptures, particularly historical passages. The RH approach necessarily yields ethical application, which is an essential part of preaching the Word. Whenever we are confronted with the saving work of God culminating in Christ, we are faced with ethical demands. A religious response of faith and obedience is required (116).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Carrick presses the point even further in a closely-reasoned, technical argument, composing the remainder of this last chapter, given to essentially two things: 1) the biblical presence and implications of the &#8220;exemplary imperative,&#8221; and 2) an expos&eacute; and indictment of &#8220;the more extreme wing&#8221; of RHP (130). For convenience of reference, we label this EW-RHP. These twin topics are the debate&#8217;s ground zero and deserve more careful consideration.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>Notes:</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>1. Also see reviews by Earl Blackburn published in the Reformed Baptist Theological Review, 1.2, pp. 194-196, and Jim Elliff at http://www.ccwonline.org/imperative.html (both attached).<br>2. Assistant Professor of Applied and Doctrinal Theology at Greenville Presbyterian Theological Seminary, Taylors, South Carolina, and one of the principal homiletics instructors at the seminary. He is a graduate of Oxford University and is currently involved in D. Min. studies at Westminster Theological Seminary, California. He was formerly minister of the Cheltenham Evangelical Church, U.K., and of the Matthews Orthodox Presbyterian Church, North Carolina, U.S.A.<br>3. E.g., see John Stott, Between Two Worlds, &#8220;Contemporary Objections to Preaching,&#8221; pp. 50-91; Brian Borgman, My Heart for Thy Cause, pp. 127-141; Gardiner Spring, The Power of the Pulpit (entire volume); Martyn Lloyd- Jones, Preachers and Preaching, &#8220;The Primacy of Preaching&#8221; and &#8220;No Substitute,&#8221; pp. 9-44; John MacArthur et al., Rediscovering Pastoral Ministry, pp. 250-261, etc.<br>4. &#8220;The Idea of Biblical Theology as a Science and as a Theological Discipline,&#8221; inaugural address in 1894 as Professor of Biblical Theology at Princeton Theological Seminary, in Redemptive History and Biblical Interpretation edited by Richard Gaffin, p. 15.<br>5. Ibid, p. 7.<br>6. Lee Irons, Pastor, Redeemer OPC in Encino, CA, available at www.pcea.asn.au/0008_tpb/Red_Hist_Prchg.htm.<br>7. &#8220;Redemptive-Historical Preaching: An Assessment,&#8221; in katek?men: Let Us Hold Fast, 13.1, Summer 2001, published by Greenville Theological Seminary (attached).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div></div><div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/scott-meadows-imp-1/">Review: The Imperative of Preaching Part I | D. Scott Meadows</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/scott-meadows-imp-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chapter 5 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Later and Complete Reconciliation with the Apostle Paul</title>
		<link>/7-john-mark/</link>
					<comments>/7-john-mark/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 21:31:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=15500</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chapter 5 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Later and Complete Reconciliation with the Apostle Paul This is the 7th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 6 parts here: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. We do not know how the turn-around in the life of John Mark came about. We [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/7-john-mark/">Chapter 5 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Later and Complete Reconciliation with the Apostle Paul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2><strong>Chapter 5 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Later and Complete Reconciliation with the Apostle Paul</strong></h2>



<p><em>This is the 7th part of a 9 part series, you can find the other 6 parts here: <a href="/the-bible-tells-stories-about-people/">1</a>, <a href="/pt-2-his-probable-and-improbable-escapade-as-a-young-man-mark-1451-52/">2</a>, <a href="/mark-career-3/">3</a>, <a href="/chapter-3-mark/">4</a>, <a href="/john-mark-5/">5</a>, <a href="/6-john-mark/">6</a>.</em></p>



<p>We do not know how the turn-around in the life of John Mark came about. We do not know how long it took for John Mark to return to or regain the Apostle Paul’s good graces. All we know is that some years later things had, in fact, changed drastically.&nbsp; Colossians and Philemon were written about twelve years after the apostolic council in Jerusalem.&nbsp; That council took place in or around the year 50.&nbsp; Colossians and Philemon were written during Paul’s first imprisonment in Rome in the year 62.&nbsp; And by then Paul’s attitude about John Mark was much different.&nbsp; This is evident in three passages.&nbsp; The first two are in the closely related books of Colossians and Philemon.</p>



<ul><li><em>Colossians 4:10 Aristarchus, my fellow prisoner, sends you his greetings; and also Barnabas&#8217;s cousin Mark (about whom you received instructions; if he comes to you, welcome him) </em>and<em> Philemon 1:24 as do Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, Luke, my fellow workers. </em>In these passages Paul encourages the Colossian church to welcome John Mark and calls him his fellow worker.&nbsp; Furthermore, Paul’s attitude continued to be steadfastly favorable to John Mark.&nbsp; Probably five years later and just before his death and during his second imprisonment in Rome, Paul once more spoke of Mark with great esteem.</li><li><em>2 Timothy 4:11 Only Luke is with me. Pick up Mark and bring him with you, for he is useful to me for service. </em>Still at the end of his life, Paul regards the one whom he had no doubt once thought useless for ministry as useful to him for the ministry. An abiding change had taken place in Paul’s opinion of John Mark. It was, furthermore, a change that lasted until the very time of Paul’s death. 2 Timothy was written shortly before Paul’s martyrdom in the year 67.&nbsp; Thus, five years after writing Colossians and Philemon Paul’s admiration for Mark had not dwindled, but actually increased.</li></ul>



<p><strong><em>We learn that because of Christ we must give forgiveness, grace, and second chances to people who have blown it in the past!&nbsp; </em></strong>Paul clearly did! The example of John Mark also condemns us for writing off Christians who have blown it. We must hold out the possibility that their sin may be forgiven and that the grace of a second chance at useful ministry may be given them!</p>



<p><strong><em>We learn that because of Christ Christians may grow in grace and become more useful than they were in the past!&nbsp; </em></strong>John Mark is a wonderful example that immature Christians who do foolish and unstable things may grow and become useful.&nbsp; I am sure if he did not say it, that Paul was certainly tempted to say that John Mark was <strong><em>useless</em></strong> for the ministry.&nbsp; Yet by the end of his life, he was forced to say—he was glad to say—that John Mark was <strong><em>useful</em></strong>. <em>Useless Christians may be come useful Christians!</em> <em>And that can be true for you!</em></p>



<p>But wonderful as this is, there is another and final reference to John Mark in the New Testament. It constitutes the sixth chapter in John Mark’s remarkable career and will lead us into the seventh and last chapter. We will consider it in the next post.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/7-john-mark/">Chapter 5 of John Mark’s Remarkable Career—His Later and Complete Reconciliation with the Apostle Paul</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/7-john-mark/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>J. V. Fesko’s Reforming Apologetics—Retrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the Faith—A Critical Review (2 of 4)</title>
		<link>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-2-of-4/</link>
					<comments>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-2-of-4/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 12:28:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[J.V. Fesko]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositionalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Van Til]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11715</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Part 1 Introduction But this somewhat personal preface to the appearance of Fesko&#8217;s book provides no clear idea of the nature of Fesko&#8217;s volume and its argument.&#160; To understand where Fesko is coming from involves an understanding of some important currents which have arisen in Reformed scholarship in recent years. One of those currents has [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-2-of-4/">J. V. Fesko’s Reforming Apologetics—Retrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the Faith—A Critical Review (2 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align:left"><a href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-1-of-4/">Part 1</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph {"fontSize":"medium"} -->
<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Introduction</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>But this
somewhat personal preface to the appearance of Fesko&#8217;s book provides no clear
idea of the nature of Fesko&#8217;s volume and its argument.&nbsp; To understand <em>where Fesko is coming from</em> involves an understanding of some
important currents which have arisen in Reformed scholarship in recent years.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>One
of those currents has been the growing appreciation for the accomplishments of
what is known as the high Reformed Scholasticism of the late 16<sup>th</sup>
and 17<sup>th</sup> centuries.&nbsp; This
current is deeply reflected in the subtitle of Fesko&#8217;s work: <em>Retrieving the Classical Reformed Approach
to Defending the Faith</em>.&nbsp; The <em>Classical Reformed Approach</em> of which
Fesko speaks is a reference to the high Reformed Scholasticism just mentioned.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>To
understand the story of the emergence of this renewed appreciation for Reformed
Scholasticism, one must go back to and provide a brief introduction to a theory
popular in previous generations of historians. The theory is known as <em>Calvin versus the Calvinists</em>.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>&nbsp; Fesko mentions this theory explicitly and
takes issue with it in many places. (48, 50, 52, 53, 56, 67-69) This theory
over the years was elaborated in many ways.&nbsp;
Here is a chart which suggests its character and claims.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:image {"id":11722,"align":"center","width":475,"height":353} -->
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/Calvin-and-Calvinists-3-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-11722" width="475" height="353"></figure></div>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>A key issue that informs Fesko&#8217;s critique of Van Til and
Presuppositionalism has to do with this claim that Calvin differed from his
theological descendants in rejecting the scholastic tradition informed by the
philosophical methodology of Aristotle.&nbsp;
Reformed historians under the influence of especially the work of
Richard Muller have raised serious questions about this view of Calvin.&nbsp; Muller in his <em>Unaccommodated Calvin</em><a href="#_ftn2">[2]</a>
and <em>Post-Reformation Reformed Dogmatics</em><a href="#_ftn3">[3]</a>has argued that this distinction is not
only exaggerated but probably false.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is important with regard to Van Til and Presuppositionalism
because of two well-known claims of Van Til.&nbsp;
The first is that Calvin significantly and even drastically differed
from the Medieval Scholastics in his approach to apologetics and especially
natural theology.&nbsp; The second is that
later Reformed theologians drifted from Calvin into a view of apologetics that
actually returned to the views of Medieval Scholasticism.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The view associated with Muller and other contemporary historical
theologians is that to understand Calvin properly, he must be situated within the
classical, Christian theological tradition and not contrasted with it.&nbsp; This means that, far from being contrasted,
for instance, with Thomas Aquinas and the Medieval theological tradition, he
must be interpreted as working within it.&nbsp;
Similarly, this means that far from contrasting him with his Calvinist
theological successors he must be interpreted in harmony with them.&nbsp; Thomas Aquinas, the Medieval theologians,
Calvin, and the &#8220;Reformed Scholastics&#8221; of the succeeding generation are all
seen as utilizing the same scholastic methodology.&nbsp; Muller argues in <em>Unaccommodated Calvin </em>that, though this scholastic method is not as
apparent in Calvin, it informs many of his writings.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Flowing from this thesis is another and even more important
consequence.&nbsp; There is much more
commonality in Calvin&#8217;s actual theological system and affirmations with the Reformed
and especially the Medieval &#8220;Scholastics&#8221; than has generally been recognized. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This is a startling claim and not just for Presuppositionalists. Central
to Van Til&#8217;s claims regarding Presuppositionalism is a contrast especially with
Medieval Scholasticism&#8217;s approach to apologetics.&nbsp; The notion that Calvin had much more in
common with Thomas Aquinas than has been generally recognized is both
challenging and serious to Presuppositionalism.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>What shall we make of this new paradigm of contemporary Reformed
historians?&nbsp; How should we respond to it
and the challenge it poses for Presuppositionalism&#8217;s claims?&nbsp; Though I am in general carried by Muller&#8217;s
thesis, I also believe that it is easily subject to overstatement and
abuse.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>I am carried by it in so far as it is clear that many of the contrasts
between Calvin and the later Calvinists have been based on significant
misunderstandings of or imbalanced, one-sided treatments of Calvin.&nbsp; Into this category, for instance, must be
placed Brian Armstrong&#8217;s not too subtle attempt to present Calvin as the father
of Amyraldianism.<a href="#_ftn4">[4]</a>&nbsp; Into the same category must be placed R. T.
Kendall&#8217;s horrendous attempt to appropriate Calvin to universal atonement and his
intellectualist view of faith.<a href="#_ftn5">[5]</a>&nbsp; I am not familiar with any attempts to
appropriate Calvin for passibilist or semi-passibilist views of God, but it is
clear to me that Calvin held to classical views of the doctrine of God as
propounded by both Medieval and Protestant Scholastic theologians.&nbsp; This is an important point for those arguing
for a more &#8220;scholastic&#8221; Calvin.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>At the same time, a warning must be stated.&nbsp; The current scholarly trend towards a scholastic Calvin must not be pressed to the point where certain differences between Calvin and some of his Reformed successors are denied.&nbsp; It is clear that there are differences between Calvin and the Reformed on a number of the subjects noted in the chart above.&nbsp; It seems to me that Calvin did define saving faith in terms which made assurance of salvation essential to saving faith.&nbsp; It seems clear to me that his views of the Christian Sabbath are neither as consistent nor complete as those of his Puritan successors.&nbsp; The degree of difference between Calvin and the Calvinists on these issues has been overstated. Seriously wrong practical conclusions have been drawn from these differences. Nevertheless, differences clearly do exist. On both of these issues I prefer the views of the confessional tradition found in the Westminster and 1689 Baptist Confession to those of Calvin. While at many points the confessional tradition closely reflects (and sometimes almost verbatim) the views of Calvin, there are distinctions between Calvin and the Calvinists that cannot be denied.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>There are also places where I agree with Calvin against his Reformed
successors.&nbsp; It is well-known that a
revolutionary, political tradition developed among Calvin&#8217;s Presbyterian
successors.&nbsp; It is really clear that
Calvin is not the author of this tradition and in fact would have rejected this
development.&nbsp; I have documented the
reasons for this assertion in my essay on <em>Political
Revolution in the Reformed Tradition: An Historical and Biblical Critique.</em><a href="#_ftn6">[6]</a>&nbsp; Suffice to say here, Calvin makes his
anti-revolutionary view clear in the <em>Institutes</em>
(4:20), in his commentaries on the key passages, and in his letters to the
French Reformed movement.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In the prevailing enthusiasm for Muller&#8217;s thesis, these distinctions
must not be forgotten.&nbsp; Muller himself in
<em>Unaccommodated Calvin</em> refuses to
claim Calvin for a full-blown doctrine of limited atonement.<a href="#_ftn7">[7]</a>&nbsp; William Cunningham (1805-1861) cannot be
accused of being influenced by 20th century historiography.&nbsp; Yet he cautions against wrongly flattening
the difference between Calvin and his successors.&nbsp; He has this to say about Calvin and the
Calvinists:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>And it has often been alleged that Beza, in his very able discussions
of this subject, carried his views upon some points farther than Calvin himself
did, so that he has been described as being <em>Calvino
Calvinior</em>.&nbsp; We are not prepared to
deny altogether the truth of this allegation; but we are persuaded that there
is less ground for it than is sometimes supposed, and that the points of
alleged difference between them in matters of doctrine, respect chiefly topics
on which Calvin was not led to give any very formal or explicit deliverance,
because they were not at the time subjects of discussion, or indeed ever
present to his thoughts.<a href="#_ftn8">[8]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Though some may think that John Murray was too influenced by the
historiography of his day, he provides this analysis of the issue.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>It would be unhistorical and theologically unscientific to overlook or
discount the developments in the formulation of Reformed doctrine that a
century of thought and particularly of controversy produced.&nbsp; Study even of Calvin&#8217;s later works, including
his definitive edition of the <em>Institutes</em>
(1559), readily discloses that his polemics and formulations were not oriented
to the exigencies of debates that were subsequent to the time of his
writing.&nbsp; It is appropriate and
necessary, therefore, that in dealing with Calvin, Dort, and Westminster we
should be alert to the differing situations existing in the respective dates
and to the ways in which thought and language were affected by diverse
contexts.&nbsp; This is particularly necessary
in the case of Calvin.&nbsp; Too frequently he
is enlisted in support of positions that diverge from those of his successors
in the Reformed tradition.&nbsp; It is true
that Calvin&#8217;s method differs considerably from that of the classic Reformed
systematizers of the seventeenth century.&nbsp;
But this difference of method does not of itself afford any warrant for
a construction of Calvin that places him in sharp contrast with the more
analytically developed formulations of Reformed theology in the century that
followed.<a href="#_ftn9">[9]</a></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>A definitive evaluation of Fesko&#8217;s claims based on Muller&#8217;s
historiography must await the following review of his volume.&nbsp; These cautionary thoughts are intended simply
to set the stage for that evaluation.<br></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a>Two important statements of this
historical paradigm are these: Brian G. Armstrong, <em>Calvinism and the Amyraut Heresy: Protestant Scholasticism and Humanism
in Seventeenth Century France</em> (Madison, Wisconsin: University of Wisconsin
Press, 1969.); <em>John Calvin: A Collection
of Essays</em>, ed. by G. E. Duffield, (Grand Rapids, Eerdmans, 1968).&nbsp; In this collection see especially Basil
Hall&#8217;s &#8220;Calvin against the Calvinists,&#8221; 25f.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref2">[2]</a>Richard A. Muller, <em>The Unaccommodated Calvin</em> (Oxford: New
York, 2000). </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref3">[3]</a>Richard Muller, Post-Reformation
Reformed Dogmatics, 4 vols. (Grand Rapids:<br>
Baker, 2003). </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref4">[4]</a>Armstrong, <em>Calvinism and the Amyraut Heresy.</em> </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref5">[5]</a>R.
T. Kendall, <em>Calvin and English Calvinism
to 1649</em> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1979.) </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref6">[6]</a>This essay was my thesis for my ThM
written for Grand Rapids Baptist Theological Seminary. It is currently
unpublished.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref7">[7]</a>Muller, <em>The Unaccommodated Calvin</em>, 6.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref8">[8]</a>William
Cunningham, <em>The Reformers and the
Theology of the Reformation</em>, pp. 349, 350.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref9">[9]</a><em>Crisis in the Reformed Churches</em>, ed. by
Peter Y. Dejong, &#8220;Calvin, Dort, and Westminster &#8211; A Comparative
Study,&#8221; John Murray, pp. 150, 151.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-2-of-4/">J. V. Fesko’s Reforming Apologetics—Retrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the Faith—A Critical Review (2 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-2-of-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>J. V. Fesko’s Reforming Apologetics—Retrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the Faith—A Critical Review (1 of 4)</title>
		<link>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-1-of-4/</link>
					<comments>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-1-of-4/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 16:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[J.V. Fesko]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presuppositionalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed apologetics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Van Til]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11709</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Preface Let us be frank.&#160; Fesko&#8217;s Reforming Apologetics is challenging for Presuppositionalists.&#160; I have been a convinced Presuppositionalist in my understanding of the defense of the faith for something over 40 years.&#160; Of course, this commitment has not been without remaining questions.&#160; Who can read Cornelius Van Til and not have questions?&#160; Who can think [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-1-of-4/">J. V. Fesko’s Reforming Apologetics—Retrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the Faith—A Critical Review (1 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>Preface</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Let
us be frank.&nbsp; Fesko&#8217;s <em>Reforming Apologetics</em> is challenging for
Presuppositionalists.&nbsp; I have been a
convinced Presuppositionalist in my understanding of the defense of the faith
for something over 40 years.&nbsp; Of course,
this commitment has not been without remaining questions.&nbsp; Who can read Cornelius Van Til and not have
questions?&nbsp; Who can think about
Presuppositional apologetics and not ponder some very deep and difficult
issues?&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Part
of the reason for my problem is my own education.&nbsp; Though I have read a good deal of philosophy
over the years, I never quite finished a philosophy minor in college.&nbsp; A knowledge of philosophy is, as Fesko&#8217;s book
itself makes clear, really helpful in discussing biblical apologetics with its
unavoidable focus on epistemology.&nbsp; Fesko
admits that Thomas Aquinas was influenced by the Aristotelian philosophy in his
day.&nbsp; He argues that a Kantian and
Idealist philosophical background was important in the formulation of Van Til&#8217;s
apologetic approach.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Still,
I have been convinced that Van Til&#8217;s approach embodied a commitment to the
distinctives of the Reformed faith lacking in other systems.&nbsp; More importantly, I have found its key
insights in Scripture.&nbsp; I am a
Presuppositionalist because of my understanding of Scripture and not because of
my understanding of philosophy. I found in Van Til key advances in embodying
scriptural truth in Christian apologetics.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>All
that being said, Presuppositionalism has fallen, it seems to me, on dark
days.&nbsp; For perhaps 50 years
Presuppositionalism has been, if not the reigning system of apologetics in
Reformed circles, a very popular viewpoint.&nbsp;
Of course, there was push back at times.&nbsp;
30 years or so ago I read <em>Classical
Apologetics: A Rational Defense of the Christian Faith and a Critique of
Presuppositional Apologetics </em>authored by R. C. Sproul, John Gerstner, and
Arthur Lindsley (Zondervan: Grand Rapids, 1984).&nbsp; I found its argument unconvincing and (some
of) its theology problematic.&nbsp; I think it
did little to stem the rising tide of Presuppositionalism.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>It
appears, however, in our day that a re-evaluation of Presuppositionalism has
gained momentum. I suspect that one influence might be &#8220;reverence&#8221; for R. C.
Sproul.&nbsp; Sproul is one of the major
influences in &#8220;the Reformed resurgence.&#8221; His passing into glory may have given
his well-known opposition to Presuppositionalism a new appeal for some.&nbsp; </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Another cause of this re-evaluation may be that every theological system is subject to a kind of degeneration&#8212;especially when it enjoys the kind of popularity that Presuppositionalism has gained in Reformed circles. This can be illustrated from Van Til&#8217;s idea of paradox. Paradox is important in Van Til&#8217;s approach.&nbsp; Cf. John Frame&#8217;s Essay, <em><a rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Van Til: The Theologian (opens in a new tab)" href="https://frame-poythress.org/van-til-the-theologian/" target="_blank">Van Til: The Theologian</a></em>.&nbsp; I certainly agree with him about the importance of this concept. There has been, it appears to me, misuse or at least sloppy use of the important concept of paradox prominent in Van Til&#8217;s approach. Presuppositionalists have occasionally said things that are not only paradoxical, but downright irrational.&nbsp; The adversaries of Van Til have also trumpeted some of his (and his followers) more novel-sounding theological statements.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>An additional cause of re-evaluation is thatPresuppositionalism has additionally been co-opted by viewpoints that must be suspect by those who follow the Reformed Confessions.&nbsp; One is Theonomy. Christian Reconstructionism has proudly proclaimed that one of its foundational tenets is Presuppositionalism.<a href="#_ftn1">[1]</a>&nbsp; I am convinced that the Theonomy of Rousas Rushdoony and Gary North cannot be squared with the Reformed Confessional tradition.&nbsp; Statements critical of both Calvin and the Westminster Confession by them actually admit this.&nbsp; To a lesser extent even Greg Bahnsen, whose views of Van Til&#8217;s apologetics I respect, also contradicts at points the Reformed tradition.&nbsp; My views of these men and their theonomy are set out in an essay entitled:&nbsp; <em>Theonomy </em>[or Christian Reconstruction] : A Reformed Baptist Assessment. It is available <a href="http://www.reformedreader.org/rbs/tarba.htm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="online (opens in a new tab)">online</a>. Suffice to say, many if not most Presuppositionalists are traditionally confessional and have actually rejected Theonomy in the sense taught by its classic exponents.  </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Another
cause of re-evaluation is the embrace of viewpoints which possibly deviate from
the tenets of Classical Theism by some Presuppositionalists. Leading Presuppositionalists
like Scott Oliphint in books defending Presuppositional apologetics have
adopted viewpoints that appear to raise questions about the simplicity and
impassibility of God. Cf. K. Scott Oliphint, <em>Covenantal Apologetics: Principles and Practice in Defense of Our Faith</em>,
(Wheaton, IL: Crossway, 2013).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>For
all of these reasons, not a few in our day are ready to re-evaluate
Presuppositionalism&#8217;s claim to be the truly Reformed apologetic.&nbsp; This is, of course, neither fair nor
logical.&nbsp; Neither Theonomy, nor
revisionist views of classical theism, follow from Van Til or
Presuppositionalism.&nbsp; Nevertheless,
suspicion remains in some minds.&nbsp; Thus, if
there is not a crisis, there are at least major questions regarding
Presuppositionalism and its claims.&nbsp; As a
confessional Reformed Baptist, these things make it more difficult to respond
to Fesko&#8217;s challenge to Presuppositionalism.<br></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:separator -->
<hr class="wp-block-separator">
<!-- /wp:separator -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="#_ftnref1">[1]</a>Peter J.
Leithart, &#8220;An Interview with Dr. R. J. Rush&shy;doony,&#8221; The Counsel of
Chalcedon (Sept. 1985): 14-17; Gary North, <em>Honest Reporting as Heresy:&nbsp; My
Response to Christ&shy;ianity Today</em> (Tyler, TX: Institute for Christian
Economics, 1987), 7.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph --><div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author"><div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div><div class="saboxplugin-desc"><div itemprop="description"><p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div></div><div class="clearfix"></div></div><span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-1-of-4/">J. V. Fesko’s Reforming Apologetics—Retrieving the Classical Reformed Approach to Defending the Faith—A Critical Review (1 of 4)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/j-v-feskos-reforming-apologetics-retrieving-the-classical-reformed-approach-to-defending-the-faith-a-critical-review-1-of-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Importance of Accreditation (2 of 2)</title>
		<link>/the-importance-of-accreditation-2-of-2/</link>
					<comments>/the-importance-of-accreditation-2-of-2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2019 14:52:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10718</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In the first post in this short series I acknowledged that we are spending a good bit of time, effort, and money to achieve accreditation with the Association of Reformed Theological Seminaries.  When I was asked why this matter of accreditation was so important to CBTS, I thought that was a natural, legitimate, and important [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-importance-of-accreditation-2-of-2/">The Importance of Accreditation (2 of 2)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: x-large;">In the <a href="/the-importance-of-accreditation-1-of-2/">first post</a> in this short series I acknowledged that we are spending a good bit of time, effort, and money to achieve accreditation with the Association of Reformed Theological Seminaries.  When I was asked why this matter of accreditation was so important to CBTS, I thought that was a natural, legitimate, and important question.  Having briefly mentioned what the reasons for accreditation are not, I now come to speak to what they are.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong><em>What the Reasons Are: </em></strong>As I see it, there are three reasons for CBTS to pursue accreditation.  Before I state those reasons, let me say that we would not pursue such accreditation if we were shut up to the traditional accrediting agencies. Being accredited by such agencies would entangle us in trying to meet merely traditional, highly complicated, and likely unattainable standards which would distract us from our mission.  It is only because an agency like the Association of Reformed Theological Seminaries exists that we are able pursue accreditation.  It caters to smaller, conservative, confessionally Reformed seminaries like our own. But given the existence of such an accrediting agency, we are happy to pursue accreditation for the following reasons.</span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><span style="font-size: x-large;"><span style="font-size: x-large;"><em><strong>Academic Accountability</strong>—</em>Every institution (including both churches and seminaries) is in danger of becoming narrow, provincial, and complacent. Unless institutions make themselves accountable to other like institutions, they may not live up to reasonable operating standards.  While CBTS is more than an academic institution, it is nevertheless an academic institution and ought to hold itself to reasonable and accepted standards for such institutions.  ARTS’ standards, in our experience and estimation, represent reasonable and accepted academic standards for institutions like ourselves.  Thus, accreditation by ARTS is a way of holding ourselves accountable to high but reasonable academic standards and preventing CBTS from becoming complacent, provincial, and thus sub-standard in our practices.</span></span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><span style="font-size: x-large;"><span style="font-size: x-large;"><em><strong>Financial Development</strong>—</em>Holding ourselves to customary academic standards provides verification and confirmation to potential donors. This makes CBTS an attractive recipient of their charitable giving.  This is not a mere theory.  It is, in fact, the strong encouragement we have received from major donors to the seminary which have been an important incentive for us to pursue accreditation.</span></span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><em><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Student Recruitment</strong>—</span></em><span style="font-size: x-large;">Accreditation is also important for student recruitment. Of course, such accreditation is not important to all of our students, but it is important to a significant number of the students who we recruit.  So much is this the case that our plans are to make a major push for student recruitment after we are accredited (as we hope to be) in the fall of 2019.  Accreditation by ARTS also provides a further assurance to our students that their degree from CBTS would be accepted for doctoral studies should they wish to pursue such studies.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong><em>Conclusion: </em></strong>This is why we are pursuing accreditation at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary.  It is important for ourselves as an institution to hold ourselves to appropriately high academic standards.  It is important for the financial development of the seminary in order to provide credibility to present and potential donors.  It is important for student recruitment.  It provides a proof of academic credibility to potential students.</span></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-importance-of-accreditation-2-of-2/">The Importance of Accreditation (2 of 2)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-importance-of-accreditation-2-of-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Biblical Philosophy of Theological Education (2 of 7)</title>
		<link>/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-2-of-7/</link>
					<comments>/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-2-of-7/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 18:32:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Theology Matters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9658</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>While the first post in this series considered &#8220;The Material Substance of Theological Education&#8221; in this post a second subject comes into view. &#160; II. The General Authority for Theological Education A. This Authority Identified The Apostle Paul leaves no doubt as to what agency is responsible for the maintenance and promotion of Christian truth [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-2-of-7/">A Biblical Philosophy of Theological Education (2 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><em><span style="font-size: large;">While the <a href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-1-of-7/">first post</a> in this series considered &#8220;The Material Substance of Theological Education&#8221; in this post a second subject comes into view.</span></em><br />
<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">II. The General Authority for Theological Education</span></strong></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">A. This Authority Identified</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The Apostle Paul leaves no doubt as to what agency is responsible for the maintenance and promotion of Christian truth in the world.&nbsp; It is clearly the church of Jesus Christ that is charged with this responsibility.&nbsp; 1 Timothy 3:15 is plain:&nbsp; &#8220;&#8230; but in case I am delayed, I write so that you will know how one ought to conduct himself in the household of God, which is the church of the living God, the pillar and support of the truth.&#8221;</span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong><span style="font-size: x-large;">B. This Authority Specified</span></strong></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The question may be raised, however, as to what Paul means exactly by the term, church, in 1 Timothy 3:15.&nbsp; To be specific, the question is whether Paul is thinking of what theologians have called the universal church or whether he is instead thinking of the local church.&nbsp; This is not a distinction which ought to be too sharply drawn in 1 Timothy 3:15. This is so because it really appears that Paul (in this passage and some others) understands the local church to be a particular expression of the universal church and speaks of it in terms which assume this relationship.&nbsp; It is clear, for instance, in this passage that Paul is writing to Timothy with regard to his particular responsibilities to guide the church in Ephesus and that this is prominent in his thought in this passage.&nbsp; It also seems clear, however, that he regards this church at Ephesus in light of its connection with the universal church.&nbsp; Paul could hardly mean to describe the local church at Ephesus&#8212;in itself and by itself&#8212;as the house of God, the church of the living God, or the pillar and support of the truth.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Here, then, we must fall back on a broader scriptural understanding of the church and see that each particular church is seen as a local expression of the universal church.&nbsp; Though recognizing their spiritual unity as part of the universal church, Reformed Baptist ecclesiology sees each particular church as governmentally independent and in that sense autonomous.&nbsp; Cf. the <a href="http://www.arbca.com/1689-chapter26" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1689 Baptist Confession, chapter 26, paragraphs 5-7</a>.&nbsp; At the same time, it recognizes that it is vital for these churches to cooperate for the better achievement of their tasks in the world.&nbsp; Such cooperation may take many scriptural forms, and in Reformed Baptist life it has taken many forms.&nbsp; According to the Confession it may involve formal associations of churches where this is providentially possible&#8212;as long as such associations do not infringe on the independence of the local church.&nbsp; Cf. the <a href="http://www.arbca.com/1689-chapter26" target="_blank" rel="noopener">1689 Baptist Confession, chapter 26, paragraphs 14-15</a>.&nbsp; It has often been thought that such tasks as missions (church-planting) and theological education (the training of ministers of the Word or pastor-teachers) especially require, or at least are more easily and better accomplished by means of, such cooperation.&nbsp; It is the assumption of this blog series that this thinking is correct.</span></p>
<p><a href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-3-of-7/"><strong>Part 3</strong></a></p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-2-of-7/">A Biblical Philosophy of Theological Education (2 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-biblical-philosophy-of-theological-education-2-of-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Pastor&#8217;s Heart</title>
		<link>/the-pastors-heart/</link>
					<comments>/the-pastors-heart/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[CBTSeminary]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 20:04:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9510</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>By Pastor Jim Savastio I have pastored in Louisville, KY for nearly 30 years.&#160; Louisville, as many of you will know, has become something of the American Mecca for Reformed Theology.&#160; This is in large measure to the labors of Southern Seminary and Dr. Albert Mohler.&#160; Among the privileges that come from laboring in such [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-pastors-heart/">The Pastor&#8217;s Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Pastor Jim Savastio</p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">I have pastored in Louisville, KY for nearly 30 years.&nbsp; Louisville, as many of you will know, has become something of the American Mecca for Reformed Theology.&nbsp; This is in large measure to the labors of Southern Seminary and Dr. Albert Mohler.&nbsp; Among the privileges that come from laboring in such a town is the opportunity to meet and, in some cases, pastor young men aspiring to the work of the ministry.&nbsp; Inevitably such young men display academic competence and theological acumen.&nbsp; There are, however, several aspects of life and training which are often lacking if a man is to pursue a faithful and beneficial ministry in the long term.&nbsp; In this post I will deal with the matter of a shepherd&#8217;s heart.&nbsp; When I speak of &#8216;heart&#8217; I am addressing the matter of one&#8217;s thinking, affections, and consequent actions.&nbsp; I have often found that theology students love theology and that they tend to delight in one another.&nbsp; What I am most keen to see in them is a love for their own flock in which they are members.&nbsp; As a pastor who is always on the lookout for men who can and will serve the Lord here or in other places, I am concerned that they be skilled in the truth and in the passionate, accurate, clear and practical application of that truth in teaching.&nbsp; I am interested to know that these are godly men who spend time with the Lord in the word and in prayer.&nbsp; I want to see men who are in the battle in regard to their sins.&nbsp; But what I am most interested in is this&#8212;are these men shepherds?&nbsp; How do you tell a shepherd from a non-shepherd?&nbsp; You watch him around sheep.&nbsp; Sheep are drawn to him and he is drawn to them.&nbsp; While I understand that men training for ministry are not yet shepherds, this is the work to which they aspire.&nbsp; Not to be theologians, not to be professors, not even to be preachers&#8212;to be pastors, shepherds who care for the souls of their sheep. To that end allow two exhortations towards those who aspire to ministry as well as those who are in ministry.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>True shepherds know their flocks and are known by their flocks</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">This truth is laid out both implicitly and explicitly in the scriptures.&nbsp; This is an aspect of the shepherd/sheep relationship Jesus himself highlights in John 10:14, &#8220;I am the good shepherd; and I know My<em> sheep, </em>and am known by My own.&#8221;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">To the casual observer it may seem odd that a shepherd can actually know his sheep. Don&#8217;t they all look alike?&nbsp; Aren&#8217;t they all the same? Jesus, as the Good Shepherd, asserts that he knows his sheep individually and intimately.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">While no earthly shepherd can fully know the sheep the way that the Lord does, nonetheless there is something here that any shepherd after the Lord&#8217;s heart will embrace.&nbsp; The pastor must, in the words of Proverbs 27:23, be diligent to know the state of his flock.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">The day is coming when every pastor will give an account of his stewardship. Every true hearted pastor lives day by day with the reality of Hebrews 13:17 impressed upon his heart, &#8220;They watch over souls as those who must give an account.&#8221;&nbsp; How can any man do that if he has no knowledge of the people to whom he preaches?&nbsp; Ask any earthly shepherd about his flock and he is ready to answer. How many sheep does he have?&nbsp; Which are the strongest?&nbsp; Which are the weakest?&nbsp; What do they need to survive and thrive?&nbsp; The pastor knows these things because he lives and labors among his people. They matter to him.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">He knows their weaknesses and their vulnerabilities.&nbsp; Pastors, likewise, are to live and labor among a people to whom they are attached with deep bonds of affection. &nbsp;Pastors are exhorted by Peter to shepherd the flock that is among them, exercising (putting into practice) the oversight (1 Peter 5:1ff).&nbsp; The phrase, &#8216;exercising oversight&#8217; means to carefully look after. What is the state of the flock?&nbsp; Are they thriving?&nbsp; Struggling?&nbsp; Weary?&nbsp; Troubled?&nbsp; Worldly?&nbsp; Are they in the Word?&nbsp; Do they have a solid assurance?&nbsp; Are they benefiting from the ministry?&nbsp; Are they at peace with their brethren?&nbsp; How are things in their homes?&nbsp; What are their peculiar burdens?&nbsp; Do the shepherds know these things?&nbsp; Do the shepherds care?&nbsp; Pastors must see these things as being a part of their calling and stewardship for which they will give an account.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">This knowledge goes both ways.&nbsp; Pastors are not to be enigmatic figures to their congregations.&nbsp; Paul commanded the believers in Thessolonica in reference to their elders, &#8220;And we urge you, brethren, to recognize those who labor among you, and are over you in the Lord and admonish you.&#8221; (1 Thess 5:12)&nbsp;&nbsp; The word translated as &#8216;recognize&#8217; in the NKJV is translated by others as respect, honor, or appreciate.&nbsp; The KJV gives the word as &#8216;know&#8217;.&nbsp;&nbsp; These various English words are attempts to translate the Greek word<strong><em>,&nbsp; eido.</em></strong>&nbsp; The word means to know, to perceive, to pay close attention, to inspect or behold.&nbsp; The sheep know whether or not their pastor is qualified, not merely on the basis of his pulpit skills and theological acumen, but because they have some knowledge of his life.&nbsp; He is a man, after all, who is given to hospitality.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>True shepherds love their flocks</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">&#8220;The hireling flees because he is a hireling and does not care about the sheep.&#8221; (John 10:13)&nbsp;&nbsp; The actions of the shepherd differ from the actions of the hireling due, in large measure to his affection for the sheep.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">What makes the earthly shepherd stand his ground when the wolf attacks?&nbsp;&nbsp; Is it simply a sense of duty and stewardship?&nbsp; Is it that he is fearful of his job or the wrath of the owner?&nbsp; Jesus tells what places him squarely in the way of danger&#8212;he cares for the sheep.&nbsp; His heart is towards them.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">Love is the most essential element of the Christian faith.&nbsp; All believers are to experience a principled, Spirit wrought affection for one another.&nbsp; There is a special sense in which pastors are to love those entrusted to their care.&nbsp; &nbsp;The opening salvo of 1 Corinthians 13 has much to say to men in the ministry: &#8220;Though I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, but have not love, I have become sounding brass or a clanging cymbal.&nbsp; <sup>2</sup> And though I have <em>the gift of </em>prophecy, and understand all mysteries and all knowledge, and though I have all faith, so that I could remove mountains, but have not love, I am nothing.&#8221;&nbsp; What good is preaching, what profit or power is there in study and counseling if the pastor does not love those to whom he is preaching?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">If a shepherd is to labor for any length of time it is essential to share the heart of Paul expressed in 1 Thessalonians 2:7, 8<strong>&nbsp; &#8220;</strong>But we were gentle among you, just as a nursing <em>mother </em>cherishes her own children.&nbsp; <sup>8</sup> So, affectionately longing for you, we were well pleased to impart to you not only the gospel of God, but also our own lives, because you had become dear to us.&#8221;</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;">There are men who, out of principle and force of will, strive to give their lives to the flock.&nbsp; They will preach to them and pray for them at the cost to self or health or family, but such an endeavor, if it is not steeped in love, will build resentment in the long haul, towards the brethren, towards ministry and ultimately towards God himself.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/user/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/02/01222959/CBTS-Logo.png" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/user/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">CBTSeminary</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p><strong>CBTS Faculty fully subscribe to the 1689 Confession of Faith, hold an advanced<br />
degree in their field of instruction, and possess significant pastoral experience.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="saboxplugin-web "><a href="http:" target="_self" >http:</a></div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/the-pastors-heart/">The Pastor&#8217;s Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-pastors-heart/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 3 of 7)</title>
		<link>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/</link>
					<comments>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rexford Semrad]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2017 11:54:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reformed Theology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[He Died for Me]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeffrey Johnson]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7928</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>part 1, part 2 Johnson, Jeffrey. He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#38; the Universal Gospel. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp. Critical Evaluation (Continued) Exegesis An extremely disappointing aspect of He Died for Me was Johnson’s exegesis, or rather, the lack thereof.  For instance, under the heading The Exegetical Argument for Universal [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/">A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 3 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: small;"><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-1-of-7/">part 1</a>, <a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-2-of-7/">part 2</a></span></p>
<p>Johnson, Jeffrey. <a href="http://amzn.to/2uStkPA" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><em>He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &amp; the Universal Gospel</em></strong></a>. Conway, AR: Free Grace Press, 2017.  201 pp.</p>
<p><span style="font-size: x-large;"><strong>Critical Evaluation (Continued)</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: large;"><strong>Exegesis</strong></span></p>
<p>An extremely disappointing aspect of <em>He Died for Me</em> was Johnson’s exegesis, or rather, the lack thereof.  For instance, under the heading <em>The Exegetical Argument for Universal Sufficiency</em>, he states: “Though every proof text will be highly contested, such as 1 Timothy 2:4–6, Hebrews 2:9–10, and 1 John 2:2, I’m not sure how much closer the apostle Paul could have been in making a distinction between sufficiency and efficacy when he claimed that Christ “is the Savior of all people, especially of those who believe” (1 Tim. 4:10)” (130). But he does not provide any exegesis for any of these passages.</p>
<p>Instead, Johnson makes the claim that the purpose for the illustration of the brass serpent was to explain how Christ can be the Savior of all people (129, 130), claims that high Calvinists must explain why such terms as <em>all</em> and <em>world</em> do not mean all people (130), and then states that they typically do so by building a case that restricts <em>all</em> and <em>world</em> to the elect (131).  Then he moves on to John 3:15-21.  After a short discussion of why he believes that <em>world</em> in John 3:16 cannot mean the elect alone, he comes to this conclusion: “Both those who hear and believe and those who hear and do not believe have one thing in common—they both heard the universal offer of the gospel. And if they both (believers and unbelievers) heard the offer, it strongly suggests that they both are included in the ‘world’ of the ‘whosoever.’”</p>
<p>Much stands against Johnson’s seemingly assumed interpretations of the four passages he listed.  The limitation of the universal language in these passages is not something artificially imposed by high Calvinists.  Louis Berkhof, whom Johnson repeatedly claims as a moderate Calvinist,<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> provides solid exegetical arguments for the limited nature of the universal language in each of them in his <em>Systematic Theology</em>. <a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a>  And he does not do so by merely equating the world with the elect.  And John Calvin, Johnson’s most quoted moderate Calvinist, would take issue with him on both 1 Timothy 4:10 and 1 John 2:2.</p>
<p>Calvin was far from regarding 1 Timothy 4:10 as proof of sufficiency for all men but efficacy only for the elect.  He did not think the term <em>Savior</em> should be taken in the sense of eternal salvation:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #666666;">To make this more clear, it ought to be understood that this is an argument drawn from the less to the greater; for the word <em>soter</em> is here a general term, and denotes one Who defends and preserves. He means that the kindness of God extends to all men. And if there is no man who does not feel the goodness of God towards him, and who is not a partaker of it, how much more shall it be experienced by the godly, who hope in him? <a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a></span></p></blockquote>
<p>And in reference to 1 John 2:2, Calvin explicitly denies that the Lombardian Formula is suitable to the passage, but declares, “under the word all or whole, he does not include the reprobate, but designates those who should believe as well as those who were then scattered through various parts of the world. For then is really made evident, as it is meet, the grace of Christ, when it is declared to be the only true salvation of the world.” <a href="#_ftn4" name="_ftnref4">[4]</a></p>
<p>I do not know which surprised me more: that he included Hebrews 2:9-10 when the context so clearly indicates that the everyone for whom Christ tasted death was every one of His brethren, or the fact that he seemed to equate the <em>whosoever</em> of John 3:16 with the <em>world </em>of John 3:16.  The phrase translated “whoever believes” is more literally rendered “every believing one” or “every believer” and therefore cannot be a reference to the reprobate as well as the elect or a reference to the world in general.  The final exegetical issue that I will mention comes from another section of the book.  First Corinthians 15:3, according to Johnson, “implies that Paul had no problem telling everyone that ‘Christ died for our sins” (113).  Paul is not speaking to unbelievers in this passage, but rather to the church for whom Christ died.  There is no reason to assume that Paul was here giving a direct quote of the words he used in preaching the gospel to unbelievers.  The fact that there is not one example in any of the Gospels or the book of Acts of anyone telling unbelievers that Christ died for them strongly suggests that this is not the proper interpretation.</p>
<p><i>Continue to </i><a href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-4-of-7/"><strong>part 4</strong></a><i>.</i></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> While I do not fully reject Johnson’s division of Calvinists into Hyper, High, Moderate, &amp; Low, I’m not sure how helpful it really is, and it definitely seems as if his reasoning for declaring some to be Moderate is a bit arbitrary.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> Louis Berkhof, <em>Systematic Theology </em>(1939; reprint, Grand Rapids: Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., 1988), 395-98.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> John Calvin, <em>Calvin’s Commentaries</em>, vol. 21, <em>Commentaries on The Epistles to Timothy, Titus, and Philemon</em> (Edinburgh, Scotland: Calvin Translation Society; reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker Book House, 2009), 112.</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref4" name="_ftn4">[4]</a> John Calvin, <em>Calvin’s Commentaries</em>, vol. 22, <em>Commentaries on The Catholic Epistles</em> (Edinburgh, Scotland: Calvin Translation Society; reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker, 2009), 173.</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/rex/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2021/03/23164330/rex-semrad.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/rex/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Rexford Semrad</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Rexford Semrad has served as an administrator at Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary since 2015. He is married to his wife of 32 years, Marion, and has 8 children. He is a member of Grace Reformed Baptist Church of Owensboro, KY where he serves as a Deacon and a Gifted Brother. Among other things, Rex particularly enjoys theology, hot sauce and Church history.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/">A Critical Review of “He Died for Me: Limited Atonement &#038; the Universal Gospel” (part 3 of 7)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-critical-review-of-he-died-for-me-limited-atonement-the-universal-gospel-part-3-of-7/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith (part 3)</title>
		<link>/modern-exposition-of-the-1689-baptist-confession-of-faith-part-3/</link>
					<comments>/modern-exposition-of-the-1689-baptist-confession-of-faith-part-3/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sam Waldron]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2016 09:23:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[1689]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dr. Sam Waldron]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Modern Exposition]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/blog/?p=1806</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A wonderful defense of the importance of creeds and confessions has stood at the opening of A Modern Exposition since its first publication in 1989 (the 300th anniversary of its first adoption in London in 1689). I did not write that defense. It was written by Dr. Robert Paul Martin who went to be with [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/modern-exposition-of-the-1689-baptist-confession-of-faith-part-3/">Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith (part 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: justify;">A wonderful defense of the importance of creeds and confessions has stood at the opening of A Modern Exposition since its first publication in 1989 (the 300th anniversary of its first adoption in London in 1689). I did not write that defense. It was written by Dr. Robert Paul Martin who went to be with the Lord a few months ago in 2016.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">
<p style="text-align: justify;">I have always wondered if &#8220;Dr. Bob&#8221; received sufficient credit for this fine essay. In my preface to the Fifth Edition of A Modern Exposition I attempt to make sure he does. Here is what I say:</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">&#8220;Finally, let me dedicate to Dr. Robert Paul Martin and his family this 5th Edition of A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession. His Introduction on the Legitimacy and Use of Confessions has stood at the beginning of A Modern Exposition in each of its editions including the present one. He has in my view never received the credit he deserves for that outstanding little essay. &#8220;Dr. Bob&#8221; passed away a few months ago in 2016, but his godliness and labors for Christ&#8217;s Kingdom are not forgotten.&#8221;</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Dr. Sam Waldron</p>
<div class="saboxplugin-wrap" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person" itemscope itemprop="author">
<div class="saboxplugin-gravatar"><a  href='/author/sam-waldron/'><img src="https://cbtseminary.s3.amazonaws.com/media/2019/02/02212033/waldronmediapic3.jpg" alt="" itemprop="image"></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-authorname"><a href="/author/sam-waldron/" class="vcard author" rel="author" itemprop="url"><span class="fn" itemprop="name">Sam Waldron</span></a></div>
<div class="saboxplugin-desc">
<div itemprop="description">
<p>Dr. Sam Waldron is the Academic Dean of CBTS and professor of Systematic Theology. He is also one of the pastors of Grace Reformed Baptist Church in Owensboro, KY. Dr. Waldron received a B.A. from Cornerstone University, an M.Div. from Trinity Ministerial Academy, a Th.M. from Grand Rapids Theological Seminary, and a Ph.D. from Southern Baptist Theological Seminary. From 1977 to 2001 he was a pastor of the Reformed Baptist Church of Grand Rapids, MI. Dr. Waldron is the author of numerous books including A Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith, The End Times Made Simple, Baptist Roots in America, To Be Continued?, and MacArthur’s Millennial Manifesto: A Friendly Response.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="clearfix"></div>
</div>
<span class="et_bloom_bottom_trigger"></span><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/modern-exposition-of-the-1689-baptist-confession-of-faith-part-3/">Modern Exposition of the 1689 Baptist Confession of Faith (part 3)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">Covenant Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/modern-exposition-of-the-1689-baptist-confession-of-faith-part-3/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
